<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="wang xueyan">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 4, August 2016, Pages 520-530</time>
    <title>Extending lead user theory to users’ innovation-related knowledge sharing in the online user community: The mediating roles of social capital and perceived behavioral control</title>
    <author>Yong Sauk Hau.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace1. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace <author>Minhyung Kang.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
School of Business, Yeungnam University, 280 Daehak-ro, Gyeongsan-si, Gyeongsangbuk-do 712-749, South Korea
b
Department of Advanced Industry Fusion, Konkuk University, 120 Neungdong-ro, Gwangjin-gu, Seoul 143-901, South Korea
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.02.008</doi>
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">In the context of the online user community, we empirically examine the relationship between user’s lead userness and their innovation-related knowledge sharing and the mediating effects of their social capital and perceived behavioral control on the relationship.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">User’s lead userness is positively related to their innovation-related knowledge sharing.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">Users social capital and perceived behavioral control jointly and fully mediate the positive relationship between user’s lead userness and their innovation-related knowledge sharing.</highlight>
    <abstract> 
        <![CDATA[
The research on users as a source of innovation has been coming into blossom and the studies about the effect of users’ lead userness on their innovation-related activities are drawing more and more attention from both academic and business circles. However, there have been few empirical studies exploring the relationship between users’ lead userness and their innovation-related knowledge sharing behavior in the context of online user community and the mediating effects of users’ social capital and their perceived behavioral control on this relationship.By empirically analyzing the 140 data collected from an online user community that is used as an important source of innovation for a company with the structural equation modeling analysis through the partial least squares method,]]><h target="2" match="full"> this study reveals that users’ lead userness has a positive relationship with their innovation-related knowledge sharing in the online user community </h>and <h target="3" match="full">users’ social capital and perceived behavioral control jointly and fully mediate this positive relationship.</h> Based on the new findings, this study is expected to provide useful implications which can contribute to widening and deepening the research stream about the effect of users’ lead userness on their innovation-related knowledge sharing in the online user community.</abstract>
    <keywords>Lead userness</keywords>
    <keywords>Innovation-related knowledge sharing</keywords>
    <keywords>Online user community</keywords>
    <keywords>Social capital</keywords>
    <keywords>Perceived behavioral control</keywords>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
The role of user communities in product and service innovations has received a lot of attention because they can be used as an effective and efficient external source of innovations (Pisano & Verganti, 2008; Hienerth, von Hippel, & Berg Jensen, 2014; Von Hippel, 2005). In user communities, users not only share their innovation-related knowledge but also develop it by giving and receiving feedback from other users (Pisano & Verganti, 2008; Franke & Shah, 2003; Hau & Kim, 2011), which makes it possible for the communities to work as a major source of innovations (Von Hippel, 2005; Von Hippel, 2007; Jeppesen & Molin, 2003; Hau & Kim, 2011). In addition, rapid advances in information technology (IT) have made it easier for more and more users to participate in online user communities and perform innovation-conducive activities such as innovation-related knowledge creation and sharing through various digital devices such as smartphones and tablet PCs (Hau & Kim, 2011; Sawhney, Verona, & Prandelli, 2005). Therefore, online user communities have been drawing an increasing number of attention from academic scholars as a vital source of product and service innovations and many firms including IBM, Audi, Microsoft, BMW and Nokia are trying to effectively and efficiently absorb users’ innovation-related knowledge through online user communities (Mahr & Lievens, 2012; Füller, Mühlbacher, Matzler, & Jawecki, 2009).
]]><h target="1" match="full">This study attempts to empirically analyze the relationship between users’ lead userness and their innovation-related knowledge sharing in the online user community, focusing on the mediating effects of users’ social capital and perceived behavioral control between the relationship.</h><![CDATA[ Many prior studies have pointed out that users’ lead userness is a critical factor to their innovation-related activities such innovation-related knowledge owing, creating, and sharing (Franke, von Hippel, & Schreier, 2006; Schreier & Prügl, 2008; Von Hippel, 2001; Lilien, Morrison, Searls, Sonnack, & von Hippel, 2002; Von Hippel, 2007; Von Hippel, 1986) and also plays a crucial role in making them in the context of online user communities (Colazo, 2014; Mahr & Lievens, 2012; Hung, Chou, & Dong, 2011; Marchi, Giachetti, & de Gennaro, 2011). However, there have been few studies empirically analyzing the relationship between users’ lead userness and their innovation-related knowledge sharing in the context of the online user community and considering the potential mediators such as users’ social capital and perceived behavioral control between the relationship in their empirical analysis. Therefore, in order to deepen and widen the research stream related to the lead userness and innovation-related knowledge sharing in the online user community, this study tries to answer the three research questions as follows.
(i)
What is the relationship between users’ lead userness and their innovation-related knowledge sharing?

(ii)
How does users’ social capital mediate the relationship between their lead userness and innovation-related knowledge sharing?

(iii)
How does users’ perceived behavioral control on their innovation-related knowledge sharing mediate the relationship between their lead userness and innovation-related knowledge sharing?


This study empirically tests three hypotheses, developed from the combination of the lead user theory, the social capital theory and the social cognitive theory, concerning these research questions based on structural equation modeling (SEM) analysis through the partial least squares (PLS) method by using the data from an online survey of 140 members of an online user community which is used as an external source of a firm’s innovation-related knowledge.

This paper is made up of six sections. This first section introduces the research questions with the research background and purpose of this study. The second section presents the literature review on the prior studies related to the topic of this research. The third section provides the three hypotheses and research model for this study with the theoretical background for them. The fourth section explains the research methodology used for this study. The fifth section reports the empirical analysis results and the last section summarizes the major findings of this study, discusses the implications and contributions from them, and provides the suggestions for future research based on the limitations of this research.]]></section>
    <section name="Literature review;Theoretical background and research model" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Literature review
The research on users as a source of innovation has been coming into blossom (Bogers, Afuah, & Bastian, 2010), sparking various studies about the relationship between users’ lead userness and their innovation-related activities especially in the context of online communities. For example, Colazo (2014) empirically tested the effectiveness of the problem-solving efforts by the lead users in three problem-solving stages (problem detection, analysis and removal) on developing the C programming language. The ordinary least square regression results from this study revealed that problem detection, analysis, and removal efforts by lead users had inverse association with development productivity, whereas their problem detection and analysis efforts had direct relationships with product popularity based on the 29 project team level data. By using qualitative (netnography) and quantitative (ANCOVA and MANCOVA) methods, Mahr and Lievens (2012) showed that lead users’ solution-focused contribution provided the highest value in their innovation-related knowledge creation. Hung et al. (2011) provided the empirical evidence that innovative users were more likely to show the lead userness and they were more likely to use user-toolkits to generate innovations to satisfy their needs. Marchi et al. (2011) empirically revealed that users’ product knowledge and capability of sharing it were critical factors to identifying lead users. Based on a case study of Audi’s Virtual Lab, Füller and Matzler (2007) indicated that virtual customer integration made it possible for a firm to virtually integrate lead users’ innovation-related ideas and knowledge into their innovation process for new product development. Sawhney et al. (2005) pointed out that the Internet-based virtual environments enabled firms to more easily select lead users who have expertise in solving innovation-related problems through the case studies of Ducati (a motorcycle firm)’s and Eli Lilly (a pharmaceutical firm)’s online user communities. Table 1 synthesizes these prior studies according to their type of research, research context, and type of innovation-related activity on which they focus, and major findings.
Table 1. Synthesis of the prior studies.
Source	The type of research	Research context (online community)	The type of innovation-related activity on which each research focuses	Major findings (related to the topic of this paper)
Colazo (2014)	Quantitative	Open source software community (C programming language development)	Innovation-related knowledge creating	Problem-solving efforts by lead users have direct or inverse relationship with the quality of new products and the development productivity for them
Mahr & Lievens (2012)	Qualitative & quantitative	Nokia Betlabs (an online community for mobile service innovations)	Innovation-related knowledge creating	Lead users’ solution-focused contribution are more valuable than their problem-focused contribution
Hung et al. (2011)	Quantitative	Youtnwant.com (an online community providing the web toolkits to facilitate user innovation)	Innovation-related knowledge creating	Innovative users are more likely to be lead users than general users and they are more likely to utilize user toolkits to customize their needs than general users
Marchi et al. (2011)	Quantitative	Ducati (a motorcycle firm)’s online user community	Innovation-related knowledge owning and sharing	Willingness to cooperate and product knowledge are important factors to identifying lead users
Füller & Matzler (2007)	Qualitative	The Virtual Lab of AUDI (an online community for a virtual customer integration)	Innovation-related knowledge owing and sharing	Virtual customer integration enables a firm to virtually integrate lead users’ ideas and knowledge into its innovation process for new product development
Sawhney et al. (2005)	Qualitative	Ducati’s and Eli Lilly (a pharmaceutical firm)’s online user communities	Innovation-related knowledge owing	Virtual environments based on the Internet enables firm to much more easily select lead users who have innovation-related knowledge
Our synthesis of the prior studies reveals that they are limited in three aspects in spite of their major findings. First, prior studies tend to focus more on innovation-related knowledge creating or owing than innovation-related knowledge sharing among users’ innovation-related activities. But, it is innovation-related knowledge sharing that enables online user communities to create and develop collective innovation-related knowledge transcending any individual user’s knowledge, and makes the communities become one of the crucial sources of innovation (Hau & Kim, 2011). Second, the quantitative prior studies paid little attention to social factors such as social capital in their empirical analysis. Online user communities are a kind of society where users make social relationships (Hau & Kim, 2011), and social factors influence users’ innovation-related activities (Füller, Jawecki, & Mühlbacher, 2007; Hau & Kim, 2011). Third, the prior studies shed little light on potential mediators such as users’ perceived behavioral control on innovation-related activities in the relationship between users’ lead userness and their innovation-related activities, only concentrating on the direct relationship between them. Therefore, this study attempts to overcome the limitations of the prior studies by focusing on users’ innovation-related knowledge sharing and considering users’ social capital and perceived behavioral control as the mediators in the research model.
3. Theoretical background and research model
This section explains the hypothetical relationships in the proposed research model in Fig. 1 and presents the theoretical background based on the lead user theory, the social capital theory, and the social cognitive theory for them.
Fig. 1
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. The research model.
3.1. Lead user theory: the Base Model
Lead user theory (Von Hippel, 1986) posits that lead users can be used as a source of innovative and commercially attractive products or services (Franke et al., 2006; Von Hippel, 2005) and are distinguished from other users through the lead userness which are lead users’ two distinct characteristics: (1) being ahead of the market trend and (2) high benefits from innovation (Von Hippel, 2005; Schreier & Prügl, 2008; Franke et al., 2006). In the context of the lead userness, being ahead of the market trend and high benefits from innovation suggest a significant relationship between users’ lead userness and their innovation-related knowledge sharing. Users’ Innovation-related knowledge sharing in an online user community refers to users’ behaviors of voluntarily providing their knowledge conducive to creating new products or services, improving existing products or services, or solving major or minor problems in them for the community members (Hau & Kim, 2011). To actually engage in innovation-related knowledge sharing in an online user community, a user must have both cutting-edge knowledge of important market trends in products or services and sufficient motivation for innovation (Füller et al., 2007; Hau & Kim, 2011). Being ahead of the market trend implies that lead users have up-to-date information and knowledge about major trends in products or services as well as about future needs of them in the market (Von Hippel, 1986, 2005). High benefits from innovation means that lead users expect relatively high benefits from obtaining solutions for their dissatisfied needs with the products or services in the current market (Von Hippel, 2005), which provides them with sufficient motivation for innovations. Accordingly, users’ lead userness is positively related to their inclination to share their knowledge in online user communities (Jeppesen & Laursen, 2009). Being ahead of the market trend and the high benefits from innovation are independent dimensions in lead userness, i.e., not necessarily interrelated (Franke et al., 2006). Therefore, this study treats lead userness as a formative construct composed of the being ahead of the market trend and the high benefits from innovation in the research model and hypothesizes the lead userness to be positively related to innovation-related knowledge sharing in the following Hypothesis 1.
Hypothesis 1

Users’ lead userness is positively related to their innovation-related knowledge sharing in the online user community.


3.2. Social capital theory: the Mediating Model I
An online user community is a type of society where users interact with other community members (Hau & Kim, 2011; Füller et al., 2007). For example, users not only share their ideas, opinions, information, and knowledge about products or services that they actually experience but also receive feedback about them from other community members, which facilitates the creation and development of innovation-related knowledge that firms can use for product and service innovations (Franke & Shah, 2003; Prahalad & Ramaswamy, 2004; Chesbrough, 2006; Hau & Kim, 2011). Such interactions among users in communities result from their community-based social motives (Franke &Shah, 2003), and innovation-related knowledge sharing in online user communities is a type of users’ social interaction that can be influenced by their social capital (Hau and Kim, 2011). Social capital is referred to as “the sum of the actual and potential resources embedded within, available through, and derived from the network of relationships possessed by an individual or social unit” (Nahapiet & Ghoshal, 1998; p. 243). In other words, social capital indicates a person’s total relational resources resulting from the person’ connections with people or societies in his or her, online or offline, social networks (Chang & Chuang, 2011; Okoli & Oh, 2007; Wasko & Faraj, 2005).
Social capital is a formative construct (Hau, Kim, Lee, & Kim, 2013) composed of relational, structural, and cognitive dimensions (Nahapiet & Ghoshal, 1998) that can be represented by social trust, social ties, and shared goals, respectively (Chow & Chan, 2008). Therefore, this study addresses social capital as a formative construct composed of social trust, social ties, and shared goals in the research model. Concerning the social trust, when a person makes a group effort, the person trusts the other person who contributes his or her valuable share (Burt, 2007). In a user community, users make innovation-related group activities accompanied by significant time such as sharing their valuable ideas, information, experience or know-how as well as spending their time in giving useful advice to other members’ questions or opinions about products (Franke & Shah, 2003; Füller et al., 2007). According to Franke and Shah (2003)’s empirical findings, the lead userness distinguishes the innovator–users from non-innovator users and the innovator–users with lead userness voluntarily spend much more time with their peers in their community for the joint efforts for their community and make more good contributions to it, which can make the positive relationship between the lead userness and social trust. Furthermore, social trust is one of the significant determinants to knowledge sharing in online communities (Lin, Hung, & Chen, 2009).
In regard to the social ties, a user community is a knowledge-intensive society in which information and knowledge about products or services are shared and discussed, facilitating the development of innovation-related knowledge (Füller et al., 2007; Hau & Kim, 2011). In a user community, lead users have in-depth knowledge about products and keep their knowledge updated by engaging in active interactions with other users (Jeppesen & Molin, 2003). Therefore, lead users’ good knowledge and active interactions are useful for making good social relationships with other members in such a knowledge-intensive society as a user community, which can generate the positive relationship between the lead userness and social ties. Moreover, good social relationships represented by social interaction ties positively influence online community members’ knowledge sharing behavior (Chiu, Hsu, & Wang, 2006).
In terms of the shared goals, the shared goals for innovation in a user community play an important role in leading its members to make a joint effort to assist each other and perform innovation-related activities free of charge (Franke & Shah, 2003). The innovator–users with lead userness in a user community get significant and useful help for innovations from their community members (Franke & Shah, 2003), which can drive lead users to eagerly keep and share the goals of helping each other and sharing innovation-related knowledge with more members in the user community. Therefore, there can be the positive relationship between the lead userness and the shared goals. Furthermore, the shared goals are one of the significant antecedents to users’ innovation-related knowledge sharing in the online user community (Hau & Kim, 2011). Accordingly, the following Hypothesis 2 is generated based on the association in the Hypothesis 1.
Hypothesis 2

The relationship between users’ lead userness and their innovation-related knowledge sharing is mediated by their social capital in the online user community.


3.3. Social cognitive theory: the Mediating Model II
According to social cognitive theory (Bandura, 1977, 1986), a user’s perceived behavioral control in their innovation-related knowledge sharing can play a significant role in his or her actual knowledge sharing behavior. Perceived behavioral control indicates an individual’s perception of the level of easiness or difficulty in performing a target behavior (Ajzen, 1988; Fishbein & Ajzen, 1975; Bandura, 1986; Ajzen, 2002). In this sense, perceived behavioral control indicates a users’ degree of confidence of his or her ability to share innovation-related knowledge in the online user community (Hau & Kim, 2011). Because lead users are ahead of the important market trend, which provides them with cutting-edge knowledge of products or services (Jeppesen & Molin, 2003), they can be confident of their actual innovation-related knowledge sharing behavior. Accordingly, lead userness can have a positive relationship with users’ perceived behavioral control of their innovation-related knowledge sharing behavior. Furthermore, Hau and Kim (2011) provided empirical evidence that users’ perceived behavioral control has a positive effect on their innovation-conducive knowledge sharing. But their findings are limited in that they focused merely on the effects of users’ perceived behavioral control represented only by their self-efficacy of innovation-conducive knowledge sharing. Social cognitive theory defines the self-efficacy as an internal-control factor and the controllability as an external-control factor composing the perceived behavioral control (Ajzen, 2002; Bandura, 1986). The controllability in the social cognitive theory usually refers to users’ perception about the external conditions for their behaviors such as the availability of resources or technologies necessary for engaging in a target behavior (Venkatesh, Morris, Davis, & Davis, 2003). In line with this, a user’s controllability of the user community system in the context of this study means the user’s judgment about the availability of IT resources, knowledge or technologies required for him or her to use the online community system. In user communities, the innovator-users with lead userness are not only active members of the communities but also opinion leaders in them (Franke & Shah, 2003), which is impossible without lead users’ high availability of IT resources, knowledge or technologies necessary for their communications and interactions in the context of an online user community, and can imply the positive relationship between the lead userness and the controllability. Accordingly, this study proposes the following Hypothesis 3 about the relationship between the lead userness and the perceived behavioral control composed of the two independent factors, the self-efficacy and the controllability.
Hypothesis 3
The relationship between users’ lead userness and their innovation-related knowledge sharing is mediated by their perceived behavioral control on innovation-related knowledge sharing in the online user community.]]></section>
    <section name="Research methodology" category="methods">
        <![CDATA[
4. Research methodology
This section explains the research subject, the development of measurement items and the online survey for data collection, followed by the empirical analysis method for testing the hypotheses in the research model.

4.1. Research subject
In order to adopt an appropriate research subject for this study, we had performed field studies about various online user communities including online games, automobiles, and digital camera user communities for 27 months. We examined whether they could be adequate for this research based on three criteria: (i) the online user community should be used as an important external source of innovation-related knowledge for a firm (ii) innovation-related knowledge sharing should actively occur among the users in the community (iii) the lead userness should exist in the users’ characteristics in the community. The result from our field studies confirmed that Aion Game Chosun (http://aion.gamechosun.co.kr/) satisfied the three criteria. Aion is a massive multiplayer online role-playing game (MMORPG) developed by NCSOFT (www.ncsoft.com). It is globally played in Europe, the U.S., China, Japan, and South Korea and the Aion Game Chosun is an online user community for Aion users. In the online game industry, users plays crucial roles in creating innovation (Jeppesen & Molin, 2003) and online user communities are a major external source of innovation-related knowledge (Hau & Kim, 2011). By registering and participating in the Aion Game Chosun, we closely observed users’ innovation-related knowledge sharing behavior within the community and we made interviews with the R&D team leader for the Aion in the NCSOFT and the operator for the Aion Game Chosun, which confirmed that the Aion Game Chosun was the appropriate research subject for this study.
4.2. Measurement development
We adapted the verified measurement items in the previous studies to our research context. The items for being ahead of the market trend and high benefits from innovation were adapted from Franke and Shah (2003). The items for social tie, social trust, and shared goals were based on Chow and Chan (2008), Chiu et al. (2006), and Hau and Kim (2011). Self-efficacy was measured based on the items adapted from Paviou and Fygenson (2006), Hau and Kim (2011), and Venkatesh et al. (2003). The items for the controllability of online community systems were adapted from Venkatesh et al. (2003). Innovation-related knowledge sharing was assessed using items based on Hau and Kim (2011). A seven-point Likert type scale was used to assess the respondent’s agreement with each item (1 = “never agree” to 7 = “strongly agree”) for the measurement of all constructs in the research model, except for innovation-related knowledge sharing. The respondents were asked to measure their perceived frequency of sharing innovation-related knowledge (1 = “never” to 7 = “very often”). Three experts in games and four experts in knowledge management examined the wording and structure of the questionnaire. Based on their feedback, some ambiguous item expressions were revised to increase readability. Appendix A summarizes the operational definitions of all constructs and measurement items.
4.3. Data collection
An official document explaining the purpose and rationale of this study was sent on the November in 2009, to Aion Game Chosun to request its cooperation. After a week, Aion Game Chosun replied its willingness to cooperate. Two face-to-face meetings with the operator of Aion Game Chosun were held to discuss how the survey could be conducted effectively. As a result, a URL for the online survey was posted on the front page of the website of Aion Game Chosun in 2010. This post explained the purpose of this research and provided contact details and pictures of the researchers to increase the study’s credibility in the eyes of potential respondents. A gift certificate worth about $3 was given to each participant to encourage his or her participation in the survey. As a result, 295 individuals participated in the survey, and with those responses with missing or inappropriate data (e.g., out-of-range selection of response options) excluded, a total of 140 responses were obtained for the final analysis. Table 2 summarizes the profile of these 140 respondents.
Table 2. The sample profile.
Item	Frequency (N = 140)	Share (%)
Gender	Male	127	90.7
Female	13	9.3
Age	15–19	29	20.7
20–29	88	62.9
30–39	19	13.6
40–49	3	2.1
50≤	1	0.7
Aion Game Chosun Community Membership Period (in months)	≤7	95	67.9
8–14	36	25.7
15–21	5	3.6
22–28	2	1.4
29≤	2	1.4
Aion play period (in months)	≤7	58	41.5
8–14	75	53.6
15–21	3	2.1
22–28	3	2.1
29≤	1	0.7
Aion game level	≤10	4	2.9
11–20	9	6.4
21–30	11	7.9
31–40	23.	16.4
40≤	93	66.4
4.4. Analysis method
PLS Graph version 3.0 was employed to test the research model for the following three reasons: First, PLS is well suited for testing research models with formative constructs such as the lead userness, social capital and perceived behavioral control in this study’s model (Chin, 1998; Hair, Hult, Ringle, & Sarstedt, 2014). Second, this study needs to test the mediating effects of the social capital and perceived behavioral control and PLS is effective in testing mediating effects (Hair et al., 2014). Third, we tested the normality of the data for this study through Kolmogorov–Smirnov and Shapiro–Wilk tests with IBM SPSS version 22, which showed that it did not follow the normal distribution. PLS can effectively analyze data showing non-normality, as in the case of this study (Efron, 1988; Hair et al., 2014).]]></section>
    <section name="Empirical analysis results" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
5. Empirical analysis results
A two-stage procedure was employed for the SEM analysis to test the hypotheses. More specifically, step I was the test of the measurement model and step II was the test of the structural model, suggested by Anderson and Gerbing (1988). This section reports the test results for the measurement and structural models, followed by the common method bias test results for this study.
5.1. The test of the measurement model
Two steps were taken to test the measurement model. In the first step, the internal reliability of our measurement items was assessed by using Cronbach’s α for each construct in the research model. Cronbach’s α should be equal to or greater than 0.7 for sufficient internal reliability (Nunnally, 1978). As shown in Table 3, the lowest value of Cronbach’s α for the measurement items was 0.823, indicating sufficient internal reliability.
Table 3. The internal reliability and convergent validity.
Construct	Cronbach’s α	CR	AVE	Item	Factor loading	Mean	SD	t-Value
Being ahead of the market trend	0.832	0.884	0.606	BeAhead1	0.707	4.621	1.602	12.607
BeAhead2	0.811	4.343	1.683	25.827
BeAhead3	0.777	4.457	1.856	21.597
BeAhead4	0.866	4.407	1.618	33.824
BeAhead5	0.722	3.871	1.937	11.355

High benefits from innovation	0.849	0.893	0.629	HiBene1	0.841	4.936	1.574	22.174
HiBene2	0.880	5.214	1.463	41.645
HiBene3	0.839	4.921	1.415	34.850
HiBene4	0.798	5.271	1.444	16.977
HiBene5	0.570	4.586	1.373	6.691

Social tie	0.943	0.959	0.855	STie1	0.916	3.907	1.635	66.447
STie2	0.945	3.664	1.643	96.828
STie3	0.919	3.621	1.732	55.427
STie4	0.919	3.514	1.813	62.950

Social trust	0.931	0.948	0.786	STrust1	0.866	3.764	1.884	29.279
STrust2	0.899	3.786	1.790	56.989
STrust3	0.894	3.821	1.780	48.940
STrust4	0.895	3.764	1.761	38.926
STrust5	0.879	3.829	1.596	38.638

Shared goals	0.925	0.947	0.817	SGoal1	0.920	4.500	1.529	70.278
SGoal2	0.908	4.486	1.406	43.805
SGoal3	0.895	4.471	1.500	44.980
SGoal4	0.894	4.486	1.505	48.218

Self-efficacy of IRKS	0.823	0.884	0.655	SelfE1	0.831	5.000	1.404	26.074
SelfE2	0.845	4.864	1.440	30.153
SelfE3	0.805	4.421	1.455	20.659
SelfE4	0.754	4.400	1.473	14.386

Controllability of online community systems	0.843	0.906	0.762	ControSys1	0.879	5.243	1.725	49.125
ControSys2	0.876	5.471	1.580	38.378
ControSys3	0.864	5.114	1.610	25.254

Innovation-related knowledge sharing	0.918	0.934	0.638	IRKS1	0.778	3.736	1.652	21.049
IRKS2	0.857	4.336	1.520	34.182
IRKS3	0.759	3.750	1.688	17.319
IRKS4	0.824	4.207	1.612	22.632
IRKS5	0.818	4.107	1.656	26.449
IRKS6	0.708	4.414	1.488	10.778
IRKS7	0.845	4.071	1.669	31.729
IRKS8	0.791	4.221	1.627	14.505
Note: CR: Composite reliability; AVE: Average variance extracted; SD: Standard deviation; IRKS: Innovation-related knowledge sharing.

In the second step, a confirmatory factor analysis was conducted to check the convergent validity and discriminant validity of measurement items. There is sufficient convergent validity if the following four conditions are satisfied: (i) the average variance extracted (AVE) exceeds 0.5 (Fornell & Larcker, 1981), (ii) composite reliability (CR) exceeds 0.7 (Chin, 1998), (iii) all t-values exceed 1.96 (Gefen & Staub, 2005), and (iv) all factor loadings are greater than or equal to 0.5 (Hair, Black, Babin, & Anderson, 2010). The lowest values for the AVE, CR, t-values, and factor loadings were 0.606, 0.884, 6.690, and 0.570, respectively, indicating sufficient convergent validity for the measurement items shown in Table 3. There is sufficient discriminant validity if the square root of the AVE exceeds all of the correlations between constructs (Chin, Gopal, & Salisbury, 1997). As shown in Table 4, the square root of the AVE exceeded all of the correlations between the constructs in the research model, indicating sufficient discriminant validity for the measurement items.
Table 4. The correlation matrix and discriminant validity.
BeAhead	HiBene	STie	STrust	SelfE	ControSys	IRKS	SGoals
BeAhead	0.778							
HiBene	0.412	0.793						
STie	0.583	0.143	0.924					
STrust	0.422	0.034	0.581	0.886				
SelfE	0.538	0.391	0.492	0.333	0.809			
ControSys	0.332	0.472	0.210	0.078	0.385	0.872		
IRKS	0.576	0.219	0.647	0.408	0.517	0.244	0.798	
SGoals	0.405	0.338	0.421	0.526	0.422	0.351	0.454	0.903
Note: Numbers along the diagonal indicate the square root of the AVE, and off-diagonal numbers indicate correlations between constructs. BeAhead: Being ahead of the market trend; HiBene: High benefits from innovation; STie: Social tie; STrust; Social trust; SelfE: Self-efficacy of innovation-related knowledge sharing; ControSys: Controllability of online community systems; IRKS: Innovation-related knowledge sharing; SGoals: Shared goals.

5.2. The test of the structural model
This section reports the main effects test results based on the test of the structural model. Then, it provides the respective mediating effects test results of social capital and perceived behavioral control and the joint mediating effect test results of them.

5.2.1. Main effects test
The test results for the structural model in Table 5 show that all main effects in the research model were significant, providing support for Hypothesis 1. In the base model, lead userness was positively related to innovation-related knowledge sharing (Hypothesis 1: path coefficient = 0.624, P < 0.001), and the 39% of the variance in innovation-related knowledge sharing was explained by lead userness (R2 = 0.390). The results for Mediating Model I verify that lead userness was positively related to innovation-related knowledge sharing (path coefficient = 0.273, P < 0.05) and social capital (path coefficient = 0.364, P < 0.01), showing that social capital was positively related to innovation-related knowledge sharing (path coefficient = 0.518, P < 0.001), and the 53% of the variance in innovation-related knowledge sharing was explained by lead userness and social capital (R2 = 0.530). The results for Mediating Model II show that lead userness was positively related to innovation-related knowledge sharing (path coefficient = 0.364, P < 0.01) and perceived behavioral control (path coefficient = 0.655, P < 0.001). They indicate that perceived behavioral control was positively related to innovation-related knowledge sharing (path coefficient = 0.375, P < 0.01), and the 45.2% of the variance in innovation-related knowledge sharing was explained by lead userness and perceived behavioral control (R2 = 0.452).
Table 5. Results for the structural model.
Model	Base Model	Mediating Model I	Mediating Model II
Dependent variable	IRKS	IRKS	IRKS
Relationship	ß	t-value	ß	t-value	ß	t-value
Lead userness → IRKS	0.624	8.110	0.273	2.297	0.364	2.706
Lead userness → Social capital			0.663	11.556		
Social capital → IRKS			0.518	5.560		
Lead userness → PBC					0.655	9.949
PBC → IRKS					0.375	2.846
R2	0.390	0.530	0.452
Note: IRKS: Innovation-related knowledge sharing; ß: Path coefficient; PBC: Perceived behavioral control .

Lead userness was a formative construct composed of being ahead of the market trend (path coefficient = 0.576, P < 0.001) and high benefits from innovation (path coefficient = 0.611, P < 0.001). Social capital was a formative construct consisting of social tie (path coefficient = 0.383, P < 0.001), social trust (path coefficient = 0.483, P < 0.001), and shared goals (path coefficient = 0.344, P < 0.001). Perceived behavioral control was another formative construct composed of self-efficacy (path coefficient = 0.671, P < 0.001) and the controllability of online community systems (path coefficient = 0.525, P < 0.001). Table 5 summarizes the main effects test results.
5.2.2. Respective mediating effects test
To test Hypothesis 2 and Hypothesis 3 in the Mediating Model I and II, the Sobel test (Sobel, 1982) was conducted to statistically examine the respective significance of the mediating effects of social capital and perceived behavioral control on the innovation-related knowledge sharing. The level of significance was measured using the z-value based on Sobel (1982) as follows:
z−value=abb2sa2+a2sb2Note: a denotes the unstandardized path coefficient between independent and mediating variables; Sa stands for the standard error of the unstandardized path coefficient in the relationship between them; b stands for the unstandardized path coefficient between mediating and dependent variables; Sb stands for the standard error of the unstandardized path coefficient in the relationship between them.
This formula requires unstandardized path coefficients represented by the symbols including a and b. However, the PLS method provided standardized path coefficients. Therefore, unstandardized path coefficients were calculated based on Bontis et al. (Bontis, Booker, & Serenko, 2007). More specifically, unstandardized path coefficients were calculated by multiplying standardized path coefficients by the standard deviation of the dependent variable, and then they were divided by the standard deviation of the independent variable. As shown in Table 6, the z-value was calculated using the formula based on unstandardized path coefficients.
Table 6. Results of the Sobel test.
Model	Relationship	SPC	SDDV	SDIV	USPC	SE	z-value
Mediating Model I (Hypothesis 2)	Lead userness → Social capital	0.663	16.111	10.514	1.016	0.057	2.748
Social capital → IRKS	0.518	10.306	16.111	0.331	0.119
Mediating Model II (Hypothesis 3)	Lead userness → PBC	0.655	7.460	10.514	0.465	0.066	3.369
PBC → IRKS	0.375	10.306	7.460	0.518	0.135
Note: SPC: Standardized path coefficient; SDDV: Standard deviation of the dependent variable; SDIV: Standard deviation of the independent variable; USPC: Unstandardized path coefficient; SE—standard error; IRKS—innovation-related knowledge sharing; PBC: Perceived behavioral control.

]]><h target="3" match="part"><![CDATA[The results of the Sobel test in Table 6 indicate that the z-value for the Mediating Model I (Hypothesis 2) was 2.748 (P < 0.01), implying that social capital was a significant mediator of the relationship between lead userness and innovation-related knowledge sharing.]]></h> As shown in Table 5, the standardized path coefficient between them was 0.624 when the path was direct, but it decreased to 0.273 when social capital mediated the path (a 56.2% difference).
        <h target="3" match="part"><![CDATA[As shown in Table 6, the z-value for the Mediating Model II (Hypothesis 3) was 3.369 (P < 0.001), providing support for the significant mediating effect of perceived behavioral control on the relationship between the lead userness and innovation-related knowledge sharing.]]></h> As shown in Table 5, the standardized path coefficient between them was 0.624 when the mediating role was excluded, but it decreased to 0.364 when perceived behavioral control served as a mediator (a 41.6% difference).
5.2.3. Joint mediating effect test
We extended and applied the essential logics of Baron and Kenny (1986)’s mediating effect testing method for a presumed mediator to testing the joint mediating effect of the social capital and perceived behavioral control in the research model. According to Baron and Kenny (1986), if the significant main effect of the independent variable on the dependent variable becomes insignificant after the effect of the mediator has been reflected, then, it is a strong sign for the existence of the significant effect of the full mediator. <h target="3" match="part">Our another path analysis by using PLS Graph version 3.0 has shown that the significant and positive relationship (path coefficient = 0.624, t-value = 8.110) between the lead userness and innovation-related knowledge sharing in the base model has become insignificant (t-value = 0.959) after the joint effect of the social capital and perceived behavioral control has been reflected as shown in the following Fig. 2. Therefore, the joint mediating effect of social capital and the perceived behavioral control has proven to be significant and full.</h><![CDATA[
Fig. 2
Download full-size image
Fig. 2. The joint mediating effect test result.
5.3. Common method bias test
We carried out the common method bias test according to Podsakoff, Mackenzie, Lee, and Podsakoff (2003)’s suggestion on the basis of Liang, Saraf, Hu, and Xue (2007) to examine the common method bias in this study. Table 7 indicates that the average variance substantively impacted by the measurement items was 0.709 and the average variance impacted by the method factor was 0.007. Accordingly, the ratio of the method variances to the substantive variances was 1:95.2, confirming the little possibility of the common method bias in the empirical test results in this research.
Table 7. Results of the common method bias test.
Construct	Item	Method factor loading (R1)	R12	Substantive factor loading (R2)	R22
Being ahead of the market trend	BeAhead1	0.145	0.021	0.593***	0.352
BeAhead2	−0.095	0.009	0.886***	0.785
BeAhead3	−0.192*	0.037	0.927***	0.859
BeAhead4	0.106	0.011	0.783***	0.613
BeAhead5	0.044	0.002	0.687***	0.472
High benefits from innovation	HighBene1	0.110*	0.012	0.794***	0.630
HighBene2	−0.085	0.007	0.917***	0.841
HighBene3	0.006	0.000	0.837***	0.701
HighBene4	−0.089	0.008	0.836***	0.699
HighBene5	0.085	0.007	0.533***	0.284
Self-efficacy of IRKS	SelfE1	−0.097	0.009	0.901***	0.812
SelfE2	−0.160*	0.026	0.958***	0.918
SelfE3	0.094	0.009	0.737***	0.543
SelfE4	0.186*	0.035	0.622***	0.387
Controllability of online community systems	ControSys1	−0.049	0.002	0.900***	0.810
ControSys2	−0.084*	0.007	0.912***	0.832
ControSys3	0.135**	0.018	0.806***	0.650
Social tie	STie1	−0.051	0.003	0.957***	0.916
STie2	−0.055	0.003	0.990***	0.980
STie3	0.099	0.010	0.839***	0.704
STie4	0.009	0.000	0.912***	0.832
Social trust	STru1	−0.054	0.003	0.902***	0.814
STru2	−0.041	0.002	0.927***	0.859
STru3	−0.058	0.003	0.933***	0.870
STru4	0.091	0.008	0.834***	0.696
STru5	0.063	0.004	0.837***	0.701
Shared goals	SGoal1	−0.038	0.001	0.946***	0.895
SGoal2	−0.046	0.002	0.940***	0.884
SGoal3	0.058	0.003	0.855***	0.731
SGoal4	0.028	0.001	0.874***	0.764
Innovation-related knowledge sharing	IRKS1	−0.01	0.000	0.787***	0.619
IRKS2	0.114	0.013	0.762***	0.581
IRKS3	−0.006	0.000	0.764***	0.584
IRKS4	−0.06	0.004	0.874***	0.764
IRKS5	−0.03	0.001	0.843***	0.711
IRKS6	0.014	0.000	0.697***	0.486
IRKS7	−0.032	0.001	0.871***	0.759
IRKS8	0.008	0.000	0.785***	0.616
Average	0.007		0.709
*
P < 0.05.
**
P < 0.01.
***
P < 0.001.]]></section>
    <section name="Conclusion" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
6. Conclusion
This section present the summary about the major findings, implications and contributions of this study, followed by the suggestions for future research based on the limitations of this study.

6.1. Summary of major findings
Based on the SEM analysis by using the data collected from 140 users in the online game user community used for an important external source of innovation-related knowledge for a firm, this study presents three interesting findings.]]><h target="2" match="full"> First, users’ lead userness has a significant and positive relationship with their innovation-related knowledge sharing in the online user community.</h> Second, the respective mediating effects of users’ social capital and perceived behavioral control on this relationship are significant and partial.<h target="3" match=""> Third, the joint mediating impact of the social capital and perceived behavioral control on the relationship is significant and full.</h>

6.2. Implication and contribution
The major findings of this research are expected to make good contributions by providing the following useful implications which previous studies have barely presented until now.

        <h target="3" match="full">First, this study sheds a new light on the joint full mediating effect of users’ social capital and perceived behavioral control between the relationship between users’ lead userness and their innovation-related knowledge sharing in the online user community.</h><![CDATA[ Until now, a number of previous studies have focused mainly on the direct relationship between users’ lead userness and their innovation-related activities. For example, the seminal research on the direct relationship such as Von Hippel (1986), Von Hippel, Thomke, and Sonnack (1999), Von Hippel (2001), Franke and Shah (2003), and Von Hippel (2005) concentrated mainly on the point that users’ lead userness had a direct and positive impact on their behaviors of sharing or creating the knowledge related to commercially successful innovations, saying nothing about the existence of important mediators which can serve as the bridges between the lead userness and users’ innovation-related activities. In line with this, even recent studies such as Colazo (2014) and Mahr and Lievens (2012) also focused only on the direct positive or negative relationship between lead users’ innovation-related activities and their outcomes. However, this study has empirically revealed a new point that users’ social capital and perceived behavioral control act as a significant bridge between the lead userness and users’ innovation-related knowledge sharing in the online user community. This finding can present an important new implication that the existence of users’ lead userness is not directly connected to their voluntary sharing of innovation-related knowledge. In other words, the impact of users’ lead userness gets linked to their innovation-related knowledge sharing, jointly and fully mediated by users’ social capital consisting of social tie, social trust, and shared goals in their online community and their perceived behavioral control composed of the self-efficacy of the innovation-related knowledge sharing and controllability of the online community system.
Second, this study sheds another new light on the role of social capital in the research stream concerning individuals’ innovation-related activities such as knowledge sharing or creation. So far, previous studies about them have indicated the moderating effect of social capital between employees’ knowledge sharing and their sharing of best practice (Mura, Lettieri, Radaelli, & Spiller, 2013) or the inverted U-shaped relationship between research scientists’ social capital and their knowledge creation (MaFadyen & Cannella, 2004) in the offline contexts. In the online contexts, the direct relationship between online community members’ social capital and their knowledge sharing (Chiu et al., 2006; Wasko & Faraj, 2005) has been salient up to now. But, this study has empirically confirmed the significant mediating role of social capital between users’ lead userness and their innovation-related knowledge sharing in the online user community, which reveals that social capital can play a mediating role in knowledge sharing in the context of the online user community in addition to the roles of social capital which have been presented by the previous studies until now.
Third, this research illuminates a new point that users’ perceived behavioral control made up of not only their self-efficacy but also controllability of their online community system mediates the relationship between users’ lead userness and innovation-related knowledge sharing in the online user community. This point is in accordance with Hau and Kim (2011)’s finding that users’ perceived behavioral control represented only their self-efficacy is positively related to their innovation-related knowledge sharing. But, this study enrich it by empirically revealing that users’ perceived behavioral control composed of not their self-efficacy but also controllability of online community system plays a significant role in connecting users’ lead userness to their innovation-related knowledge sharing. This emphasizes the importance of the online based contextual characteristic of user communities to users’ important interactions such as innovation-related knowledge sharing occurring within the communities. Within the online user communities, any user’s interaction cannot be made without his or her controllability of online community system, which makes the controllability of online community system become a significant component of the perceived behavioral control on users’ innovation-related knowledge sharing.
6.3. The suggestions for future research based on the limitations of this study
In spite of the three useful implications, the analysis results from this study are based on data collected from an online game user community in South Korea. In this regard, it will be better for future research to collect the data from online communities for various products in multiple countries to increase the generalizability of its results. In addition, this study depends mainly on the quantitative analysis method by using the cross-sectional data. It will be more effective in increasing the rigorousness of the future research to use not only the quantitative analysis method but also the qualitative analysis method such as multiple times series case studies. Furthermore, future research based on more recent data will be able to provide a more vivid picture of the relationship between users’ lead userness and their innovation-related knowledge sharing in the online user community.]]></section>
</publication>