<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="wang xueyan">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 3, June 2016, Pages 414-424</time>
    <title>A mixed methods approach to the posting of benevolent comments online</title>
    <author>Yoon-Jung Jang.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace <author>Hee-Woong Kim. </author>Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace <author>Yoonhyuk Jung.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacec. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
CJ Olive Networks, Seoul, Republic of Korea
b
Graduate School of Information, Yonsei University, 50 Yonsei-Ro, Seodaemun-Gu, Seoul 120-749, Republic of Korea
c
School of Business Administration, Ulsan National Institute of Science and Technology (UNIST), 50 UNIST-gil, Ulsan 44919, Republic of Korea
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.02.001</doi>
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">Mixed methods: qualitative study with interview and quantitative study with survey.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">Social exchange theory with benefit-cost assessment.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">Four benefit factors and one cost factor in the qualitative study.</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">Research model testing with six decision factors in the quantitative study.</highlight>
    <highlight id="5">Three main antecedents of posting benevolent comments online in terms of self-interest, altruism, and rationality.</highlight>
    <abstract> 
        <![CDATA[
Cyberbullying by way of malicious online comments has been identified as a critical social issue. As a way to combat cyberbullying, it is important to promote the posting of benevolent comments, especially in response to malicious comments. ]]><h target="1" match="part">In this study, we adopted a mixed methods approach in using social exchange theory to explore what motivates people to post benevolent comments online. We first adopted a qualitative study to explore the decision factors involved. These were then used as the basis for development of a theoretical research model to undertake a quantitative study.</h> The results explain how people decide to post benevolent comments online. The study makes a strong theoretical contribution in demonstrating the decision factors underlying the posting of benevolent comments. It also has practical implications by providing guidance on how to combat cyberbullying through promoting the posting of benevolent online comments.</abstract>
    <keywords>Online comments</keywords>
    <keywords>Cyberbullying</keywords>
    <keywords>Malicious comments</keywords>
    <keywords>Benevolent comments</keywords>
    <keywords>Social exchange theory</keywords>
    <keywords>Mixed methods</keywords>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
Cyberbullying or electronic harassment has recently caused a vast amount of damage across the globe. In Singapore, 59.4% of students underwent at least one type of cyberbullying, and 28.5% were the targets of abusive comments on Facebook (Kwan & Skoric, 2013). In Australia, Charlotte Dawson who had hosted a TV program named “Next Top Model” committed suicide in 2012 after she was the target of malicious and abusive comments. Moreover, a survey of 3000 teachers by the National Association of Schoolmasters Union of Women Teachers, which is a teacher’s union in Britain, found that 42% of them had received insulting comments on their performance.1 Malicious comments are made as part of attacks that amount to cyberbullying.
The identification of cyberbullying as a critical social issue in the context of comments online and in social media has also attracted attention to the search for ways to prevent it and to deal with those who commit it. For example, there is a campaign on Facebook called “Help Stop the Stomping” that has the goal of preventing cyberbullying.2 Within the European nations, an anticyberbullying campaign named “The Big March” is considered the world’s first virtual global march in pursuit of children’s right to be safe from cyberbullying.3 “Sunfull” is an Internet campaign to promote posting benevolent comments online to counter bullying and the hateful comments that are posted.4 All of these anticyberbullying campaigns have in common the goals of not only stopping the posting of malicious comments, but also motivating people to post benevolent comments (i.e., comments that express goodwill and/or help others) as a kind behavior to foster civility on the Internet. However, promotion of the posting of benevolent comments should rank higher in importance in all these campaigns than merely stopping the posting of malicious comments because their cessation does not necessarily lead to the posting of benevolent comments. Posting benevolent comments may lead to the development of online social norms that in turn may reduce the posting of malicious comments and lead to a lessening of cyberbullying.
Despite the importance of benevolent online comments as a way to oppose cyberbullying, there is a lack of understanding about what motivates people to post benevolent comments in the online and social media contexts (Kim, Chan, & Gupta, 2015). Prior research on cyberbullying has mainly addressed issues of conceptual definition (Abu-Nimeh, Chen, & Alzubi, 2011; Slonje, Smith, & Frisén, 2013; Vandebosch & Cleemput, 2008), classification of cyberbullying types (Aoyama & Talbert, 2010), reasons for it (Varjas, Talley, & Meyers, 2010), the relationship between cyberbullying and traditional bullying (Brown, Demaray, & Secord, 2014; Kwan and Skoric, 2013), assessments of cyberbullying (Cetlin, Yaman, & Peker, 2011; Mason, 2008), its effects (Talwar, Gomez-Garibello, & Shariff, 2014; Dredge, Gleeson, & de la Piedad Garcia, 2014), and its prevention (Beale & Hall, 2007; Bhat, 2008; Diamanduros, Downs, & Jenkins, 2008; Keith & Martin, 2005).Of particular interest in the literature is the research on the prevention of cyberbullying. Even the few studies that have been done merely discussed strategies and guidance for school counselors and parents to prevent cyberbullying (Beale & Hall, 2007; Bhat, 2008; Diamanduros et al., 2008) and the creation of a culture of respect in the cyber world (Keith & Martin, 2005). Missing from the research is a theory-based empirical explanation of what factors lead to the posting of benevolent comments online.
This study thus aims to determine what motivates people to post these benevolent comments. Posting benevolent comments online can be viewed as a social exchange in which individuals offer something to someone without negotiating terms and without knowing whether or when the recipient will reciprocate (Molm, Takahashi, & Peterson, 2000). ]]><h target="2" match="part">Hence, this study adopts social exchange theory to explore the posting of benevolent comments online.</h> <![CDATA[Social exchange theory holds that individuals decide if they want to perform such a behavior (i.e., posting benevolent comments) based on a cost-benefit analysis of its worth (Blau, 1964; Molm et al., 2000).
       This research used a mixed methods approach for an exploratory qualitative study that was followed by a confirmatory quantitative study with a “developmental” purpose (Venkatesh, Brown, & Bala, 2013; p. 26). A sequential combination of qualitative and quantitative methods (i.e., mixed methods) is useful for developing a deeper understanding of a phenomenon (Lee, Noh, & Kim, 2013).]]><h target="3" match="part"> The first stage of this research adopted a qualitative research method and then identified cost and benefit factors specific to the posting of benevolent comments.</h> The identification of these factors was based on interviews with persons who had posted comments. <h target="2" match="part">The second stage used a quantitative research method by developing a theoretical research model based on social exchange theory and using the cost and benefit factors explored in the first stage.</h><![CDATA[ The model was validated by collecting survey data from online users. In this way, this study expects to advance the theoretical understanding of the posting of benevolent comments in an online context and knowledge of the drivers of this activity. Moreover, the study can inform social network service (SNS) providers on how to combat cyberbullying through informing them of the relevant cultural aspects of the online and social media contexts and teaching techniques to promote the posting of benevolent comments.]]></section>
    <section name="Social exchange theory" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Social exchange theory
Social exchange refers to “reciprocal acts of benefits, in which individuals offer help, advice, approval, and so forth to one another without negotiation of terms and without knowledge of whether or when the other will reciprocate (Molm et al., 2000; p. 1396)”. Accordingly, in a social exchange actors initiate exchanges by performing a beneficial act for another without knowing whether, when, or to what extent the other will reciprocate. Posting a benevolent comment as prosocial behavior on the Internet (Sproull, Conley, & Moon, 2005) is an act of voluntarily posting or commenting to provide information or emotional support such as encouragement, compliments, and consolation to benefit or help an individual or a group in an online and social media context. People tend to have no clear expectation of a future return from posting such comments. Posting a benevolent comment thus represents a social exchange. Furthermore, social behaviors in cyberspace have been explained from the social exchange perspective (e.g., Chiu, Hsu, Wang, 2006; Faraj & Johnson, 2011). ]]><h target="2" match="part">herefore, this study uses social exchange theory as its theoretical lens.</h><![CDATA[As one of the core theories used in social media research (Ngai, Tao, & Moon, 2015), social exchange theory posits that people calculate the overall worth of a social exchange based on a comparison between benefits and costs (Blau, 1964; Molm et al., 2000). Because the terms are not precisely specified in social exchange and actors do not know whether or when a recipient will reciprocate, actors consider only expected benefits and costs in their overall worth assessment. In such exchanges, the currencies of exchange are tangible and intangible resources (Kankanhalli, Tan, & Wei, 2005). Payable resources or negative outputs revealed as the result of an exchange are referred to as “cost” such as time and effort; resources produced as the result of an exchange or positive outputs are referred to as “benefits” such as emotional support and trust (Ellison, Gray, & Lampse, 2014). Social exchange theory postulates that people act to maximize their benefits and minimize their costs (Molm, 1997). The overall worth of an exchange derived from such a comparison determines whether a social exchange occurs (Blau, 1964; Molm et al., 2000). Therefore, this study explores these benefit and cost factors through the following qualitative study, then tests them by developing a theory-based research model based on the factors explored earlier.]]></section>
    <section name="Qualitative study;Quantitative study" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
3. Qualitative study
3.1. Research method
We first conducted an exploratory qualitative study. This exploratory study adopted an interview approach; such an approach has several strengths, such as exploring relevant factors and inferring relationships between them in a targeted research context (Yin, 2008). ]]><h target="2" match="part">Interview questions – developed and posed to comply with social exchange theory – dealt with the benefits and costs of posting benevolent comments online.</h><![CDATA[
In recruiting interviewees, we used the snowball sampling technique (Biernacki & Dan, 1981), a process of chain referral: when members of the target population are located, they are asked for the names and contact information of other members of the target population. This technique has been used to create sampling frames with nonprobability methods of selection (Biernacki & Dan, 1981; Sudman & Kalton, 1986). Qualitative studies tend to use a nonprobability sampling approach because the relevance to the research topic determines the data sampling (Neuman, 2006).
For qualitative data collection (i.e., interviews), we first recruited eight students enrolled in courses taught by the co-authors in Korea. All of these recruits had posted comments online at least once before. Each subject then recruited additional interviewees (i.e., their acquaintances). We selected only interviewees who had previously posted benevolent comments online. These first eight students then recruited 49 other persons, all Koreans, with posting experience for a total sample size of 57. These 57 subjects used several online sites such a Nate Pann, Daum Agora, SLR Club, PAXNet, Today’s Humor, and People Using Macs. The number of interviewees was determined by confirming theoretical saturation (Strauss & Corbin, 1998).5 Interviewees comprised 21 students (36.8%), 29 professionals (50.9%), 4 homemakers (7.0%), and 3 others (5.3%). There were 26 females (54.4%) and 31 males (45.6%) interviewees. Their average age was 29.8 years: 6 interviewees were between ages 14 and 19 (10.5%), 22 between ages 20 and 29 (38.6%), 18 between ages 30 and 39 (31.6%), 6 between ages 40 and 49 (10.5%), and 5 older than 49 (8.7%). We conducted face-to-face interviews with each subject. In these open interviews, subjects were asked to list the tangible and intangible benefit and cost factors of their online postings of benevolent comments with three main questions: (1) have you ever posted benevolent comments online before? (2) what benefits are there in your posting of benevolent comments? (3) what costs are there in your posting of benevolent comments? Then they answered additional questions to clarify the factors they listed. The average interview time per person was 10–20 min.
The interview transcripts were subjected to content analysis based on an open coding approach (Corbin & Strauss, 2008). Three researchers participated in this coding. Two researchers coded the data using an open coding approach (Corbin & Strauss, 2008) in which codes were not predetermined but rather emerged from the data. To avoid potential bias, one coder had been uninvolved in the data collection. During the open coding, each coder examined the interview transcripts line by line to identify codes, i.e., concepts, within the textual data that could explain interviewees' decision making. This helped us to develop them into theoretical constructs. Subsequently, a theoretical framework was used to interpret and interrelate the concepts, thus developing our research model for use in the quantitative study.
3.2. Data analysis and results
A total of 159 responses (i.e., codes) from 57 interviewees were conceptualized into the five main concepts (i.e., super-codes) that were derived from the open coding of the transcripts of the interviews on costs and benefits (see Table 1). The inter-rater agreement scores between the two coders averaged 0.82, and Cohen’s Kappa scores (Cohen, Underwood, & Gottliebb, 2000) averaged 0.81. Inter-rater disagreements were reconciled by the third coder who was uninvolved in the data collection and through discussion among the three raters. Next, relevant codes were grouped into five main concepts: four types of benefits and one cost concept. Representative terms were selected as the names of the concepts. As a result, 159 codes were grouped into five concepts (super-codes).
Table 1. Coding results.
Category	Concept	Examples of responses	Frequency (%)
Benefits	Pleasure	I get pleasure from helping others. I feel that I have done something good and feel worthwhile. I feel pleasure and satisfaction by actualizing altruism per se.	42 (35.0%)
Social contribution	An atmosphere on the Internet forums with many nasty comments can be purified. I feel as if I am contributing by sharing my information.	34 (28.3%)
Social companionship	I can feel like I belong to an online community when I write. I can build a companionship by posting a benevolent comment.	17 (14.2%)
Self-presentation	I can reveal myself by presenting my thoughts. I feel like I have become a kind or righteous person through the posting.	16 (13.3%)
Others	I can earn money by posting comments. When I need information, others will leave it for me.	11 (9.2%)

Costs	Social anxiety	Nasty comments like “You are pretending to be nice,” “Do not be pretentious,” and “You look like a part-timer.” I am being blocked by reactions like, “Who the heck are you.”	36 (92.3%)
Others	I need a lot of time to write. It tires me to log in to write.	3 (7.7%)
Total			159
Table 1 shows the overall occurrence of four main concepts in the benefit category and one main concept in the cost category. The four main concepts account for 90.8% of the total responses in the benefit category: pleasure (35.0%), social contribution (28.3%), social companionship (14.2%), and self-presentation (13.3%). The single main concept, social anxiety, accounts for 92.3% of total responses in the cost category.
The coding results revealed that personal psychological benefits (e.g., pleasure and self-presentation) or social benefits (e.g., social contribution and social companionship) in an intrinsic realm were mentioned more frequently. As for cost factors, time and effort tended to be the ones typical for conducting social exchange behavior (Kankanhalli et al., 2005). However, the coding results showed that only a few responses considered time and effort a cost. Instead, this study identified a psychological cost factor, social anxiety, which has not gained much attention in previous research. The subsequent quantitative study tested these cost and benefit factors.

4. Quantitative study
4.1. Theoretical framework
]]><h target="3" match="part">Based on the qualitative study, we developed the theoretical framework (see Fig. 1). Those four benefit factors derived from the coding results were mapped to the benefits category of social exchange theory, and the cost factor was mapped to the costs category of the theory.</h><![CDATA[ Some of the factors were renamed in consideration of the research context, i.e., online. In addition to these benefit and cost factors explored earlier, we proposed a new factor, the perceived net value of posting benevolent comments. Social exchange theory explains that people decide on a social exchange based on its overall worth (i.e., net value) as determined by comparing benefits and costs (Blau, 1964; Molm et al., 2000). The theoretical framework in Fig. 1 explains how the coding results from qualitative study and social exchange theory correspond to our model constructs and interrelationships between factors in terms of net value assessment.
Fig. 1
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Theoretical framework.
This study interprets the posting of benevolent comments mainly as social exchange behavior. According to social exchange theory, all benefit- and cost-related factors indirectly affect social exchange behavior (i.e., posting benevolent comments) through perceived net value. However, some of those factors can directly affect posting behavior. In terms of the relationship between the possible direct effects on posting behavior of the factors we explored, we can further regard a social exchange as a specific type of social behavior (e.g., posting comments in a public online community). For a better and more thorough interpretation of the factors explored in the qualitative study, we also adopted the viewpoint of social choice (i.e., decision making in social behavior) (Margolis, 1984).
Social choice theory explains that people decide social behavior in three ways: rationality, altruism, and self-interest (Margolis, 1984).The first approach in social choice is rationality. From the rationality perspective, people make their social choices based on an assessment of net value through comparison of the benefits and costs of these choices (Blau, 1964; Molm et al., 2000). Net value assessment in social exchange theory corresponds to the rationality motivator in social choice theory. The second approach is altruism, which means that an individual performs an action to benefit others without the expectation of reciprocity or compensation for it (Wakefield, 1993). The third approach is self-interest, which means that an individual performs an action to meet his or her needs or desires (Rocha & Ghoshal, 2006).]]><h target="5" match="part"> We can interpret the decision-making roles of pleasure, online social contribution, and perceived net value, respectively, in terms of self-interest, altruism, and rationality (see Fig. 1).</h> <![CDATA[All three of these will be discussed in the next section. The other three factors (online self-presentation, online social companionship, and online social anxiety) cannot be explained in terms of either the three motivators of social choice or the net value of social exchange theory. For this reason, we do not propose them as direct antecedents as we did in the research model.
In summary, the theoretical framework accomplishes four things. First, it interprets those factors identified from the exploratory qualitative study in terms of social exchange theory and social choice theory. Second, it identifies a new factor that was not detected in either the exploratory qualitative study or in previous research on online posting. Third, it explains the relationships between the identified factors and how these identified factors work together to lead to the posting of benevolent comments. And last, this theoretical framework then becomes the basis for development of the following research model.

4.2. Research model and hypotheses
We developed our research model based on the theoretical framework (see Fig. 2). For a complete interpretation of the factors we identified, we used both the net value assessment of social exchange theory (Blau, 1964; Molm et al., 2000) and the three motivators (self-interest, altruism, and rationality) of social choice (Margolis, 1984) to explain the direct antecedents of posting behavior.Social exchange theory supports the rationality perspective of the direct effect of perceived net value on the intention to post benevolent comments online (Blau, 1964; Molm et al., 2000). This theory also explains the effects of the identified benefit and cost factors on perceived net value. This study also proposes that two factors, online social contribution and pleasure, respectively, have direct effects on the bases of altruism (Wakefield, 1993) and self-interest (Rocha & Ghoshal, 2006) Thus, we applied social exchange theory to six hypotheses (H1, H4, H5, H6, H7, and H8) and social choice theory to three (H1, H2, and H3). We also included three control variables (age, gender, and the frequency of visiting each online site) because age, gender, and experience can influence behavior in an online context.
Fig. 2
Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Research model.
The intention to post benevolent comments means the degree to which one believes that one will post benevolent comments on a selected online site (Lin, 2007). As the core variable of social exchange theory, perceived net value refers to the net benefits (perceived benefits relative to perceived costs) in posting benevolent comments on a selected online site (Sirdeshmukh, Singh, & Sabol, 2002; Zeithaml, 1988). If the benefits exceed the costs, positive net benefits would be perceived, and from the rationality perspective, the individual would be likely to participate in the social exchange because people have a tendency to act in a way that maximizes their net benefit (Blau, 1964; Molm et al., 2000; Zeithaml, 1988). Therefore, as the perceived net value of posting benevolent comments increases, an individual is all the more likely to post benevolent comments on the selected online site.
H1

Perceived net value has a positive impact on the intention to post benevolent comments


This study reflects previous research in defining pleasure as the degree to which an individual feels good or happy with posting benevolent comments on a selected online site (Holbrook, Chestnut, & Olive, 1984). The pursuit of self-interest means an individual’s motivation stems from a drive to do whatever it takes to satisfy his or her individual desires without regard to how those actions affect others (Adams & Maine, 1998). There are two types of self-interest, depending on whether interests other than one’s own are taken into account (Rocha & Ghoshal, 2006). This study considers only one type of self-interest, which is the one in which people are assumed to pursue only their own interests (i.e., egoism) without regard for others’ interests (i.e., altruism). The object of self-interest is pleasure in general (Rocha & Ghoshal, 2006). Furthermore, pleasure has the role of intrinsic motivation (i.e., an interest or enjoyment in an activity), compared with extrinsic motivation (i.e., performance of an activity), in determining human behavior (Ryan & Deci, 2000). Therefore, pleasure related to posting as an intrinsic motivation leads an individual to post benevolent comments in the selected online site because of the individual’s self-interest.
H2

Pleasure has a positive impact on the intention to post benevolent comments


Based on the general concept of social contribution, this study defines online social contribution as the degree to which one believes that one’s posting of benevolent comments is socially valuable in a selected online site (Israel, 1971; Keyes, 1998). Altruism has something to do with an individual’s behavior in benefiting another without the expectation of reciprocity or compensation for it, and that leads to the idea that altruism is defined by the occurrence of a beneficial outcome of an action (Wakefield, 1993). The beneficial outcome of an action leads an individual to choose and perform the action in terms of altruism. By posting benevolent comments on an online site, users may think that they are making a social contribution to the site and benefiting some of its members. Therefore, social contribution as an altruistic outcome should lead people to choose and perform posting benevolent comments on the selected online site.
H3

Online social contribution has a positive impact on the intention to post benevolent comments


As for the benefits in the assessment of net value, there are different types of benefits, such as emotional, functional, and social ones (Rintamaki, Kanto, & Kuusela, 2006; Sweeney & Soutar, 2001). Emotional benefit is a utility based on the arousal of feelings or affective states (Sweeney & Soutar, 2001). People are known to rely on their feelings to form overall judgments (Schwarz & Clore, 1988). Hedonic sources of net value, such as playfulness and entertainment, have long been recognized as affecting net value (Kim, Gupta, & Koh, 2011; Rintamaki et al., 2006). Therefore, as the feeling of pleasure increases from the posting of benevolent comments on the selected online site, the overall net value of the posting should increase.
H4

Pleasure has a positive impact on perceived net value


Functional benefit is a utility acquired from perceived quality and expected performance of behavior (Sweeney & Soutar, 2001). Thus, online social contribution is perceived as a functional benefit from the poster’s perspective because the posting of benevolent comments can function as a way to contribute to a selected online site. Therefore, because one can contribute to an online site by posting benevolent comments, a person should perceive higher net benefits from the posting.
H5

Online social contribution has a positive impact on perceived net value


Social benefit is a utility based on the ability to enhance one’s social well-being, e.g., social image and relationships (Sweeney & Soutar, 2001). Online self-presentation means the extent to which an individual presents his or her preferred images through posting benevolent comments on a selected online site (Kim, Chan, & Kankanhalli, 2012). People have a tendency to present themselves in a preferred manner to others (Schau & Gilly, 2003). Thus, people perceive benefits if they can present their preferred images on an online site (Kankanhalli et al., 2005). Therefore, as people perceive higher benefits from online self-presentation through the posting of benevolent comments, the net benefits of the posting should increase.
H6

Online self-presentation has a positive impact on perceived net value


As another social benefit, online social companionship means the level of online friendship gained from the posting of benevolent comments on a selected online site (Rook, 1987). Social companionship is often referred to as the benefit of friendship gained by sharing activities such as leisure (Rook, 1987). People can make new friends and manage relationships through online communication, i.e., posting benevolent comments, on a selected site. Previous research also has explained that social relationship support is an important benefit in social behavior (Kim et al., 2011). Therefore, as people develop and manage social relationships through posting benevolent comments, they should perceive higher net benefits from the postings.
H7

Online social companionship has a positive impact on perceived net value


As a cost factor, online social anxiety means the level of distress or mental uneasiness resulting from the posting of benevolent comments on a selected online site (Schlenker & Leary, 1982). Social anxiety stands for an anxiety expressed as a result of an individual evaluation that was given or is to be given in a real or imaginary social situation (Schlenker & Leary, 1982). Two different factors exist in social anxiety: a concern over a social situation in general (e.g., giving a public speech, meeting with someone for the first time, and being elected a leader) and a concern over a situation of social failure or disapproval (e.g., being a target of criticism, making a mistake, and being misunderstood) (Schlenker & Leary, 1982). The second category is the one that concerns online social anxiety in this study; it results from a social evaluation that an individual will receive via posting benevolent comments on a selected online site. Therefore, online social anxiety as a psychological cost should decrease the overall net benefits of the posting.
H8

Online social anxiety has a negative impact on perceived net value


4.3. Research method
We developed the survey instrument by adopting existing validated scales wherever possible. Scales for online social contribution were adapted from Keyes (1998). Scales for pleasure were adopted from Holbrook et al. (1984). To assess online self-presentation, we adapted scales from Kim et al. (2012). Scales for online social companionship were modified from Choi, Dekkers, and Park (2004). We developed measurement items for online social anxiety by referring to the scales of La Greca and Lopez (1998). Scales of perceived net value were adapted from Sirdeshmukh et al. (2002). To assess the intention to post benevolent comments, we adapted scales from Lin (2007). Two information systems (IS) researchers reviewed the instrument and checked its face validity. We also conducted a sorting exercise with five IS graduate students as judges. They correctly placed the items onto the intended constructs. Last, the measurement instrument was reviewed in a focus group of four online users to check for any ambiguity of wording or format. The scales are shown in Appendix A. The measurement items, except the pleasure construct, were anchored on seven-point Likert scales (1 = strongly disagree, 7 = strongly agree). Podsakoff, Mackenzie, Lee, & Podsakoff (2003) recommended using different scale endpoints and formats for measures to reduce method biases caused by commonalities in scale endpoints and anchoring effects.
This study surveyed users of several online sites. A database from a market research firm with more than 350,000 panel members was used to create a sample pool of respondents. Then the market research firm randomly selected 5000 members from the pool, each of whom was invited by email to participate in the online survey via a link to the web-based survey questionnaire. For the survey, we selected several online sites where all members can post and read comments in public anonymously (e.g., Nate Pann, Daum Agora, SLR Club, PAXNet, Today’s Humor, and People Using Macs). At the beginning of the survey, participants were asked to choose one of the selected online sites they visit frequently and answer the survey questions in terms of the selected online site. The survey was conducted over a period of one week.

We received 205 valid responses (see Table 2). There were 103 female (50.2%) and 102 (49.8%) male respondents. The average age of respondents was 32.8 years (standard deviation = 11.7): 26 respondents in their 10s (12.7%), 70 in their 20s (34.1%), 43 in their 30s (21.0%), 38 in their 40s (18.5%), and 28 in their 50s or older (13.7%). Respondents comprised 20 middle and high school students (9.8%), 42 undergraduate/graduate students (20.5%), 113 professionals (55.2%), 16 homemakers (7.8%), and 14 others. These respondents are members of and use several online sites, such as Nate Pann (51.2%), Daum Agora (28.3%), SLR Club (5.4%), PAXNet (4.4%), Today’s Humor (2.0%), People Using Macs (2.0%), and others. Each respondent averages visiting the selected online site 8.85 times per week (standard deviation = 17.12). We tested for nonresponse bias by comparing early and late respondents, i.e., those who replied during the first three days and those who responded during the last three days. We found no significant differences between the two respondent groups based on the sample attributes (gender, age, and occupation).
Table 2. Demographics of respondents.
Demographic variable		Frequency (percentage)
Gender	Female	103 (50.2%)
Male	102 (49.8%)

Age (mean = 32.8, standard deviation = 11.7)	10s	26 (12.7%)
20s	70 (34.1)
30s	43 (21.0%)
40s	38 (18.5%)
50s or older	28 (13.7%)

Occupation	Middle and high school students	20 (9.8%)
Undergraduate and graduate students	42 (20.5%)
Professionals	113 (55.2)
Homemakers	16 (7.8%)
Others	14 (6.7%)

Total		205 (100%)
4.4. Data analysis and results
We conducted an exploratory factor analysis (EFA) through principal components analysis with varimax rotation using SPSS. We identified seven factors with an eigenvalue greater than 1.0. When compared across factors, the items loaded highest on their own factors. The seven factors explained 72.34% of the total variance. This study then conducted a confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) using Smart PLS 2.0 in accordance with a two-stage methodology (Anderson and Gerbing, 1999). As shown in Table 3, the standardized path loadings were all significant and exceeded 0.7. The average variance extracted (AVE) for each construct exceeded 0.5. The composite reliability (CR) and Cronbach’s α for all constructs exceeded 0.7. The convergent validity of the measurement instrument was thus supported.
Table 3. Results of convergent validity testing.
Construct	Std. loading of each item	AVE	CR	Cronbach’s α
Online social contribution (CNT)	0.72, 0.88, 0.84, 0.86	0.69	0.90	0.85
Pleasure (PLS)	0.85, 0.90, 0.91, 0.84	0.77	0.93	0.90
Online self-presentation (PRS)	0.92, 0.91, 0.88	0.81	0.93	0.89
Online social companionship (CMP)	0.77, 0.83, 0.84, 0.79	0.65	0.88	0.82
Online social anxiety (ANX)	0.85, 0.94, 0.95	0.84	0.94	0.90
Perceived net value (VAL)	0.90, 0.92, 0.88	0.81	0.93	0.88
Intention to post benevolent comments (INT)	0.90, 0.94, 0.93	0.85	0.95	0.91
The discriminant validity of the measurement model was assessed by comparing the square root AVE for each construct with the correlations between the particular construct and other constructs (Table 4). If the square root of AVE exceeds the correlations between the construct and other constructs, then it indicates discriminant validity (Fornell & Larcker 1981). The square root of AVE for each construct (diagonal term) exceeded the correlations between the construct and other constructs (off-diagonal terms).
Table 4. Descriptive statistics and correlations between latent variables.
Mean	S.D.	CNT	PLS	PRS	CMP	ANX	VAL	INT
CNT	4.78	1.02	0.71						
PLS	4.58	1.11	0.53	0.75					
PRS	4.53	1.19	0.57	0.66	0.74				
CMP	4.15	1.16	0.56	0.49	0.65	0.71			
ANX	4.30	1.44	−0.19	−0.21	−0.36	−0.36	0.89		
VAL	4.30	1.21	0.50	0.57	0.54	0.48	−0.34	0.74	
INT	4.64	1.24	0.56	0.58	0.58	0.52	−0.35	0.69	0.77
Note 1: Leading diagonal in bold font shows the squared root of AVE of each construct.

Note 2: online social contribution (CNT), pleasure (PLS), online self-presentation (PRS), online social companionship (CMP), online social anxiety (ANX), perceived net value (VAL), intention to post benevolent comments (INT).


Because three of the correlation terms in Table 4 exceeded the prescribed threshold of 0.6, we conducted a second test of discriminant validity. This second test used a process of constrained testing as suggested by Anderson and Gerbing (1998). Based on the results of this test (see Table 5), all χ2 statistics (Δχ2 ranges from 215.17 to 450.28) were found significant, indicating that the measurement model was significantly better than alternative models (obtained by combining pairs of latent constructs). Hence, the discriminant validity of the instrument was established.
Table 5. Constrained testing results.
Pair	Base model	Constrained model	χ2 test
χ2	d.f.	χ2	d.f.	Δχ2	Δd.f.	Significance
PRS—PLS	1147.12	558	1597.40	566	450.28	8	p < 0.001
CMP—PRS	1147.12	558	1449.39	566	302.27	8	p < 0.001
INT—VAL	1147.12	558	1362.29	566	215.17	8	p < 0.001
Note: pleasure (PLS), online self-presentation (PRS), online social companionship (CMP), perceived net value (VAL), intention to post benevolent comments (INT).


We then examined the structural model (see Fig. 3). The hypothesis testing results indicate that perceived net value (H1), pleasure (H2), online social contribution (H3), and one control variable (i.e., frequency of visiting to the selected online site) have significant effects on the intention to post benevolent comments, explaining 57% of its variance. The results also indicate that pleasure (H4), online social contribution (H5), and online social anxiety (H8) have significant effects on the perceived net value of posting benevolent comments, explaining 44% of its variance. However, we did not find significant effects of online self-presentation (H6) and online social companionship (H7) on perceived net value.

Fig. 3
Download full-size image
Fig. 3. Results of Structural Model Testing (+: p < 0.1, *: p < 0.05, **: p < 0.01, ***: p < 0.001, ns: insignificant at the 0.1 level).

Because of a lack of support by either social exchange theory or social choice theory, the research model does not propose any direct effects of three factors (online self-presentation, online social companionship, and online social anxiety) on posting intention. We also conducted a post-hoc analysis to test for any direct effects of these three factors on intention to post. However, we still could not detect any significant effect by them on intention to post.

We conducted an additional post-hoc analysis to determine if the perceived net value of posting benevolent comments mediates the effects of benefit and cost factors on intention as posited by social exchange theory (Blau, 1964; Molm et al., 2000). For this purpose, we used a bootstrapping procedure according to the guidelines of Zhao, Lynch, & Chen (2010) and Hayes (2013). We used the PROCESS macro (Hayes 2013) with a 95% confidence interval and 5000 bootstrap resamples that used bias corrected bootstrapping in SPSS version 21. Confidence intervals that do not contain zero indicate a significant indirect effect, i.e., mediation. This testing showed a significant indirect effect of pleasure on intention through perceived net value (indirect effect = 0.3630, standard error = 0.0753, lower confidence interval = 0.2301, upper confidence interval = 0.5273); a significant indirect effect of online social contribution on intention through perceived net value (indirect effect = 0.3505, standard error = 0.0673, lower confidence interval = 0.2275, upper confidence interval = 0.4897); a significant indirect effect of online social anxiety on intention through perceived net value (indirect effect = −0.1912, standard error = 0.0548, lower confidence interval = −0.2997, upper confidence interval = −0.0881).]]></section>
    <section name=" Discussion and implications" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
5. Discussion and implications
5.1. Discussion of findings
This study has three key findings. The most notable finding is that the perceived net value of posting benevolent comments is a main motivator that leads to intention to post. This finding agrees with the social exchange theory (Molm, 1997), which explains that the overall assessment of a social exchange behavior (i.e., posting benevolent comments) determines the behavior. It means that from the rationality perspective, people assess overall net value based on tangible and intangible benefits and costs in deciding to post online. This finding is similar to the significant role of net value assessment in decision making in other contexts, e.g., adoption of mobile Internet services (Kim et al., 2007).
            Our results also showed the significance of the other two factors (online social contribution and pleasure) on intention to post. People decide on their social choices, i.e., posting benevolent comments online, based on altruism and self-interest as well as rationality (Margolis, 1984). The significance of online social contribution and pleasure explain that people decide to post benevolent comments by considering how their posts add value to others (i.e., other members of an online site) as well a benefit themselves. Consideration of the value added to others, i.e., online social contribution, is an altruism-based decision-making approach in social choice (Wakefield, 1993). Consideration of value added to one’s self, i.e., pleasure, is a decision-making approach based on self-interest (Rocha & Ghoshal, 2006). ]]><h target="5" match="part">Thus, the significance of these three factors (perceived net value, online social contribution, and pleasure) explains the three ways in which social behavior is determined: rationality, altruism, and self-interest (Margolis, 1984).</h><![CDATA[
Our next finding was that three factors (pleasure, online social contribution, and online social anxiety) have significant effects on perceived net value. Of all the benefit factors explored in the qualitative study, only two (online social contribution and pleasure) are significant to perceived net value. Online social contribution and pleasure represent benefits, respectively, to the corresponding social group and to the self. This finding explains that social benefit (i.e., online social contribution) and personal benefit (i.e., pleasure) increase the perception of net value. As a cost factor, online social anxiety has a significant effect on perceived net value. There are monetary and nonmonetary costs. In the online context, nonmonetary costs play an important role in decision making. This finding explains that social anxiety represents a psychological cost in assessing the overall value of posting benevolent comments on an online site.
However, we did not find a significant effect of online self-presentation on perceived net value. This could be because the level of self-exposure is quite low in online postings so that it is hard to feel value by projecting identity. Specifically, on the online sites used for this study, people tend to present themselves only through nicknames or identities that preserve anonymity, which from the self-presentation perspective makes it difficult to perceive much value in posting. Another potential reason is the mediating effect of pleasure on the relationship between online self-presentation and perceived net value. People can derive pleasure from having an online presence because it can lead to recognition by others (Ma & Agarwal, 2007). That is, people may gain pleasure from their online self-presentation that they and others can view. A post-hoc analysis with the bootstrapping procedure shows that online self-presentation is indirectly significant to net value through pleasure (indirect effect = 0.2485, standard error = 0.0563, lower confidence interval = 0.1459, upper confidence interval = 0.3720). Online self-presentation has a significant effect on pleasure, explaining 39% of its variance (see Fig. 3).
The study also did not find a significant effect of online social companionship on perceived net value. The communication environment in an online context is very restrictive in most cases (Tang, 2010). Moreover, most users of the online sites used for this study do not have offline interactions with each other, unlike with Facebook. The characteristics of non-face-to-face interaction make it difficult to find social companionship in such an online context (Amichai-Hamburger, Kinsbury, & Schneider, 2013). Consequently, people do not seem to perceive much value from the online social companionship perspective in this context.
5.2. Limitations and future research direction
This study has several limitations. First, this study used an exploratory qualitative study based on interviews to explore the potential benefit- and cost-related decisional factors in terms of social exchange theory. As described by Yin (2008), such an approach risks reflexivity (i.e., an interviewee may say what he or she thinks the interviewer wants to hear) that can bias the results. Second, the study explained the decision making in posting benevolent comments online in terms of rationality, altruism, and self-interest in accordance with previous research (Margolis, 1984). We cannot rule out the possibility that posting benevolent comments online is a function of other variables that the model does not take into account. For example, there can be extrinsic and intrinsic motivational factors (Ryan & Deci, 2000). Future research can test different decisional factors from diverse theoretical perspectives and identify the most influential perspective and determining factors in decisions to post benevolent comments. The characteristics of online sites (e.g., membership, offline relationships, use of real identities, and online site norm) and traits of individuals (e.g., kindness and social skills) can also affect posting behavior. Furthermore, this study collected data from subjects in Korea. Future research can test the effect of cultural differences on posting behavior.
Third, the use of a single source of data in the quantitative study, which can cause common method bias, may also be a limitation of this study. Future research should consider using objective data, such as the number of postings. Future research should also collect objective data with which to analyze the content of each posting. For example, a text mining approach with sentiment analysis can classify each posted comment as either benevolent or abusive. Next, despite our proposed posting of benevolent comments as a way to counter cyberbullying, we have not clearly examined the consequences of such postings. Future research should examine their effectiveness as tools to end cyberbullying.

5.3. Implications for research
]]><h target="1" match="part">This study offers several key implications for research, especially because it is among the first to use a mixed methods approach in combination with social exchange theory to comprehensively examine the decision factors leading to the posting of benevolent comments online.</h><![CDATA[ This study especially serves as an initial attempt to examine the posting of benevolent comments online as a way to combat cyberbullying. Anticyberbullying campaigns2,3,4 commonly highlight the importance of promoting the posting of benevolent comments while stopping the posting of malicious comments that amount to cyberbullying. Previous research examined the reasons for cyberbullying (Varjas et al., 2010) and discussed strategies and guidance for school counselors and parents to use in the prevention of cyberbullying (Beale & Hall, 2007; Bhat, 2008; Diamanduros et al., 2008). Previous research lacked an explanation of the motivation to post benevolent comments. Thus, this study adds value to the literature on cyberbullying by examining the posting of benevolent comments as a way to combat this online bad conduct.
This study has another implication in terms of extending how social exchange theory can be applied across mixed methods. The previous research lacked a theory-based empirical explanation of what factors lead to the posting of benevolent comments. In contrast, this study adopted mixed methods based on the application of social exchange theory (Blau, 1964; Molm et al., 2000). Although both quantitative and qualitative research are valuable alone, a mixed methods approach is potentially superior to a single method design because it can provide richer insights into the target phenomena and develop novel theoretical models (Lee et al., 2013).]]><h target="2" match="part">Based on the key argument (i.e., cost-benefit analysis of the worth of social exchanges) of social exchange theory, this study in its first stage explored benefit- and cost-related decision factors through a qualitative research method.</h> <![CDATA[The second stage then interpreted how these decision factors work together and lead to the posting of benevolent comments based on social exchange theory and on the three perspectives (rationality, altruism, and self-interest) involved in social choice (Margolis, 1984). Thus, the study contributes to the literature by identifying factors (e.g., social anxiety, perceived net value) and generating new insights into how these identified factors work together to lead to the posting of benevolent comments. Specifically, this study contains the three main implications of social exchange theory: (1) guiding the first stage qualitative study in exploring cost and benefit related factors in the posting (Table 1), (2) interpreting those explored factors and the interrelationships between them in the theoretical framework (Fig. 1), and (3) explaining how the factors work together and lead to the posting of benevolent comments (Fig. 2).
Last, this study contributes to our understanding of decisional factors that lead directly and indirectly to the posting of benevolent comments. Specifically, this study demonstrates that perceived net value directly motivates people to post benevolent comments in keeping with social exchange theory and the rationality perspective (Margolis, 1984). This study further demonstrates that online social contribution and pleasure, respectively, motivate people to post benevolent comments because of altruism and self-interest (Margolis, 1984). As for indirect relationships, this study demonstrates that perceived net value mediates the effects of benefit- and cost-related factors (i.e., online social contribution, pleasure, and online social anxiety) on intention to post benevolent comments.
5.4. Implications for practice
If cyberbullies frequent a specific SNS, it becomes known for its malicious posts and content. Continued and persistent of such posts will lead to dissatisfaction and social network fatigue among other users and cause many of them to abandon the SNS (Zhang, Zhao, Lu, & Yang, 2015). Thus, combating cyberbullying is important for the sustainability of SNS providers. For this reason, SNS providers need to understand how to combat cyberbullying. In line with this, there are several anticyberbullying campaigns (e.g., “The Big March” campaign, “Sunfull” campaign, and “Help Stop the Stomping” campaign on Facebook). All have in common the goals of not only stopping the posting of malicious comments, but also of motivating people to post benevolent comments.
From a practical perspective, this study has implications for promoting the posting of benevolent comments to combat cyberbullying and create a new benevolent culture in the cyber world. As exemplified in the “Help Stop the Stomping” campaign and the “Sunfull” campaign, helping others by posting benevolent comments online is a typical example of prosocial behavior on the Internet (Son, Lee, Cho, & Kim, 2016; Sproull et al., 2005). The findings in this study explain how people decide to post benevolent comments, which informs SNS providers how to promote the posting of such comments on their sites. Specifically, these providers should pay attention to the roles four significant factors (perceived net value, online social contribution, pleasure, and online social anxiety) play in motivating the posting of benevolent comments.
Our findings suggest that SNS providers should understand that online users assess the overall net value of posting benevolent comments based on a comparison between the relevant costs and benefits. Therefore, SNS providers should work to improve the net value of such postings. The assessment of net value considers not only tangible elements but also intangible elements, such as psychological ones. According to our findings, two intangible benefit factors (pleasure and online social contribution) increase net value.
Pleasure in posting benevolent comments and online social contribution through such postings represent personal and social aspects, respectively, of online activity. That is, people may feel that they contribute to an online site by posting benevolent comments (e.g., helping others by providing emotional support, posting positive comments, and providing advice online to people in need). SNS providers should consider how to design a system to highlight the contribution of each user in relation to each posting. For example, SNS systems can assess and display the social contribution score of each user. The assessment can be done based on the frequency and content of postings. Each posting can also be assessed by other users, i.e., readers of each posted comment, which is similar to the ‘Like’ function of Facebook.

A social contribution score developed as part of a new system design can affect the pleasure of each user. People may perceive pleasure by their posting of benevolent comments alone. They may also perceive pleasure by checking their social contribution explicitly, based on a contribution score. Furthermore, those users may feel even greater pleasure if they could receive feedback from readers about their postings. Sticker-like graphics (e.g., emoticons) have been used as messages in the use of SNS.6 It may be possible to design SNS in a new way so that people can reply to each posted comment by posting stickers. Such graphical stickers might provide a more pleasurable experience for users, i.e., readers, as well as posters.
We also found that one psychological cost factor, online social anxiety, decreases net value. People worry about how others will respond to their posting benevolent comments online. That is, some users may reply to others’ postings by posting abusive comments. SNS providers can identify those who frequently post abusive comments as responses to others’ posting and consider limiting their postings. The system also can consider identifying a list of malicious words that should not be used in the postings. It may be possible to prohibit the use of such words. Overall, this study takes an important step in examining the posting of benevolent comments as a form of online prosocial behavior with a potential to combat anticyberbullying. We hope that more effort will be devoted to this important research area and that the proposed model will serve as a useful guide for such future work.]]></section>
</publication>