<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="wang xueyan">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 6, Part B, December 2016, Pages 1174-1183</time>
    <title>Solving knowledge sharing disparity: The role of team identification, organizational identification, and in-group bias</title>
    <author>Yu-Qian Zhu.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspace
Department of Information Management, National Taiwan University of Science and Technology, No.43, Sec. 4, Keelung Rd., Da'an Dist., Taipei 106, Taiwan, ROC
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.08.003</doi>
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">We validate the existence of knowledge sharing disparity in organizations: people are more willing to share within their own team than to the whole organization.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">Strong team identification, coupled with weak organizational identification predicts knowledge sharing disparity.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">In-group bias was found to mediate the relationship between team identification, organizational identification and knowledge sharing disparity.</highlight>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
Knowledge sharing across team boundaries in an organization is important for two reasons: first, teams can learn from each other and benefit from new knowledge developed by other units (Cohen & Levinthal, 1990), thus reduce duplication of efforts and gain valuable complementary expertise such as technological know-how and knowledge about markets (Hansen, 1999), which helps to avoid the risk of reinventing the wheel or repeating past mistakes, and ultimately improves organizational performance (Almeida & Soares, 2014). Second, knowledge transfer among organizational units provides opportunities for mutual learning and internal cooperation that stimulate the creation of new knowledge and innovation, which in the long term contributes to the firm’s competitiveness (Tsai, 2001).
However, in most organizations, the sharing of knowledge is greatly hindered by functional and divisional boundaries: what one group or unit learns typically does not get shared with the other groups or units in the organization (Hansen, 1999; Jarvenpaa & Staples, 2001; Tsai, 2001). Jarvenpaa and Staples (2001) observed that knowledge is mostly disseminated to other individuals in the same group, while only occasionally does some of the knowledge get distributed through formal systems, i.e., the corporate knowledge management system (KMS) to the whole organization so that it can be shared with “organizationally-remote strangers they will never meet in person” (Constant, Kiesler, & Sproull, 1994). We define this as knowledge sharing disparity, i.e. the fact that people are far more likely to share with members in their work group than with other teams in the organization.
Although prior research has investigated knowledge sharing in organizations from various lenses (Ghobadi, 2015; Wang & Noe, 2010), such as organizational/team contexts, social capital, cultural characteristics, motivational factors, individual characteristics and knowledge ownership perceptions (e.g., Constant et al., 1994; Jarvenpaa & Staples, 2001), little systematic research exists that 1) validates that the knowledge sharing disparity in organizations really exists, 2) examines knowledge sharing from a within-team versus across team perspective by juxtaposing within-team sharing and sharing with organization KMS, and 3) explores the reasons for the knowledge sharing disparity. Indeed, if the sharing of knowledge is no longer hindered by functional and divisional boundaries, and if we share as much to organization KMS as we do to our team mates, everybody and every team benefits. In this research, we try to address the knowledge sharing disparity issue by first validating its existence, then investigating its causes from an identification and in-group bias perspective. We examine the interplay between team identification and organizational identification, and their joint effects on the knowledge sharing disparity and in-group bias. With this research, we hope to enhance our understanding of the knowledge sharing disparity phenomenon, explore ways to tackle it, and ultimately enable the movement of knowledge to be equally fluent within and across team boundaries.]]></section>
    <section name="Theoretical background and hypotheses" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Theoretical background and hypotheses
2.1. Why we share: the motivational perspective of knowledge sharing
Constant et al. (1994) assert that knowledge and expertise belongs to a special category of information that is part of people's identity. Indeed, knowledge and information can be seen as an asset that is to be owned and controlled by individuals in order to elevate their own power and status relationships in organizations (Markus, 1983). Thus, individuals go through rational decision making process to share when expected benefits outweigh costs (time, effort, power etc) (Bock, Zmud, Kim, & Lee, 2005). As knowledge and expertise are highly valued, an individual that chooses to share knowledge risks losing his/her unique value in the organization (Bock et al., 2005). Therefore, organizations investing in knowledge management systems often face difficulties in getting employees to share their ideas (Cabrera & Cabrera, 2002).
To facilitate knowledge sharing, it is important to understand why we share. If we zoom our focus on the motivational factors of knowledge sharing, noticeably in extant research there are two not-mutually-exclusive perspectives. The first perspective takes the view of knowledge sharing as an economic exchange, where individuals behave out of rational self-interest. Thus, knowledge sharing will occur when there are immediate, explicit benefits like monetary reward, profit sharing, gain sharing, employee stock options or credits towards promotion (e.g. Cabrera, Collins, & Salgado, 2006; Bartol & Srivastava, 2002; Bock et al., 2005; Wang & Hou, 2015). The other perspective sees knowledge sharing as social exchange, where participants expect future, moral-obligated returns rather than immediate rewards for sharing their knowledge (Blau, 1964). Social factors such as relationship building, reputation, trust and social capital are brought forth into the picture (Chiu, Hsu, & Wang, 2006; Hashim & Tan, 2015; Hau, Kim, Lee, & Kim, 2013; Hsu & Lin, 2008; Liang, Liu, & Wu, 2008). In social exchange, although self-interest is still at play, interdependence among participants becomes an important factor as well (Lawler & Thye, 1999), thus participants are willing to forego explicit, immediate returns typical of economic exchange to build relationships through sharing, with an expectation of future reciprocal returns.
Social exchange, however, is placed against the context of social interactions (Blau, 1964), as social distance increases, trust and reciprocity decrease (Buchan, Croson, & Dawes, 2002). For these distant strangers in other business units that an individual may have little or no chance of interacting with, social exchange may not be able to exert its influence. Kogut and Zander (1996) point out that the knowledge-based view of the firm brings into sharp focus the importance of identity as “firms provide a sense of community by which discourse, coordination and learning are structured by identity.”, Research suggests that “identification can exist in the absence of interpersonal interaction and group cohesion” (Cardador & Pratt, 2006: p. 175). Thus, identification becomes another important aspect in knowledge sharing intentions.
Some earlier research has investigated identification and sharing intentions in various contexts. Kankanhalli, Tan, and Wei (2005) argued that when identification is strong, the need for organizational reward and the consideration of the cost for knowledge sharing such as effort required may not be significant factors to knowledge contributors because the concern for organizational outcomes may dominate. Ravishankar and Pan (2008) see identification as both influential and relevant to knowledge management research; Chiu et al. (2006) reported that identification was positively related to the quantity of knowledge shared in virtual communities, Hsu and Lin (2008) found that community identification contributed to blogger’s intention to share via blogging. Chang and Chuang (2011) discovered that identification was positively related to both the quality and quantity of knowledge sharing in virtual communities. Table 1 below provides a comparison of these three perspectives in knowledge sharing literature.
Table 1. Perspectives on knowledge sharingn.
Economic exchange	Social exchange	Identification
Characteristics	Has clear, explicit terms of transaction; return or rewards are usually immediate	Does not have clear explict terms of transaction. Participants expect future, moral-obligated returns	The “self” is merged into the group through identification, knowledge sharing is not viewed as “transaction” any more
Factors involved	Monetary reward, profit sharing, gain sharing, stock options, credits towards promotion	Trust, reputation, organization support, organization commitment	Social identity
Role of self-interest	Very important	Important, but relationship building comes into play	The person acts out of the interest of the group, instead of self-interest.
Exchange partners	The organization, since rewards typically come from organizational level policies	The receivers of the knowledge, as well as the organization	Other people in the same group
Sample literature	Cabrera et al., 2006; Bartol & Srivastava, 2002; Bock et al., 2005; 2005; Wang & Hou, 2015	Chiu et al., 2006; Hashim & Tan, 2015; Hau et al., 2013; Hsu & Lin, 2008; 2005; Liang et al., 2008	Ravishankar & Pan, 2008; Chiu et al., 2006; Hsu & Lin, 2008; Chang & Chuang, 2011; 2005
2.2. Multiple identifications in organizations and the knowledge sharing disparity
Tajfel (1972) defined social identity as the “individual’s knowledge that he belongs to certain social groups together with some emotional and value significance to him of this group membership.” Social identification is the internalization of a social identity (Ashforth & Mael, 1989). Through identification, an individual perceives him or herself as psychologically intertwined with the fate of the group, as sharing a common destiny and experiencing its successes and failures (Mael & Ashforth, 1992). In adopting the identity of the group, the individual experiences corresponding change in motives, expectations, affective connotations, background knowledge, beliefs, norms, and values (Turner & Onorato, 1999). Identification encourages the individual to vicariously partake in accomplishments beyond his or her powers (Katz & Kahn, 1978), or even undertake personally harmful activities worthwhile insofar as they aid the larger self (Staw, 1984).
Social identity defines how we as individuals interact with relevant social groups. With social identity, an individual is no longer just an individual (personal identity), but also part of a group (Abrams & Hogg, 1990; Turner & Onorato, 1999), where one is psychologically intertwined with the fate of the group, and personally experiences the successes and failures of the group (Ashforth & Mael, 1989). Under the influence of social identity, individuals may display motives and behaviour that conflict with their personal identities (Ashforth & Mael, 1989), for example, sharing knowledge to the rest of the team. Thus, social identity has the potential to overcome the innate problem of personal boundaries of knowledge and to move valuable knowledge from person to person, and from group to group. Knowledge sharing is no longer considered an exchange, as the “self” is merged into the group through identification (van Knippenberg & Hogg, 2003). The person becomes one with the group and acts out of the interest of the group, instead of self-interest (Ashforth & Mael, 1989). Therefore, instead of calculated behaviour such as “if you scratch my back, I will scratch yours” or “one good turn deserves another”, sharing in the context of social identification becomes “one for all and all for one”. It becomes like what you would do to your family members: you share because you are one team and one family.
Identification could encourage the individual to undertake personally harmful activities to aid their social group (Staw, 1984). Thus, although knowledge is deemed as an asset that is to be owned and controlled by individuals in order to elevate their own power and status relationships in organizations (Markus, 1983), he or she may be willing to sacrifice his/her own control of personal knowledge for the good of the whole social group, as long as he or she identifies with the social group. Therefore, the level of identification determines the level of knowledge sharing. For organizations in which people have similar levels of organization and team identification, there should be no knowledge sharing disparity, as they should be equally likely to share with the team and with organization KMS. However, if people identify more with their teams rather than with organization, then it is possible that there is a gap in the sharing within team and with organization KMS.
Through a meta analysis of 40 independent samples, Riketta and Van Dick (2005) reported that people are more likely to identify with their teams than with the organization First, people want to fit in and stand out at the same time, and this balance can best be achieved by belonging to smaller categories rather than to large inclusive groups (Riketta & Van Dick, 2005). This leads to a preference for the team instead of the organization as a target for identification (Knippenberg & Schie, 2000). Second, people are more likely to identify with social groups with which they are more familiar with and which they perceive to be more similar to the self (Knippenberg & Schie, 2000). As people spend most of their organizational life in teams, their workgroup membership should be perceptually more salient than their organizational membership (Riketta & Van Dick, 2005). Thus, it is highly likely that there is knowledge sharing disparity in organizations due to the fact that people identify more with their teams than with the organization. However, up till this day, it has only been conceptually developed, but never tested empirically. This research tries to validate the existence of the knowledge sharing disparity and examining the antecedents of the knowledge sharing disparity by proposing:
H1

There are knowledge sharing disparities in organizations: individuals are more willing to share with his/her own team than sharing with organization KMS


If identification is a key driver in knowledge sharing, it follows that high identification with the team will contribute to the knowledge sharing disparity, i.e. the gap between knowledge shared within teams and with the organization KMS, as it widens the gap by increasing sharing with the team; while high identification with the organization will decrease the knowledge sharing disparity, as it drives people to acts out of the interest of the organization (Ashforth & Mael, 1989) by sharing more with the organization, thereby closing the gap. Therefore, we propose:
H2

Team identification is positively associated with the knowledge sharing disparity

H3

Organizational identification is negatively associated with the knowledge sharing disparity.


2.3. In-group bias as a result of multiple identifications
Theory suggests that strong identification with a social group may lead to in-group bias: the systematic tendency to evaluate one’s own membership group (the in-group) or its members more favorably than a non-membership group (the out-group) or its members (Hewstone, Rubin, & Willis, 2002). Therefore, we believe that identification can influence knowledge sharing disparity not only directly, but also indirectly via in-group bias. People in organizations possess both team identification and organizational identification. How do they manage two identities? Social identity complex theory maintains that for memberships in multiple in-groups that are not fully convergent or overlapping, the individual is faced with the choice of a primary social identity (Roccas & Brewer, 2002). Perceived similarity, proximity, shared goals, and common perceived enemies or threats can affect identification with a group, and thus affecting the choices of a primary social identity in organizations (Turner, 1987). Prior research validated that people are more likely to identify with their teams than with the organization (Riketta & Van Dick, 2005). In today’s organizations with the increasing use of internal competition to foster performance (Baer, Leenders, Oldham, & Vadera, 2010), teams are frequently asked to compete with other teams in the same organization for rewards and favorable evaluations, which may lead to the exclusion of members from competing teams to an employee’s in-group. Furthermore, the prevalence of territoriality in organizations, i.e. an individual’s or a team’s behavioral expression of his or her feelings of ownership toward a physical or social object such as projects, key knowledge, office space (Brown, Lawrence, & Robinson, 2005) also accentuates the in-group and out-group differences within the same organization. Therefore, it is likely that individuals will choose their team as the primary social identity, and view their own team as the in-group, whereas other teams in the organization as out-groups.
Therefore, we have:
H4

Team identification is positively related to in-group bias.


If, however, people develop strong organizational identification, then the in-group (team) versus out-group (rest of the organization) difference should become blurred, and the out-group (rest of the organization) may converge with the in-group. Roccas and Brewer (2002) reasoned that when the overlap of multiple group identities is perceived to be high, the individual maintains a relatively simplified identity structure whereby memberships in different groups converge to form a single in-group identification (Roccas & Brewer, 2002), i.e., both organization and team become in-groups. Brown and Williams (1984) suggested that individuals that treat their group identity as synonymous with their organization identity are unlikely to view other groups negatively. Ashforth and Mael (1989) argued that the tendency of in-group bias is likely to occur where organization identity is weak and groups are clearly differentiated and bounded. In organizations where there is strong organizational identification, it is unlikely that there are strong in-groups as strong organizational identification unifies every organization member (Ashforth & Mael, 1989). Therefore, we propose:
H5

Organizational identification is negatively related in-group bias.


2.4. In-group bias and the knowledge sharing disparity
In-group bias theory predicts that people has a systematic tendency to evaluate one’s own membership group (the in-group) or its members more favorably than a non-membership group (the out-group) or its members (Hewstone et al., 2002), i.e., in-group favorism. There are two possible consequences of in-group biases: in-group favorism, and out-group negativity, i.e., negative attitudes, evaluations, and treatment toward out-groups (Tajfel & Turner 1979). Studies have found that in-group is strongly favored in knowledge sharing and external knowledge may be considered as invalid and unreliable (Adler & Kwon, 2002). Similarly, in-group bias for one’s own team would execrate the knowledge sharing disparity as it intensifies the differences between “us” and “them” in an organization, thus hurting the willingness to share with organization KMS, as a reflection of out-group negativity. At the same time, in-group bias may further add to the willingness to share within the team (in-group favorism), resulting in wider gaps in the knowledge sharing disparity. Thus, we propose:
H6

In-group bias is positively related to intentions to share with the team

H7

In-group bias is negatively related to intentions to share with organization KMS

H8

In-group bias is positively related to the knowledge sharing disparity.]]></section>
    <section name="Research method" category="methods">
        <![CDATA[
3. Research method
3.1. Respondents and procedure
Survey data collection was commissioned to the market research firm iSurvey in Taiwan. iSurvey sent out 4890 online solicitations to random samples of their nation-wide panel of 180,000 adults over 18 who had expressed an interest in participating in iSurvey’s research projects. Participants were compensated with “survey cash,” which could eventually be converted into a monetary compensation. 1500 (31 percent) responded positively to our request for participation. As our survey had a number of requirements, such as 1) participants work in organizations that have knowledge management system implemented and in use; 2) participants work in teams, rather than independently, many respondents did not pass the eligibility screening, leaving a total of 283 complete responses. Due to contractual terms with iSurvey, data from the first 250 participants who completed the survey were provided for analysis (Fig. 1).
The questionnaire followed a translation-back translation procedure to ensure that the accuracy of the translation (Brislin, 1970). A pre-test was held with 12 engineers from a system integration company to evaluate the clarity and interpretability of the questionnaire. Pilot test was carried out by iSurvey with 20 members. Table 2 below captures the demographic information about our sample. Our sample covers a wide range of industries (20 in total), education levels, tenure with company, and job functions, which we consider as a strength that could lead to wider generalizability of the results compared with samples from a single company, or a single industry.
Table 2. Sample demographics (n = 250).
Demographic	Category	Percentage	Count (n)
Age	20–29	28.0%	70
30–39	32.0%	80
40–49	33.6%	84
50 and above	6.4%	16
Gender	Male	49.2%	123
Female	50.8%	127
Education	High school	2.4%	6
Associate degree	18.8%	47
Bachelor's degree	54.0%	135
Master's and above	24.8%	62
Tenure in current organization	less than 1 year	18.4%	48
1–5 years	32.4%	81
6–10 years	22.4%	56
11–15 years	12.0%	30
16–20 years	6.8%	17
21 years and above	8.0%	20
Industry	Agriculture	0.8%	2
Manufacturing	36.4%	91
Services	62.8%	157
Job function	Sales	26.4%	66
Marketing	10.8%	27
R&D	22.8%	57
manufacturing	4.4%	11
Quality	4.0%	10
Purchasing	1.2%	3
Finance	5.6%	14
HR	3.6%	9
Administration	2.0%	5
3.2. Measures
All measurement items were adapted from prior research (see Appendix for measurement items). Organizational identification and team identification were from Mael and Ashforth (1992), and were directly measured with seven-point Likert scales (ranging from 1 = strongly disagree to 7 = strongly agree), whereas in-group bias and knowledge sharing disparity was measured indirectly. In-group bias was adapted from Esses, Haddock, & Zanna, 1993, and was operationalized by substracting one’s attitude towards other teams in the organization from one’s attitude towards his/her own team (Mummendey & Schreiber, 1983; Levin, Van Laar, & Sidanius, 2003). Attitude was measured with semantic differentials and a feeling thermometer (Esses et al., 1993). The semantic differentials consisted of rating one’s own team, as well as other teams in the organization on four items anchored at −3 (lazy, bad, negative, unpleasant) and +3 (hardworking, good, positive, pleasant). The feeling thermometer asked participants to rate one’s own team and other teams in the organization by selecting a number between 0–100, with zero anchored at cold/negative and 100 anchored at warm/positive. The responses from the semantic differentials and the feeling thermometer were then converted into 1–7 points for analysis. Knowledge sharing intention items were from Bock et al. (2005). The knowledge disparity was calculated by substracting one’s intentions to share with organization KMS from one’s intentions to share with his/her own team following prior research on disparity (Harper et al., 2008).]]></section>
    <section name="Analysis and results" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
4. Analysis and results
4.1. Reliability, validity, and correlations
The data was analyzed using Partial Least Squares (PLS) analysis with SmartPLS 2.0 M3 (Christian, Wende, & Becker, 2014) and SPSS. Kolmogorov–Smirnov and Shapiro–Wilk tests showed that all the variables deviated significantly from normality, thereby limiting the validity of maximum likelihood estimation techniques. Given the sample characteristics, partial least squares (PLS) estimation technique was chosen as it makes no distributional assumptions (Chin, 1998). PLS is an advanced structural equation modelling technique that supports both exploratory and confirmatory research, and tests the measurement model and theoretical model simultaneously (Chin, 1998).
The adequacy of the measurement model was verified using several indices of reliability and validity. First, we performed EFA and deleted several items due to cross loading. The final EFA results were reported in the Appendix. Second, the loadings of items on their respective constructs were examined to establish convergent and discriminant validity. Items with low loading were deleted. As shown in Table 3, all remaining items exceeded the recommended threshold of 0.60 (Hair, Black, Babin, Anderson, & Tatham, 2006), exhibiting satisfactory convergent reliability. Finally, internal consistency of each scale was assessed using composite reliability and Cronbach’s alpha, for which the lowest values were 0.87 and 0.81 respectively. Furthermore, the average variance extracted (AVE) for all constructs exceeded Chin’s (1998) guideline of 0.5.
Table 3. Results of reliability and validity.
Item number	Item loading	Item number	Item loading
Team identification	Willingness to share with team
CR = 0.91, Alpha = 0.88, AVE = 0.72	CR = 0.94, Alpha = 0.92, AVE = 0.76
1	0.81	1	0.86
2	0.91	2	0.91
3	deleted due to cross loading	3	0.90
4	0.83	4	0.81
5	0.83	5	0.87
organizational identification	Willingness to share with organization KMS
CR = 0.93, Alpha = 0.89, AVE = 0.82	CR = 0.92, Alpha = 0.90, AVE = 0.75
1	0.87	1	0.87
2	deleted due to cross loading	2	0.93
3	deleted due to cross loading	3	0.91
4	0.94	4	0.74
5	0.92	5	deleted due to cross loading
In-group bias	Knowledge sharing disparity
CR = 0.92, Alpha = 0.89, AVE = 0.74	CR = 0.87, Alpha = 0.81, AVE = 0.63
1	deleted due to low loading	1	0.79
2	0.86	2	0.89
3	0.89	3	0.67
4	0.85	4	0.81
5	0.84		
Finally, discriminant validity was examined in three ways. First, Barclay, Higgins, and Thompson (1995) suggested that the square root of average variance extracted (AVE) for each construct should be larger than the inter-construct correlation. Second, the loading of an item within a construct should be greater than its loading in other constructs. Finally, discriminant validity was also assessed by examining factor correlations. Factor correlations should be less than 0.80 for discriminant validity (Kling, 2001). The correlation matrix in Table 4 and the EFA results in Appendix showed that all three criterion for discriminant validity have been met after the deletion of items.
Table 4. Descriptive statistics and correlation matrix.
Variables	Mean	S.D.	M3	M4	Correlation Matrix
TID	OID	BIAS	ITTM	ITKM	DISP
Team identification (TID)	5.01	0.98	−0.39	0.26	0.85					
Organization identification (OID)	4.87	1.00	−0.54	1.25	0.70	0.91				
In-group bias (BIAS)	0.36	0.87	−0.51	5.27	0.22	0.00	0.86			
Intentions to share with team(ITTM)	5.43	0.90	−0.59	0.31	0.66	0.46	0.31	0.87		
Intentions to share with KMS (ITKM)	5.16	0.96	−0.58	0.37	0.55	0.44	0.01	0.77	0.87	
Knowledge sharing disparity (DISP)	0.22	0.50	1.56	4.58	0.10	−0.05	0.40	0.25	−0.40	0.79
M3: skewness; M4: kurtosis. The diagonal line of correlation matrix represents the square root of AVE.


The discriminant validity of knowledge sharing with team and knowledge sharing with organization KMS is further ensured with the paired-sample T-test of intentions to share with team and intentions to share with KMS. We tested whether there is difference between an individual’s intentions to share with the team and to share with organizational KMS. Results showed a significant higher mean of intentions to share with team than intentions to share with KMS for the sample. The mean difference between intentions to share with team and intentions to share with KMS is 0.27, with a standard deviation of 0.64, t = 6.70, and P = 0.000, demonstrating that there is really difference between the two constructs. Table 3 and 4 summarized these results.
In addition, we conducted Harman’s one-factor test to identify if common method bias is of concern with our data (Podsakoff, MacKenzie, Lee, & Podsakoff, 2003). The results showed that the highest covariance explained from a single component was 37.6%, indicating that common method bias does not constitute a major issue.
4.2. Hypotheses testing
Hypothesis 1 was tested via conducting paired-sample T-test of intentions to share with team and intentions to share with KMS in SPSS. Results showed significant higher intentions to share with team than intentions to share with KMS item per item (Table 5). For each item measuring intentions to share, intentions to share with team is significantly higher than intentions to share with organization KMS. The mean difference between intentions to share with team and intentions to share with KMS is 0.27, with a standard deviation of 0.64, t = 6.70, and P = 0.000. Thus, hypothesis 1 is supported. There is indeed knowledge sharing disparities among sharing in teams, and sharing with organization KMS.
Table 5. Paired sample tests for H1.
Paired Differences	s.d.	s.e.	t	df	Sig. (2-tailed)
1	sharing with team 1-sharing with KMS 1	0.30	0.88	0.06	5.39	249	0.00
2	sharing with team 1-sharing with KMS 2	0.28	0.81	0.05	5.48	249	0.00
3	sharing with team 1-sharing with KMS 3	0.24	0.76	0.05	5.07	249	0.00
4	sharing with team 1-sharing with KMS 4	0.30	0.71	0.04	6.63	249	0.00
s.d.: standard deviation; s.e.: standard error mean, t: t value; df: degree of freedom.


Hypotheses 2 and 3 argued that team identification is positively related to the knowledge sharing disparity, while organizational identification is negatively related to the knowledge sharing disparity. We ran these two hypotheses in SmartPLS with knowledge sharing disparity as the dependent variable, and team identification and organizational identification as independent variables. The results show that as predicted, team identification is positively related to the knowledge sharing disparity (beta = 0.37, T = 2.99, P < 0.01); and organizational identification is negatively related to the knowledge sharing disparity (beta = −0.33, T = −2.64, P < 0.01). Therefore, H2 and H3 are both supported.
H4 to H8 explored the mediation of in-group bias in the identification—sharing disparity relationship. The hypotheses were tested using SmartPLS. Fig. 3 summarized the results.
H4 and H5 proposed that team identification is positively related to in-group bias and organizational identification is negatively related to in-group bias. As Fig. 2 shows, these two hypotheses received support.
Fig. 1
Download high-res image (164KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Below summarizes our research model.
Fig. 2
Download high-res image (109KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Results for H2 and H3.
Fig. 3
Download high-res image (193KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 3. Results for H4 to H8.
H6 and H7 argued that in-group bias is positively related to intentions to share with the team, and negatively related to intentions to share with organization KMS. The results supported H6, with beta = 0.32, P < 0.01, validating in-group favorism. However, out-group negativity, or decreased intention to share with organization KMS did not find support, showing that with our sample, in-group bias mainly manifests itself via in-group favorism.
Finally, H8 maintained that in-group bias is positively related to the knowledge sharing disparity. This is substantiated with the results, with a beta = 0.38, P < 0.01, confirming that in-group bias is a key driver of the knowledge sharing disparity.]]><h target="3" match="full"> Note that the effects of team identification and organizational identification became non-significant after in-group bias was introduced as the mediator, showing that in-group bias fully mediates the relationship between team identification, organizational identification and the knowledge sharing disparity.</h><![CDATA[
4.3. Control variables and additional tests
We tried to control for gender, age, education, and tenure with the company. Age, education and tenure with the company did not have significant effects on the dependent variables, thus, we removed them from the final model. Gender, however, is significantly related to intentions to share with the team. Specifically, female is less willing to share with the team (beta = −0.15, p < 0.05). We differentiated industries that are knowledge intensive, where knowledge is both the input for production and output as goods and services (Bresnahan, Brynjolfsson, & Hitt, 2002), such as information technology and engineering, from those industries in which the primary input is resources, such as transportation, retail etc. We also differentiated job positions that are knowledge intensive, such as R&D or finance, from those that are more operation intensive, such as administration or sales. However, the industry type and job positions did not have significant impacts on the sharing intentions or the sharing disparity.
We performed additional tests to see if team identification and organizational identification interact to influence in-group bias and the knowledge sharing disparity. However, the interaction term was not significant during either test, thus there was only individual effects, but no interactive effects of team identification and organizational identification. The strength of team identification’s effects on in-group bias and knowledge sharing disparity does not change when the level of organization identification changes. Rather, they display separate effects on in-group bias and knowledge sharing disparity, as Fig. 4 shows below. ]]><h target="2" match="part">Based on the coefficients of team identification and organizational identification’s effects on in-group bias and knowledge sharing disparity, we can see that when an individual employee has strong team identification but weak organizational identification, he/she will develop in-group bias and tend to have higher knowledge sharing disparity.</h><![CDATA[ When the employee has both strong team identification and organizational identification, then he/she will exhibit low in-group bias and has lower knowledge sharing disparity. If an employee has weak team identification and weak organization identification, then although there will be no in-group bias, there will also be little sharing among either the team or the organization KMS. Interestingly, if an employee has high organization identification and low team identification, thus he/she will develop reverse in-group bias and knowledge sharing disparity, i.e., he/she will prefer people outside his/her teams and share more to organization KMS rather than with his/her team members. In our sample of 250 respondents, there were actually 26 people whose organization identification score was higher than their team identification score by at least 0.5 point (total points = 7), 25 people who preferred other teams in the organization than their own teams by at least 0.5 point (total points = 7), and 24 people who were more willing to share with organization KMS than with their team members.
Fig. 4
Download high-res image (142KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 4. Effects of team identification and organization identification on in-group bias and knowledge sharing disparity.]]></section>
    <section name=" Discussion and conclusion" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
5. Discussion and conclusion
5.1. Discussion
Researchers have long observed the existence of knowledge sharing disparity: in most organizations, what one group or unit learns typically only gets shared within the team, but does not get to other groups or units in the organization (Hansen, 1999; Jarvenpaa & Staples, 2001; Tsai, 2001). ]]><h target="1" match="part"><![CDATA[This research is one of the first to not only validate the existence of the knowledge sharing disparity with empirical data from people across various industries, but also investigate its causes.]]></h><![CDATA[ Based on social identity theory and in-group bias theory, we were able to identify the causes of knowledge sharing disparity: team identification is positively related to knowledge sharing disparity while organization identification helps to reduce knowledge sharing disparity. ]]><h target="3" match="full">We further identified the mediator: in-group bias, which fully mediates the relationship between team identification, organizational identification and the knowledge sharing disparity.</h><![CDATA[ Just like knowledge sharing disparity, in-group bias arises as a result of strong team identification and weak organizational identification. In-group bias in knowledge sharing, however, is manifested mostly in the form of in-group favorism, rather than out-group negativity.
5.2. Theoretical implications
Our research contributes to extant literature in several ways. First, although the phenomenon that knowledge is mostly disseminated to other individuals in the same group, and only occasionally does some of the knowledge get distributed through formal systems, i.e., the corporate knowledge management system (KMS) was widely observed (Constant et al., 1994), the knowledge sharing disparity has remained largely conceptual and not been empirically validated. ]]><h target="1" match="part">We were among the first to validate that the knowledge sharing disparity in organizations really exists.</h><![CDATA[
Second, we explored the factors leading to the knowledge sharing disparity by integrating theories of social identity and knowledge sharing. By tracking both organization and team identification within the knowledge sharing context, we are able to untangle the complex relationships of team and organizational identification, and the knowledge sharing disparity. ]]><h target="2" match="part">Team identification is like a double-edge sword: although it enhances sharing intentions within teams, strong team identification coupled with weak organizational identification may result in in-group bias, which leads to the knowledge sharing disparity.</h><![CDATA[

Third, this research extends our understanding of knowledge sharing with the intergroup relations perspective and investigated the role of in-group bias in intentions to share at both the team and organization level. We examined knowledge sharing from a within-team versus across team perspective by comparing and contrasting within-team sharing and sharing with organization KMS and discovered in-group bias as the mediator between team identification, organizational identification and the knowledge sharing disparity.

Finally, we offer new empirical insights on identification in the organization knowledge sharing context. Although prior research has acknowledged the importance of identification in knowledge sharing in various contexts such as virtual community and blog space, relatively little is known about the role of identification in organizational knowledge sharing except for the pioneering work by Kankanhalli et al. (2005). Studying identification in the organizational knowledge sharing context is warranted for two reasons. First, unlike leisurely sharing of knowledge in virtual communities or online hobby forums, work is a major part of adult life experiences and constitutes an important component in people’s identity (Aryee & Luk, 1996). Second, leisurely sharing of knowledge in virtual communities or online hobby forums typically does not diminish one’s own opportunities for career advancement or enhance the advancement opportunities of others, as described in the knowledge sharing dilemma in organizations. While Kankanhalli et al. (2005) found no direct relationship between identification and knowledge sharing in organizations, our findings indicate that identification may still play an important role in organizational knowledge sharing and warrants more research.
5.3. Managerial implications
How do we prevent knowledge sharing disparity and ensure that knowledge moves freely from person to person, and from team to team? The results indicate that to solve knowledge sharing disparity, there are three possible routes that managers could resort to.

First, the results show that team identification is positively related to knowledge sharing disparity. Thus, to facilitate knowledge sharing throughout the organization, we need to keep team identification in check. Traditionally, we have acknowledged the benefits and encouraged the development of team identification, as it is reported to positively affect various group dynamics, such as conformity to group norms to the development of trust (Ashforth, Harrison, & Corley, 2008), and is positively associated with group satisfaction, group extra-role behavior, group climate, and negatively related to turn-over intentions (Riketta & van Dick, 2005). However, some scholars are wary of the possible consequences of too much team identification, and have warned us against these negative effects, including stereotyping and degrading of out-group members (Tajfel, 1981), overconformity, inflexibility, resistance to organizationally beneficial actions, and reduction of creativity (Ashforth et al., 2008; Ashforth & Mael, 1996; Dukerich, Kramer, & Parks, 1998). Similarly, too much identification with one’s own team may inadvertently become an obstacle in reducing knowledge sharing disparity. Some companies have introduced innovative ways to blur and break the team barrier among employees. For example, Lego got rid of fix seating in their London office and divided the workplace into flexible workzones so that “all employees have to get used to the fact that they do not have a dedicated desk, and that their activities during the work day determine where they are – not what department they are part of” (Lego, 2014). As a result, they created a more flexible environment where employees meet new colleagues all the time; the traditional, physical concept of ‘a department’ dissolved; there were increased cross-organizational collaboration and employees from very different parts of the organization could learn from each other (Lego, 2014).
Second, for managers hoping to achieve fluent movement of knowledge not only within teams, but also within the whole organization, they should emphasize on achieving one organization identity and make corresponding arrangements to enhance organizational identification. One possible way to achieve this is to form a common in-group identity through cooperative interdependence such as common goals and shared interests (Gaertner & Dovidio, 2000). This common superordinate identity can then promote trust and reduce intergroup differentiations and biases. With a common in-group identity, employee’s team identification and organizational identification can fully converge, thus benefit knowledge sharing within the whole organization. Apple, for example, built a strong corporate identity as a company “committed to bringing the best user experience to its customers through its innovative hardware, software and services.” A common identity could served as an incredible motivator for employees, who perform at their best and collaborate together when they know how they fit into a larger objective (Leinwand & Mainardi, 2014).
]]><h target="3" match="full">Finally, the results indicate that the in-group bias mediates the relationship between team identification, organizational identification, and knowledge sharing disparity.</h><![CDATA[ It is typical for members to develop higher team identification than organizational identification (Riketta & Van Dick, 2005), however, identifying in-group bias as the mediator allows us to intervene in the process and prevent the knowledge sharing disparity from occurring. One possible intervention is through social interaction. Research has shown that increasing interactions and understanding could reduce in-group bias (Pettigrew & Tropp, 2006). Therefore, organizations should conduct activities that facilitate interactions among teams such as organization-wide team-building exercise, socialization, and build organization-wide communication channels. Prior research indicates that increased group identification does not always lead to in-group bias: when the relationship between groups is cooperative, and when the out-group is trusted, the detrimental effects of in-group bias is minimized (Montoya & Pittinsky, 2011). Silicon Valley companies have long understood the importance of social interactions among all employees across all functions. Google, for example, designed their new campus to maximize chance encounters. Facebook put several thousand of its employees into a single mile-long room to increase personal interactions among its employees (Waber, Magnolfi, & Lindsay, 2014). Waber et al., 2014 observed that chance encounters and unplanned interactions between knowledge workers improves performance, gives employees access to new knowledge, exposing them to different kinds of expertise, and accelerating their learning.
5.4. Limitations and future research
As with most research, the results of this study should be interpreted in consideration of several limitations, which highlight avenues for future research. First, although we controlled for several variables, this study did not incorporate some important factors that may affect knowledge sharing in organizations such as organizational culture, organization network structure and IT infrastructure. Future research could further explore the impact of these factors on the knowledge sharing disparity. Second, this research explored in-group favorism and out-group derogation in knowledge sharing, but did not investigate under what circumstances out-group derogation will occur together with in-group favorsim. Future research could explore the contextual factors that lead to the existence of both in-group favorsim and out-group derogation. Finally, this research measured only intentions to share, but not actual sharing behaviours. Since there is a gap between intentions and actual behaviour (Kuo & Young, 2008), this research may not accurately predict actual sharing behaviours. Future research could investigate how identification leads to actual sharing behaviors.]]></section>
</publication>