<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="wanghongmei">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 6, Part A, December 2016, Pages 1124-1132</time>
International Journal of Information Management
    <title>A longitudinal exploration of the relations between electronic word-of-mouth indicators and firms’ profitability: Findings from the banking industry</title>
    <author>Chuanyi Tang.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Matthias R. Mehl.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Mary Ann Eastlick.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacec. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Wu He.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaced. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Noel A. Card.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacee. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
Department of Marketing, Strome College of Business, Old Dominion University, Norfolk, VA 23529, United States
b
Department of Psychology, The University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ 85721, United States
c
Division of Retailing and Consumer Sciences, The University of Arizona, Tucson, AZ 85721, United States
d
<![CDATA[Department of Information Technology & Decision Sciences, Strome College of Business, Old Dominion University, Norfolk, VA 23529, United States]]>
e
Measurement, Evaluation, and Assessment Program, Neag School of Education, The University of Connecticut, Storrs, CT 06269-3064, United States
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.03.015</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">We employ Automatic Text Analysis to extract valuable information contained in text online reviews.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">We examine the patterns of the bi-directional relations between eWOM indicators and banks’ profitability over time.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">Both star ratings and expressed anger in eWOM significantly predict firms’ future profitability.</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">Star ratings are a consistent predictor of firms’ future profitability over time and expressed anger explains additional variance of firms’ future profitablility beyond the star ratings.</highlight>
    <highlight id="5">Both star ratings and verbalized positive feelings reflect firms’ past financial performance.</highlight>

    <absrtact><![CDATA[
Abstract
Prior research on electronic word-of-mouth (eWOM) has focused on the predictive utility of star ratings.  ]]><h target="1" match="full">Extending these studies conceptually and methodologically, this paper employed Automatic Text Analysis to investigate the predictive utility of evaluative textual information contained in online reviews.</h><![CDATA[ Based on a real-world dataset that matched eWOM with annual financial performance of 68 banks over an eight-year period,  ]]><h target="2" match="full">this study tested patterns of the bi-directional relations between eWOM indicators and banks’ profitability over time.</h><![CDATA[  ]]><h target="3" match="full">Results showed that both star ratings and consumers’ verbalized emotions in eWOM significantly predicted increases in firms’ future profitability, which is measured by Return on Assets.</h><![CDATA[ ]]><h target="4" match="full"> Star ratings emerged as a consistent predictor, and their effects lasted for at least two years. Expressed anger predicted lower profitability in the following year and explained additional variance beyond the star ratings. Finally, higher firm profitability was prospectively related to higher star ratings and more verbalized positive feelings in next year’s eWOM.</h><![CDATA[
]]></absrtact>
    
    <keywords>Electronic word-of-mouth</keywords>
    <keywords>Social media</keywords>
    <keywords>Profitability</keywords>
    <keywords>Text analysis</keywords>
    <keywords>Sentiment analysis</keywords>
    
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction"><![CDATA[
1. Introduction
The advent of the Internet has dramatically expanded the scale and scope of consumers’ word-of-mouth (WOM) communication. As a result, the power of electronic word-of-mouth (eWOM) on firms’ market performance has recently attracted great research attention (e.g., Chen & Xie, 2008; Dellarocas, Awad, & Zhang, 2007; Ho-Dac, Carson, & Moore, 2013). Companies are expected to harness user-generated eWOM to better understand consumers and create competitive advantage in order to excel in the business environment (Dey, Haque, Khurdiya, & Shroff, 2011). However, as a relatively new research area, theory construction and methodology development in this area are still in their infancy, although consumers have posted thousands of online reviews containing their thoughts, emotions, and evaluations regarding a multitude of products and services, the potential value of the information contained in the textual reviews has barely been explored.
 ]]><h target="1" match="part">To this end, the present research intends to introduce Automatic Text Analysis (ATA) as an efficient method for quantifying the valuable information contained in eWOM and demonstrate the value of text analysis indicators adding to eWOM research.</h><![CDATA[ Specifically, this paper used text analysis to extract two linguistic indicators from textual reviews, expressed anger and verbalized positive feelings, and  ]]><h target="2" match="part">then tested the pattern of the associations among star ratings, the linguistic eWOM indicators, and firms’ profitability in a longitudinal dataset.</h><![CDATA[ This study represents a pioneering effort to explore how the quantified textual content of eWOM is related to firms’ profitability.


]]></section>

    <section name="Literature review" category="background"><![CDATA[
2. Literature review
2.1. The concept and formats of eWOM
Henning-Thurau et al. (2004) defined eWOM as: “any positive or negative statement made by potential, actual or former customers about a product or company, which is made available to a multitude of people and institutions via the Internet.” EWOM is distributed through various internet channels such as consumer forums, boycott websites, personal emails, chat rooms, and instant messages (Cheung & Thadani, 2012). Among these channels, consumer review forums – web-based consumer-opinion platforms used by consumers to publicize and communicate their opinions, recommendations, and complaints – are one of the most widely used eWOM formats. In a survey of 2000 internet users, more than 70% of the respondents reported that online reviews had a significant influence on their purchase decisions and the respondents noted that online consumer reviews had a greater influence than the reviews generated by professionals (comScore, 2007). Given its importance, this study focuses on consumer eWOM through online reviews.
Unlike the traditional WOM characterized by face-to-face or telephone communication, eWOM is text-based with a sender typing a message on the Internet and a number of consumers reading this message on the Internet. The enormous quantity of text-based eWOM messages available on the Internet poses both opportunities and challenges to researchers and managers. On the one hand, eWOM provides free access to voluminous, authentic consumer information. On the other hand, utilizing the huge amount of unstructured textual information can be challenging (Lehto, Park, Park, & Lehto, 2007).
2.2. Automatic text analysis
 ]]><h target="1" match="part">Capable of processing a large amount of text data effectively, Automatic Text Analysis (ATA) techniques have great potential in overcoming the challenge and deriving valuable insights from the text-based eWOM. ATA, which is also called computer-based text analysis, is the computer-aided method of extracting statistically manipulable information</h><![CDATA[ (Shapiro & Markoff, 1997). Through text analysis, researchers can discover hidden sentiment, patterns, traits, and relationships. Despite the different terminologies and technologies used, the common aim of text analysis is to transfer the unstructured text information into structured information, which can then be analyzed with traditional data mining and statistical techniques.
With the advances in computer technology, many computer-based text analysis tools and software have been developed. The typical functions of these text mining tools include information extraction, text categorization, text clustering, document summarization, and association analysis. According to Tang and Guo (2015), text analysis can be conducted from a qualitative approach, a quantitative approach, or a combination of both. Qualitative analysis tools are used to generate non-numerical information. For example, Kozinets (2002) adapted ethnography to the online community context and developed “netnography” as an online marketing research tool to qualitatively study consumer behavior. In contrast, the quantitative tools are used to generate numerical data. Because its output is objective and can be directly used in conventional statistical analysis, the quantitative approach has been more widely used in current research and many text mining tools (e.g., SAS text miner, SPSS Modeler with Text Analytics, LIWC) have been developed. Recently, a number of innovative studies have employed quantitative analysis tools to obtain valuable information from eWOM. For example, based on the mining of the text content on Facebook and Twitter sites of the three largest pizza chains, He, Zha, and Li (2013) employed a combination of two text mining tools including SPSS Clementine text mining tool and Nvivo 9 and demonstrated how to use social media to conduct competitive analysis. Employing Linguistic Inquiry and Word Count (LIWC), Ludwig et al. (2013) examined the influence of affective content and linguistic style matches in online reviews on consumers’ conversion rates.
In this study, we used Linguistic Inquiry and Word Count (LIWC, Pennebaker, Francis, & Booth, 2001), a popular text analysis software for several reasons. First, LIWC extracts quantitative information, making the resulting data amenable to statistical analysis. Second, LIWC not only analyses basic grammatical features of texts, but also provides information about important psychological processes (e.g., Positive Feelings and Anger). Third, LIWC operates automatically and eliminates the burden of manual coding. Fourth, LIWC is currently one of the most widely used and extensively validated ATA tool in academic research (Lyons, Mehl, & Pennebaker, 2006; Pennebaker, Mehl, & Niederhoffer, 2003).
LIWC employs a word count strategy, which is the foundation of many text analysis tools. LIWC compares each word of a given text to an internal dictionary and then generates linguistic indicators by calculating the percentage of words falling into a number of categories (e.g. words indicating emotional, cognitive, or social processes). The assumption of LIWC is that the percentage of emotion-related words used within a given category can serve as a reliable and valid measure of an individual’s emotional state. For example, the more negative emotion words used the stronger negative emotions a consumer have. A series of validation studies (e.g., Cohn, Mehl, & Pennebaker, 2004; Mehl & Pennebaker, 2003) have provided empirical evidence of the validity and reliability of this method.
2.3. The relationship between eWOM and firms’ market performance
Some prior studies have empirically examined market performance (i.e., product revenues and diffusion) in relation to eWOM. As suggested by Cheung and Thadani (2012), studies on the impact of eWOM communication can be classified into two levels: market-level analysis and individual level analysis. The market-level analysis focuses on the impact eWOM on firms’ market performance. These studies (e.g., Chevalier & Mayzlin, 2006; Dellarocas, Awad, & Zhang, 2004; Joeckel, 2007) have provided relatively consistent evidence that the volume and valence of eWOM are significantly related to product sales and stock prices. For example, Dellarocas et al. (2004) found that the number of posted movie reviews predicted both first week box-office revenues as well as total box-office revenues. Chevalier and Mayzlin (2006) found that favorable consumer ratings were positively related to book sales. The individual-level analysis focuses on the impact of eWOM communication on the buying intention and behavior of individual consumers. For example, Chu and Kim (2011) suggested that social network factors (e.g., tie strength) affected consumers’ eWOM behaviors. Gruen, Osmonbekov, and Czaplewski (2006) reported that customer know-how exchange influenced customers’ perceptions of product value and likelihood to recommend the product. Sparks, Perkins, and Buckely (2013) found that both the source and content of online reviews influenced consumers’ beliefs, attitudes and purchase intention.
Although the existing research has furthered our understanding of eWOM, as a relatively new area some important research gaps still exist in the literature (King, Racherla, & Bush, 2014). One such limitation lies in the lack of a method that can efficiently deal with huge volumes of textual reviews. As a result, most previous studies have focused on the volume or the star ratings of online reviews and have relatively neglected any information contained in the textual reviews. To address this methodological issue, the current study employed text analysis to extract consumer information from eWOM reviews. Another limitation is that prior research focused on the relationship between eWOM and product sales. It is conceivable that the benefits of WOM extend not only increasing revenue but also enhancing profitability, which has been relative neglected in the previous research. To fill this gap, the present study sought to examine the relationship between eWOM and firms’ profitability. A third limitation is that most prior studies (e.g., Chevalier & Mayzlin, 2006; Liu, 2006) have only tested the uni-directional impact of eWOM on firms’ performance, ignoring the possibility of alternative directions of prediction—namely that a firm’s performance also predicts eWOM. Godes and Mayzlin (2004) argued that high WOM today does not necessarily predict firms’ good performance tomorrow. Instead, it may be just a reflection of firms’ good performance yesterday.  ]]><h target="2" match="part">This study employed longitudinal path analysis and tested the potential bi-directional relations between eWOM and firm performance.</h><![CDATA[

]]></section>

    <section name="Hypotheses development" category="research model and hypotheses"><![CDATA[
3. Hypotheses development
Because each online review consists of a star rating and a verbal text, we broke down the relations between eWOM and firms’ profitability into two categories: (1) the relations between star ratings and profitability; and (2)  the relations between eWOM-derived linguistic indicators and profitability. The relationships in each category are discussed separately in the following sections.

3.1.  The relationship between star ratings and firms’ profitability
There are two main reasons why star ratings are positively associated with firms’ financial performance. First, star ratings, which represent consumers’ overall evaluation of a product or service, can be regarded as proxies of consumers’ perceived quality (Joeckel, 2007) because in the marketing literature, perceived quality is also defined as a global judgment of a firm’s offering (e.g., Parasuraman, Zeithaml, & Berry, 1985; Zeithaml, 1988). High product quality leads to high consumer loyalty and repeated purchases, thereby contributing to firms’ revenue and profitability (Anderson, 1994; Hallowell, 1996; Zeithaml, 2000). Second, star ratings’ effect on firm profitability can also come from the persuasion effect of consumer reviews. Because increasing number of consumers choose to read online reviews as part of their buying process, online reviews have increasingly become an important source of information that can influence consumers’ awareness, attitudes, and actual decisions regarding a certain product or service (Liu, 2006). If the ratings of a product or service are high, readers may think that the quality of the product or service is good, and as a result are more likely to purchase it. Furthermore, positive eWOM enhances the overall reputation of a firm (Anderson, 1994), which in turn leads to the firm’s long-term revenue, profitability, and even future idiosyncratic stock returns (Keller, 2003; Luo, 2007).
H1a. Higher star ratings in online reviews prospectively predict higher profitability of the firm in the future.
Most previous studies emphasized the effects of eWOM on firms’ future performance, whereas the effects of firms’ financial performance on future eWOM have been relatively ignored. In this paper, we propose that a firm’s high profitability may lead to consumers’ positive star ratings in the future for several reasons. First, if a firm demonstrates good profitability, it must have provided satisfactory products or services to its customers so that it can maintain its revenue and profit. Thus, a firm’s high profitability may imply that the firm’s product or service has high quality. Satisfied product quality in turn contributes to consumers’ positive WOM on the product (Matos & Rossi, 2008). Second, a firm’s superior profitability may help it establish a positive image or reputation and produce financial performance halo, which means that a firm’s previous financial performance influences individuals’ evaluation of the firm (Brown & Perry, 1994). Due to the halo effect, some individuals may give high evaluations and ratings to those companies with high profitability (Brown & Perry, 1994). Thus, we propose that the higher a firm’s profitability, the more likely consumers will give high ratings to the firm.
 H1b. Firms’ higher profitability prospectively predicts higher star ratings for the firms in the online reviews in the future.
3.2.  The relationship between eWOM-derived linguistic indicators and firms’ profitability
Arguably, the text in online reviews contains valuable market information. For example, most online reviews contain both verbalized positive and negative evaluations, which are not fully redundant with the overall star ratings. The coexistence of positive and negative evaluations in consumer reviews is consistent with previous findings. For example, Bradburn (1969) suggested that the simultaneous operation of multifaceted product or service attributes may elicit consumers’ differentially valenced consumption experience. Because of the complexity of banking services, a range of multifaceted service features may simultaneously evoke varying consumption experiences—some may be negative and others positive.
To explore the complexity of consumption experience and to develop a more nuanced measure of the evaluative information contained in consumer online reviews, we applied text analysis to the online reviews to quantify the presence of verbalized positive and negative emotions. This study employed Linguistic Inquiry and Word Count (LIWC; Pennebaker, Francis, & Booth, 2001) and used two linguistic indicators: Verbalized Positive Feelings (e.g. happy, glad, love) and expressed Anger (e.g., hate, mad, suck). Positive Feelings reflect consumers’ positively valenced experience towards a service or company. Anger has been widely accepted as an important predictor of consumer loyalty and post-purchase behaviors, such as repurchase and WOM (Folkes, 1984; Mattsson, Lemmink, & McColl, 2004).
Because idiosyncratic patterns of word use can serve as linguistic markers of social and psychological processes (Pennebaker, Mehl, & Niederhoffer, 2003), it is reasonable to assert that emotion-related words used by consumers may reflect their underlying emotional states.  ]]><h target="5" match="part">Furthermore, we propose that the verbalized positive feelings in online reviews, implying positive emotional states of consumers, have positive effects on firms’ future revenue and profitability.</h><![CDATA[  ]]><h target="4" match="part">Additionally, expressed anger in online reviews, implying negative emotional states of consumers, has negative effects on firms’ future revenue and profitability.</h><![CDATA[
The hypothesized effects of verbalized emotions in eWOM on firms’ profitability can be explained from two perspectives. First, verbalized emotions reflect consumer loyalty: verbalized positive feelings may indicate high customer loyalty given that positive emotions often result from a satisfactory consumption experience or a good customer-company relationship. In contrast, expressed anger may indicate lower customer loyalty because anger usually results from consumers’ frustration or dissatisfaction with a product or service. Another perspective for understanding the relationship between emotions and a firm’s profitability draws on the effects of emotional contagion. Emotional contagion refers to the social transfer of emotions from one person to another with the result that the receiver “catches” the emotions that the sender displayed (Schoenewolf, 1990). In the context of eWOM, the emotional states contained in the online reviews may be contagious and can create a “ripple” effect that has the potential to change the affective state of readers, thus influencing customers’ perceptions and evaluations of a product or service. Especially when consumers have no information about a product or service, they may observe the emotions displayed in online reviews and then adopt the emotions toward the product or service as a result of a desire to search for social information. As a result, the emotions expressed in online reviews may change the readers’ affective states accordingly.
 H2a. Verbalized positive feelings contained in firms’ online reviews prospectively predict firms’ higher profitability in the future.H3a. Expressed anger contained in firms’ online reviews prospectively predicts firms’ lower profitability in the future.
As discussed above, a firm’s high profitability may signal that the firm’s products or services are of high quality and that the firm has a positive image or reputation. High product quality and positive corporate reputation in turn contribute to consumers’ positive consumption experience.  ]]><h target="5" match="part">As a result, a consumer’s interaction with a firm with a good financial performance is more likely to produce high positive emotional state and little negative emotional state, which may be reflected in extensively verbalized positive feelings and minimally expressed anger in consumers’ online reviews.</h><![CDATA[

H2b. Higher profitability prospectively predicts more verbalized positive feelings in the firms’ online reviews in the future.
H3b.  Lower profitability prospectively predicts more expressed anger in the firms’ online reviews in the future.
Star ratings are similar to a consumer’s self-reported evaluation of a product or service, whereas the text contained in an online review captures the consumer’s spontaneous, momentary (or automatic) word choice. The text within an online review may contain much richer information than the star rating for several reasons. First, it is very common that both positive and negative evaluations co-exist within an online review, which cannot be captured by an overall star rating. Second, online reviews are written in a naturally-occurring, real-world situation, and the reviews may therefore be more reflective of automatic evaluative processes. The text-analytically derived linguistic indicators can help researchers to identify nuanced meanings and unconscious information contained in the textual reviews. For example, text analysis has been successfully used to derive information about unconscious psychological processes such as implicit motives (Lundy, 1988; Smith, 1992). Third, text analysis does not share much common method variance with the self-report rating scale. For example, text-analytically derived implicit motives are uncorrelated with self-reported explicit motives, and implicit motives uniquely predict important life outcomes (McClelland, Koestner, & Weinberger, 1989). Above all, we propose that text analysis can capture unique information contained in online reviews. In other words, the eWOM-derived linguistic indicators may explain additional variance in a firm’s profitability over and beyond what star ratings explain. In statistical terms, we expect that after removing the variance explained by star ratings, linguistic indicators will still be predictive of firms’ profitability.
 H4a. The eWOM-derived linguistic indicators (Positive Feelings and Anger) prospectively predict additional variance in firms’ future profitability beyond star ratings.H4b. After removing the variance explained by star ratings, a firm’s prior profitability still prospectively predicts the eWOM-derived linguistic indicators (Positive Feelings and Anger).
In addition to the above hypothesized relationships, we incorporated the effect of the firms’ eWOM indicators (e.g., star ratings) in the first year on those in the second year and the effect of firms’ profitability in the first year on those in the second year in the model. These are important co-existing effects that should be considered in the model. However, since these relationships are straightforward and not the focus of this study, we did not hypothesize them.

]]></section>

    <section name="Methodology" category="methods"><![CDATA[
4. Methodology
4.1. Data collection
We chose the banking industry as the research context for four reasons. First, banking is an important service sector in the U.S. Economy. Second, banking is closely related to consumers’ daily lives. Thus, consumers are likely to exchange their experience and information about banks on the Internet. Third, as in other service contexts, banking services are characterized as intangible and immeasurable. Although banking products themselves (e.g., checking, savings, and loans) provided by different banks are similar, the quality of the services may vary considerably. Moreover, perceived vendor risk and trust are associated with consumers’ choice of banking services (Kim & Prabhakar, 2000). Thus, consumers may seek information from online reviews to make informed choices among different banks (Bansal & Voyer, 2000).
Online review data were collected from www.epinions.com. This online forum was selected because it is one of the most popular online review forums, with a large number of online members and visitors. Also, it is an independent third party website, where reviews are relatively unbiased because it does not allow filtering of comments (Goetzinger, Park, & Widdows, 2006). At the time of data collection, there were 229 banks listed on Epinions.com that had consumer reviews. Of these 229 banks, we identified 68 banks that had consumer reviews for at least two years and publicly accessible annual financial data. Because some banks had too many reviews for an exhaustive analysis, we incorporated all of a bank’s reviews if it had less than 10 reviews one year, but randomly selected 10 plus 10% of total reviews if a bank had more than 10 reviews. The data on the banks’ annual financial performances were mainly collected from two public databases: Compus Stat and Mergent online. Some additional data were collected from their annual reports on individual banks’ websites. We matched each bank’s average star ratings and eWOM-derived linguistic indicators for each year with its annual financial performance to establish the dataset. The covered time period was 2000–2007, before the economic recession.
4.2. Measurement
Each review from Epinions.com consists of a textual review and a numerical star rating ranging from 1 to 5. We recorded the star rating and downloaded the textual review manually for each review. After all the textual reviews were cleaned (e.g. correct misspellings and typos), they were imputed in LIWC software to conduct text analysis. In this study, we focused on two specific linguistic indicators: expressed anger and verbalized positive feelings. Our approach is essentially sentiment analysis, however our approach slightly differs from the widely used sentiment analysis approach. In most sentiment analyses (e.g., Bollen, Mao, & Zeng, 2011; Mostafa, 2013), the sentiment of the text is summarized as a bipolar indicator of positive or negative affect. However as discussed in 3.2, consumers may have mixed feelings about a product, being satisfied with certain features while dissatisfied with others. In this situation, using both positive and negative sentiment indicators together can better capture consumers’ real feelings and attitudes toward a product or service. Finally, we calculated the averages of star ratings and eWOM-derived linguistic indicators at a year level. For the measure of banks’ profitability, we used annual return on asset (ROA). ROA is an overall measure of a bank’s net profit per dollar of assets, reflecting how much profit a firm is able to generate for each dollar of asset invested. It has been widely used in the banking industry and academic research on corporate profitability (e.g., Duncan & Elliott, 2002; Reidenbach & Moak, 1986).
4.3. Data analysis
 ]]><h target="2" match="part">We used Longitudinal Path Analysis (Little, Preacher, Selig, Card, 2007) and employed Lisrel 8.8 to test the across-time relationship between eWOM indicators and firms’ profitability.</h><![CDATA[ Because all constructs used single measures, we used manifest variables in these models.  ]]><h target="2" match="part">We fit three separate models to test the relationships between the three eWOM indicators (star rating, Positive Feelings, and Anger) and firms’ profitability (H1–H3) respectively.</h><![CDATA[ We then regressed each year’s average star rating on that year’s ROA, saving the residuals (containing variance in ROA not explained by star ratings) for each year. We used these residuals in Model 4 and 5 to evaluate the relations between the two linguistic indicators and profitability, controlling for star ratings. This approach allowed us to evaluate whether the linguistic indicators explained additional variance of banks’ future profitability beyond star ratings (H4a) and whether linguistic indicators can still be predicted by a firm’s past profitability even after the variance explained by star ratings is removed (H4b).
In all models, we propose that the effects of eWOM on firm profitability or the effects of firm profitability on eWOM would occur in the second and third years. For example, we predicted that eWOM from 2000 predicted firm profitability in 2001 and 2002; 2000 firm profitability predicted consumers’ eWOM in 2001 and 2002. Given that we had eight years of annual observations and limited information on the effects with more than three-year lags, we did not model the effects with a lag of more than 3 years to minimize capitalization on chance. Furthermore, we constrained the path coefficients to be equal over time in the models. Although this equating of paths precludes our ability to evaluate historic changes in these relations, it gives us greater statistical power and precision in estimating longitudinal relations.

]]></section>

    <section name="Results" category="results"><![CDATA[
5. Results
The overall model fit for model 1 (see Fig. 1 and Table 1) was acceptable, χ2(52) = 115.64, CFI = 0.91, RMSEA = 0.10 (90% C.I. = 0.06; 0.14). ]]><h target="4" match="part">Supporting H1a, star ratings predicted increases in firms’ profitability in the second (β = 0.07, p < 0.01) and third </h><![CDATA[(β = 0.04, p < 0.05) years.  match="part">Results also show that banks’ profitability predicted increases in consumers’ star ratings during the second year (β = 0.09, p < 0.05), supporting H1b.</h><![CDATA[ The overall model fit for model 2 (see Fig. 2 and Table 2) was acceptable, χ2(52) = 113.93, CFI = 0.92; RMSEA = 0.10 (90% C.I. = 06; 0.14). Results show that Positive Feelings did not predict increases in firms’ profitability. Thus, H2a was not supported. Firm profitability predicted increases in consumers’ Positive Feelings in the second year (β = 0.05, p < 0.01), lending support to H3a. The overall model fit for model 3 (see Fig. 2 and Table 2) was acceptable, χ2(52) = 98.24, CFI = 0.93, RMSEA = 0.09 (90% C.I. = 0.05; 0.13).  ]]><h target="3" match="part">Results show that Anger is significantly related to firm profitability in the second year (β = −0.07, p < 0.01), supporting H2b.</h><![CDATA[ However, inconsistent with H3b, results show that banks’ profitability did not predict decreases in Anger in eWOM.
Fig. 1
Download high-res image (548KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 1. The relations between star ratings and profitability.
Table 1. Result of path analysis (Star ratings and profitability).
Path	Unstandardized Solution (Standard Error, Wald Statistic)	Completely Standardized Solution
Star ratings of year N → Star ratings of year N + 1	0.22 (0.10, 2.27)*	0.25*
Star ratings of year N → Profitability of year N + 1	0.07 (0.02, 3.70)**	0.07**
Star ratings of year N → Profitability of year N + 2	0.03 (0.02, 2.18)*	0.04*
Profitability of year N → Profitability of year N + 1	0.74 (0.05, 14.14)**	0.73**
Profitability of year N → Star ratings of year N + 1	0.09 (0.04, 2.08)*	0.09*
Profitability of year N → Star ratings of year N + 2	−0.06 (0.04, −1.62)	−0.06
*
p < 0.05.
**
p < 0.01.
Fig. 2
Download high-res image (1MB)Download full-size image
Fig. 2. The relations between verbalized emotions and profitability.
Table 2. Result of path analysis (Verbalized emotions and profitability).
Positive Feelings	Anger
Path	Unstandardized Solution(Standard Error, Wald Statistic)	Completely Standardized Solution	Unstandardized Solution(Standard Error, Wald Statistic)	Completely Standardized Solution
Emotions of year N → Emotions of year N + 1	0.63 (0.09, 7.29)**	0.68**	0.69 (0.12, 5.55)**	0.66**
Emotions of year N → Profitability of year N + 1	−0.02 (.02, −1.07)	−0.02	−0.04(0.02, −2.56)**	−0.07**
Emotions of year N → Profitability of year N + 2	0.02 (0.02, 1.06)	0.03	.00 (.01, −0.17)	0.00
Profitability of year N → Profitability of year N + 1	1.11 (0.12, 9.39)**	0.84**	0.77 (0.11, 7.28)**	0.75**
Profitability of year N → Emotions of year N + 1	0.07 (0.03, 2.13)*	0.05*	0.01 (0.03, 0.20)	0.00
Profitability of year N → Emotions of year N + 2	−0.03 (.02, −1.49)	−0.02	0.08 (0.05, 1.59)	0.04
*
p < 0.05.
**
p < 0.01.
To compare the unique predictive utility of the three eWOM indicators, we created residualized firm profitability variables from which star rating information was removed (i.e., statistically controlled). The overall model fit for model 4 (see Fig. 3 and Table 3) was acceptable, χ2(52) = 99.35, CFI = 0.93, RMSEA = 0.08 (90% C.I. = 0.03; 0.12). ]]><h target="3" match="part"> Results show that Positive Feelings significantly predicted increases in residualized profitability during the second year (β = 0.06, p < 0.01), above and beyond the influence of star ratings.</h><![CDATA[ Thus, H4a was supported for verbalized positive feelings. Results also show that residualized profitability was positively related to Positive Feelings in the second year (β = 0.10, p < 0.01) and the third year (β =0.16, p < 0.01).  ]]><h target="4" match="part">These findings indicates that after removing the variance explained by past star ratings, higher firm profitability was prospectively predictive of consumers’ higher Positive Feelings in the future.</h><![CDATA[ Thus, H4b was supported for verbalized positive feelings. The overall model fit for model 5 (see Fig. 3 and Table 3) was acceptable, χ2(52) = 88.19, CFI = 0.94, RMSEA = 0.07 (90% C.I. = 0.07; 0.11). ]]><h target="3" match="part"> Results show that Anger significantly predicted decreases in residualized profitability at the second year (β = −0.04, p < 0.01).</h><![CDATA[ Thus, H4a was supported for expressed anger.  ]]><h target="3" match="part">However, results show that residualized profitability was not significantly related to Anger. Thus, H4b was not supported for expressed anger.</h><![CDATA[
Fig. 3
Download high-res image (1MB)Download full-size image
Fig. 3. The relations between verbalized emotions and residualized profitability.
Table 3. Result of path analysis (Verbalized emotions and residualized profitability).
Positive Feelings	Angers
Path	Unstandardized Solution(Standard Error, Wald Statistic)	Completely Standardized Solution	Unstandardized Solution(Standard Error, Wald Statistic)	Completely Standardized Solution
Emotions of year N → Emotions of year N + 1	−0.02 (.15, −0.14)	−0.02	.03 (.14, 0.22)	0.02
Emotions of year N → Residualized Profitability of year N + 1	0.05 (0.02, 2.65)**	0.06**	−0.04 (0.01, −2.72) **	−0.04**
Emotions of year N → Residualized Profitability of year N + 2	0.02 (0.01, 1.73)	0.03	.01 (.01, 0.66)	0.01
Profitability of year N → Profitability of year N + 1	−0.14 (.20, −0.71)	−0.13	0.20 (0.20, 1.01)	0.22
Profitability of year N → Residualized Emotions of year N + 1	0.14 (0.05, 2.96)**	0.10**	−0.04 (.03, −1.22)	−0.03
Profitability of year N → Residualized Emotions of year N + 2	0.21 (0.05, 4.13)**	0.16**	0.13 (0.07, 1.85)	0.07
*p < 0.05.

**
p < 0.01.

]]></section>

    <section name="Discussion and implications" category="discussion"><![CDATA[
6. Discussion and implications
 ]]><h target="5" match="part">This study provides evidence that star ratings are good predictors of firm performance, which is consistent with previous studies</h><![CDATA[ (Chevalier & Mayzlin, 2006; Dellarocas, Awad, & Zhang, 2004). Extending the previous studies, we found that the effects of star ratings on firms’ profitability are persistent and last for at least two years. This study further found that the linguistic indicators of verbalized emotions generated by text analysis are prospectively associated with firms’ future profitability. Although we did not find a strong relationship between positive feelings and firms’ future profitability (the relationships are significant only after controlling star ratings),  ]]><h target="3" match="part">our results show that expressed anger significantly predicted decreases of firms’ profitability in the second year.</h><![CDATA[ This result is consistent with previous findings (e.g., Mattsson, Lemmink, & McColl, 2004; Westbrook, 1987) regarding the strong negative relations between anger and consumers’ loyalty and buying behaviors.  Moreover, previous studies (e.g.,Ba & Pavlou, 2002; Cheung, Luo, Sia, & Chen, 2009) suggested that negative reviews are perceived more credible and salient.]]><h target="4" match="part"> More interestingly, results show that the linguistic indicators of anger and positive feelings explained additional variance of firms’ future profitability beyond star ratings.</h><![CDATA[ This finding implies that star ratings fail to capture all information contained in textual reviews, it is worthwhile to explore this “surplus” evaluative information hidden in the textual reviews, and text analysis and LWIC provide an effective and informative way to study eWOM. This result echoes Ludwig et al. (2013) which suggested that the affective content and linguistic styles of the text reviews are important in understanding the market impact of eWOM.
 ]]><h target="2" match="part">This study provides the first evidence for the bi-directional relations between eWOM indicators and firm profitability.</h><![CDATA[  ]]><h target="4" match="part">Extending prior research, this study found that high eWOM this year not only predicts firms’ good performance next year</h><![CDATA[  ]]><h target="5" match="part">but also reflects firms’ good performance last year.</h><![CDATA[  ]]><h target="3;4" match="part">Specifically, star ratings both predict firms’ future profitability and reflect firms’ prior profitability.</h><![CDATA[  ]]><h target="4" match="part">Verbalized anger is better at predicting firms’ future profitability than at reflecting firms’ prior profitability,</h><![CDATA[ ]]><h target="5" match="part"> while verbalized positive feelings work better at reflecting firms’ past profitability than at predicting firms’ future profitability.</h><![CDATA[  ]]><h target="4" match="part">These results suggest that star ratings and verbalized anger can be effectively used to predict firms’ future financial performance and firms’ profitability can be successfully employed to predict the positivity of eWOM in the future.</h><![CDATA[

The findings of this study shed new light on the relationship between eWOM and company performance and provide important implications to eWOM researchers. First, eWOM researchers need to know that relationships between eWOM and firm performance are complex and multi-dimensional. Beyond its relationships with firm’s sales and stock prices as found in previous studies (e.g., Dellarocas et al., 2007; Luo, 2007), this study found that eWOM is associated with firms’ profitability.  ]]><h target="2" match="part">Moreover, the relationships between eWOM and firm performance are longitudinal and bi-directional</h><![CDATA[.  ]]><h target="5" match="part">Second, our results show that consumers’ emotional responses contained in eWOM are critical in understanding the relationship between eWOM and firm performance.</h><![CDATA[ Text analysis is an effective tool that can help researchers capture the affective content contained in eWOM. In addition, this study integrated the knowledge from multiple disciplines including information technology, marketing, communication, and social psychology. As suggested by Cheung and Thadani (2012), eWOM research is interdisciplinary in nature. Thus, eWOM researchers should be open-minded and keep an eye on the related new theoretical and methodological development in other areas.
The findings of this paper also provide significant managerial implications, specifically highlighting the value of eWOM in reflecting and forecasting firms’ profitability. Researchers and managers should pay more attention to the valuable information contained in eWOM.  ]]><h target="4" match="part">They can use star ratings and text analysis indicators generated from eWOM to predict future profitability, thereby making better future plans.</h><![CDATA[  ]]><h target="5" match="part">At the same time, firms’ profitability can be used to project the positivity of consumer eWOM, and through which manage the image or reputation of the firms.</h><![CDATA[ In investigating eWOM, managers and researchers should not only check the average star ratings in online reviews, but also analyze the textual reviews since these texts may provide additional information beyond star ratings. ]]><h target="1" match="part"> ATA is a promising method in generating valuable information from eWOM.</h><![CDATA[ Managers and researchers should especially pay attention to the positive and negative emotions contained in the text reviews because these emotions may provide new insights into consumers’ minds and exert significant impact on firms’ performance (Ludwig et al., 2013; Tang & Guo, 2015; Teng, Khong, Goh, & Chong, 2014).
As more and more customers are engaged in various social media platforms, there is a strong need for managers to monitor and understand what their customers are saying on a daily, weekly, or monthly basis so that they can transform social media data into useful knowledge for making actionable decisions and improving marketing effectiveness. Nowadays firms are expected to develop business analytics capabilities and harness online user-generated data to extract business insights, understand consumer sentiment, and create marketing intelligence in order to excel in the business environment (Dey, Haque, Khurdiya, & Shroff, 2011). For example, He et al. (2015) suggested that companies can use a social media competitive analytics tool with sentiment benchmarks to glean industry-specific marketing intelligence.  ]]><h target="1" match="part">In the above processes, ATA provides a way to effectively obtain valuable consumer insights from a large amount of user-generated data.</h><![CDATA[ Specifically, ATA can be used to monitor customer opinions on a daily basis and predict firm performance in a timely manner.

]]></section>

    <section name="Conclusion" category="conclusion"><![CDATA[
7. Conclusion
This paper contributes to the literature on eWOM and text analysis in several important ways. First, prior eWOM studies have exclusively focused on the relationship between eWOM and sales.  ]]><h target="3" match="part">This paper went one step further, and provided evidence of the existence of significant relationship between eWOM and firm profitability.</h><![CDATA[ Second, previous studies mainly emphasize the predictive utility of eWOM on firm performance.  ]]><h target="2" match="part">This study demonstrates that the relations between eWOM and firm performance are bi-directional.</h><![CDATA[ Third, most previous studies emphasized the role of star ratings while neglecting the information contained in textual reviews. ]]><h target="4" match="part"> In contrast, our results show that the linguistic indicators generated from textual reviews explain additional variance in firm performance beyond star ratings.</h><![CDATA[ Fourth, this study demonstrates that LIWC is an efficient and easy-to-use tool in studying eWOM and the LIWC indicators including Positive Feelings and Anger are powerful in predicting firm performance. Our results also suggest that sentiment analysis should provide indicators on both positive and negative emotions for a given text instead of using a categorical indicator of positive, negative, and neutral because it helps to better capture the mixed feelings consumers have toward a product. Fifth, by employing longitudinal path analysis and a real-word data set over eight years, ]]><h target="2" match="part"> this study empirically identified patterns of relationships between eWOM indicators and profitability over time.</h><![CDATA[

Several potential study limitations merit consideration. First, the generalizability of the findings should be examined in future studies. In this study, we collected all the reviews from a single online forum and employed a relatively small number of firms. In addition, we focused on the banking industry. As other industry-specific studies (e.g., Litivin, Goldsmith, & Pan, 2008; Kim & Prabhakar, 2000), our findings will help bank managers develop and implement social media-based IT and marketing strategies. In order to safely generalize the findings to other industries and contexts, future studies are needed to test the generalizability of our results by employing a larger sample size, collecting online reviews from multiple sources, and testing the effects in multiple contexts. Second, although this study shows that LIWC is an effective tool for studying eWOM, its word count strategy has limitations (Mehl & Gill, 2010; Mehl, 2006). Thus, more research should be conducted to establish the validity and utility of LIWC. In addition, there are many other text analysis tools available in the market. Future research is needed to evaluate and compare the advantages and disadvantages of different text analysis tools. Third, this study focused on two text analysis indicators including Positive Feelings and Anger. Some other indicators (e.g., cognitive processions) should be examined to explore their value in business research.
]]></section>
</publication>