<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>

    <publication marker= "liu yang">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 1, February 2016, Pages 60-72</time>
    <title>Fairness and devotion go far: Integrating online justice and value co-creation in virtual communities</title>
    <author>En-Yi Chou</author>. Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspace
    <author>Cheng-Yu Lin</author>. Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspace
    <author>Heng-Chiang Huang</author>. Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspace
Department of International Business, National Taiwan University, No. 1, Sec. 4, Roosevelt Rd., Taipei 106, Taiwan, ROC
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2015.09.009</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
•
    <highlight id="1">We identify five distinct perceived online justice dimensions in virtual communities.</highlight>
•

     <highlight id="2">We examine both in- and extra-role value co-creation behavior in virtual communities.</highlight>
•
 <highlight id="3">Sense of virtual community mediates the influence of perceived online justice on value co-creation behavior.</highlight>
•
            <highlight id="4">Virtual community practitioners can develop, maintain, and sustain the virtual community by helping members form fairness perceptions during participation.</highlight>

Abstract
    <abstract>  <![CDATA[Although building long-term, successful virtual communities is important, rare studies have examined both in- and extra-role value co-creation behaviors from the perspective of social exchange theory and equity theory. ]]>
        
       <h target="1;3" match="full">  Specially, we incorporate five different online justice perceptions into our model and examine the mediating role of “sense of virtual community” between these perceived online justice antecedents and both in- and extra-role online value co-creation behavior (reflected by knowledge contribution and online community citizenship behaviors, respectively).  </h>
        
        <h target="4" match="full"> We empirically examine the model using data from 278 members of virtual communities. The results reveal that perceived online justice leads to value co-creation behavior through sense of virtual community. The findings elicit several implications for theory and practice.</h>
        
    </abstract>
    

Keywords
    <keywords>Perceived online justice</keywords>
    <keywords>Sense of virtual community</keywords>
    <keywords>Online value co-creation behavior</keywords>
    <keywords>Knowledge contribution behavior</keywords>
    <keywords>Online community citizenship behavior</keywords>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
The Internet has had a significant and progressive impact on people’s daily lives for the past few decades. With the Internet and the development of other technologies generating an unprecedented proliferation of virtual communities around the world (Andersen, 2005), increasingly more users are relying on the Internet to obtain useful information instead of offline sources (Yen, Hsu, & Huang, 2011). In addition, an increasing number of users now connect with one another through online channels to share interests and form virtual communities (Blanchard, 2008; Koh & Kim, 2003; Tonteri, Kosonen, Ellonen, & Tarkiainen, 2011). Prior research has explored different aspects of online user behavior, such as peer-to-peer information sharing and problem solving (Hennig-Thurau, Gwinner, Walsh, & Gremler, 2004; Mathwick, Wiertz, & De Ruyter, 2008; Wasko & Faraj, 2000, 2005), intentional information seeking and social interactions involving communities (Bagozzi & Dholakia, 2002; Yi & Gong, 2013), and time spent chatting online (Dholakia, Bagozzi, & Pearo, 2004; Yen et al., 2011). Yet, although virtual communities are rapidly growing, many still fail because of a lack of sufficient active contributors and continuous supply of knowledge content (Chen & Hung, 2010). The success of virtual communities greatly depends on the contributions of members (Bagozzi & Dholakia, 2002; Dholakia et al., 2004; McWilliam, 2000). Despite the many advantages derived from user participation behavior, previous studies on such behavior have ignored the phenomenon that users often act as value co-creators of virtual communities (Bendapudi & Leone, 2003; Vargo & Lusch, 2004; Yen et al., 2011). Indeed, within virtual contexts, value can be co-created with and determined by the users in the consumption process and through value-in-use (Lusch & Vargo, 2006; Vargo & Lusch, 2004, 2008). Therefore, scholars and practitioners should work to understand and value users’ co-creation behavior in virtual communities.
Extant literature has focused on managing customers as human resources (Groth, 2005; Groth, Mertens, & Murphy, 2004) and found that users exhibit value co-creation behaviors in virtual communities. Most previous studies have addressed either knowledge contribution or knowledge-sharing behaviors (Bock, Zmud, Kim, & Lee, 2005; Chen & Hung, 2010; Chiu, Hsu, & Wang, 2006; Chen, Yang, & Tang, 2013; Hashim & Tan, 2015; Hsu, Ju, Yen, & Chang, 2007; Wasko & Faraj, 2005) or citizenship behaviors, including voluntary behavior (Kang, Lee, Lee, & Choi, 2007), helping behavior (Fang & Chiu, 2010; Wasko & Faraj, 2005; Yen et al., 2011), and the spread of positive word of mouth (Mathwick et al., 2008). Previous organizational behavior research has identified two types of value co-creation: in-role behavior (e.g., task performance), which refers to behavior necessary for successful value co-creation, and extra-role behavior (e.g., organizational citizenship behavior), which is voluntary behavior that provides extraordinary value to the firm and is required for value co-creation (Bove, Pervan, Beatty, & Shiu, 2009; Groth, 2005; Yen et al., 2011; Yi & Gong, 2008, 2013; Yi, Nataraajan, & Gong, 2011). Indeed, as partial employees of virtual communities, community users contribute by performing both in- and extra-role co-creation behaviors (Groth, 2005).
Within the context of online communities, knowledge contribution behavior serves as the basis for smooth operations, while online community citizenship behavior represents a crucial means of promoting the effectiveness of online communities (Dholakia et al., 2004; Williams & Cothrel, 2000). Similar to in-role behavior, knowledge contribution behavior refers to behavior that is expected and required of members to share and co-create knowledge. Conversely, online community citizenship behavior, analogous to extra-role conduct, refers to discretionary efforts directed toward helping, feedback, advocacy, and tolerance in virtual communities (Groth et al., 2004; Lengnick-Hall, Claycomb, & Inks, 2000). Both knowledge contribution behavior and online community citizenship behavior are vital and have been most often applied to characterize customers’ online community participation (Yen et al., 2011). ]]><![CDATA[To gain deeper insights into such a value co-creation phenomenon, this study shows that users’ online value co-creation behavior comprises knowledge contribution behavior (in-role) and online community citizenship behavior (extra-role). ]]><h target="2" match="part">Although prior studies have stressed the importance of online value co-creation behavior, rare research on virtual community has integrated both types of online value co-creation behaviors into a model. Therefore, to adopt a more comprehensive perspective, this study proposes a co-creation-based integrated framework by incorporating both in- and extra-role value co-creation into the model.</h>

       
        
<![CDATA[Given that distinctive contributions may come from each type of value co-creation behavior, identifying the antecedents underlying such behavior in virtual communities should help both academics and practitioners gain insights into how to stimulate members’ value co-creation in virtual communities (Grewal, Levy, & Kumar, 2009; Verhoef et al., 2009). Online interactions represent a multi-sided process between one user and other community members, and by participating in virtual communities, users can form justice perceptions. Justice, regarded as the fundamental basis for relationship maintainability and sustainability in a social exchange (Fang & Chiu, 2010; Lind, Kulik, Ambrose, & de Vera Park, 1993), is an effective and readily available mechanism for dealing with diverse, uncertain circumstances (Lind & Van den Bos, 2002), such as the virtual context. Specifically, Chiu et al. (2006) call for research to examine whether online justice perceptions influence individuals’ behaviors in virtual communities. In this regard, we extend the notion of users as partial employees (Hennig-Thurau et al., 2004) and adopt social exchange theory (Cropanzano & Mitchell, 2005; Homans, 1961) and equity theory (Adams, 1965; Leventhal, 1980) to identify various perceived online justice dimensions, including distributive justice, procedural justice, interpersonal justice, and informational justice. In addition, drawing on the complementary perspective (Kay & Jost, 2003), we add a complementary justice factor that has not yet been examined in extant literature.
Previous work suggests that sense of virtual community is a psychological outcome in virtual communities (Oh, Ozkaya, & LaRose, 2014) and reflects the extent to which individual users feel that they belong to virtual communities. Because sense of virtual community can lead to appropriate behavior (Zhao, Lu, Wang, Chau, & Zhang, 2012), we further use this variable as a critical mediator between users’ justice perceptions and online value co-creation behavior in virtual communities.
]]><h target="3" match="full">Using survey responses from 278 active virtual community members, we develop, validate, and test a model that investigates the impacts of the justice dimensions on participants’ in- and extra-role value co-creation behavior in online communities.</h>

<h target="1" match="full"> The results corroborate our propositions that members’ justice perceptions (i.e., distributive, procedural, interpersonal, informational, and complementary justice) can facilitate the psychological mechanism of sense of virtual community, which in turn leads to positive in- and extra-role value co-creation behavior (i.e., knowledge contribution behavior and online community citizenship behavior).</h> 
        
<![CDATA[These results provide important implications for both research and business practice.
The remainder of this article proceeds as follows. In Section 2, we review the literature on online value co-creation behavior and different justice perceptions in virtual communities. A synthesis of previous research leads to hypotheses and helps formulate a research framework for the study. In Section 3, we describe the methods and measurements and, in Section 4, provide the results. Section 5 discusses the managerial and research implications and presents limitations and future research directions.]]>
</section>
    <section name="Literature review and hypothese" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Literature review and hypotheses
2.1. Value co-creation
Prior research has considered value co-creation and its groundwork from different perspectives, such as “value-in-experience” (Prahalad & Ramaswamy, 2004) and “value-in-use” (Vargo & Lusch, 2004). Prahalad and Ramaswamy (2000) first emphasized the changing role of customers from passive audiences to active co-creators of experience. Companies can thus achieve a competitive advantage by co-opting customer competence (Bendapudi & Leone, 2003). Co-creation involves an effort between multiple parties to create value of experience collaboratively. Such co-creation experience depends highly on individuals (Prahalad & Ramaswamy, 2004). Indeed, each individual's uniqueness or specialness may affect the co-creation process.
Value-in-use means that value for the user is created or emerges during participation (Bendapudi & Leone, 2003), indicating that a user is engaged in the value-creating process (Grönroos, 2011). Because value is created as value-in-use by the user for the user, the user as an integrator of resources in the value-creating process can be viewed as a value co-creator (Edvardsson, Tronvoll, & Gruber, 2011; Grönroos & Voima, 2013; Grönroos, 2011). Ramaswamy (2011) emphasized that co-creation is the process by which mutual value is expanded together. Therefore, encouraging users to be co-creators of value has presented a fundamental tenet of involvement in the value co-creation process and could be the next frontier for competitive effectiveness (Bendapudi & Leone, 2003; Grönroos, 2011; Vargo & Lusch, 2004, 2008). Because co-creation implies participation in networking structures (Etgar, 2008), this study accepts Vargo and Lusch’s (2004) standpoint, viewing users as co-creators of value in virtual communities, and value co-creation behaviors may occur within the participation process, which takes place after interactions with other members.
2.2. Online value co-creation behavior
2.2.1. In- and extra-role online value co-creation behavior
A virtual community is the gathering of people for whom electronic communication is a primary form of interaction (Ridings & Gefen, 2004); who share common interests, goals, or practices and engage in social interactions through the Internet (Chiu et al., 2006; De Valck, Van Bruggen, & Wierenga, 2009); and who connect, communicate, and get to know one another better over time (Williams & Cothrel, 2000). Two types of online value co-creation behavior—namely, knowledge contribution behavior and online community citizenship behavior—are of vital importance because they enable the community to accumulate resources and grow over time.
Knowledge is critical to sustain a virtual community (Wasko & Faraj, 2005), and many community members are no longer passive audiences but rather have become active co-creators of knowledge (Sawhney, Verona, & Prandelli, 2005). For a virtual community to sustain itself over time, it must continually foster the willingness of community members to share knowledge and exchange information jointly (Chiu et al., 2006; Wasko, Teigland, & Faraj, 2009). Therefore, the significance of member-generated content should be emphasized. In other words, both social interactions and knowledge generation are the key resources embedded within the network that sustain virtual communities.
Along with knowledge contribution behavior, other voluntary behaviors, such as assisting other users and conveying positive word of mouth, help sustain a virtual community, and their aggregation is beneficial for its successful functioning. These spontaneous, voluntary, and beneficial behaviors exert positive influences on the effective functioning of a virtual community, and thus such behavior can be viewed as customer citizenship behavior in a virtual community setting, which we call “online community citizenship behavior.” Online community citizenship behaviors are inherently moral behaviors, in that individuals choose to perform a specific behavior that is beneficial to both the online community and its members. Building on Yi and Gong’s (2013) and Yen et al.’s (2011) taxonomies of citizenship behavior, we identified a four-dimensional online community citizenship behavior framework: (1) feedback, which refers to providing or suggesting additional information to help community members and the community itself in the long run; (2) advocacy, which refers to recommending the community to others (e.g., friends, family); (3) helping, which refers to individual behavior geared toward assisting other members; and (4) tolerance, or the willingness to be patient when the posted knowledge does not meet expectations of useful information (as in the case of delays or mistakes) (Groth et al., 2004; Groth, 2005; Lengnick-Hall et al., 2000). These extra-role behaviors exceed the expectations of typical activities in which members are often involved when participating in online communities (Yen et al., 2011).
2.2.2. Sense of virtual community
The sense of virtual community concept is rooted in the sense of community framework developed by McMillan and Chavis (1986). Sense of community was originally defined as the feeling members have of belonging to a community (Tonteri et al., 2011) or personal knowledge about belonging to a collective that includes others (Koh & Kim, 2003). Prior research has found that many of the individual feelings, commitments, and perceptions are similar in online and offline groups (Blanchard, 2007). Specifically, members’ beliefs about one another and the community and their shared faith that their needs will be met through their commitment to the community exist not only in offline groups but also in virtual communities. Therefore, a sense of virtual community, which shares many of the core characteristics of sense of community, has received increasingly more attention and is viewed as the foundation of the development of a virtual community. For the purposes of this study, we define “sense of virtual community” as the degree to which members feel a sense of belonging to a specific online group or virtual environment (Koh & Kim, 2003). We conceive sense of virtual community as containing three dimensions: membership, influence, and immersion (Chen et al., 2013; Keng, Ting, & Chen, 2011; Koh & Kim, 2003). Membership indicates that people experience feelings of belonging to their virtual community, influence implies that people influence other members of their community, and immersion means that people feel the state of flow during virtual community navigation. These three dimensions reflect the affective, cognitive, and behavioral aspects of virtual community members, similar to the general construct of attitude in the areas of marketing and behavioral science (Chen et al., 2013; Koh & Kim, 2003).
2.2.3. Sense of virtual community and online value co-creation behavior
Users who participate in a virtual community not only obtain information from others but also share their experiences with them (Casaló, Flavián, & Guinalíu, 2007; Tonteri et al., 2011). When people share a strong sense of community, they are more motivated to engage in online value co-creation behavior in the community (Chavis & Wandersman, 1990). A strong positive relationship between the sense of belonging and online users’ knowledge contribution behavior helps sustain virtual communities (Chai & Kim, 2012; Chen et al., 2013). As members identify themselves as part of the community, they feel an obligation and the need to give back to the online collective (Tonteri et al., 2011; Wasko & Faraj, 2000). Therefore, members with high levels of sense of virtual community feel obligated to share their thoughts, ideas, knowledge, and experiences with the virtual community.
In addition, members are more willing to exert extra efforts when they feel a sense of emotional involvement with, attachment to, or affective commitment to the group (Bagozzi & Dholakia, 2002). Therefore, members of virtual communities are likely to engage in community-like behavior such as helping others and giving mutual support to achieve certain objectives (Tonteri et al., 2011), and sense of virtual community results in continued engagement in such behavior (Blanchard, 2008). On the basis of these arguments, we hypothesize the following:
H1

Sense of virtual community has a positive effect on knowledge contribution behavior.

H2

Sense of virtual community has a positive effect on online community citizenship behavior.


2.3. Perceived online justice and sense of virtual community
In online community settings, favorable attitudes usually enable individuals to perceive their influence on other members (Koh & Kim, 2003). Because comparison is an important part of social exchange and provides the standard against which all relationships are judged (Ward & Berno, 2011), social exchange theory is one of the fundamental theories for understanding behavior between individuals and within groups (Blanchard, 2008). Equity theory further adopts social exchange theory to evaluate fairness in interpersonal interactions from a different lens (Adams, 1965; Kassin, Fein, & Markus, 2013; Messick & Cook, 1983). As justice constitutes the essential part of relationship maintainability in social exchange (Lind et al., 1993), it refers to perceptions of fairness and assessment of the appropriateness of performance outcomes or processes (Cropanzano & Greenberg, 1997) and usually represents a cognitive appraisal concept. Equity theory (Adams, 1965) states that an individual’s perception of the fairness of exchange relationships is determined by comparing his or her own output/input ratio with a referent other. A fair balance between input and outcome usually establishes a sense of fairness or justice (Cropanzano & Greenberg, 1997). Applied to the online setting, virtual participation is usually goal oriented, and one of its key motivating factors is perceived justice, which gives users the feeling of equity (Tonteri et al., 2011). When individuals engage in the exchange of value in virtual communities, the offering of knowledge or help must be equivalent to that received, along with the equity of the exchange (Adams, 1965; Wasko & Faraj, 2000). Thus, the need to understand online justice perceptions driving the virtual community participation is of crucial importance. In terms of previous literature, perceived justice can be distinguished according to four dimensions: procedural, distributive, interpersonal, and informational justice (Colquitt & Rodell, 2011). In addition, within the context of virtual community, we identify complementary justice as a fifth form of justice perception.
Users who visit a virtual community are not only seeking information or knowledge to solve specific problems; they are also taking part in the community to meet other people, gain support, stay connected with friends, have fun, and attain a sense of belongingness (Chiu et al., 2006). The quality of participation in virtual communities can affect whether a user will visit the site again, which is a prerequisite for building a sense of virtual community. Social cognitive theory argues that a person’s behavior is partly shaped and controlled by the influences of contextual factors and the person’s cognition (Chen & Hung, 2010), thus helping establish the relationships between the five factors of perceived justice and a sense of virtual community.
2.3.1. Distributive justice and sense of virtual community
Within the virtual community context, distributive justice refers to a user’s perceptions of fairness about returns or outcomes in terms of his or her community participation (Chiu, Wang, Shih, & Fan, 2011). According to equity theory, individuals determine the fairness of their outcomes by assessing the extent to which the ratio of their outcomes to their inputs is equivalent to the reference group ratios (Cloutier, Denis, & Bilodeau, 2013; Greenberg, 1990). That is, individuals strive to maintain equitable relationships, such that the ratio of outcomes to inputs is equal to the related individuals (Olivera, Goodman, & Tan, 2008). A psychological contract is made when users, participating in virtual communities, perceive other members as performing reciprocal behaviors fairly (Chiu et al., 2011). Indeed, reciprocity helps sustain supportive relationships and collective actions (Chiu et al., 2006; Mathwick et al., 2008; Wasko & Faraj, 2005). In addition, Robinson, Kraatz, and Rousseau (1994) argue that the psychological contract leads to relationship commitment. Consequently, distributive justice positively affects a sense of virtual community. Thus, we propose the following:
H3

Perceived distributive justice has a positive effect on sense of virtual community.


2.3.2. Procedural justice and sense of virtual community
Procedural justice refers to a user’s perceptions of fairness in the rules and procedures used to deal with issues that arise in the posting process (Colquitt, Conlon, Wesson, Porter, & Ng, 2001; Chiu et al., 2011). Virtual communities such as bulletin board system (BBS) groups, general forums, or professional forums are places in which individuals can share opinions and have discussions about various topics. For members, following the stipulated rules or guidelines to ensure effective conversation is one of the main purposes of these forums. If a member fails to comply with these rules or specific procedures, his or her posting may result in a ban from the entire site. For example, if someone posts lewd or offensive content or links, his or her posting will be eliminated because of the regulated procedure of the community. Individuals usually evaluate the extent to which procedures were followed and obeyed to form a sense of fairness. Therefore, procedural justice fulfills key psychological needs on the part of the individual and injects a sense of belonging in a relationship (Colquitt, LePine, Piccolo, Zapata, & Rich, 2012). Within the context of virtual communities, a sense of virtual community is fostered through user participation; therefore, users who perceive greater procedural justice in a virtual community tend to be more motivated to participate in the community, which in turn leads to a greater sense of virtual community. In contrast, unfairly regulating postings or unjustly handling problems or conflicts among members likely discourages users from participating in the community. Accordingly, we propose the following:
H4

Perceived procedural justice has a positive effect on sense of virtual community.


2.3.3. Interpersonal justice and sense of virtual community
Research indicates that interpersonal justice is fostered when organizations treat employees with dignity and respect and refrain from improper remarks or comments during the enactment of procedures (Colquitt et al., 2012; Greenberg, 1990). Indeed, many organizations implement justice climates, focusing on social relations, supportiveness, morale, and warmth, which in turn enhance employees’ sense of belonging (Carr, Schmidt, Ford, & DeShon, 2003). In virtual communities, interpersonal justice refers to individuals’ evaluation of fairness with regard to how other members treat them during virtual community participation (Chiu et al., 2011). Folger and Cropanzano (1998) show that the way members of virtual communities are treated during knowledge-sharing affects their perceptions of interpersonal fairness. This implies a clear role for members in virtual communities in terms of the satisfaction knowledge contributors attain through acts that show concern and respect and that are made in a truthful manner (Chiu et al., 2011). A highly interactive virtual community can encourage members to share experiences and communicate with one another, thus producing a sense of belonging (Keng et al., 2011). Therefore, we posit the following:
H5

Perceived interpersonal justice has a positive effect on sense of virtual community.


2.3.4. Informational justice and sense of virtual community
Informational justice refers to the extent to which virtual communities openly share information with all members to provide a sense of justification for the procedures implemented (Ellis, Reus, & Lamont, 2009; Greenberg, 1993). In other words, informational justice reflects the extent to which information is communicated in the virtual community. Because community members want to acquire knowledge about a certain topic or gain access to up-to-date information, their justice perceptions of the process of acquiring information are related to establishing membership, an important foundation of sense of virtual community (Colquitt et al., 2001; Tonteri et al., 2011). Thus, we hypothesize the following:
H6

Perceived informational justice has a positive effect on sense of virtual community.


2.3.5. Complementary justice and sense of virtual community
Kay and Jost (2003) speculated about the social and psychological mechanisms of “poor but happy,” “rich but miserable,” “poor but honest,” and “rich but dishonest” stereotypes. Such complementary perceptions represent the fairness of the social system. Because the equity of a complement is so important, an individual may feel the need to restore the balance sheet when he or she is falling short (Kassin et al., 2013). Within the online context, complementary justice means that some individuals have greater access to and influence on specific knowledge/information of certain topics than other members in the community, and vice versa. For example, in an online computer discussion forum, a user might not be familiar with all detailed information about various computer brands. However, if the user can easily access and share some information on one specific topic, he or she may feel valuable to the community, thus gaining a complementary justice perception. Furthermore, when members share information/knowledge useful to the community, they may gain confidence in what they can do, leading to increased self-efficacy (Constant, Kiesler, & Sproull, 1994; Hsu et al., 2007). In other words, individuals may enhance their perceived self-efficacy on the upside, compensating his or her losses of self-efficacy on the downside. As members improve their personal status and reputation by sharing valuable knowledge in the community, greater access to some information through participation can foster a sense of virtual community by evoking self-complementary mechanisms (Tonteri et al., 2011). We thus underscore the role of complementary justice (as exemplified by a “You have expertise in X, but I am specialized in Y” scenario) in contributing to members’ sense of belonging to virtual communities. Specifically, we suggest that perceived complementary justice when participating in the online community facilitates members’ positive attitudes toward the community. Thus, we hypothesize the following:
H7

Perceived complementary justice has a positive effect on sense of virtual community.


2.4. Mediation effects
Justice is viewed as the heart of relationship maintainability in all relational exchanges (Lind et al., 1993). Perceptions of online justice increase the probability of members’ long-term participation and raise their sense of belonging. Several studies have indicated that a member’s positive judgment of, feeling about, and past experience with a virtual community lead to a greater sense of belonging (Chen et al., 2013; Tsai, Cheng, & Chen, 2011). Therefore, we suggest that all five different dimensions of justice perceived by community members contribute to their sense of virtual community. Indeed, prior research has found that a sense of community increases the likelihood of members’ contribution and participation in a virtual community (Chiu et al., 2006; Yoo, Suh, & Lee, 2002). Through a strong sense of cohesiveness to a virtual community, members are willing to expend efforts to share knowledge with others because they believe this is the right thing to do (Wasko & Faraj, 2005) and will be more likely to maintain the community by continuously contributing knowledge to others.
Extant virtual community literature shows that the sense of virtual community conceptualization depends on members’ perceptions and overall acceptance of a certain online community. Chai and Kim (2012) explained that a stronger sense of belonging encourages users’ participation in knowledge contribution. When individuals believe they belong to a certain community, they will think of themselves and other community members as a collective and commit time and efforts to do something good for the community. Thus, a strong sense of virtual community can facilitate members’ knowledge contribution and online community citizenship behavior.
According to this discussion, this study suggests that sense of virtual community plays an important role in connecting users’ justice perceptions and knowledge contribution behavior in virtual communities. Members who perceive fairness in the community will continue to contribute their knowledge if they feel emotionally attached to the community. Therefore, we hypothesize the following:
H8

Sense of virtual community mediates the effect of all five justice dimensions on knowledge contribution behavior.


Sense of belonging refers to the feelings of attachment and affinity that members have for their virtual communities. Such attachment and belongingness, reflecting one’s desire to maintain social relationships with others in a community, create a continuing sense of obligation to help others (Chen et al., 2013; Wasko & Faraj, 2005). With a strong sense of cohesiveness and belongingness with other members, an individual will behave altruistically and pro-socially, contributing to the welfare of others without apparent compensation (Wasko & Faraj, 2000). We argue that members’ justice perceptions in virtual communities will facilitate their intention to help others through the development of sense of virtual community. Therefore, sense of virtual community acts as a mediator linking perceived justice and online community citizenship behavior. Thus, we hypothesize the following:
H9

Sense of virtual community mediates the effect of all five justice dimensions on online community citizenship behavior.


2.5. Control variable
Participation in a virtual community means actually performing online value co-creation behavior. Therefore, “customer readiness” reflects a mental desire that prompts users’ in- and extra-role value co-creation behaviors in virtual communities. Customer readiness contains role clarity, motivation, and ability which extant research identifies as predictors of knowledge contribution (Meuter, Bitner, Ostrom, & Brown, 2005; Reinholt, Pedersen, & Foss, 2011). Role clarity reflects an individual’s knowledge and understanding of what to do, motivation refers to a desire to receive benefits or rewards associated with participation in the virtual community, and ability indicates possession of the required skills and confidence that enable an individual to perform effectively in a virtual community. The model incorporates these three control variables as they may influence users’ knowledge contribution behavior and online community citizenship behavior.
Summing up the aforementioned arguments and hypotheses, we present the theoretical framework of this study in Fig. 1.
Research model
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Research model.]]>
</section>

    <section name="Method" category="methods">
        <![CDATA[
3. Method
3.1. Data collection
We developed an online questionnaire that was posted on different online communities and forums to recruit diverse respondents. Similar to Chou, Wang, and Tang’s (2015) typology of virtual communities, respondents were recruited from different kinds of virtual communities, including general forums (i.e., UrCosme, Fashion Guide, or KENLU.net), professional or technical forums (i.e., DC view, letsplay3atoys.com, or Figure Hobby Club), and discussion boards (i.e., iPeen.com or sisgo.com), but excluding BBS (e.g., Ptt.cc, as specially mentioned here1). Although Ptt.cc has over 200,000 boards covering various topics, plus more than 40,000 articles and one million comments posted per day, Ptt.cc was excluded from the data collection process for several reasons. First, some Ptt.cc boards have become inactive with a negligible amount of postings for consecutive months. Second, some active boards are loaded with meaningless threads which are irrelevant to the discussed topics. Third, some Ptt.cc users may encounter offensive responses from others due to divergence of opinion (such as differences in political ideologies). Those who feel offended may choose to “opt-out” and the remainder will dominate. The resulting climate of the platform becomes one-sided or uniform, which may jeopardize the representativeness of Ptt.cc as a source of data collection.
To ensure the quality and representativeness of our data, the selected virtual communities were chosen based on their rankings in Alexa, the world's most famous analytics-providing website. All respondents were asked to register to avoid multiple responses from a single person (IP addresses were recorded). The online survey specifically inquired respondents’ virtual community participation experiences. Initially, 299 subjects responded to our survey. After deleting 21 unusable observations, the final sample contained 278 observations. The number-one virtual community most users participated in was professional or technical forums (53.1%), followed by general forums (26.7%) and discussion boards (20.2%). The age of respondents varied from 18 to 50 years, and 75.9% were between the ages of 21 and 35. Roughly three-fifths of the respondents were male (58.6%), and approximately 62.9% held a university or bachelor's degree. With regard to participation duration, 83 (29.9%) had belonged to the community for one to three years, 76 (27.3%) had belonged for three to five years, and 87 (31.3%) had belonged for more than five years.

3.2. Measurements
We adopted or modified the measurement items employed from previous studies. In a pretest, participants were asked to fill out an initial draft of the questionnaire, which enabled us to refine the items further to arrive at the final version. All items were measured with seven-point Likert scales, ranging from 1 (strongly disagree) to 7 (strongly agree). We measured knowledge contribution behavior with items adapted from Chen and Hung (2010) and Hsu et al. (2007). We measured distributive, procedural, and interpersonal justice with Chiu et al.’s (2011) four-item scale. We assessed informational justice with Ellis et al.’s (2009) three-item measure. We developed six items for complementary justice on the basis of Seevers, Skinner, and Dahlstrom’s (2010) study. Following Yi and Gong (2013) and Zhang (2010), we treat online community citizenship behavior and sense of virtual community as second-order constructs with reflective first-order dimensions in this study. Diamantopoulos and Winklhofer (2001) suggested that the choice of reflective or formative constructs depends on causal priority between the indicator and the latent variable. When one construct is viewed as an underlying factor that gives rise to something that is observed, its indicators tend to be realized, and thus reflective measurements are more suitable. Adapted from Yi and Gong (2013), online community citizenship behavior, measured as a second-order construct, contained four reflective first-order dimensions: feedback, advocacy, helping, and tolerance. Sense of virtual community comprised three first-order dimensions that reflect the degree of community members’ membership in, influence on, and immersion in the selected online community (Koh & Kim, 2003). Finally, we adapted measures of customer role clarity, motivation, and ability to participate in the virtual community from Dellande, Gilly, and Graham (2004).
3.3. Common method variance
We collected our data using a single survey instrument. To address the potential concerns of common method bias, we used several procedural and statistical remedies. First, we undertook the procedural remedies of maintaining respondent anonymity to reduce respondents’ tendency to make socially desirable or acquiescent (lenient) responses (Podsakoff, MacKenzie, Lee, & Podsakoff, 2003). Second, we separated measurement items for perceived justice, sense of virtual community, and co-creation behaviors to reduce the likelihood of respondents guessing the relationship between predictor and criterion variables and consciously matching their responses to these measures (Parkhe, 1993). In addition, we conducted Harman’s one-factor test on crucial variables in our theoretical model (Harman, 1976; Podsakoff et al., 2003). Common method bias is present if the factor analysis results in a single factor or if one general factor accounts for more than 50% of the covariance. The results from this test showed that the highest covariance explained was 36.8%, indicating that common method bias is not a problem.]]>
</section>
    <section name="Results" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
4. Results
All models were run on LISREL 8.71 (Jöreskog & Sörbom, 1996) in the current study. LISREL is viewed as one of the most widely used Structural Equation Modeling (SEM) techniques in IS research. Following the two-step analytical procedures (Hair, Anderson, Tatham, & Black, 1998), we will first examine the measurement model, and then the structural model. The aim of the two-step approach is to assess the reliability and validity of the measures before using them in the full model.
4.1. Measurement model assessment
For a measurement model to have sufficiently good model fit, the chi-square value normalized by degrees of freedom (χ2/df) should not exceed 5, Non-Normed Fit Index (NNFI) and Comparative Fit Index (CFI) should exceed 0.9 (Bentler, 1989), and root mean square of approximation (RMSEA) should be lower than 0.08 (Byrne, 1998). For the current CFA model, χ2/df was 2.02 (χ2 = 2069.49; df = 1022), NNFI = 0.98, CFI = 0.98, and RMSEA = 0.058, suggesting adequate model fit. In addition, the composite reliability (CR) of constructs uses item loadings to construct factor scores that exceed Fornell and Larcker’s (1981) criterion of 0.70 in the measurement model and thus provides a good measure of internal consistency. We calculated convergent validity using factor loadings (Chin, 1998; Fornell & Larcker, 1981; Gefen, Straub, & Boudreau, 2000). In Appendix A, loadings of all items are greater than the recommended cutoff value of 0.60 (Bagozzi & Yi, 1988) on their intended constructs, with significant t-values at p < 0.01 (Chin, 1998), providing support for convergent validity of the measures (Gefen et al., 2000). As Table 1 shows, all constructs’ average variances extracted (AVE) were greater than 0.50 (Bagozzi & Yi, 1988; Fornell & Larcker, 1981), meaning that the variances captured by the measurement items were greater than the measurement errors.
Table 1. Correlations convergent validity, and discriminant validity.
Mean	S.D.	CR	AVE	PDJ	PPJ	PIJ	PINJ	PCJ	SOVC	KCB	OCCB	RC	AB	MO
PDJ	4.39	1.02	0.88	0.64	0.80										
PPJ	4.95	0.90	0.81	0.59	0.47	0.77									
PIJ	4.73	0.91	0.88	0.66	0.61	0.58	0.81								
PINJ	5.10	0.94	0.81	0.59	0.47	0.56	0.59	0.77							
PCJ	4.54	0.92	0.89	0.62	0.50	0.30	0.37	0.38	0.79						
SOVC	4.53	0.87	0.80	0.57	0.62	0.52	0.67	0.55	0.59	0.76					
KCB	4.65	1.00	0.90	0.65	0.57	0.53	0.53	0.54	0.63	0.70	0.81				
OCCB	4.86	0.76	0.85	0.59	0.58	0.55	0.61	0.60	0.58	0.72	0.69	0.77			
RC	4.88	0.90	0.89	0.62	0.49	0.58	0.52	0.69	0.49	0.66	0.67	0.72	0.79		
AB	5.17	0.89	0.93	0.68	0.53	0.45	0.53	0.62	0.49	0.65	0.62	0.72	0.71	0.83	
MO	5.13	0.86	0.89	0.57	0.54	0.55	0.60	0.72	0.48	0.70	0.66	0.66	0.72	0.65	0.75
S.D. – standard deviation; CR – composite reliability; AVE – average variance extracted; bolded diagonal elements are the square roots of AVE.

PDJ – perceived distributive justice; PPJ – perceived procedural justice; PIJ – perceived interpersonal justice; PINJ – perceived informational justice; PCJ – perceived complementary justice; SOVC – sense of virtual community; KCB – knowledge contribution behavior; OCCB – online community citizenship behavior; RC – role clarity; AB – ability; MO – motivation.


For satisfactory discriminant validity, the square root of the AVE should exceed the variance shared between a construct and other constructs (Chin, 1998; Fornell & Larcker, 1981). Table 1 shows the correlation matrix and indicates that the square roots of each AVE value are greater than the off-diagonal elements. The table also provides strong evidence of discriminant validity.
In addition to validity assessment, we checked for possible multicollinearity among the major constructs. Multicollinearity indicates the extent to which an independent variable covaries with other independent variables, and excessively high multicollinearity would violate the assumption that independent variables are mutually independent of each other. In our survey, the maximum variance inflation factor of all independent variables is 2.12, which is much lower than 10. Thus, according to Mason and Perreault (1991), multicollinearity among the constructs does not exist.
4.2. Structural model assessment
The structural model reflecting the assumed linear, causal relationships among the constructs were tested with the data collected from the validated measures. The model fit indices were within accepted thresholds: χ2 to degrees of freedom ratio of 1.95 (χ2 = 2019.67; df = 1034), NNFI = 0.98, CFI = 0.99, and RMSEA = 0.059. The results of the LISREL analysis indicate that, as expected, all hypothesized paths in the research model were statistically significant. Fig. 2 shows standardized path coefficients for the model. As predicted, the results show that sense of virtual community was positively associated with knowledge contribution behavior (β = 0.69, p < 0.01) and online community citizenship behavior (β = 0.82, p < 0.01), thus confirming H1 and H2, respectively. In addition, there was a positive relationship between perceived distributive justice and sense of virtual community (β = 0.15, p < 0.05), in support of H3. Users’ perceptions of procedural justice significantly influenced sense of virtual community, with a path coefficient of 0.15 (p < 0.05). The results also provide support for H4; both perceived interpersonal justice (β = 0.22, p < 0.01) and perceived informational justice (β = 0.19, p < 0.01) were positively related to sense of virtual community, in support of H5 and H6, respectively. Furthermore, users’ perceptions of complementary justice was positively related to sense of virtual community (β = 0.40, p < 0.01), indicating support for H7.
Results of structural modeling analysis
Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Results of structural modeling analysis.
4.3. Mediating effect
In accordance with Baron and Kenny’s (1986) testing procedure, Table 2 shows that sense of virtual community (M) fully mediates both the effects of perceived distributive and informational justice (X) on knowledge contribution behavior (Y): (1) the X → Y path is significant (e.g., βdistributive = 0.15, p < 0.01; βinformational = 0.15, p < 0.01); (2) the X → M path is significant (e.g., βdistributive = 0.16, p < 0.01; βinformational = 0.10, p < 0.05); (3) the M → Y path is significant (β = 0.59, p < 0.01); and (4) the X → Y path (with M included) drops from 0.15 and 0.15 to non-significant values of 0.05 and 0.09, indicating a strong mediation effect. However, sense of virtual community is found to partially mediate the impacts of the other three justice antecedents (i.e., perceived procedural justice, perceived interpersonal justice, and perceived complementary justice) on knowledge contribution behavior, because the M → Y paths for all antecedents are significant while the X → Y paths (with M included) are still significant (Kenny, Kashy, & Bolger, 1998). The results illustrate the partial mediating role of sense of virtual community in the research model, thus confirming partial support for H8. In contrast with knowledge contribution behavior, sense of virtual community (M) fully mediates both the effects of perceived distributive and interpersonal justice (X) on online community citizenship behavior (Y). Meanwhile, sense of virtual community partially mediates the effects of the remaining three justice antecedents (i.e., perceived procedural justice, perceived informational justice, and perceived complementary justice) on online community citizenship behavior (see Table 2). From these findings, H9 is also partially supported.
Table 2. Results of mediation test.
Constructs	Path coefficient	Mediation existence
Independent variable (X)	Mediator (M)	Dependent variable (Y)	X → Y	X → M	X + M → Y	
X → Y	M → Y	
PDJ	SOVC	KCB	0.15***	0.16***	0.05	0.59***	Full
PPJ	SOVC	KCB	0.20***	0.11**	0.14***	0.59***	Partial
PIJ	SOVC	KCB	0.12**	0.33***	0.10**	0.59***	Partial
PINJ	SOVC	KCB	0.15***	0.10**	0.09	0.59***	Full
PCJ	SOVC	KCB	0.40***	0.32***	0.22***	0.59***	Partial
PDJ	SOVC	OCCB	0.12**	0.16***	0.03	0.57***	Full
PPJ	SOVC	OCCB	0.16***	0.11**	0.10**	0.57***	Partial
PIJ	SOVC	OCCB	0.19***	0.33***	0.01	0.57***	Full
PINJ	SOVC	OCCB	0.22***	0.10**	0.17***	0.57***	Partial
PCJ	SOVC	OCCB	0.31***	0.32***	0.13***	0.57***	Partial
PDJ – perceived distributive justice; PPJ – perceived procedural justice; PIJ – perceived interpersonal justice; PINJ – perceived informational justice; PCJ – perceived complementary justice; SOVC – sense of virtual community; KCB – knowledge contribution behavior; OCCB – online community citizenship behavior.


**
p < 0.05.
***
p < 0.01.]]>
</section>
    <section name="Discussion, implications, and limitations" category="discussion">
        <![CDATA[
5. Discussion, implications, and limitations]]>
<h target="1" match="full">This study contributes to research on virtual communities by incorporating online justice perceptions that ultimately lead to value co-creating behaviors, including in-role knowledge contribution and extra-role online community citizenship behavior. <h target="2" match="full">The results indicate that all five justice perceptions have significant effects on both in- and extra-role value co-creation behaviors indirectly through the mediating role of members’ sense of virtual community.</h> 
   

<![CDATA[ According to these findings, members assess the fairness of an exchange by comparing their inputs with outcomes. Thus, if the results meet their expectations, they will judge that they were treated fairly (Maxham & Netemeyer, 2002) and feel more attach to the community. Furthermore, when members perceive the procedural process of participating in the community as fair, they are more likely to have positive feelings toward the community (Chebat & Slusarczyk, 2005; Yi & Gong, 2008). Interactional justice usually entails interactions, and our results show that individuals interact with respect and dignity in the community. With regard to informational justice, our results also show a high degree of knowledge sharing and information exchange. Therefore, perceived informational justice is a crucial factor affecting participants’ attachment to the community. Finally, complementary justice indicates that a member has greater access to a specific topic than other participants in the virtual community. Furthermore, individuals with a strong sense of virtual community are more likely to perceive positive behavioral outcomes and are prompt to exhibit knowledge contribution and online community citizenship behaviors.
In addition, using Baron and Kenny’s (1986) test of mediating effect, we show that sense of virtual community is a significant mediating variable between the five dimensions of perceived online justice and online value co-creation behavior in virtual communities. Although perceived justice is vital in a virtual environment, emotional attachment to the virtual community may be a more important factor that transfers the individual’s online justice perceptions to actual online value co-creation behavior. We found full mediation between sense of virtual community and perceived interpersonal justice, perceived informational justice, and knowledge contribution behavior and partial mediation between sense of virtual community and perceived procedural justice, perceived complementary justice, and knowledge contribution behavior. Moreover, ]]><h target="3" match="part">we found that perceived procedural and interpersonal justice influenced community participants’ online community citizenship behavior through sense of virtual community.</h>
        <![CDATA[The results indicate that sense of virtual community provides an important mediating mechanism through which perceived justice variables exert influences on participants’ in- and extra- role value co-creation behavior in the virtual community. ]]> <h target="4" match="full">This implies that participants’ justice perceptions have indirect but critical influences on in-role knowledge contribution behavior and extra-role citizenship behavior through sense of virtual community.</h>
        
        <![CDATA[5.1. Theoretical implications
This study provides several important insights into the study of online community participation (Li, 2012; Malinen, 2015; Talò, Mannarini, & Rochira, 2014). First, we built a model that incorporates both in- and extra-role value co-creation behaviors and empirically tested it in virtual communities. In the past decade, virtual communities have rapidly gained popularity as a vehicle for collective learning and knowledge creation (Ardichvili, Page, & Wentling, 2003). Prior studies have demonstrated that virtual communities are places in which participants share and co-create value through online discussions and knowledge exchange (Wasko & Faraj, 2005). Therefore, online value co-creation has been deemed the next frontier in competitive effectiveness. However, studies specifically examining users’ value co-creation behavior in virtual communities are still rare, as is research from both in- and extra-role behavioral perspectives. Taking into account the importance of online value co-creation, this article endeavors to fill the gap by examining both in-role knowledge contribution and extra-role online community citizenship behavior in virtual communities.
Second, our results indicate that sense of virtual community, which includes membership, influence, and immersion, has a positive effect on both in- and extra-role online value co-creation behavior. Although prior research has implied that sense of belonging affects online community user participation (Lin, 2008), we further demonstrate that people who are motivated, emotional attached to the community, and feel a sense of belonging to the community participate more in it—for example, by exchanging information, inviting friends to join the community, and contributing knowledge to the community. Our study thus adds to the online value co-creation literature by empirically highlighting the importance of sense of virtual community.
Third, we found that people’s justice perceptions and subsequent sense of virtual community positively affect their willingness to conduct knowledge contribution and online community citizenship behaviors in virtual communities. Previous studies have explored value co-creation in virtual communities from different theoretical perspectives, such as social capital theory (Chiu et al., 2006; Wasko & Faraj, 2005; Zhao et al., 2012), social cognition theory (Chiu et al., 2006; Hsu et al., 2007; Zhang, Fang, Wei, & Chen, 2010), motivation theory (Ardichvili et al., 2003; Wasko & Faraj, 2005), and commitment–trust theory (Hashim & Tan, 2015). Although online value co-creation behaviors have been investigated in information management literature, scant studies have discussed such behavior in virtual communities through the lenses of equity theory and social exchange theory. Our findings complement prior research by showing that members’ perceived online justice may lead to online value co-creation through the mediating effect of sense of virtual community.
Finally, our results showed that members’ sense of virtual community may arise from their online justice perceptions. The integration of online justice perceptions in the virtual community context seems a necessary step to better understand the drivers that motivate members to become involved in these communities (Chiu et al., 2006). Similar to organizational employees or customers, virtual community members also perceive justice through the participative process. We include four different justice dimensions from justice literature: distributive, procedural, interpersonal, and informational (Colquitt et al., 2001; Colquitt et al., 2012; Greenberg, 1993). We also add another justice perception from the complementary perspective (Kay & Jost, 2003)—that is, perceived complementary justice. Thus, future research on value co-creation is likely to benefit from further investigation of various online justice perceptions in virtual communities.
5.2. Implications for practice
This study enhances understanding of the roles of community justice perceptions and value co-creation behavior in a virtual community and thus provides practical implications for managing online participants. Although prior studies have established the importance of sense of virtual community, the significant impacts of participants’ justice perceptions on their participating attitude are noteworthy. From a managerial perspective, this research suggests that focusing on the five types of justice perceptions may be an effective way to encourage participants’ knowledge contribution and citizenship behaviors. Managers should thus consider participants’ perceived online justice as part of the participation process to maximize their emotional attachment to the virtual community.

As the results of our study indicate, sense of virtual community fully mediates the relationship among perceived interpersonal justice, informational justice, and knowledge contribution behavior. Informational justice helps eliminate barriers to knowledge exchange, but without specific rules or guidelines, the value co-creation required for successful knowledge contribution or helping behavior might be difficult to attain. Thus, managers should establish standard procedures to enhance knowledge sharing and information exchange in the community. In addition, to spur activity in virtual communities, managers could organize social interactions to improve members’ sense of virtual community. For example, managers could attempt to create better relationships among participants by facilitating the norm of reciprocity, which would enhance members’ attachment to the community.

In addition, we found that perceived complementary justice relative to specific topics is an important antecedent of in-role knowledge contribution and extra-role citizenship behavior. Therefore, managers should actively create more interactive channels in the virtual community for participants and provide more useful information related to different topics. By doing so, participants will gain more confidence and be willing to participate in the community.]]>

<h target="4" match="part">The mediating role of sense of virtual community suggests that managers should foster their participants’ belongingness to and consciousness in the community (Muniz  O'guinn, 2001). An individual’s sense of belonging to a group usually derives from the participation process—that is, interactions with other members, participation outcomes, and even the rules made by the group. As opinion leaders are the members who frequently share knowledge, interact with others, and solve community problems, managers could invite these leaders to act as moderators of virtual communities to ensure the fairness of member participation. Doing so might facilitate additional member involvement, thereby contributing to the community's knowledge and attracting more newcomers.
</h>

<![CDATA[5.3. Limitations and future research directions
This study has several limitations. First, we employed cross-sectional data to examine our theoretical model. Although we derived the proposed research hypotheses theoretically, all the hypothetical causal relationships can only be inferred rather than proved. Future longitudinal studies therefore should assess perceived online community justice, sense of virtual community, and both in- and extra-role online value co-creation behavior at several points in time to generate more insights into the management of virtual communities. Second, we controlled for respondents’ customer readiness in the study, in an attempt to keep the theoretical arguments consistent and the model parsimonious. As virtual communities are a public cyberspace for individuals to communicate and interact with one another, institutional and environmental factors may provide some additional explanatory power. Thus, further research could take institutional or environmental variables into account when examining virtual community participation. Finally, we collected measures for all constructs in this study through a single self-reported instrument, and thus common method variance may be a concern, according to Straub, Limayem, and Karahanna-Evaristo (1995). We undertook some procedural and statistical remedies to alleviate the potential common method variance problem in this study. Future research using more rigorous research methodologies, such as collecting predictors and dependent variables in different time, is still a necessity.]]>
</section>
    <section name="Conclusion" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
6. Conclusion
Using social exchange and equity theories, we developed and tested a theoretical model that investigated the antecedents (i.e., online justice perceptions) conducive to the cultivation of sense of virtual community and the consequences reflected by in- and extra-role value co-creation behaviors in virtual communities. By combining the organizational justice literature with the virtual community research streams, the results indicated that all five perceived online justice antecedents significantly affect sense of virtual community, which in turn has a significant effect on both knowledge contribution behavior and online community citizenship behavior. The links from online justice perceptions to in-/extra-role value co-creating behaviors through sense of virtual community may be an effective way for e-marketing managers to maintain the survival of and foster the growth of virtual communities. We have made significant progress in deepening the online community participation literature, and we hope that future research will shed more light on this and other related topics.]]>
</section>

    <section name="Appendix A" category="appendix">
        <![CDATA[
        
Appendix A.
.
Table A1. Constructs and measuring items.
Constructs	Questionnaire items	Standardized factor loadings
Perceived distributive justice	I think what I get is fair compared to how much I help the other members in the XXX virtual community	0.78
I think what I get is fair compared to the activeness of my responses to other members’ questions or problems in the XXX virtual community	0.87
I think what I get is fair compared to the speed of my responses to other members’ questions or problems in the XXX virtual community	0.82
I think what I get is fair compared to the efforts and time that I spend when contributing knowledge to the XXX virtual community	0.77
Perceived procedural justice	Decisions about deleting inappropriate postings are made consistently by the authorized supervisor in the XXX virtual community	0.72
The XXX virtual community clarifies the decisions about deleting inappropriate postings and provides additional information when requested by the members	0.76
The procedures followed by the XXX virtual community for handling problems or conflicts that arise during the knowledge-sharing process are fair	0.84
Perceived interpersonal justice	The members of the XXX virtual community treat me with courtesy	0.84
The members of the XXX virtual community show their concern for my rights as a community member	0.71
The members of the XXX virtual community treat me in a truthful manner	0.82
The members of the XXX virtual community treat me with friendliness	0.90
Perceived informational justice	The bilateral information sharing between members in the XXX virtual community is extensive	0.74
Full account of the information is provided by other members in the XXX virtual community	0.88
Consistent information posting rules are explained thoroughly in the XXX virtual community	0.72
Perceived complementary justice	I have confidence in my ability to provide more detailed knowledge in certain issues/topics than other members can do in the XXX virtual community	0.81
I have the expertise needed to provide valuable knowledge than other members can do in the XXX virtual community	0.83
I can provide more useful knowledge in certain issues/topics than other members in the XXX virtual community	0.82
I can often get unique knowledge in certain issues/topics that other members in the XXX virtual community are not aware of	0.75
The knowledge that I get from the XXX virtual community is typically better than that of the average members	0.78
Membership	I feel as if I belong to the XXX virtual community	0.90
I sense my membership in the XXX virtual community	0.92
I feel as if the XXX virtual community members are my close friends	0.82
I like the members in the XXX virtual community	0.77
Influence	I am well known as a member of the XXX virtual community	0.67
I feel that I control other members in the XXX virtual community	0.82
My postings in the XXX virtual community are often reviewed by other members	0.89
Replies to my postings appear in the XXX virtual community frequently	0.86
Immersion	I spend much time online in the XXX virtual community	0.87
I spend more time than I expected navigating the XXX virtual community	0.91
I feel as if I am addicted to the XXX virtual community	0.83
Knowledge contribution behavior	I frequently participate in knowledge-sharing activities in the XXX virtual community	0.87
I usually spend a lot of time conducting knowledge-sharing activities in the XXX virtual community	0.82
When participating in the XXX virtual community, I usually actively share my knowledge with others	0.89
When discussing a complicated issue in the XXX virtual community, I am usually highly involved in subsequent interactions	0.86
I usually involve myself in discussions of numerous issues/topics rather than specific ones in the XXX virtual community	0.84
Feedback	If I have additional useful information, I will let other members know in the XXX virtual community	0.93
When I receive valuable information from other members, I will comment about it in the XXX virtual community	0.98
When I experience a problem myself, I will let other members know about it in the XXX virtual community	0.75
Advocacy	I say positive things about the XXX virtual community to others	0.74
I recommend the XXX virtual community to others	0.93
I encourage friends and relatives to participate in the XXX virtual community	0.89
Helping	I assist other members in the XXX virtual community if they need my help	0.85
I help other members in the XXX virtual community if they seem to have problems	0.90
I teach members in the XXX virtual community if they need me to solve problems correctly	0.88
I give advice to other members in the XXX virtual community	0.81
Tolerance	If information is not delivered as expected in the XXX virtual community, I would put up with it	0.76
If other members make a mistake during information delivery in the XXX virtual community, I would be tolerant	0.69
If I have to wait longer than I normally expected to receive the information in the XXX virtual community, I would be patient	0.79]]>
</section>
</publication>
