<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker= "yu miao">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 6, Part B, December 2016, Pages 1360-1370</time>
International Journal of Information Management
    <title><h target="1" match="full">Exploring the comparative salience of restaurant attributes: A conjoint analysis approach</h></title>
    <author>Hosung Timothy Rhee</author>. Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
    <author>Sung-Byung Yang</author>. Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
     <author>Kyungho Kim</author>. Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
School of Business, Ajou University, 206 Worldcup-Ro, Yeongtong-Gu, Suwon 16499, South Korea
b
School of Management, Kyung Hee University, 26 Kyungheedae-Ro, Dongdaemun-Gu, Seoul 02447, South Korea
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.03.001</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
•
    <highlight id="1">The comparative salience of restaurant attributes is explored by employing a conjoint analysis.</highlight>
•
    <highlight id="2">The importance of each restaurant attribute varies in diverse contexts of restaurant types and customer’s origin.</highlight>
•
    <highlight id="3">Four major and fourteen minor propositions are suggested for future empirical research.</highlight>
•
    <highlight id="4">This study helps restaurant managers better prepare for customers needs and expectations.</highlight>

Abstract
    <abstract> <h target="1" match="full">This study explores how travelers select a restaurant for dining out, given that restaurant customers consider diverse attributes in making a selection. </h><h target="2" match="full">By applying a conjoint analysis, an exploratory multiple-case study is conducted for three restaurants in New York City. Findings from Study 1 (an overall travelers group) and Study 2 (two different country-of-residence groups: foreign and domestic travelers) show that food, value, atmosphere, and service are considered as substantially important criteria in selecting restaurants, in that order. However, results from Study 3 examining different restaurant types (low-priced food stand, low-priced indoor, and high-priced indoor) reveal that the food attribute is the most important factor, regardless of restaurant types, whereas the other attributes’ rankings vary. Results from Study 4 dividing the sample by both traveler origin and restaurant type demonstrate a total disparity in the importance ranking for all attributes. </h><h target="3" match="part">This study suggests that a conjoint analysis is an appropriate method for restaurant sector research in predicting the most important determinants consumers perceive among restaurant attributes. </h><h target="4" match="full">The findings may help restaurant managers develop specific strategies that fit the needs and expectations of different customer groups in terms of their type of restaurant.</h>
    </abstract>
    

Keywords
    <keywords>Restaurant attributes importance</keywords>
    <keywords>Online restaurant review</keywords>
    <keywords>Types of restaurants and travelers</keywords>
    <keywords>Conjoint analysis</keywords>
    <keywords>Multiple-case study</keywords>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
People worldwide enjoy eating out, regardless whether it is with family members or friends. Food aficionados conduct extensive information searches to find a great place to eat while sightseeing and shopping, as travelers or tourists are inclined to stop by famous eateries. Consumers use the Internet to take advantage of a variety of information about eateries, including professional and peer reviews. When customers shop online, however, they often need to make purchase decisions with incomplete information. To reduce this perceived risk, they tend to obtain information from online search engine advertising, product descriptions, and recommendation systems. Consumers now rely on online product reviews (OPRs) or discussions in online forums to help them make purchase decisions, since their helpfulness is of particular importance as consumers are likely to consider online reviews as more credible and informative than other online information, thereby facilitating consumers’ purchasing behavior (Chatterjee, 2001; Chen & Xie, 2008).
Travel review websites such as “TripAdvisor” are becoming more popular because they provide travelers with useful information related to hotel and restaurant selection, thereby saving them time and reducing expected risks. As online consumers share their experiences after purchasing and using products (Park, Lee, & Han, 2007), travelers also tend to express their experiences with hotels or restaurants in written phrases or rating scores (Rhee & Yang, 2015a). As many restaurants in Manhattan of New York City (NYC) compete to meet consumers’ basic needs, understanding how consumers select a restaurant is an urgent strategic requirement for restaurants to survive. Tourists to Manhattan may search for the most preferential restaurants to enjoy a particular type of dining experience before their visit, given that restaurants in Manhattan provide various types of cuisines. Tourists compare online information about restaurants’ attributes to narrow their selection and eventually choose the restaurant with the most attractive attribute. Given that online consumer reviews on travel review websites may positively or negatively affect restaurant reservations, restaurant managers should understand how to carefully interpret the reviews, including the information about key attributes such as value, service, atmosphere, and food, and incorporate this into the restaurant’s strategic management.
A conjoint analysis is a relevant tool in understanding how consumers make decisions about restaurant selections and to measure an attribute’s importance (Baek, Ham, & Yang, 2006; Park, 2004). Koo, Tao, and Yeung (1999) argued that a conjoint analysis helps restaurant managers to segment customer groups and meet that group’s specific needs. Accordingly, this study applies a conjoint analysis to explore the importance of the key four attributes in evaluating restaurants: value, service, atmosphere, and food from the perspectives of domestic and foreign travelers. Particularly, this study focuses on the three sample cases: “Shake Shack” (SS, a low-priced food stand), “Burger Joint” (BJ, a low-priced indoor), and “The Spotted Pig” (TSP, a high-priced indoor). These restaurants are selected for three reasons. First, these restaurants serve a more standard and typical hamburger with mass appeal, regardless of customer groups of country-of-residence. Second, burger restaurants in Manhattan are open 24-hours and have high volumes of domestic and foreign travelers, providing a convenient sample to compare restaurant attributes. Third, three restaurants were carefully selected by considering the number of online review counts on the target website of the study (i.e., TripAdvisor); when the keyword of “burger” on TripAdvisor was searched, three restaurants were ranked with high levels of online reviews. Given that the number of online reviews may indicate the intensity of underlying word-of-mouth (Duan, Gu, & Whinston, 2008), each of three selected restaurants (i.e., SS, BJ, and TSP) is more appropriate to represent a low-priced food stand, a low-priced indoor, and a high-priced indoor burger restaurant, respectively. Although including a high-priced food stand restaurant in the sample may provide the highest-quality external validity, the main data source, the travel review web site of TripAdvisor, does not have reviews of this category of restaurants. Hence, exploring three restaurant types may represent each category, leading to a high external validity for a conjoint analysis in this exploratory multiple-case study.
]]><h target="1" match="part">The purpose of this study is to explore how travelers select a restaurant, given that restaurant customers consider diverse attributes in selecting a restaurant. </h><![CDATA[More specifically, by applying a conjoint analysis, this study attempts to identify and compare the importance of attributes customers perceive while choosing a burger restaurant in diverse contexts of restaurant types as well as traveler types. The findings may help restaurant managers develop specific strategies that fit the needs and expectations of different customer groups in terms of their type of restaurant.

This study consists of the following four separate studies. The first study (Study 1) evaluates the importance of all four attributes (i.e., value, service, atmosphere, and food) using a complete customer group that includes both domestic and foreign travelers for each restaurant (i.e., SS, BJ, and TSP). In the second study (Study 2), the importance scores of each attribute are compared between foreign and domestic travelers of all eateries, and in the third study (Study 3), the attributes are compared for each restaurant separately for the combined customer group. Lastly, the fourth study (Study 4) compares each eatery’s attributes for domestic and foreign traveler groups separately. Finally, some meaningful propositions are suggested for future empirical studies based on the conjoint analysis results of the four combined studies and their related discussions.
</section>

    <section name="Literature review" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Literature review
2.1. Restaurant research employing a conjoint analysis
As the tourism market becomes globalized and the Internet serves as a more critical information source, consumers are likely to easily search for and compare restaurants, employing product or service attributes as selection criteria to simplify the selection process. Travelers tend to select restaurants depending on their own preferences or purposes for eating-out. As travelers increasingly depend on online review websites to find information about restaurants, earlier studies have recommended applying a conjoint analysis because this analytic method is useful for precisely analyzing the relative importance of restaurant attributes (Baek et al., 2006; Becker-Suttle, Weaver, & Crawford-Welch, 1994; Dube, Renaghan, & Miller, 1994; Koo et al., 1999; Park, 2004; Tse, 2001). A conjoint analysis is a useful tool in understanding and addressing the combined effects of multiple product attributes on product selection by customers (Green and Srinivasan, 1978; Wong & Chi-Yung, 2001). In addition, this analysis is more relevant in predicting overall consumer preferences by considering the aggregated utility scores of a product (Levy, 1995). Therefore, it is commonly used as a powerful marketing research tool to predict consumer choices among multiple product attributes (Baek et al., 2006).
Compared to ample studies on the selection of hotels, a conjoint analysis has been little employed to predict overall consumer preferences in the selection of restaurants although there is a similar pattern of selection between them (Koo et al., 1999). Accordingly, it is worth applying the same analytic technique to the restaurant sector to recognize the relative importance of multiple restaurants’ attributes. That is, customers tend to select a restaurant by considering the whole range of restaurant attributes in totality rather than each attribute separately (Baek et al., 2006). For example, online customers are likely to evaluate value, food, price, and atmosphere after experiencing restaurants, and then prioritize attributes based on their own satisfaction in its relative importance ratings. Consequently, knowing the relative importance of multiple attributes may help both online customers and restaurant managers respond to changes in attributes’ rankings. Customers are likely to consider the relative rank of attributes to select a restaurant, whereas restaurant managers are likely to implement effective restaurant operation strategies in response to changing customers’ satisfaction in product or service attributes. The following studies provide reasonable evidence to support applying a conjoint analysis in the restaurant sector.
First, Becker-Suttle et al. (1994) conducted a pilot study with two different age segments (senior citizens and non-senior citizens) into customer expectations of full service restaurant dining experiences. They found differences between the two age groups in some, but not all, attributes.
Second, Dube et al. (1994) developed 16 restaurant dining scenarios consisting of seven attributes and two levels for each attribute. The authors investigated the relative importance of restaurant service attributes that impact consumers’ repeat purchase intention, finding that pleasure and business purpose experiences generate different preferences. For both groups, food quality and attentive service are the most important factors for their revisit intentions. However, for pleasure occasions, helpful servers, atmosphere, and consistent food are the next important factors. For business occasions, atmosphere, consistent food, and then helpful servers are the three most important factors. Moreover, the authors converted the actual scores of one particular restaurant under investigation into utility scores to compare these with the ideal utility scores. Among the seven characteristics, the largest differences are found on food quality and staff attentiveness, with practically no difference for waiting time.
Third, Koo et al. (1999) generated a focus group consisting of 30 respondents with plenty of overseas travel experience (i.e., dining and business entertainment experiences) to answer a questionnaire. The respondents were asked to complete 27 profiles for three different eating-out purposes such as “family meal,” “business entertainment,” and “tourism” in Hong Kong. The authors found that food price affects consumers’ choice of restaurants differently depending on the purpose; consumers are price-sensitive for family meals while they are less concerned about price for business entertainment, given that business meals are usually paid by their employer. Customers prioritize service when they are selecting a restaurant for family meals more than for business meals. The atmosphere of a tourist spot is distinctly preferred by tourists in Hong Kong. The results provide empirical evidence that consumers definitely choose based on a complex set of attributes to select a target restaurant to make their buying decision, and that this decision differs depending on the dining purpose. Additionally, in terms of attributes’ relative importance, the study found that food quality, service, uniqueness, and price are the top four characteristics.
Fourth, Tse (2001) designed an experiment to explore the trade-off between service quality and price in restaurant dining experiences by constructing nine hypothetical scenarios involving three levels of service quality (equivalent of five-star hotel service, regular restaurant service, and fast food service) and three price levels for a lunch set ($30, $70, and $180). Potential customers were asked what combinational levels of restaurant service quality and price they prefer by ranking each scenario. A conjoint analysis revealed that price has a greater relative importance compared to service quality. However, the demographic data showed that while both female and male customers consider price more important than service quality, the difference between the two attributes is much smaller for females. Moreover, as the education level increases, the importance of price increases while it decreases the importance of service quality. Thus, consumers become more calculating as they gain knowledge.
Fifth, Park (2004) attempted to measure consumer values for dining out in terms of utilitarian (i.e., reasonable price, fast service, and promotional incentives) and hedonic values (i.e., mood, fast service, cleanliness, food taste, employee kindness, and facilities) and found that the relative importance of restaurant attributes and consumer buying behavior differ depending on the value sought from dining out; consumers seeking hedonic values are more likely to ascribe cleanness, atmosphere, fast service, promotional incentives (e.g., coupons), taste of food, location, employee kindness, menu variety, and facilities as important attributes in selecting a fast food restaurant. By contrast, consumers seeking utilitarian values are more likely to choose a fast food restaurant based on price, rapid service, and promotional incentives.
Lastly, Baek et al. (2006) employed survey samples consisting of college students in both South Korea and the Philippines to rank the top five of 16 attributes when they consider fast food restaurants. College students’ perceptions of the fast food restaurant selection criteria differences between South Korea and the Philippines were explored using a conjoint analysis. The results indicated that menu price is the most important attribute for college students in both countries in choosing fast food restaurants. However, the levels differed slightly. Korean college students consider brand, food-related attributes, and service- and hygiene-related attributes in sequence as the important determinants, whereas Filipino college students prioritize food-, service- and hygiene-related attributes, and brand, in that order. The authors showed that a conjoint analysis is relevant in studying how restaurant goers choose restaurants.
The aforementioned studies indicate that the four key common attributes such as value, service, atmosphere, and food can be considered as the most important factors when restaurant goers select a restaurant. Nonetheless, most previous studies have employed a conjoint analysis based on the data collected via survey questionnaire. However, the studies using “online review scores” could be more convincing and natural than the ones employing a survey questionnaire research method in that the former well represents the actual post-behavior attributes (Rhee & Yang, 2015a). In this sense, this study intends to fill the gap in the existing studies about the selection of restaurant by suggesting a conjoint analysis based on online rating scores. Specifically, this study examines the relative importance of hamburger restaurant attributes for different customer groups (i.e., domestic versus foreign travelers) in Manhattan. Knowing the findings may help restaurant managers to attract the expected customers from their competitors, as well as increase the satisfaction level of their existing customers. A conjoint analysis of restaurant attributes by customer characteristics may help restaurant managers to more progressively segment the market and determine their positioning (Amirani & Baker, 1995).
2.2. Restaurant attributes
2.2.1. Value
Although value is a broad term, people instinctively associate it with the price one has to pay for a product or service (Clark and Wood, 1998; Koo et al., 1999). It is a net benefit customers can gain after the total costs incurred. There are many variables in total costs one could perceive depending on personal preferences in prioritizing attributes. Restaurant consumers acquire experiential values from dining out. In restaurant dining experiences, one customer could place the utmost importance on price and fast and attentive service, while another could stress the quality of food and atmosphere in deciding whether or not they received good value for their money spent. Although the customers may feel that the price is on a high side, they could feel they are receiving a good value for money if they realize they are getting good quality food and service.
It is well known that customer satisfaction and behavioral intentions are likely influenced by price fairness or “value for money” (Andaleeb & Conway, 2006). Marketing theorists define perceived price fairness as whether or not consumers see the price as reasonable, acceptable, and just (Bolton, Warlop, & Alba, 2003). Consumers tend to compare perceived prices with their internal reference prices, which are most frequently paid and market prices in similar transactions. However, customers may view the price as unfair if it is unjustified given prevailing market conditions (Kimes & Wirtz, 2003). Perceived prices are often evaluated depending on the comparative sensitivity of costs. That is, if costs increase, consumers perceive a price increase to be fair, whereas they will form the opposite perception if costs are flat or declining. Accordingly, value or perceived price fairness leads to customer satisfaction and loyalty, while perceived price unfairness is likely to be connected to consumers’ dissatisfaction, complaints, and decreased brand loyalty.
2.2.2. Service
Ladhari, Brun, and Morales (2008) categorized 29 items into five dimensions, such as tangibles, reliability, responsiveness, assurance, and empathy to represent perceived service for restaurants. The tangibles’ dimension deals with customers’ detection of restaurant appearance, cleanliness, seating area comfort, and an attractive and legible menu. Reliability measures the restaurant’s dependable operations in terms of whether the ordered food is correctly served on time and any mistakes are corrected without delay. The staff’s attentiveness and expeditious action in serving customers are the focus of responsiveness, whereas the servers’ detailed knowledge of the menu items and their professional mannerisms in answering inquiries are the main elements of assurance. The employees’ sensitivity in sincerely caring for customers’ needs and wants is assessed by the empathy dimension. All 29 items have statistically significant effects on consumers’ positive and negative emotions that determine their satisfaction level, which in turn, influences whether customers would recommend the restaurant to others, become a loyal patron, and spend more money on the menu. Therefore, perceived service directly influences customer satisfaction, which influences consumers’ future visit intentions.
2.2.3. Atmosphere
Atmosphere can be defined as “the conscious designing of space to create effects in buyers” (p. 50), which is used to express the quality of the surroundings (Kotler, 1973). The interior design could evoke certain emotions that would positively affect their purchasing behavior. Atmospheric elements such as music, lighting, color, and scent often represent the quality of the surroundings that tourists tend to consider as one of the important restaurant attributes, given that the atmosphere is closely related with customers’ sensory stimuli. Heide and Grønhaug (2009) argued that creating and providing a distinctive atmosphere is a key factor for Norwegian hotels to satisfy guests. Accordingly, restaurant atmosphere may have a powerful impact on customers’ emotions, attitudes, and behavior. Kotler (1973) contended that attractive space design generates specific emotional effects in buyers, increasing the probability of consumers’ buying decision. Mehrabian and Russell (1974) proposed that the physical environment influences consumers’ emotional responses (e.g., pleasure and arousal), which, in turn elicits an approach or avoidance behavior toward the particular environment. Ryu and Jang’s (2007) research on the combined effects of multiple atmospheric variables on behavioral intentions, specifically in upscale restaurants, ambience (e.g., music, aroma, and temperature), and employee appearance are the important influences on customers’ emotional responses that affected their post-dining behavioral intentions.
2.2.4. Food
Although the food attribute is inherently important for securing diners’ satisfaction, the term food quality still lacks precise information, and an inquiry to determine more detailed attributes within the term could provide meaningful information. Kivela, Inbakaran, and Reece (1999) saw the importance of this problem and recommended presentation, tastiness, menu item variety, and temperature as critical sub-attributes that could influence diners’ satisfaction and potential re-patronage. Healthy options and freshness are two other attributes they mentioned as parts of the food quality attribute. Results from a survey questionnaire of 300 patrons of five mid- to upper-scale restaurants located in the Midwest and Eastern part of the U.S. indicate that presentation, taste, and temperature, in that order, had significant impacts on customer satisfaction, whereas healthy options replace temperature in influencing return intentions (Namkung & Jang, 2007). Hence, perceived food quality directly influences diners’ satisfaction, encouraging their future visit intention.]]>
</section>

    <section name="Research methodology" category="methods">
        <![CDATA[
3. Research methodology
3.1. Research sample and design
Hamburger restaurants have emerged as a typical representative of a global business as global travel, communication, and media have spread rapidly. Diverse foods from around the globe are sold in NYC, and hamburgers rank fourth among ten iconic foods in NYC (Sietsema, 2012). Visitors to NYC, defined as domestic travelers who live in the U.S. or as foreign travelers who live out of the U.S. (Rhee & Yang, 2015b), are more likely to find burger restaurants on every street or avenue. A hamburger restaurant is regarded as a place not only for economic and efficient dining but also for socializing and entertainment. Hamburger restaurant managers should manage diverse attributes to develop customer-oriented marketing strategies, given that the relative importance of restaurant attributes may differ depending on restaurant and consumer types.
This research adopts an explorative multiple-case study encompassing three eateries in Manhattan. Shake Shack (SS), Burger Joint (BJ), and The Spotted Pig (TSP) were selected because hamburgers (cheeseburgers) are their main dish, a food known globally whose price is generally economical to appeal to the masses. Additionally, each of these eateries has different setups: (1) SS is a low-priced food stand located in the middle of the park; (2) BJ is a low-priced indoor fast-food type restaurant located inside a midtown hotel; and (3) TSP is a high-priced stand-alone, full-scale restaurant with a full-service wait staff. Table 1 provides further details about each restaurant.
Table 1. Summary of selected restaurants.
Category	Shake Shack	Burger Joint	The Spotted Pig
Overview	A low-priced food stance located in the park	A low-priced restaurant located in the hotel lobby	A high-priced upscale European casual dining restaurant; serving British & Italian dishes; operated by a renowned chef, April Bloomfiled
Locations	Between the mid and downtown (Madison Square Park) area of NYC	In the midtown area of NYC	In the downtown (Greenwich Village) area of NYC
Flagship menu	Hamburger (Shackburger cheeseburger)
$4.75	Hamburger (Cheeseburger)
$8.27	Hamburger (Chargrilled cheeseburger) including French fries
$21
Seating capacity	Outdoor seating only inside the park	20–25; a limited seating area	100; bar and dining area
Wait staff	No	No	Yes
Employing information from the “restaurants travelers recommend” section of the TripAdvisor website, the leading travel review website, the importance scores for four attributes (value, service, atmosphere, and food) are calculated using a conjoint analysis, which is a de-compositional statistical method to examine the values of each attribute based on the overall ratings or rankings of each combination of attributes. This method portrays a real-life situation of consumers’ mindset when selecting a particular product or service because consumers usually evaluate a product or service as a whole instead of scrutinizing each attribute and summing them up to arrive at a conclusive rating. For this research, travelers’ reviews for three eateries, expressed in the numerical ratings (i.e., integer) of one through five (i.e., one being the lowest and five being the highest scores), are de-composed into four attribute categories with one overall rating. The importance score for each attribute is generated by applying the scores from these five categories in a conjoint analysis. The greater the importance value of an attribute, the more a traveler considers that attribute in providing an optimum rating for a restaurant. In other words, from the restaurant perspective, management should carefully control the combination values of the four attributes to consistently maintain the most favorable total part-worth values.

As explained, Study 1 analyzes the importance value of each attribute utilizing the combined data of domestic and foreign travelers across the three eateries. Study 2, similar to Study 1, evaluates the importance value of each attribute across the three eateries, but focuses on separate data of domestic and foreign traveler groups, respectively. Study 3 examines the importance scores of each attribute for each of three different restaurant types utilizing the combined data-set. Finally, Study 4 scrutinizes two different country-of-residence groups for each of three different restaurant types.

3.2. Data collection
The entire data-set for the three selected restaurants was collected from TripAdvisor website, using web-harvesting methods with the R programming language, which supports automatic gathering a large amount of data from websites (Gandrud, 2013). The overall ratings, as well as rating scores of the four attributes (i.e., value, service, atmosphere, and food), were collected as numerical numbers, which were then used for calculating the importance scores of each attribute. As for the domestic versus foreign traveler groups, each reviewer’s address information was gathered as a raw text first, and then it was categorized into two groups based on Rhee and Yang’s (2015a) recommendation. Reviews without the reviewer’s origin information were omitted for the study. Since the data covers a full one-year period from January 1st to December 31st, 2013, any possible biased results from only considering a specific or limited period within one-year period could be minimized. For example, Rhee and Yang (2015a) argued that a one-year observation period makes it possible to control for expected biased reviews that tend to occur during the busy seasons such as Christmas and New Year’s Eve days. A total of 471 reviews, of which 212, 131, and 128 belong to SS, BJ, and TSP, respectively, qualified for the research after the data cleansing process. Dividing the data-set into two groups yields a total of 76, 51, and 41 domestic travelers and 136, 80, and 87 foreign travelers for SS, BJ, and TSP, respectively. Table 2 describes the frequency and percentage for three categories, such as the time period for reviewing each burger restaurant, country-of-residence of reviewers (i.e., domestic versus foreign travelers) in each eatery, and overall review ratings for each restaurant.
Table 2. Summary of the collected data-set.
Category	Sub-category	Shake Shack	Burger Joint	The Spotted Pig
Freq.	Pct.	Freq.	Pct.	Freq.	Pct.
Review Date	2013.10–2013.12	45	21.23	29	22.14	33	25.78
2013.7–2013.9	64	30.19	39	29.77	32	25.00
2013.4–2013.6	54	25.47	36	27.48	33	25.78
2013.1–2013.3	49	23.11	27	20.61	30	23.44
Sub-total	212	100	131	100	128	100

Country-of-Residence	Domestic travelers	76	35.85	51	38.93	41	32.03
Foreign travelers	136	64.15	80	61.07	87	67.97
Sub-total	212	100	131	100	128	100

Overall Ratings	5	112	52.83	62	47.33	50	39.06
4	66	31.13	46	35.11	45	35.16
3	22	10.38	12	9.16	18	14.06
2	5	2.36	6	4.58	12	9.38
1	7	3.30	5	3.82	3	2.34
Sub-total	212	100	131	100	128	100]]>
</section>

    <section name="Results" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
4. Results
4.1. Study 1: overall customer (domestic and foreign travelers) group across the three restaurants (SS, BJ, and TSP)
Using the combined data of domestic and foreign travelers for all three eateries, Study 1 explores the comparative salience of the four key restaurant attributes. The results in Table 3 of the conjoint analysis show that the food attribute is considered the most important factor in the overall travelers group, with an importance score of 0.326. Fig. 1 depicts a visual graph of how the four key attributes align across the restaurants. The results also indicate that value, atmosphere, and service are ranked in sequential order, where their respective importance scores are 0.264, 0.226, and 0.183.
Table 3. Attribute rankings for the overall customer group for three restaurants.
Attributes	Importance	Rank
Value	0.264	2
Service	0.183	4
Atmosphere	0.226	3
Food	0.326	1
Fig. 1
Download high-res image (158KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Study 1: Importance values for the four attributes.
4.2. Study 2: comparison between domestic and foreign travelers for three restaurants (SS, BJ, and TSP)
To elaborate on findings from Study 1, Study 2 carefully explores the comparative importance scores of the four key attributes for foreign and domestic traveler groups. As shown in Study 1, each group in Study 2 ranks the four key attributes the same, but the results in Table 4 and Fig. 2 provide slightly different implications for each customer group. Both the value and service attributes’ importance ratings are lower for foreign travelers (0.265 and 0.182) than for domestic travelers (0.272 and 0.211). However, foreign travelers’ ratings for the atmosphere and food attributes (0.234 and 0.319) are higher than those of domestic travelers (0.219 and 0.299).
Table 4. Attribute rankings for domestic versus foreign travelers for all three restaurants.
Attributes	Domestic travelers	Foreign travelers
Importance	Rank	Importance	Rank
Value	0.272	2	0.265	2
Service	0.211	4	0.182	4
Atmosphere	0.219	3	0.234	3
Food	0.299	1	0.319	1
Fig. 2
Download high-res image (300KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Study 2: Importance values for the four attributes by type of traveler (domestic versus foreign).
4.3. Study 3: overall restaurant customer group (domestic and foreign travelers) for each restaurant
The third study examines the attributes for the overall customer group for each type of restaurant: a low-priced food stand (i.e., SS), a low-priced indoor (i.e., BJ), and a high-priced indoor (i.e., TSP). Comparing the three eateries from the perspective of all customers, Table 5 shows that restaurant customers, regardless of burger restaurant type, consider the food attribute the most important factor, with importance rating scores of 0.317 in BJ, 0.292 in TSP, and 0.279 in SS. Fig. 3 presents the visual comparison. The comparative importance level of the value attribute is similar in both SS (0.266) and BJ (0.269), while its importance is lower in TSP (0.243). Service value (0.257) in SS is much greater than those of BJ (0.159) and TSP (0.193). Conversely, the importance value of SS’s atmosphere attribute (0.198) is much less than those of BJ (0.255) and TSP (0.272).
Table 5. Attribute rankings of the overall restaurant customer group for each restaurant.
Attributes	Shake Shack	Burger Joint	The Spotted Pig
Importance	Rank	Importance	Rank	Importance	Rank
Value	0.266	2	0.269	2	0.243	3
Service	0.257	3	0.159	4	0.193	4
Atmosphere	0.198	4	0.255	3	0.272	2
Food	0.279	1	0.317	1	0.292	1
Fig. 3
Download high-res image (661KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 3. Study 3: Importance values for the four attributes by type of restaurant.
4.4. Study 4: domestic versus foreign traveler groups for each restaurant
To further drill down into the results from Study 3, Study 4 scrutinizes two different country-of-residence groups (i.e., domestic versus foreign customer groups) for each of the three different restaurant types (i.e., SS, BJ, and TSP). The results of Study 4 are summarized in Table 6.
Table 6. Attribute rankings for domestic versus foreign restaurant customers at each restaurant.
Restaurant type	Attributes	Domestic customers	Foreign customers
Importance	Rank	Importance	Rank
Shake Shack	Value	0.257	2	0.273	1
Service	0.255	3	0.254	3
Atmosphere	0.201	4	0.211	4
Food	0.288	1	0.261	2

Burger Joint	Value	0.228	3	0.265	2
Service	0.156	4	0.186	4
Atmosphere	0.274	2	0.248	3
Food	0.342	1	0.300	1

The Spotted Pig	Value	0.321	1	0.231	3
Service	0.234	3	0.180	4
Atmosphere	0.158	4	0.281	2
Food	0.287	2	0.308	1
4.4.1. Shake Shack
When comparing the evaluation of domestic with foreign customers eating at SS, as shown in Table 6, the four attributes have close importance values. The largest importance difference between two groups is found in the food attribute (0.027), whereas for service it is almost equal (i.e., the relative importance values for service are 0.255 for domestic customers and 0.254 for foreign customers) (also see Fig. 4).
Fig. 4
Download high-res image (580KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 4. Importance values of the four attributes by type of traveler at Shake Shack.
4.4.2. Burger Joint
Comparing domestic and foreign restaurant customers eating at BJ reveals a similar difference in values across all four attributes (see Table 6). The largest difference between the two groups is in the food attribute (0.042), with minimal importance difference in the atmosphere attribute (0.026). Interestingly, the importance values of two attributes (value and service) are greater for foreign travelers, but the pattern reverses for the remaining two attributes (atmosphere and food) (also see Fig. 5).
Fig. 5
Download high-res image (525KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 5. Importance values for the four attributes by domestic versus foreign customers at Burger Joint.
4.4.3. The Spotted Pig
Unlike the findings for SS and BJ, the importance values for TSP in Table 6 vary haphazardly between domestic and foreign travelers. The atmosphere attribute generates the largest importance difference (0.123), while the food attribute produces the smallest importance difference (0.021) between the two groups (also see Fig. 6).
Fig. 6
Download high-res image (573KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 6. Importance values for the four attributes by type of traveler (domestic versus foreign) at The Spotted Pig.]]>
</section>

    <section name="Discussion and propositions" category="discussion">
        <![CDATA[
5. Discussion and propositions
Applying a conjoint analysis, this study explored how the comparative importance of restaurant attributes differ depending on the characteristics of restaurant customer groups (i.e., domestic versus foreign customers) and type of eatery (i.e., a low-priced food stance, a low-priced indoor, and a high-priced indoor). This study employed a sample of travelers to Manhattan that are more likely to find burger restaurants in NYC’s 21 iconic burger restaurant list on every street or avenue, providing a good research setting to understand how travelers to Manhattan select their restaurants.

Study 1 investigated the comparative importance scores of restaurant attributes for the overall customer group. The results in Table 3 show that food, value, atmosphere, and service are ranked in that order for the combined sample of domestic and foreign travelers. As the existing study found that the tourists in Hong Kong regard food quality and value as the top two attributes in selecting a restaurant (Koo et al., 1999), similar results are obtained for tourists in Manhattan. However, the results of Study 1 show distinctive findings by providing more detailed relative importance of the attributes; when choosing hamburger restaurants in Manhattan, travelers tend to consider food as the top priority, value and atmosphere attributes as the next priority in sequential order, and the service attribute as relatively less important. The results indicate that the food attribute is the most important determinant in choosing burger restaurants, providing evidence that food, along with value, the functional and economical attributes of fast food restaurants, is the basic factor in choosing food restaurants (Baek et al., 2006; Park, 2004). By contrast, the results further suggest that customers are less likely to be concerned about the service attribute in choosing burger restaurants in Manhattan. Based on these results, the following propositions can be assumed:
]]><h target="3" match="part">Proposition 1. Travelers would prioritize each restaurant attribute differently.
Proposition 1a. Among the four restaurant attributes, travelers would place the highest importance on the food attribute.
Proposition 1b. Among the four restaurant attributes, travelers would place the least importance on the service attribute.</h><![CDATA[
By using all restaurants in a combined data-set, Study 2 examined how the comparative importance scores of the four key restaurant attributes differ by type of traveler divided into foreign versus domestic traveler groups. Travelers would choose by their own preference and enjoy burgers at Shake Shack, Burger Joint, and The Spotted Pig. However, travelers may expect a differing importance levels when choosing burger restaurants. For example, travelers might expect a different importance level for the service attribute depending on the type of restaurant, as well as the customer group. Hence, the expected different importance scores of attributes that customers consider when choosing burger restaurants in Manhattan was compared in Study 2.

The results in Table 4 show that the actual importance levels of value and service are higher for domestic rather than foreign travelers, where importance rating scores for both factors in the former group are 0.272 and 0.211, and are 0.265 and 0.182 in the latter. However, the actual importance scores of atmosphere and food attributes are much higher in the foreign traveler group than the domestic one, where the importance rating scores for atmosphere and food attributes for domestic travelers are 0.219 and 0.299, and 0.234 and 0.319 for foreign travelers. Fig. 2 shows additional interesting findings that the service attribute is the least important in both foreign and domestic groups, but the difference of relative importance in this attribute is quite high, suggesting that foreign tourists to Manhattan are less likely to put the priority on the service attribute. It is interesting that foreign customers emphasize hedonic factors (e.g., atmosphere) more than domestic customers in evaluating burger restaurants. Domestic travelers consider utilitarian factors (e.g., value and rapid service) more than foreigners when selecting burger restaurants. These findings definitely imply that travelers prioritize restaurant attributes depending on their origin. Accordingly, the findings in Study 2 provide the following propositions:
Proposition 2. Both domestic and foreign travelers would prioritize the four restaurant attributes in the same order in total importance but a different way in its relative importance.
Proposition 2a. Domestic travelers would emphasize the value and service attribute more than foreign travelers.
Proposition 2b. Foreign travelers would emphasize the atmosphere and food attributes more than domestic travelers.</h><![CDATA[
Study 3 examined the comparative importance scores of the four key restaurant attributes for the overall customer group for each of low-priced food stand (SS), low-priced indoor (BJ), and high-priced indoor restaurants (TSP). The results in Table 5 provide four interesting findings.
First, the results in Table 5 show that restaurant customers visiting burger restaurants in NYC, regardless of burger restaurant type, consider the food attribute the most important factor, with scores at SS, BJ, and TSP of 0.279, 0.317, and 0.292, respectively. These results support a recent argument that the food itself is the most important food-related factor (Baek et al., 2006; Park, 2004).
Second, the results in Table 5 show that compared to actual importance scores (0.243) of the value attribute of TSP, the same scores in both SS and BJ are considered relatively more important determinants in evaluating low-priced eateries, with importance scores of 0.266 and 0.269, respectively. These findings provide an interesting interpretation; hamburger restaurant customers in Manhattan tend to evaluate value almost equally when they visit low-priced food stand or indoor eateries, but they tend to consider value relatively less important when they visit the high-priced indoor restaurants. The reason for this may suggest that the value attribute in food stands is of relatively less importance than in low-priced indoor restaurants, but the value in high-priced burger restaurants is a basic qualification, not an additional attribute for the selection of restaurants.
Third, Study 3 also shows that the comparative importance scores for the service attribute are the highest in low-priced food stands (SS), where the importance scores are 0.257. In contrast, the actual importance scores for BJ and TSP were 0.159 and 0.193, respectively. These results may imply that restaurant customers visiting low-priced food stand eateries are likely to consider better service of relatively greater importance. But, the service attribute may be regarded as a hygiene factor in choosing low-priced or high-priced indoor eateries: that is, a low level of service in both BJ and TSP may cause customers’ dissatisfaction. However, customers tend to regard a high-level of service as a corollary to low- and high-priced indoor restaurants, in that social convention dictates that customers leave a percentage of the bill to the wait staff as a tip for service.

Fourth, the actual importance score for the atmosphere attribute at TSP is 0.272, which is a highly important factor in evaluating high-priced indoor eateries, whereas the same scores at both SS and BJ are 0.198 and 0.255, respectively, and where the atmosphere attribute is considered relatively less important. The results demonstrate that travelers emphasize the atmosphere attribute in choosing high-priced indoor burger restaurants, and are more concerned about value in both low-priced food stands and low-priced indoor restaurants. These findings suggest that travelers in NYC enjoy the hedonic aspect in high-priced indoor restaurants, and are likely to enjoy the economical attributes at the others. These findings imply the following propositions:

]]><h target="3" match="part">Proposition 3. Restaurant goers would prioritize the four key restaurant attributes differently depending on the type of restaurant.
Proposition 3a. Regardless of the restaurant type, travelers would place the utmost importance on the food attribute among all attributes.
Proposition 3b. Travelers would prioritize the value attribute in low-priced restaurants.
Proposition 3c. Travelers would prioritize the service attribute in food-stand restaurants.
Proposition 3d. Travelers would prioritize the atmosphere attribute in indoor restaurants.</h><![CDATA[
Study 4 more carefully scrutinized Study 3 to determine how the two separate domestic and foreign customer groups consider the comparative importance scores of the four key attributes for each of three restaurant types. The results in Table 6 show that domestic customers’ top preference at a low-priced food stand (SS) is the food attribute (importance score = 0.288), and that value (0.257), service (0.255), and atmosphere (0.201) follow in that order. The findings, however, also reveal that foreign customers’ top preference at SS is value (importance score = 0.273), and that food (0.261), service (0.254), and atmosphere (0.211) follow in sequence. The results imply that both domestic and foreign customers regard food and value, at least at the low-priced food stand restaurant, as the most important. However, the results carefully qualify that foreign customers are likely to emphasize value and atmosphere attributes more than domestic customers, whereas this group considers the food itself as the most important determinant.
For the BJ (a low-priced indoor), the results in Table 6 show that both domestic and foreign customers’ top preferences are food (importance scores for each group are 0.342 and 0.300, respectively), indicating that food, regardless of traveler type, is the most important factor at low-priced indoor restaurants. The results further reveal that foreign customers place a higher priority on value (0.265) and service (0.186), compared to domestic customers’ preference for the same factors (value, 0.228; service, 0.156). However, the reverse is shown in Table 6, for the food and atmosphere attributes; domestic customers place more importance on food and atmosphere factors in selecting low-priced indoor restaurants.
For the TSP (a high-priced indoor), the results in Table 6 show that domestic customers’ top preference is value (0.321), and that food (0.287), service (0.234), and atmosphere (0.158) follow in that order. The results also indicate that foreign customers’ top preference for this type of restaurant is food (0.308, with atmosphere (0.281), value (0.231), and service (0.180) following in sequence. The results imply that foreign customers are likely to emphasize food and atmosphere more than other attributes in selecting high-priced indoor burger restaurants, whereas domestic customers prioritize value and service. These findings lead to the following propositions:
]]><h target="3" match="part">Proposition 4. For specific restaurant types, domestic and foreign travelers would prioritize different attributes.
Proposition 4a. For low-priced food stands, foreign travelers would emphasize the value and atmosphere attributes more than domestic travelers.
Proposition 4b. For low-priced food stands, domestic travelers would place a higher importance on the food attribute than foreign travelers.
Proposition 4c. For low-priced indoor restaurants, foreign travelers would prioritize the value and service attributes more than domestic travelers.
Proposition 4d. For low-priced indoor restaurants, domestic travelers would emphasize the atmosphere and food attributes more than foreign travelers.
Proposition 4e. For high-priced indoor restaurants, foreign travelers would place a higher importance on the atmosphere and food attributes more than domestic travelers.
Proposition 4f. For high-priced indoor restaurants, domestic travelers would prioritize the value and service attributes more than domestic travelers.</h><![CDATA[
</section>

    <section name="Conclusion and implications" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
6. Conclusion and implications
6.1. Findings
]]><h target="2" match="part">The findings in Study 1 confirm that food taste and value are basic attributes in choosing restaurants, supporting prior research (Baek et al., 2006; Park, 2004). The findings in Study 2 demonstrate that attributes’ comparative importance varies according to traveler type (i.e., domestic versus foreign travelers). Foreign customers emphasize hedonic factors in their selection of burger restaurants, whereas domestic travelers consider utilitarian factors, implying that marketing managers may pay more attention to atmosphere to attract foreign travelers, and focus on service for domestic customers. Study 3 carries two interesting findings. First, travelers visiting burger restaurants in NYC, regardless of restaurant types, consider food quality the most important factor. Second, customers emphasize the atmosphere attribute (i.e., the hedonic aspect) more when selecting indoor burger restaurants, and are more concerned about the value attribute (i.e., the utilitarian aspect) in low-priced restaurants. Furthermore, the results from Study 4 shows that foreign customers are more likely to emphasize food and atmosphere attributes than domestic customers in selecting high-priced indoor burger restaurants, whereas domestic customers prioritize value and service. The findings from Studies 3 and 4 may motivate restaurant managers (or operators) to focus on only one or two attributes in that they should make a strategic decision to leverage limited restaurant resources. In other words, restaurant managers can evaluate the relative importance of each attribute by comparing total importance with that of each attribute, and then efficiently allocate resources.</h><![CDATA[
6.2. Managerial implications
This research attempted to identify and compare the attributes that travelers to NYC perceive as important when selecting a burger restaurant. Restaurant managers can prioritize these attributes to sustain a constant flow of customers by managing the key restaurant attributes to attract customers in NYC. These attributes could be a necessary core competency to create and sustain competitive advantage in the restaurant industry. For this purpose, restaurant managers should carefully consider the key restaurant attributes in evaluating customers’ attitudes and responses to restaurant marketing strategies, given that customers place their experiences on online travel or restaurant websites after purchase. Continuously monitoring and collecting attribute data via these websites are necessary because online customers tend to rest on online reviews to collect information related to their purchase decision (Kim, Suh, & Suh, 2008; Lee, Lee, & Tan, 2013; Rhee & Yang, 2015a, 2015b). ]]><h target="4" match="part">Accordingly, understanding how the relative importance values of restaurant attributes influences restaurant selection may help restaurant managers quickly respond to changes in attributes’ relative importance.</h><![CDATA[
6.3. Theoretical implications
The findings from the conjoint analysis have also theoretical implications. First, this study confirms that a conjoint analysis is an appropriate method not only for hotel sector but also for restaurant sector research in predicting the most important determinants consumers perceive while choosing restaurants. More specifically, this study employed a conjoint analysis to analyze voluntary data (i.e., restaurant customers are willingly expressing their opinions on online review websites) to evaluate four restaurant attributes and confirmed that, as Rhee and Yang (2015a) argued, OPRs better represent consumers’ real thinking and intentions, compared to survey questionnaires and scenario-based experiments. Moreover, unlike the survey questionnaire approach, which often carries social desirability effects and common method bias issues, OPR data-set does not have to address these problems. Accordingly, it is suggested that a conjoint analysis can better predict consumer behavior in the restaurant arena.
Second, extant empirical studies have tended to focus on examining the impacts of restaurant attributes on customers’ attitude (i.e., satisfaction) or behavior (i.e., intention to revisit) by applying a regression or structural equation model. Therefore, this study could expand this partial tendency of restaurant research by validating the comparative importance of restaurant attributes through a conjoint analysis. Particularly, the relative importance or ranking of each attribute has rarely been explored using online review data; thus, it could be a stepping stone for the hypotheses development of future empirical studies. Furthermore, the relationship between customers’ overall satisfaction (i.e., overall rating scores) and specific dimensional or functional satisfaction (i.e., rating scores of each of four attributes) in varying contexts of restaurant types (i.e., low-priced food stand, low-priced indoor, and high-priced indoor) as well as traveler types (i.e., domestic and foreign) could be a new and interesting subject of future research.

<![CDATA[6.4. Limitations and future research
Similar to many prior studies, this study also has some limitations. First, this study employed data only for three types of restaurants in NYC, the busiest city in the world. Accordingly, future findings can be strengthened by adding different restaurant types and comparing different locations. Second, this study targeted relatively well-operated restaurants, so the sample would benefit by including restaurants of varying degrees of efficiency. Third, the combination of a conjoint analysis (based on ratings) and a content analysis (the textual review itself) could generate a higher-quality interpretation in understanding how restaurant consumers choose different types of restaurants. Finally, this study has a self-limitation in terms of the generalizability of the results as it takes an exploratory approach. Although the theory-driven approach has yet to be studied in the tourism research area, propositions suggested in the study could be empirically validated in future research.]]>
</section>

Acknowledgement
This work was supported by the National Research Foundation of Korea Grant funded by the Korean Government (NRF-2014S1A2A2028351).
</publication>