<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication maker="liu bin">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 1, February 2016, Pages 105-112</time>
International Journal of Information Management
    <title>Corruption as a source of e-Government projects failure in developing countries: A theoretical exposition</title>
    <author>Adel M. Aladwani.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspace
    <![CDATA[Department of QM & IS, College of Business Administration, Kuwait University, Kuwait]]>
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2015.10.005</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">Details the influence of corruption on e-Government failure in developing countries.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">Argues that corruption could restrict moral and governance capabilities of e-Governments initiatives.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">Argues that such restriction causes failure of e-Governments to meet stakeholders' expectations.</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">Sets the stage for further scientific inquiries into this important topic.</highlight>

    <abstract><![CDATA[
Abstract
While the literature has touted e-Government as a tool for combating corruption, no study has discussed so far how corruption could influence e-Government project failure. This article tries to fill part of this void in past research by proposing a contextual framework that highlights the role corruption plays in stimulating the failure of e-Government projects in developing countries. ]]> <h target="2;3" match="part;part"> Informed by prior relevant literature on general systems, organizational information processing, corruption, as well as e-Government, the proposed framework argues that the prevalence of corruption in developing economies could restrict moral and governance capabilities of administrative systems overseeing e-Governments in a way that could lead to the failure of these entities to produce initiatives that meet stakeholders' expectations.</h> <![CDATA[ This theoretical study discusses this idea and underscores the value of the suggested framework for guiding scientific inquiries into this important topic and helping the public officials interested in planning, managing, and auditing e-Government initiatives.
]]></abstract>

    <keywords>e-Government</keywords>
    <keywords>Failure</keywords>
    <keywords>Corruption</keywords>
    <keywords>Framework</keywords>
    <keywords>Developing countries</keywords>
    
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction"><![CDATA[
1. Introduction
The past decade has seen increasing efforts from researchers to identify the salient contextual sources of e-Government failure (for reviews see, Avgerou, 2008; Heeks and Bailur, 2007; Müller and Skau, 2015; Rana, Dwivedi, & Williams, 2015; Titah and Barki, 2006; Yildiz, 2007, 2012; Zhang, Xu, & Xiao, 2014). Although much useful managerial insights have been offered thus far about this topic, e-Government project failure not only remains quite common but also continues to escalate in many developing countries (United Nations, 2014). This perplexing fact has been calling upon researchers to address the evident irregularity and to identify far-reaching contextual causes of e-Government project failure in these countries. In response, some scholars (Corojan and Criado, 2012; Heeks, 1999; Kim, 2014) have mentioned that corruption may play an influential role in stimulating the failure of e-Government projects in developing nations; but they stopped short from explaining how this actually takes place. This article will try to explore this idea by describing how corruption can act as a source of e-Government project failure in developing countries.
So far, prior scientific discussions over the relationship between e-Government and corruption remain largely one sided and focus on understanding how the former can influence the latter. Whilst e-Government has been touted as an effective tool for combating corruption and improving governance in developing countries (e.g., Abu-Shanab, Harb, & Al-Zoubi, 2013; Bertot, Jaeger, & Grimes, 2010; Bhatnagar, 2002; Corojan and Criado, 2012; Elbahnasawy, 2014; Kim, 2014; Krishnan, Teo, & Lim, 2013; Shim and Eom, 2008), no study has discussed so far how corruption can induce e-Government project failure (see the analysis by: Rana et al., 2015). This is unfortunate because pervasive corruption has been shown to be one of the most important contextual factors that could influence the maturity of e-Government initiatives (Singh, Das, & Joseph, 2007); important research and practical insights could be missed if researchers continue to overlook the other possible ways through which e-Government and corruption might be related.
The present study represents an early attempt to discuss the implications of corruption for e-Government project failure in developing nations. ]]> <h target="2" match="part"> The article argues that e-Government failure in developing economies comes to exist in part because of the role played by corruption forces. It proposes that e-Government projects fail because of cultural, economic, political, and judiciary corruption effects, which distort information processing capabilities of administrative systems (e.g., capability to deal with moral and governance needs) that ultimately cause e-Government to stop short from meeting stakeholders' expectations.</h><![CDATA[ The basis of this theorizing comes from viewing the organization as an information processing entity that receives information from and interacts openly with its environment (Ackoff, 1971; Galbraith, 1973; Kast and Rosenzweig, 1973). The value of this view stems from the fact that corruption could significantly influence e-Government failure, albeit this impact might find its way through associations with other contextual determinants.
The rest of the manuscript is structured as follows. Section 2 highlights the importance of the e-Government environment and argues that both external and internal contexts can influence the outcome of the e-Government project. Section 3 reviews past e-Government project failure and identifies corruption as a key determinant of e-Government failure in developing countries. Section 4 defines corruption and identifies the main conduits through which it takes place. Section 5 introduces the theoretical framework of this study, which explains how corruption can shape current e-Government realities in developing countries. The final two sections discuss the main implications of this study.

]]></section>
    
    <section name="The importance of context" category="background"><![CDATA[
2. The importance of context
Organizational theorists (Lawrence and Lorsch, 1967) have long recognized the importance of environmental factors for the effective functioning of organizations. The logic behind this contention rests in the view that the organization is a subsystem within a gestalt of systems, thus, it is open to receive inputs from and interacts with related subsystems (Ackoff, 1971; Kast and Rosenzweig, 1973). In his seminal work, Leavitt (1964) viewed the internal environment of organizations as a network of four interrelated and mutually adjusting components: people, task, technology, and structure. Organizations, however, differ in their capabilities to deal with inputs from the environment (Duncan, 1972). According to the organizational information processing theory by Galbraith (1973), this difference depends on the capabilities of an organization to receive information inputs from its environment, interact with these inputs, and manipulate them to enhance their flow in order to achieve optimal performance. Research has shown that the external environment could impose restrictions on the internal environment of the organization by hindering its structural and information processing capabilities (Duncan, 1972; Galbraith, 1973). Organizations fail because of their incapability of dealing with information challenges posed by their environment effectively.
Similarly, the e-Government literature has highlighted the importance of context for e-Government performance. For example, Aladwani (2013b) found support for the importance of culture for understanding cross-country e-Government quality ratings. Weare, Musso, and Hale (1999) also found support for the connection between external environmental factors and the diffusion of municipal-level e-Government websites in a large state in the US. Only so can a government develop effective and successful websites” (p. 160). Put another way, the dynamic environment of the e-Government website places continued pressures on e-Government resources and information processing capabilities. Moreover, the literature is packed with articles pinpointing internal causes of e-Government failure (for a review see, Avgerou, 2008; Dada, 2006; Heeks and Bailur, 2007; Titah and Barki, 2006; Yildiz, 2007). In sum, both the external and internal contexts can play important roles in shaping the outcome of the e-Government project.

]]></section>
    
    <section name="Understanding the context of e-Government failure;Corruption: a missing contextual challenge;How corruption can influence e-Government failure?; What is next?" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
3. Understanding the context of e-Government failure
Reports about e-Government failure in developing countries are frequent in the literature. In a paper dedicated for understanding failure risks for e-Government initiatives in developing countries, Heeks (2003) estimated that approximately 85% of such projects are either total or partial failures. This alarming failure estimate led some researchers to question the actual benefits of e-Government projects to developing countries (Ciborra, 2005). With such a weak foundation for meeting the highly publicized e-Government benefits, the next logical step will be to understand the root causes of e-Government failure.
The extant literature has identified a long list of contextual sources of e-Government failure in developing countries spanning the full spectrum of individual, organizational, technological, legal, political, social, and cultural characteristics. For example, some researchers (e.g., Akman, Yazici, Mishra, & Arifoglu, 2005; Aladwani, 2013a; Choudrie and Dwivedi, 2005; Dwivedi and Williams, 2008; Fu, Chao, & Farn, 2004; Gauld, Goldfinch, & Horsburgh, 2010) have found that individual characteristics such as age, gender, education and the like play important roles in accepting or rejecting e-Government projects. Other scholars (Aladwani, 2011; Luk, 2009; Wachira, 2012) found that organizational characteristics such as organizational culture and collaboration significantly influence e-Government success. Another group of scholars (Aladwani, 2013b, 2013c; Carter and Belanger, 2005) highlighted the importance of technology characteristics such as portal quality and innovation attributes for citizens' acceptance of e-Governments. At a different level, Schuppan (2009) described a model for explaining e-Government failure in developing countries that covers wider conditions including environmental and cultural characteristics. Similarly, Kamal, Hackney, and Sarwar (2013) identified significant political, stakeholder, strategic, and social issues relevant to e-Government failure in Pakistan. Weerakkody, El-Haddadeh, Sabol, Ghoneim, and Dzupka (2012) also highlighted the necessity to address political, fiscal, and social issues when developing and implementing e-Government in transition economies. Last but not least, Moon (2002) drew the attention to the role of financial, technical, and human capacities, as well as legal issues in shaping e-Government implementation effectiveness.
The above brief review shows that past research has rarely discussed the influence of corruption on e-Government project failure, thus we currently know very little how this happens. Despite the fact that the topic remains surprisingly understudied in the literature, the preliminary signs from the literature regarding the potential importance of this influence is beginning to appear. For example, Singh et al. (2007) affirm that pervasive corruption is one of the most important contextual factors that can determine the maturity of e-Government initiatives. Other studies have touched upon this issue and looked at it from the side of how e-Government can fight corruption (e.g., Abu-Shanab et al., 2013; Bertot et al., 2010; Bhatnagar, 2002; Corojan and Criado, 2012; Elbahnasawy, 2014; Kim, 2014; Krishnan et al., 2013; Shim and Eom, 2008). For example, Corojan and Criado (2012) discussed how e-Government in some Central American countries encouraged transparency and accountability and reduced corruption. Like most other e-Government scholars, the two authors have not discussed the influence of corruption on e-Government projects. As a result, the current article will try to fill part of this void in prior research by presenting a framework that explains how e-Government failure in developing countries could come to exist because of direct and indirect corruption effects. The value of understanding corruption within the context of e-Government stems from this thesis: e-Government failure could be impacted in a significant way by corruption, even if this influence sometimes is mediated through the influence of other contextual variables.
4. Corruption: a missing contextual challenge
Corruption has been defined in many different ways depending on the academic background of the researcher(s) (Anand, Ashforth, & Joshi, 2004; Bunker and Cohen, 1983; Caiden and Caiden, 1977; Klitgaard, 1988; Macrae, 1982; McMullen, 1961; Nye, 1967; Rose-Ackerman, 1975, 1978, 1996, 1999). For the purpose of this study, the common understanding of corruption as the act of exploiting public authority for personal/private gains, that was advanced by McMullen (1961), is regarded as fundamental. A similar definition has been adopted by the United Nations (1999). Corruption is thus a broad term that describes the full spectrum of tangible and intangible benefits that people with public duties raise after deviating from these formal responsibilities. Given this broad view, corruption can refer to many types of illegal/disapproved financial and administrative behaviors in the context of public jobs such as bribery (kickbacks, pay-offs), embezzlement (misappropriation), nepotism (favoritism, preferential treatment), abusing authority, and extortion (profiting through coercive means), just to name a few (Caiden, 2001; Caiden and Caiden, 1977; Rose-Ackerman, 1975, 1978, 1996, 1999; United Nations, 1999).
The literature identifies several causes and consequences of corruption. According to some scholars (Doig and Theobald, 2000; Klitgaard, 1988; McMullen, 1961; Rose-Ackerman, 1999; Shleifer and Vishny, 1993; Treisman, 2000; Wraith and Edgar, 1963), corruption occurs mainly because of cultural, political, economic, judicial, institutional, and individual reasons. Just as corruption is caused by many factors, it can – in many cases – be a source of many cultural, political, economic, judicial, institutional, administrative, and individual problems (Doig and Theobald, 2000; Mauro, 1995; Mauro, 1998; McMullen, 1961; Rose-Ackerman, 1999; Shleifer and Vishny, 1993; Treisman, 2000; Wraith and Edgar, 1963). Corruption is complicating the already problematic bureaucratic policies, regulations, and procedures, is wasting economic resources, and is creating a sense of social injustice among lower class citizens (Rose-Ackerman, 1978).]]> 
<h target="1" match="part">At a different level, corruption represents one of the most complicated and serious contextual challenges that face e-Governments in developing countries. Although corruption exists in all countries of the world and may affect all types of e-Governments, it has been found to be most prevalent – and most influential – in developing economies. The latest Corruption Perceptions Index (Transparency International, 2014) clearly shows that almost all developing countries suffer from higher levels of corruption than do advanced nations. Corruption could have detrimental effects on administrative systems overseeing e-Government projects since it limits their capability to operate in accord with good governance and morality standards. Luo (2002, p. 405) maintains that corruption is “an evolutionary hazard, a strategic impediment, a competitive disadvantage, and an organizational deficiency”. In fact, many reports coming from international organizations such as the World Bank, International Monetary Fund, and United Nations are packed with data and case studies that support the fact that corruption acts as a major impediment for good governance. Whether we talk about operational efficiency, transparency, accountability, integrity, justice, social inclusion, autonomy or some other governance demands, corruption always finds its way to sway many administrative systems from achieving good governance and adhering to high moral standards.</h><![CDATA[
5. How corruption can influence e-Government failure?
While there are many valuable endeavors in the extant literature that identify the factors that lead to e-Government failure in developing countries, no study – to the best of my knowledge – has considered corruption as a potential source of such failure.  This paper proposes a framework (Fig. 1) that tries to explain such a role in an effort to overcome this shortcoming. The figure illustrates how the intensity of the external corruption context could influence the proneness of the internal environment of the e-Government project to corruption and ultimately the possibility of its failure. The main premise here is that corruption abuses the resources made available for e-Governments and diverts them from reaching their full potential.
Study's framework
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Study's framework.
The proposed theoretical framework consists of three major parts: corruption types (cultural, economic, political, and judicial), internal effects (deterioration of the moral compass and deterioration of governance standards), and e-Government project failure dimensions (technical, content, social, and service). Although there may be many conceptualizations of e-Government project failure, the author of this article adopts a performance failure view. This conceptualization of failure covers issues related to how the e-Government project performs along certain dimensions; and as such, this view goes beyond the simple endorsement conceptualization of e-Government failure (i.e., simple yes/no usage questions). An example of such conceptualization is the one presented by Aladwani (2013b) who listed four contextual dimensions of e-Government failure/success: technical, content, aesthetics, and service. This conception is gaining popularity among e-Government scholars in recent years (Aladwani, 2013b; Batini, Viscusi, & Cherubini, 2009; Papadomichelaki and Mentzas, 2012; Wang, 2006).
Fig. 1 suggests that the prevalence of corruption in a given country could affect the proneness of e-Government to all types of corrupt acts, which could lead, among other things, to the deterioration of the ability of e-Government to operate efficiently and fairly. To discuss this point more deeply, take for example one manifestation of corruption in developing countries, societal acceptance of corrupt behaviors. When the president of one developing nation tried to describe the problem of corruption he referred to it as the “moral decadence in our country” (Klitgaard, 1988 p. 1). What this president is actually saying is that corruption is becoming a widely accepted practice and is transforming into a cultural reality. Because national culture is “the collective programming of the mind which distinguishes the members of one human group from another” (Hofstede, 1980 p. 260), it is expected that countries differ in their susceptibility to corruption (Treisman, 2000). In some developing countries, for example, Wasta or nepotism is considered by many citizens as an acceptable social behavior and is praised as a good deed. This situation arises out of systematic (or cultural) corruption as opposed to individual corruption (Caiden and Caiden, 1977); and it will almost certainly encourage and advance all kinds of corruption in a society including nepotism (Mbaku, 1994). Therefore, it came as no surprise to many neutral observers to find that it is simply acceptable in some developing countries for a public administrator to practice socially or politically motivated hiring of individuals in public jobs, e.g., in e-Government projects. Jobs in e-Government projects in these countries might be awarded to a person not because of his or her technical proficiency or high knowledge but because he or she is a next of kin to a senior public official or affiliated with some “group”. These practices are considered as corruption in social/cultural terms (Médard, 1986).
Either way, the above-described practices violate the minimum standards of human resources governance expected from e-Government officials. Building and implementing a successful e-Government depends on recruiting, training, and motivating skilled staff. According to Kim (2007, p. 320), “[t]he fundamental conditions for the excellent performance of digital government rely basically on the competence of public agents on public service delivery”. Research has shown that lack of job satisfaction among information technology personnel negatively influences organizational and job commitments (Igbaria and Guimaraes, 1993). Therefore, giving preferential treatment to individuals without adequate skills or knowledge could have detrimental effects on the overall performance of the e-Government project.
The technical, content, service, and social implications of such a deficiency for the work of the e-Government project are unmistakable. For example, assigning unqualified technical employees to the project due to nepotism implies the possibility that they might not have what is needed to support correct e-Government deliverables and satisfy the demands of the full spectrum of stakeholders. Those incompetent employees might not be in a good position to understand the e-Government logic for data coded in the strategic plan and operational standards. From the content side, incompetent personnel might not be able to discover and/or correct missing or erroneous data during e-Government project's development, operations, and/or maintenance. In highly demanding work conditions such as that of the e-Government project, where deadlines are tight and errors are unwelcomed, it is almost certain that oblivious mistakes (e.g., poor sequencing of activities, poor handling of technical errors, misinterpretation of requirements, etc.) serve as a source of conflicts between project members. In fact, not only justice, stability, and social unity but also staff satisfaction and project performance are undermined by a culture that tolerates violations and poor performance. Favoritism could lead the experienced e-Government workforce to feel unjustly treated, socially excluded, and ultimately dissatisfied. It is just hard to retain highly capable employees and maintain an objective management system in such an unfriendly and largely stressful work environment. Staff incompetence issues come at a great cost to the final project outcome in the form of poor security, availability, usability, and service turnaround, to name a few. Ultimately, these mistakes lead to citizens losing confidence in e-Government services and in the value of the portal.

Like in the case of negative impacts of culture-based corruption, it is difficult to curb the negative effects of economic-based corruption on the e-Government project. Many developing countries failed in the fight against economic-based corruption that causes governance challenges to many of their administrative systems. A new Transparency International survey found that three out of every four individuals in some developing countries testify they have been involved in a corruptive act recently (Hardoon and Heinrich, 2013). The prevalence of illegal appropriation of resources, bribery, and other economic corruption forms in some developing countries is because many individuals and organizations focus on maximizing their own gains on the expense of citizens and the good of the public (Fjeldstad, 2003). Moreover, it has been found that a country with a low economic income usually show high corruption levels (Shleifer and Vishny, 1993; Treisman, 2000). Nonetheless, corruption impacts go beyond individuals to harm societies. Mauro (1995, 1998) shows how corruption distorts economic environments through its influence on growth, public expenditures, and development projects.
In what way can economic-based corruption influence e-Government failure? Fig. 1 suggests that economic-based corruption could ultimately cause e-Government project failure through the fall of economic-based moral and governance standards. Take for example embezzlement of public resources as one of the most popular way through which government officials loot state assets (Rodriguez and Ehrichs, 2007 p. 63). The problem is as serious in the case of some public officials in developing countries who find e-Government development projects an excellent source for profiteering as in the case of some officials in these countries who tolerate such a behavior. The devious scheme could go as follows (Al-Obaidi, 2015). A public official awards “over-priced” contracts worth millions of dollars to an information technology company owned by his or her relative and shares the profit with the collaborator(s). Alternatively, an under-qualified information technology company passes bribes to a public official overseeing an e-Government project to facilitate granting a contract to the company. To cover these hidden costs, the corrupt company recruits under-qualified technical specialists, uses outdated tools, and requests several deadline extensions; and once the e-Government project is completed after long delays, the company surprises the public with the poor quality of the delivered product. Because of mishandling of budget issues, the cost per processed transaction as well as costs of maintenance will increase. Lack of cost-based optimization/efficiency will eventually increase the overall cost and decrease level of performance of the services offered to the citizens, against all e-Government promises. This situation will certainly make the people pay for the corruption and thus create negative sentiments among the majority of e-Government's stakeholders. Simply put, economic corruption influences the core of the trust relationship between the e-Government and the public at large and has many adverse effects on the outcome of the e-Government project that increase its failure chances.
The figure also suggests that political-based corruption could influence the outcome of the e-Government project. Political corruption is indeed a serious and prevalent issue in the developing world. More than one hundred thousand participants in a worldwide Transparency International study accuse interference of political parties as the main source of societal corruption (Hardoon and Heinrich, 2013 p. 15). Political corruption gains coercive powers in a non-competitive, closed political environment such as that found in most developing countries (Doig and Theobald, 2000). Therefore, it came as no surprise that political interference in the operations of the e-Government project is prevailing in many developing countries (Bhogle, 2007). This interference would not succeed, however, without compliance from some e-Government officials who cave in to vested interests and do some string pulling for politicians in exchange of favors from them. Some decision makers overseeing e-Government projects in these countries claim that without political support it would be difficult for them to secure the required work budget and resources smoothly. The direct result of this obstacle is that the project ultimately loses autonomy and fails to protect the work culture from accepting political interference as de facto.
Yielding to political tactics could compromise professional plans and decisions related to an information technology project and hence could cause its failure to operate efficiently and freely (Markus, 1983). When e-Government officials do not have autonomy to formulate and implement their choices, they will not be in a good position to handle the required technical operations effectively and efficiently or meet minimum governance standards. The politically motivated interference in e-Government development and management will limit the liberty of responsible professionals to make decisions in a timely, accurate, and useful manner as well as in the best interests of the citizens. It will surely limit the capability of e-Government officials to objectively identify, evaluate, and implement the latest information technologies. In this case, the overall cost of correcting compromised e-Government-related decisions (those nonconforming to optimal decision-making standards) is high and so does the cost of assuring the quality of e-Government services provided to the public. Compromised e-Government-related decisions and evaluation criteria as well as low quality of services will negatively influence stakeholders' perceived quality and value ratings of e-Government services. It is extremely difficult to initiate necessary corrective actions in such circumstances. The existence of such disruptive elements, together with the inability of responsible administrative systems to react appropriately, will ultimately pave the way to e-Government failure.
Finally, Fig. 1 suggests that judicial corruption can be problematic to e-Government projects in developing countries. Corruption in those countries could cast its dark shadows on both the judiciary system (Ferreyra-Orozco, 2010) and on legislative bodies (Rasmusen and Ramseyer, 1994). According to Transparency International (Rodriguez and Ehrichs, 2007), there are two prevalent forms of judicial corruption in developing countries:
(1)
Designing judicial decisions, and

(2)
Bribery to court personnel.


A recent corruption report affirms: “[i]n 20 countries, people believe the judiciary to be the most corrupt institution. In these countries, an average of 30 per cent of people who came into contact with the judiciary report having paid a bribe” (Hardoon and Heinrich, 2013 p. 17); and therefore the prevalence of such kind of corruption has always far reaching effects on all governmental contexts including that of e-Government's.
A corrupt judiciary system, which suffers from impartiality and encourages judges to design judicial decisions to please (and gain from) dominating societal powers, has many detrimental effects on the e-Government project's capability to meet high governance standards. In general, it would be difficult for judicial employees to continue breaking ethical codes in a truly transparent, honest, and accountable judicial environment as promised by the advocates of e-Governments. Therefore, corrupt judicial employees work hard to weaken e-Government controls and hinder its operations. For example, some judges in some courts in developing countries might find excuses to limit the public's access to judicial case files and rulings or cause “the disappearance of case files” as a way to extort citizens (Rodriguez and Ehrichs, 2007 p. 7). From a technical point of view, it would be impossible for the public to closely monitor judicial decisions and discover corruption without such access and without high standards of moral ethics. The prevalence of violations of public trust will eventually discourage some e-Government officials and specialists from paying adequate attention to breaching inner ethical norms and to encoding accountability and transparency principles into e-Government systems based on technically sound choices. As suggested by the work of Caiden and Caiden (1977), when corruption becomes widespread in a society, it encourages organizations to present contradictory external and internal codes of ethics; hide violations of the external code, penalize non-violators and reward violators; and excuse corruption as isolated incidents. Such corruption could put the administrative system overseeing an e-Government project under an unforgiving morality test. This would certainly causes deterioration in the perceived information accuracy and completeness as well as the integrity and fairness of the services provided by the e-Government to the public and other stakeholders. This situation raises serious questions regarding the extent to which within project decisions, content, and evaluations comply with regulatory requirements and reflect the best e-Government implementation and management practices. Eventually, the public will lose confidence in the capability of the e-Government initiative to meet the expected operational, accountability, integrity, and transparency requirements. Together, these circumstances represent a recipe for disaster, which will cause the failure of the e-Government project.
The above discussion illustrates how corruption can produce adverse e-Government project outcomes (summarized in Table 1). Obviously, however, the proposed connections among corruption, moral and governance implications of corruption, and e-Government project failure represent a subset of these dynamic and complex networks. In reality, the full list of potential negative influences of corruption on e-Government projects are neither simple (e.g., one-to-one relationships) nor limited in scope to project operations, thus the ideas of this article need expansion to develop a more thorough understanding of the raised issues.
Table 1. Potential influences of corruption on e-Government project failure.

6. What is next?
The ideas summarized in the above framework would not be complete without answering one final question: what is next? Many scholars believe discussing the following two main issues is the most logical answer this query:
(1)
Explain how the insights offered by the framework in this manuscript can guide scientific inquiries into this topic, and

(2)
Explain how the framework can help the public officials interested in planning, managing, and auditing e-Government initiatives.]]>


<h target="3" match="part"> As for the first issue, drawing on the literature on general systems, organizational information processing, corruption, and e-Government failure, the author proposed a relevant conceptual framework and argued that corruption in developing countries could limit the capabilities of the e-Government project to meet stakeholders' expectations by damaging good moral and governance standards of the overseeing administrative system. </h> <![CDATA[As a result, the proposed framework represents an early attempt to discuss how corruption can influence e-Government project failure; and to set the stage for subsequent work on the development of operational measures for the proposed concepts as well as testing the validity of the suggested relationships. In light of the above discussion, the author of this article suggests the following omnibus proposition for testing:
]]> <h target="2" match="part"> Intensity of corruption in the cultural, economic, political, and judicial environments has a direct influence on the deterioration of moral and governance standards of the administrative system overseeing the e-Government initiative, which in turn has a direct influence on its failure along the technical, content, social, and service dimensions.</h> <![CDATA[


Another fruitful approach to guide scientific inquiries into this topic would be to propose a few avenues of further investigations to expand on this framework. The first direction for future studies focuses on the influence of the interaction between the suggested concepts – and their relevant contexts – on e-Government failure. For example, there may be a need for a study that sheds more light on how the relative influence of the different corruption types on e-Government failure could change depending on the economic development of the country or some other important country-level characteristics. In addition, there may be a need for an investigation that helps e-Government officials understand which corruption types have the most relative importance within the project failure context of interest (e.g., technical, content, social, and service). The second avenue for future research focuses on expanding the proposed framework to incorporate other important elements such as the impact of anti-corruption reforms and programs on the suggested concepts and relationships. In this area, at least a couple of questions can be posed to researchers:
(1)
What anti-corruption reforms have higher priority for implementation to expedite recovery from e-Government failure? and

(2)
Is the speed of anti-corruption reforms implementation a factor in recuperating from e-Government project failure in countries with different degrees of corruption?


The third suggested direction of future research takes into account e-Government's various stakeholders roles and benefits (Rowley, 2011) into the framework. Here, the author poses another question to interested researchers for possible examination:
(1)
How do the different stakeholders' roles influence stakeholders' salient beliefs about the nature of the relationship between corruption and e-Government failure?


The aforementioned issues and many related other areas of concern represent a natural progression from this paper and deserve further interpretive-based, multilevel investigations.

The proposed framework also paves the way for practically understanding and evaluating the effect of corruption on e-Government failure; this offers key insights to interested public officials. Its goal is to increase the awareness of the many implications of corruption for e-Government projects in developing countries. The arguments put forward in this article can assist decision makers and auditors understand how the prevalence of corruption in developing countries can influence the outcomes of e-Government projects negatively.

Towards that end, the proposed framework can facilitate the identification of e-Government failure hazards and adequate decision makers' action. For example, it is recommended that decision makers view corruption as a major obstacle that hinders the e-Government project from demonstrating its potential value. In other words, officials should clearly realize that the misuse various resources of e-Government projects distract these initiatives from attaining the desired objectives. Therefore, officials have to view corruption as a multifaceted phenomenon (whether cultural, economic, political, or judicial); and it is necessary that they react accordingly. Using the proposed framework, public officials and auditors can systematically understand the possible implications of the different corruption forces for the different types of e-Government project failure. To counteract the negative influences of these corruption forces, decision makers need to design and implement appropriate programs that promote good governance standards within and ensure the integrity of the moral compass of the administrative system that supervises the e-Government initiative.

Although the framework clearly identifies some uncontrollable corruptive forces that can be expected to cause e-Government failure, the characteristics of the internal environment of the administrative system overseeing e-Government operations is largely under the control of the decision makers who can adjust these governance characteristics to increase the chances of e-Government project success. For example, e-Government officials and auditors can define acceptable codes of processional behavior, clarify/communicate ethical responsibilities for each specialist and administrator, develop and implement plans necessary for achieving transparency and accountability, promote a culture of integrity within the workplace, establish an incentive system for combating fraudulent behaviors, and establish standards of excellent performance, just to name a few.

]]></section>
    
    <section name="Summary" category="conclusion"><![CDATA[
        
7. Summary
The goal of this article was to discuss the potential role of corruption plays in shaping the failure of e-Government projects in developing countries. In line with this goal, the author suggested a theoretical framework that depicts the likely influences of corruption (whether cultural, economic, political, or judicial) on e-Government project failure (including technical, content, social, and service aspects) through deterioration of the internal environment (deterioration of the moral compass and governance standards) of the administrative system overseeing the e-Government project. Doing so permitted the author to contribute to the literature by identifying some of the paths through which corruption can lead to e-Government project failure; and by providing a theoretical foundation for empirical research and managerial insights.

Overall, the present article tried to follow a logical path by laying down the main components of the proposed framework: it identified the main concepts, it tied them together, and it logically justified the relationships among them. It gave a high-level view of how corruption influences e-Government project failure as well as the potential implications of this impact.]]> <h target="4" match="full"> Moreover, this paper tried to explain how it could contribute to the literature, influence the way researchers think about the connection between corruption and e-Government failure, and encourage further scientific discussions over a rather timely topic. </h> <![CDATA[It is hoped that the theoretical exposition of corruption roles can add knowledge to e-Government failure research and practice.
]]></section>
</publication>