<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="gaishuangshuang">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 1, February 2016, Pages 113-125</time>
International Journal of Information Management
    <title>Email-free collaboration: An exploratory study on the formation of new work habits among knowledge workers</title>
    <author>Jean-Charles Pillet</author>. Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
    <author>Kevin Daniel André Carillo</author>. Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
Grenoble Ecole de Management, 12, Rue Pierre Sémard, 38003, Grenoble, Cedex 01, France
b
Toulouse University, Toulouse Business School, 20 Boulevard Lascrosses, 31068 Toulouse, France
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2015.11.001</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
•
    <highlight id="1">The potential of social-collaboration technologies seriously questions email usage in organizations.</highlight>
•
    <highlight id="2">This research investigates the role played by the notion of habit in influencing the relationship between perceived positive attributes about a social collaboration platform and employee knowledge sharing capability.</highlight>
•
    <highlight id="3">A theoretical model is developed and tested through a quantitative case study methodology.</highlight>
•
    <highlight id="4">Habit moderates the relationships between perceived attributes (relative advantage, perceived ease of use, and compatibility to a lesser extent) and knowledge sharing.</highlight>
•
    <highlight id="5">When studying IT adoption/acceptance in the context of disruptive technologies, the link between perceptions, intention, and behavior is more complex than thought.</highlight>

Abstract
    <abstract>  Social collaboration technologies have rapidly spread across organizations, offering a unique opportunity to improve the exchange of knowledge among employees, especially in distributed work environments. <h target="1" match="full"> The increasing popularity of social-collaboration tools as an employee-oriented communication channel, inevitably raises questions about the future of email as its intensive use by knowledge workers is more and more perceived as being inefficient and unproductive.</h> <h target="2" match="part"> Through a quantitative case study methodology, this study seeks to explore the role played by the notion of habit in explaining employee knowledge sharing capability for firms implementing social collaborative practices in the context of no-email initiatives. </h>  <h target="3" match="full">Data collected within a large international IT services company, which is among the first firms having made such shift, were used to test the developed conceptual model.</h>  The findings suggest that habit is positively influenced by relative advantage and perceived ease of use while relative advantage was found to positively impact knowledge sharing capability. Besides, <h target="4" match="full">habit moderates the relationships between three attributes (relative advantage, perceived ease of use, and compatibility to a lesser extent) and knowledge sharing capability.</h>  Theoretical and practical implications developed from these findings are then discussed.</abstract>

Keywords
    <keywords>Social collaboration</keywords>
    <keywords>No-email</keywords>
    <keywords>Habit</keywords>
    <keywords>Case study</keywords>
    <keywords>Disruptive technology</keywords>
    <keywords>Knowledge sharing</keywords>/
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
In recent years, a new light has been shed upon the concept of collaboration as business organizations have started to harness concepts from the web 2.0 to enhance their workers' interpersonal communication and collaboration capabilities (Kane, Alavi, Labianca, & Borgatti, 2014). This phenomenon hinges on the development of a new class of technology, enterprise social-collaborative technology, which supports the creation and exchange of user-generated content through the use of blogs, wikis, social networking features, social tagging, and microblogging (Kaplan & Haenlein, 2010; Ngai, Tao, & Moon, 2015). Over a surprisingly brief period of time, the use of social collaborative tools has grown from limited experimentation to mainstream practices. According to the global consultancy McKinsey & Company, 83% of companies report the use of social-collaboration technologies in their organization (Bughin & Chui, 2013). Market analysts estimate the worldwide enterprise social networks and collaborative technologies market to grow from 1.0 billion in 2012 to 2.7 billion dollars by 2017 (IDC, 2013). Aside from a technological breakthrough, this represents a shift in the way people feel, think, and behave (e.g., Castells, 2013), with implications that are not yet well understood by communication and information systems researchers. This study aims at raising the awareness of researchers and practitioners about the broader nature of the social-collaboration phenomenon as it embodies a work behavior paradigm shift rather than being a mere question of IS/IT adoption.
Furthermore, faced with an urgent need to enhance internal collaboration and realizing the potential offered by social-collaboration technologies, some companies have started seriously questioning the usage of internal email as their main communication tool for employees (Johri, 2011). Indeed, knowledge workers receive massive amounts of emails everyday which results in an information overload that tends to decrease their individual performance (Evaristo, Adams, & Curley, 2015). Whereas email is a targeted communication channel that spreads out information in multiple inboxes, social-collaboration technologies offer topic-specific collaboration spaces in which information aggregates through the input of its users. Subsequently, knowledge exchange is expected to be particularly enhanced in distributed work environments (Beck, Pahlke, & Seebach, 2014). However, while email is not calibrated for efficiently circulating knowledge throughout the organization, its usage is deeply entrenched in today's organizational practices. In order for new forms of collaboration to take place, new working habits have to form and develop. Benefiting from the momentum offered by a company-wide email-free initiative, ]]> <h target="2" match="part">this study seeks to explore the key role played by the notion of habit in explaining knowledge sharing behaviors in firms implementing social collaborative practices in the context of no-email initiatives. </h> <![CDATA[ This research builds on the work of Limayem and Hirt (2003); Limayem, Hirt, & Cheung, 2007) about the importance of habits in the adoption of new technologies. No-email initiatives being still at a nascent adoption stage, it appeared pertinent to narrow down our investigation to a single case to allow an in-depth examination and understanding of the role of habit in explaining how individuals collaborate without emails. Besides, the purposeful selection of a case that is highly theoretically relevant is a means to ensure the clear delineation of the context (and thus theoretical boundaries) within which the developed theoretical model may apply (Yin, 2003).
            In the next section the theoretical background is provided. This is followed by the presentation of the developed theoretical model as well as the associated hypotheses.Then, research methodology, data analysis and results are presented. The papers wraps-up with the main contributions, limitations, and recommendations for future research.]]>
</section>


    <section name="Theoretical background" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Theoretical background
Collaboration occurs when two or more individuals who work together, support each other by sharing their ideas, knowledge or competencies with the purpose of accomplishing a given task (Hargrove, 1998). Such activity is supported by electronic technologies that help people coordinate their work with others by sharing information or knowledge (Doll & Deng, 2001). The proliferation of collaborative technologies is highly correlated to the development of globally distributed teams, a phenomenon that results from the distribution of business processes across firms and geographies (Bentley et al., 1997). The activity of such working groups is supported by workflow systems that are specifically designed to support transactional processes such as pre-defined information flows (Basu & Kumar, 2002). Yet these tools are inevitably poorly adapted to the collective exchange of unstructured information. Knowledge workers are often faced with situations they have never encountered before, hence the need for collaboration systems that efficiently help identify, disseminate, and retrieve knowledge within work groups (Doll & Deng, 2001).
2.1. The rise of social-collaboration technologies
In order to fulfill their employees' collaboration needs, organizations have started experimenting with social-collaboration technologies that apply web 2.0 principles to corporate settings. Social media, a prominent avatar of this transformation, include features such as blogs, microblogs, social networking sites, wikis, and video- or content-sharing sites (Piskorki & McCall, 2010; Kaplan & Haenlein, 2010). When used within the boundaries of an organization, this technology allows the broadcast of employee-generated content, therefore enhancing a company's internal communication capabilities (Treem & Leonardi, 2012; Leonardi, Huysman, & Steinfield, 2013; Ngai et al., 2015). The second addition of social media platforms is to allow better employee connectedness through the creation and regular activation of social ties, ultimately leading to a company's enhanced social capital (see Coleman, 1988). At IBM and HP, the implementation of an enterprise social network has led to greater employee connectedness because it supports the development of new social ties as well as reactivates existing ones (DiMicco et al., 2008; Brzozowski, 2009). This results in a unique capacity for employees of these large IT firms to identify and reach out experts beyond their own work-group, context, or country (Steinfield, Dimicco, Ellison, & Lampe, 2009). By extension, Ferron, Frassoni, Massa, Napolitano, & Setti (2010) found that employees exposed to a social networking site reported greater social capital. We note that the very nature of social media, as a broadcast medium that emphasizes on the public access of information as well as social connectedness, questions the use of recipient-targeted technologies such as email, especially in a context in which group coordination is more needed than ever.
2.2. The question of email inefficiencies
Email usage is deeply entrenched into the communication habits of employees within organizations. It has been associated with higher task accomplishment and life enrichment (Huang, Lin, & Lin, 2011) and has also given workers the ability to work anywhere at any time (Barley, Meyerson, & Grodal, 2011). However, the influence of email communication on employees has been equivocal. Studies have indicated the negative effects of email use such as deficient information quality, information overload and even decreased job satisfaction (Russell, Purvis, & Banks, 2007; Soucek & Moser, 2010). They have also highlighted the inferior ability of email communication in allowing synchronous communication (i.e. fast exchange of messages) and also deficiencies in allowing trust-based relations, compared to video conferencing where facial and emotional reactions can be more easily deciphered and interpreted (Rockmann & Northcraft, 2008; Walther & Parks, 2002).  The collaboration inefficiencies resulting from email usage are particularly salient in a group setting. Contrary to other mainstream collaborative technologies (such as conferencing systems, whiteboards, knowledge repositories, and, more recently, enterprise social media), email does not provide a public arena in which communal knowledge can be built, and shared meanings established (Bjørn and Ngwenyama, 2009). Consequently, employees receive massive amounts of emails every day, a trend that will likely continue to grow (Radicati, 2014) and lead to even more productivity loss because of the work interruptions this entails (Barley et al., 2011; Jackson, Dawson, & Wilson, 2001).This was highlighted during a five-day long experiment that took place within a large scientific organization. The trial revealed that when emails were completely turned-off, workers focused longer on their tasks, multitasked less, and experienced lower stress (Mark, Voida, Cardello, 2012).
2.3. Knowledge sharing in collaborative environments
Contrary to email, social-collaboration technologies offer “a unique opportunity to improve the exchange of knowledge among employees, especially in a distributed environment” (Beck et al., 2014). According to the knowledge-based view of the firm, knowledge is a scarce asset and the ability to manage it determines an organization's competitiveness (Grant, 1996). Thus, the effective exchange, reconfiguration, and interpretation of knowledge among employees are of critical importance (Tsai, 2001). Knowledge sharing refers to the provision of task information and know-how to help and collaborate with others to solve problems, develop new ideas, or implement policies or procedures (Cummings, 2004; Pulakos, Dorsey, & Borman, 2003). In line with growing emphasis on employee-generated content, social platforms allow online knowledge sharing to shift from a centralized to a decentralized process as individuals can broadcast information whenever they want in both formal and informal ways (Kane & Fichman, 2009). This turns the dynamic of knowledge exchange processes into a “continuous communal knowledge conversation” (Majchrzak, Faraj, Kane, & Azad, 2013) that leads to the emergence of a new “knowledge ecosystem” (Hemsley & Mason, 2012) within which individuals can navigate while performing their job. The connectivity feature offered by social media also contributes to redefining the way knowledge is shared. As employees are better connected and social connections more salient, it is expected that the sharing of knowledge is more effective (Chiu, Hsu, & Wang, 2006; Wasko & Faraj, 2005). The rationale is that networks of connections enhance a group's social capital, which in turn facilitates knowledge sharing behavior within this particular group (Kankanhalli, Tan, & Wei, 2005; Nahapiet & Ghoshal, 1998).
2.4. Habit and social-collaborative technologies
Habits are commonly understood as “learned sequences of acts that become automatic responses to specific situations which may be functional in obtaining certain goals or end states” (Verplanken, Aarts, & van Knippenberg, 1997, p. 540). When it comes to IT, habits form on the basis of past experiences during which the users learn how to use the technology (Bergeron, Raymond, Rivard, & Gara, 1995). For the purpose of this study, we define habit as “the extent to which workers tend to use social-collaborative tools automatically because of learning”. We posit that habit plays a critical role in this particular context because the use of social-collaborative tools entails a reciprocal interdependence in which earlier users are influenced by later users and vice-versa (Markus, 1987); this makes social platforms particularly vulnerable to discontinuance of usage. In the literature, there is no common consensus about how the constructs of habit, intention, and actual behavior interrelate. Research has identified three possible patterns:
Direct effects. Habit and intention act in tandem as predictors of actual behavior. In such cases, habit and intention influenced actual behavior independently. While conceptually valid, this perspective lacks overall theoretical and empirical support (Limayem et al., 2007).
Mediating effects. Intentions mediate the effect of habit on actual behavior. However, such models often provide a partial conceptualization of habit while the associated measurements encompass only a limited portion of the construct (Limayem et al., 2007). For example, Bagozzi and Warshaw (1990) found that habit adds explanatory power to TRA as a significant predictor of intention. However, frequency of past behaviors, used as a proxy of habit, omits important aspect of the construct's conceptual definition, which poses a severe conceptual limitation.
Moderating effects. Once established, habits diminish the need for cognitive effort or conscious attention to perform an activity (Wood, Quinn, & Kashy, 2002), leading individuals to follow ‘cognitive shortcuts’ (Aarts, Paulussen, & Schaalma, 1997). In IS, habits that result from experimenting a tool reduces the prevalence of other considerations such as usefulness or image perceptions in the decision to continuously use an IS (Karahanna, Straub, & Chervany,1999). In other words, the predictive power of intention to use a system is drastically reduced when habits around this usage have formed.]]>
</section>

    <section name="Model development" category="research model and hypotheses">
        <![CDATA[
3. Model development
Fig. 1 depicts the research model. It is based on the assumption that habit moderates the relationships between perceived attributes towards a social collaborative platform (relative advantage, perceived ease of use, and compatibility); and employee knowledge sharing capability. The direct effect of the positive attributes on knowledge sharing is also hypothesized. The purposeful choice for using well-established theoretical foundations (the Diffusion of Innovation Theory from Rogers, 1983) was motivated by the reason that this research essentially aims at emphasizing the complexity and subtlety of the link between perceptions, intention, and usage behavior (through the moderating effect of habit) in the particular context of social-collaboration. Additionally, this paper intends to contribute to the line of inquiry that criticizes the tendency to study IS continuance by assuming that intention drives actual behavior in a predictable manner (Legris, Ingham, & Collerette, 2003).
Research model
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Research model.
When using the Diffusion of Innovation Theory in the context of IS/IT acceptance, researchers have mainly used sub-components of the theory. Only Moore and Benbasat (1996) and Agarwal and Prasad (1997) examined the effect on usage of all innovation characteristics simultaneously. Moore and Benbasat found compatibility, perceived usefulness, and ease of use to be the most influential factors to predict continued usage decisions. The unique role of perceived usefulness and perceived ease of use in usage intention has also been outlined by Venkatesh and Bala, (2008) and Venkatesh and Davis (2000). While comprehensiveness ensures whether all relevant factors are included in a theory, parsimony dictates whether some factors should be deleted because they add little value to the understanding of a phenomenon (Whetten, 1989). For this reason, only innovation characteristics that were the most meaningful and relevant to the context of social collaborative tool usage were retained: relative advantage, compatibility, and perceived ease of use.
3.1. Explaining habit and knowledge sharing
In line with principles from the Innovation Diffusion Theory, the pace of diffusion of social-collaborative technologies depends on whether or not they can be used advantageously in a business setting (Roger, 1983). Studies on social media from the IS literature confirm that their usage is determined by factors related to the perceived benefits these can bring. Lin and Lu (2011) showed that factors of enjoyment alone fall short in predicting intentions to use social networking sites and extrinsic factors such as usefulness significantly boosts predictive models of social media usage. Motivation factors related to the perceived usefulness of a tool are expected to be even more salient in a business setting in which workers are pressured to deliver. DiMicco et al. (2008) found that the usage of social networking sites at work is primarily driven by extrinsic motivation factors such as career advancement or project promotion. Recent developments tend to confirm that the prime benefit of social networks for organizations is to enhance knowledge exchange among employees (Treem & Leonardi, 2012; Majchrzak et al., 2013; Beck et al., 2014). Social-collaboration tools rely on connectivity features, which makes expertise localization as well as knowledge access easier than with traditional knowledge management systems that usually focus on enterprise content management (Fulk & Yuan, 2013); therefore offering a relative advantage. We expect that this aspect is all the more salient in an email-free environment, where a technology explicitly comes as an alternative to an older one. Hence:
H1b

Individuals who perceive a greater relative advantage in social-collaboration tools are more likely to engage in knowledge sharing activities.


The current thinking in the IS literature positions perceived usefulness as the only construct consistently influencing user intention in both adoption and post-adoption phases. In line with expectation-confirmation theory (Oliver, 1980), the perceived relative advantage provided by a technology provides the baseline against which effective usage is confronted and satisfaction formulated (Bhattacherjee, 2001). Extending on the work of Limayem et al. (2007), we hypothesize the positive effect of relative advantage on habit through the proxy of satisfaction. Indeed, it is only under satisfactory circumstances that an activity will be performed again and again, ultimately leading to the formation of habits. Hence:
H1a

Individuals who perceive a greater relative advantage in social-collaboration tools will develop habits around their usage.


Compatibility is a multidimensional construct defined as the degree to which using an innovation is consistent with the existing sociocultural values and beliefs, past and present experiences and needs of potential adopters (Rogers, 1983, p. 250). Based on this definition, two types of compatibility can be identified: compatibility with values, referring to what people think about an innovation, and compatibility with experience, referring to what people can do with it (Tornatzky & Klein, 1982). By design, social-collaboration technologies embody values of information transparency and openness and instill norms of sharing (one's opinion, idea, feedback, etc.), as reflected by the “rate”, “like”, or “comment” features. In their analysis, Treem and Leonardi (2012) identified visibility (of content, actions, connections, etc.) as one of the four affordances of Enterprise Social Media. The usage of social-collaboration technologies thus implicitly requires workers to accept these values. However, some individuals may not feel comfortable with the transparency connotations promoted by these technologies and may refrain from sharing documents (even more when they are in an unfinished state) if this way of working does not match their personal work style (Holtzblatt, Damianos, & Weiss, 2010). Social-collaborative technologies can enhance the knowledge sharing capabilities of an individual provided that the values and norms they convey are consistent with the way this person likes to work. Besides, compatibility with past experience reflects a fit between the target technology and a user's past encounter with the technology (Karahanna, Agarwal, & Angst, 2006). The learning literature acknowledged that an individuals' prior knowledge and experience interfere with the ability to learn new concepts (McGeoch & Irion, 1952). The proliferation of social media creates opportunities for people to experiment these applications and in turn to confidently integrate them in their way of working. In the workplace, such principles translate into the sharing of information, documents, or feedbacks, or any other piece of knowledge. Hence:
H2b

Individuals who perceive a greater compatibility towards social-collaboration tools with their job are more likely to engage in knowledge sharing activities.


In 2009, about 17% of a company's workforce logged-in daily to a Facebook account or other social media such as LinkedIn (Skeels & Grudin, 2009). Frequency of behavior being an important predictor of habit (Limayem et al., 2007), it is likely that users who consider that social-collaborative technologies to be compatible with their job will develop habits around these technologies. Compatibility with prior experience implies that one has the right mental cognitive schemas to rapidly utilize the technology, the required cognitive effort during the adoption phase being drastically shortened (Karahanna et al., 2006). Therefore, users that are social-media savvy are likely to possess a mental disposition that fits social-collaborative technologies usage and are in turn quicker than others to routinely adopt their use at work. Hence:
H2a

Individuals who perceive a greater compatibility towards social-collaboration tools with their job will develop habits around their usage.


Perceived ease of use plays a unique role in technology adoption and IS research has consistently outlined its effect on usage intentions (Adams, Nelson, & Todd, 1992Szajna, 1996; Venkatesh & Davis, 2000; Venkatesh & Bala, 2008). Individuals are generally more likely to use a technology if they find it simple to interact with (Davis, 1989; Igbaria, Guimaraes, & Davis, 1995). Consequently, a technology which primary purpose is to enable collective knowledge sharing is highly dependent on usage simplicity. Hence:
H3b

Individuals who perceive that social-collaboration tools are easier to use are more likely to engage in knowledge sharing activities.


Satisfaction is a component that both intention and habit have in common (Aarts, Verplanken, & Van Knippenberg, 1997). Satisfactory experiences with a behavior is proxy for habit development as they increase one's tendency to repeat the same action again and again (Aarts et al., 1997). Conversely, a user's intention to continue using an IS is primarily determined by whether the system matches his or her initial expectations (Bhattacherjee, 2001). Satisfactory usage of a technology is deeply intertwined with the extent to which it is easy to use (Wixom & Todd, 2005). Scholars have pointed out the influence of website design on internet consumer satisfaction (Spiller & Lohse, 1997). Consequently, internet users are likely to be more loyal to websites that offer greater usability because they offer them more satisfactory experiences (Flavián, Guinalíu, & Gurrea, 2006). On the other hand, if a system is associated with negative or frustrating usage experiences, users will probably stop relying on it and never develop habits around its use. Hence:
H3a

Individuals who perceive that social-collaboration tools are easier to use will develop habits around their usage.


3.2. Explaining the moderating effect of habit on intention and behavior
The integration of habit in IS continuance models consistently reduces the prevalence of other considerations such as usefulness or image perceptions in continuance behavior (Karahanna et al., 1999). Therefore, the predictive power of intention to use a system is drastically reduced when habits around this usage have formed. In other words, the more a behavior is performed out of habit, the less intentional the activity. The rationale is that once established, habits diminish the need for cognitive effort or conscious attention to perform an activity (Wood et al., 2002), leading individuals to follow certain cognitive shortcuts when performing an activity (Aarts et al., 1997). In their study investigation the knowledge sharing continuance phenomenon, He and Wei (2009) found that habits significantly moderate the effect of intentions (to either contribute or seek knowledge) on the continuance of such activities. We therefore formulate the following hypotheses:
Habit moderates the relationship between relative advantage and knowledge sharing, such that the relationship is stronger for individuals with a high habit level.
H4a

Habit moderates the relationship between relative advantage and knowledge sharing, such that the relationship is stronger for individuals with a high habit level.

H4b

Habit moderates the relationship between compatibility and knowledge sharing, such that the relationship is stronger for individuals with a high habit level.

H4c

Habit moderates the relationship between perceived ease of use and knowledge sharing, such that the relationship is stronger for individuals with a high habit level.]]>
</section>



    <section name="Study design and method" category="methods">
        
4. Study design and method
        <h target="3" match="part"> <![CDATA[ 
4.1. Quantitative case study
The case study methodology is particularly useful to observe, explain, and/or explore a phenomenon within its real-life setting (Yin, 2003). No-email initiatives being still at a nascent adoption stage and only in pioneer organizations, it appeared pertinent to narrow down our investigation to a single case to allow an in-depth examination of the role of habit in explaining how individuals collaborate without emails.  Besides, the purposeful selection of a case that is highly theoretically relevant is a means to ensure the clear delineation of the context (and thus theoretical boundaries) within which the developed theoretical model may apply. While case studies usually rely on qualitative evidence, it is not rare, when appropriate, to use quantitative evidence (Creswell, 1998; Kaplan & Duchon, 1988; Yin, 2003).This research aims at getting an encompassing understanding of the factors influencing the implementation success of IT-enabled social-collaboration. As a consequence, the collection of quantitative data and their analysis through structural equation modeling techniques appeared as the most appropriate strategy in order to generate results that could be claimed to be representative of an entire organization, extracting as much ‘theoretical essence’ as possible from the collected data. We believe that such methodological choice increases the ‘practicality’ of the results and the associated contributions intended to provide support to organizations that are in the process of adopting social collaborative tools in no-email -related contexts (or at preliminary stages). A quantitative case study approach was thus selected.]]> </h> <![CDATA[
4.2. Case description
The organization is an international information technology services company with 80 000+ employees, operating in more than 40 countries. The knowledge-intensive-firm (KIF) employs globally distributed knowledge workers who generally do not get the opportunity to arrange face-to-face meetings due to travel expenses and time efficiency. In 2011, an internal “email ban” initiative was announced by the CEO of the firm. ]]> <h target="1" match="part">The company-wide project aimed at questioning email usage, while introducing a knowledge sharing culture.</h> <![CDATA[

This study took place as managers from an incident management unit decided to put-in some change management effort with the purpose of drastically changing collaborative behaviors that were solely email-based at that stage. The unit is comprised of 120 employees dispersed in France and Poland in five different teams. The main mission of the unit is to restore failed (or failing) services as quickly as possible so that requesters (the clients of the firm) could continue using the services with minimal disruption and a maximum of security. The core activity was supported by an incident management system in which incident-related information was captured (e.g., description, severity, status, etc.). The features of the system were quite structured, leaving little room for informal information exchanges. Yet the management acknowledged that such need clearly existed, severely impeding the effective resolution of incidents. A preliminary investigation performed by one of the researchers (through a web survey) revealed that about 25% of the situations encountered by operators were not documented in the incident management system and that 34% of these situations required the operator to seek-out for help. ]]> <h tqrget="1" match="part">The set of newly available social-collaboration tools was deemed appropriate to support communication activities and consequently to replace email as an unstructured collaboration technology.</h> <![CDATA[ The collaborative environment revolved around three tools, which overall functional coverage encompassed the various aspects and needs associated with social collaboration (Bafoutsou & Mentzas, 2002):
•
Conferencing System & Whiteboard (CSW). The videoconferencing system allowed simultaneous screen sharing and was generally used for meetings. Users could also consult and work on documents simultaneously, on each other's screen, or on a whiteboard (Coleman & Ward, 1999).In the context of this study, whiteboards were used to pin messages that anyone in the conference group could see and edit (similarly to electronic bulletin boards). Users did not draw on the virtual surface, contrary to the original intended use.
•
Enterprise Social Media (ESM). Common social mediatechnologies include blogs, microblogs, social networking sites, wikis, and video- or content-sharing sites (Piskorki & McCall, 2010; Kaplan & Haenlein, 2010). Organizations have begunexperimenting social media in the workplace, namely Enterprise Social Media for various purposes such as to build innovation communities and support ideation processes (Dahl, Lawrence, & Pierce, 2011).They are an extension of the more traditional discussion forums as ESM allow for the sharing of any digital media (e.g., slide-decks, images, polls, etc.) in a richer social context (connectivity feature).
•
Document Management System (DMS). The repositories contained information related to project organization, clients, or historical/archival information (contract, project governance, team organization, etc.). In addition, valuable knowledge could be collected and placed into shared repositories for further usage (Gunnlaugsdottir, 2003). Contrary to the other two collaboration tools, the DMS offered confidentiality management functionalities through a differentiated distribution of access rights across members.

4.3. Data collection and sample
The research project took place in August 2014. A survey questionnaire was made available on the internal survey tool and published in each collaboration space of the five teams at the end of the project (post-adoption). The respondents were informed that their participation was voluntary and the provided information kept confidential. A total of 66 valid responses were collected (of which none was excluded) providing a response rate of about 55% (120 employees in total). This is in line with the standard response rate of 60% suggested by Curran and Blackburn (2001), and in line with the response rates of studies in similar contexts (e.g., Brown, Dennis, & Venkatesh, 2010 ; Bajwa et al., 2008; Maruping & Magni, 2015). 32% of our respondents had a management position (e.g., operation manager) and 68% an operator role (e.g., incident analyst, technical support). Table 1 provides some summary information about the sample.
Table 1. Presentation of the sample.
Total respondents	Operator role	Manager role	Relative frequency of usage of the collaborative toolset (indicative)
Team A	16	12	4	High
Team O	5	2	3	N.A.
Team E	23	17	6	Low
Team G	2	0	2	High
Team L	8	5	3	High
Team R	12	9	3	Medium
Total	66	45	21	
4.4. Measurement
The conceptual definitions as well as the operationalizations of the model's constructs are provided in Table 2. All constructs were measured using 5-points Likert scales anchored between “strongly disagree” and “strongly agree”. All the constructs except knowledge sharing were drawn from pre-validated measures and reworded to fit the particular context of incident management activities. Noticeably, since social-collaboration was enabled through the combined use of three tools, the survey questionnaire explicitly stated that social-collaborative technologies referred to (CSW), (ESM) and (DMS). This minimized the unlikely possibility that the usage of alternative technologies could be captured by the survey instrument.
Table 2. Conceptualization and operationalization of the constructs.
Sources	Definition	Items
Compatibility (Moore & Benbasat, 1991)	The degree to which use of the toolset is compatible with, or requires change, in one's job	Using the social-collaboration tools is compatible with all aspects of my work (CO1)
Using the social-collaboration tools is completely compatible with my current situation (CO2)
I think that using the social-collaboration tools fits well with the way I like to work (CO3)
Using the social-collaboration tools fits into my work style (CO4)
Perceived ease of use
(Moore & Benbasat, 1991)	The degree to which the toolset is easy to learn and use	It is easy for me to remember how to perform tasks using the social-collaboration tools (EOU1)
(REV) Using the social-collaboration tools is often frustrating (EOU2)
Overall, I believe that the social-collaboration tools are easy to use (EOU3)
I believe that it is easy to get the social-collaboration tools to do what I want it to do (EOU4)
Learning to operate the social-collaboration tools is easy for me (EOU5)
Relative advantage (Moore & Benbasat, 1991)	The degree to which the use of the toolset is a benefit in one's job	Using the social-collaboration tools enables me to accomplish tasks more quickly
Using the social-collaboration tools improves the quality of work I do
Using the social-collaboration tools makes it easier to do my job
The disadvantages of my using the social-collaboration tools far outweigh the advantages
Using the social-collaboration tools enhances my effectiveness on the job
Using the social-collaboration tools increases my productivity
Habit (adapted from Limayem et al., 2007)	The extent to which workers tend to use the toolset automatically because of learning	Using the new collaborative tools has become a habit (HA1)
I use the new collaborative tools automatically (HA2)
When I start my day of work, I connect to the new social-collaborative tools (HA3)
Knowledge sharing	The capability one has in sharing knowledge and expertise with other team members	I am able to communicate effectively with my colleagues in order to solve incidents (KS1)
I can easily share my knowledge and my expertise with my colleagues (KS2)
I can easily share my knowledge and contribute to solving incidents (KS3)
I am in capacity to share my ideas with the other members of the team (KS4)
The measurement of compatibility, perceived ease of use and relative advantage were drawn from Moore and Benbasat (1991) with minor wording changes. Our operationalization of habit was inspired by measures of Limayem et al. (2007) and Limayem and Hirt (2003). HA1 and HA2 reflected the extent to which using social-collaboration tools had become natural for the individual. HA3 was added to capture the frequency of prior behavior, which is another key aspect of habit (Limayem et al., 2007). With a high enough usage frequency, the cognitive effort required to perform an activity is automatically reduced. A review of the literature revealed that the existing knowledge sharing measures were not readily available in the literature (Wang & Noe, 2010) but more importantly, also not applicable to the no-email/social-collaboration context. Some researchers used coding schemes to examine knowledge exchanges in electronic virtual communities (Wasko & Faraj, 2005) but this approach was deemed inappropriate for it would have allowed us to capture only a fringe of all knowledge exchanges. Indeed, pieces of communal knowledge were distributed across multiple virtual spaces hosted within three complementary technologies (CSW, ESM and DMS). This made it impossible to track down knowledge pieces for coding purposes. Consequently, it was decided to rather examine the capability one has to sharing knowledge, regardless of which channel was used (e.g., informal interaction, organizational database, virtual community) but also regardless of the type of knowledge that was shared (e.g., personal experience, expertise, ideas). The derived set of items captured either instrumental knowledge sharing that directly served incident solving (KS1 & KS3), or communal knowledge resulting from the sharing of personal expertise (KS2) or ideas (KS4) that indirectly contributed to solving incidents.
4.5. Data analysis technique
There are two main SEM techniques: covariance-based (usually using LISREL or EQS for instance) and component-based techniques using the Partial Least Squares approach (Marcoulides, Chin, & Saunders, 2009Wetzels, Odekerken-Schröder, & Van Oppen, 2009). The main objective of Partial Least Squares (or PLS) analysis is to maximize the explained variance of the dependent latent constructs. Covariance-based techniques aim at reproducing the theoretical covariance matrix but without focusing on explained variance (Hair, Ringle, & Sarstedt, 2011).
PLS was chosen to analyze the survey data collected in this research for several reasons. First, the overall research goal plays an important role in determining the most appropriate method. PLS is recommended in research that is exploratory (or an extension of an existing structural theory) and which involves theory development (Chin, 1998a; Hair et al., 2011). In addition, PLS techniques are usually more efficient with samples of small size (Ringle, Sarstedt, & Straub, 2012). In PLS, a structural equation model consists of 2 models (Hair et al., 2011; Wetzels et al., 2009). The outer model (or measurement model) specifies the relationships between the constructs and their associated indicators. The inner model (or structural model) connects the various constructs together. PLS models are then defined by two sets of linear equations, one for the inner and one for the outer model. In PLS, the evaluation of the outer model must be first performed before an inner model can be legitimately assessed (Chin, 1998a; Henseler, Ringle, & Sinkovics, 2009).
4.6. Instrument validation (validation of the measurement/outer model)
Internal consistency was assessed using composite reliability using a 0.70 threshold (Chin, 1998a). Individual item reliability was evaluated by examining the loadings of the measurement items (using a bootstrap procedure with 5000 resamples) with their respective construct (Hair et al., 2011; Hulland 1999). A common rule of thumb is to retain the items which loadings are greater than 0.707 (Gefen & Straub 2005; Straub, Boudreau, & Gefen, 2004). Construct convergent validity was evaluated for each construct by looking at Average Extracted Variance (AVE), with a threshold value of 0.50 (Chin, 1998a,b; Wetzels et al., 2009). Finally, construct discriminant validity was evaluated via the Fornell–Larcker criterion (Fornell & Larcker, 1981) and item cross-loadings (Hair et al., 2011; Hulland 1999).
Tables 3–5 present the results of the outer model validation phase. Composite reliability coefficients were all above 0.7. Individual item reliability was satisfactory for all constructs as all item loadings were above 0.707 with the exception of EOU2 which had a loading of 0.54, but significant (p < 0.001). After careful examination, the item was eventually retained because the composite reliability of the construct decreased when the item was omitted (Chin 1998a,b; Hair et al., 2011). All constructs' AVE values were highly above 0.5 indicating good levels of construct convergent validity. The assessment of construct discriminant validity did not raise any concern since all the item loadings were higher in their respective construct than with any of the other constructs (see Table 4). Meanwhile, the square root of the AVE of each construct was found to be greater than the correlations of the construct with the other constructs (Table 5).
Table 3. Measurement scale validation results.
Construct	Item	Mean		Loading	Reliability (CR)	AVE
Relative advantage	RA1	2.50	1.10	0.764***	.94	.830
RA2	2.70	1.01	0.957***		
RA3	2.68	1.03	0.809***		
Compatibility	COM1	2.73	1.06	0.783***	.93	.807
COM2	3.13	1.08	0.795***		
COM3	2.73	1.07	0.904***		
Ease of use	EOU1	3.60	1.04	0.807***	.80	.575
EOU2	2.88	1.08	0.540**		
EOU3	3.17	0.96	0.864***		
Habit	HAB1	2.90	1.20	0.939***	.93	.813
HAB2	2.85	1.10	0.866***		
HAB3	2.88	1.26	0.783***		
Knowledge sharing	KWS1	3.82	0.85	0.781***	.85	.595
KWS2	3.78	0.90	0.799***		
KWS3	3.93	0.99	0.633***		
KWS4	3.78	0.99	0.802***		
Table 4. Item cross-loadings.
Item/ Construct	Relative advantage	Compatibility	Ease
of use	Habit	Knowledge sharing
RA1	.90	.68	.44	.59	.30
RA2	.89	.68	.50	.64	.46
RA3	.94	.76	.48	.57	.36
CO1	.65	.88	.51	.51	.28
CO2	.69	.92	.60	.52	.28
CO3	.75	.89	.49	.59	.37
EOU1	.24	.36	.80	.43	.32
EOU2	.28	.45	.56	.26	.28
EOU3	.61	.55	.88	.53	.28
HU1	.64	.62	.55	.91	.21
HU2	.61	.54	.49	.95	.18
HU3	.54	.46	.46	.84	.18
KS1	.34	.33	.46	.13	.84
KS2	.27	.09	.24	.13	.82
KS3	.15	.18	.03	.00	.58
KS4	.43	.39	.25	.29	.81
Table 5. Correlation among variables / square root of average variance extracted values.
Relative Advantage	Compatibility	Ease
of Use	Habit	Knowledge Sharing
Relative advantage	0.91				
Compatibility	0.78	0.90			
Ease of use	0.52	0.59	0.76		
Habit	0.66	0.60	0.56	0.90	
Knowledge sharing	0.42	0.35	0.38	0.21	0.77
When analyzing a dataset, researchers in social sciences need to be particularly wary of common method bias, or CMB (Straub, 1989; Straub et al., 2004). CMB can 'inflate' the estimates of structural parameters estimates in a model, and can potentially lead to erroneous conclusions (Gefen & Rigdon, 2011). When it is not possible to collect data using different methods or sources (Podsakoff, MacKenzie, Lee, & Podsakoff, 2003), Harman's one-factor (or single-factor) test is widely used to assess the existence of CMB in a dataset (Podsakoff et al., 2003). The test consists of loading all the measurement items in an exploratory factor analysis and examining the un-rotated factor solution. The rationale behind the technique is that in the presence of CMB, the EFA analysis would result in a single factor solution which will account for a large proportion of the covariance among the measurement items (Podsakoff et al., 2003). In this study, the EFA with un-rotated solution resulted in a 4-factor solution accounting for 73% of the total variance. Meanwhile, the covariance explained by a forced one-factor solution was found to be 44%. These results strongly argue that common method bias was not a threat to the validity of the findings (Liang, Saraf, Hu, & Xue, 2007).]]>
</section>

    <section name="Results" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
5. Results
Once the measurement model evaluated, the next step involved analyzing the structural portion of the research model (Hulland, 1999; Vinzi,, Trinchera, & Amato, 2010). This section first describes the various tests that were conducted to assess the overall quality of the model followed by a more detailed analysis of the model's paths as well as an assessment of the hypothesized moderation effects.
5.1. Overall model assessment
In PLS, a hypothesis on a moderating effect is supported if the path coefficient characterizing the relationship between the interaction term (the product between the exogenous and the moderator variables) and the endogenous is significant – regardless of the coefficients associated with neither the exogenous/endogenous variable path nor the moderator/endogenous variable path (Baron & Kenny, 1986). The path coefficient capturing the moderating effect shall first be proven to differ significantly from zero. Then, the strength of the moderating effect under investigation has to be examined (Henseler & Fassott, 2010). Besides, in the case of modeling multiple moderating effects (with the same moderator) such as it is the case in this research, multi-collinearity is a common problem that can impede the quality of the research by engendering compromising computational problems (Cohen, 1978; Pedhazur, 1982). Following recommendations from PLS experts,1 we tested each moderating effect separately with the purpose of maximizing the number of usable observations (Pan, Sheng, & Xie, 2012); the modest sample size making this argument even stronger. Furthermore, Henseler and Fassott (2010) strongly recommend the computation of f2 effect size coefficients when assessing moderating effects.
Following the above considerations, it was decided to first evaluate the model without any moderating relationship (Model 1: Baseline Model). Then, each moderating effect was subsequently tested Model 2: Research Model (Habit as a Moderator). Finally, in line with Limayem et al.’s approach (2007) in their investigation of the influence of habit on continued internet usage, the direct effect of habit on knowledge sharing was also tested (Model 3: Habit as a Direct Effect).
When using PLS modeling, the degree to which the explained variance of a model is maximized is assessed through the examination of the R2 scores associated with the dependent (or endogenous) constructs (Chin, 1998a; Hair et al., 2011; Hulland, 1999). Furthermore, the tendency to omit the assessment of a model's predictive relevance has been strongly criticized in recent reviews about the use of PLS analysis techniques in social sciences (Hair et al., 2011; Henseler et al., 2009; Hulland, 1999; Ringle et al., 2012). Chin (1998b) had earlier argued that “the prediction of observables or potential observables is of much greater relevance than the estimator of what are often artificial construct-parameters.” (p. 320). In IS, the same conclusion was drawn by Ringle et al. (2012) who performed a thorough review of MISQ articles having used PLS modeling. The authors expressed serious concern when realizing that none of the reviewed studies had examined the predictive relevance of the tested structural models. Over the last few years, Stone's (1974) and Geisser's (1974) cross-validated redundancy measure Q2 has been recommended as an appropriate means to assess model predictive relevance when using PLS (Hair et al., 2011; Henseler et al., 2009; Hulland 1999; Ringle et al., 2012). Overall, positive Q2 measures indicate that a model has satisfactory predictive relevance (the higher the Q2 score the better) while negative Q2 measures signify a lack of predictive relevance (Chin, 2010; Fornell & Cha, 1994; Vinzi et al., 2010). Finally, latest PLS analysis advancements are encouraging the use of a global goodness-of-fit (GoF) criterion allowing to evaluate the overall quality of PLS models (Tenenhaus, Vinzi, Chatelin, & Lauro, 2005). Wetzels et al. (2009) recommend to use GoF baseline values of GoFsmall = 0.1, GoFmedium = 0.25, and GoFlarge = 0.36.
Table 6 reports the R2, Q2, and GoF scores for all three models (Model 1: Baseline Model/Model 2: Research Model (Habit as a Moderator)/Model 3: Habit as a Direct Effect). Overall, the analysis of the data resulted in concluding on the superiority (in terms of explanatory power) of the research model (Model 2) over the two other tested models. The research model was found to have a GoF score of 0.56, indicating a high quality model (GoF = 0.51 for Model 3 and GoF = 0.50 for Model 1). In all three models, about 51% of the variance of habit was explained by the three exogenous variables, relative Advantage, perceived ease of use, and compatibility. 38% of the variance of the dependent variable, knowledge sharing, was explained in the research model (with respectively 24% in Model 3 and 22% in Model 1). The results are highly consistent with Limayem et al. (2007) that investigated the influence of habit in the context of technology usage. Indeed, the authors compared three distinct models: Baseline Model (Without Habit) / Research Model (Habit as a Moderator)/Habit as a Direct Effect, and concluded that continuance intention in the context of Internet usage was better explained in the model where habit was considered as a moderator.
Table 6. Model quality evaluation.
Model	GoF	Endogenous variable	R2	Q2
Model 1-Baseline model
(without habit)	0.50	Habit	.506	.393
KW Sharing	.215	.070
Model 2-Research model (Habit as a moderator)	0.56	KW Sharing	.375	.144
Model 3
(Habit as a direct effect)	0.51	KW Sharing	.240	.080
5.2. Path analysis
When assessing PLS structural models, the path coefficients are used to confirm or reject the hypotheses associated with the developed research model (Chin, 1998; Hulland, 1999). A bootsrapping procedure (with 5000 re-samples) was used to estimate the standard errors of the model parameters (Henseler and Fassott, 2010). Chin (1998a) recommends to use a threshold value for the standardized paths of at least 0.20 to be considered meaningful (whereas significant path coefficients between 0.1 and 0.2 usually suggest that some further investigation is needed). Besides, the lack of consideration of a model's predictive capability added to the absence of assessment of the paths' effect size have been strongly criticized in recent reviews on PLS analysis in social sciences research (Hair et al., 2011; Ringle et al., 2012). In response to such call, f2 effect sizes as well as q2 predictive relevance coefficients were evaluated for each hypothesized path. Their examination was all the more important considering that the two scores helped in providing extra evidence when evaluating the three hypothesized moderating effects. This approach was in line with Limayem et al. (2007) when assessing the various interaction effects in their research model. Following recommendations from Henseler et al.'s (2009), Cohen's (1988) baseline values of 0.02, 0.15, and 0.35 (corresponding to small, medium, and large levels) were used to assess both effect size and predictive relevance. Table 7 presents the size and significance of each path, as well as the f2/q2 scores for all paths (and for all three models). Fig. 2 compiles the final results.
Table 7. Path analysis results.
Hypothesis	Path coeff.	f2	q2	Conclusion
Model 1–Baseline model (without Habit)				
H1a Relative advantage → Habit	0.43**	0.17	0.11	Supported
H1b Relative advantage → KW sharing	0.43*	0.06	0.05	Supported
H2a Compatibility → Habit	n.s.	0.01	0.00	Not supported
H2b Compatibility → KW sharing	n.s.	0.00	0.00	Not supported
H3a Perceived ease of use → Habit	0.28*	0.10	0.05	Supported
H3b Perceived ease of use → KW sharing	n.s.	0.07	0.00	Not supported
Model 2-Research model (Habit as a moderator)				
H4a Relative advantage × Habit → KW sharing	0.27*	0.11	0.04	Supported
H4b Compatibility × Habit → KW sharing	0.33***	0.14	0.10	Supported
H4c Perceived ease of use × Habit → KW sharing	0.25 (p=0.091)	0.10	0.03	Partially supported
Model 3-(Habit as a direct effect)				
Habit → KW sharing	n.s.	0.02	0.01	Not supported
Research model (results)
Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Research model (results).
The results demonstrated the positive effect of relative advantage on both habit (path coefficient = 0.43**, f2 = 0.17, q2 = 0.11) and knowledge sharing (path coefficient = 0.43*, f2 = 0.06, q2 = 0.05), supporting the hypotheses 1a and 1b. Habit was also found to moderate the positive relationship between relative advantage and knowledge sharing (path coefficient = 0.27*, f2 = 0.11, q2 = 0.04). This indicates that as habit increases, the strength of the relationship between relative advantage and knowledge sharing also increases. We computed a simple slopes analysis using Aiken, West, & Reno, 1991 procedure to further investigate the nature and size of the interaction. Fig. 3 shows that the simple slope of the regression of knowledge sharing onto relative advantage with a high habit level (one standard deviation above the mean) is significant (β = .737, p < .001). That is, for every additional 1% increase in relative advantage of POS, .737% of knowledge sharing will increase when the employee has high usage habits. Within low habit levels, the relationship between relative advantage and knowledge sharing was found to be non-significant (β = .132). Therefore, Hypothesis 4a is supported.
Interaction effects-simple slopes plot
Download full-size image
Fig. 3. Interaction effects-simple slopes plot.
The path between perceived ease of use and habit was found to be significant (path coefficient = 0.28*, f2 = 0.10, q2 = 0.05) while no significant relationship was found between perceived ease of use and knowledge sharing. In addition, the hypothesis associated with the moderating effect of habit on the relationship between perceived ease of use and knowledge sharing (Hypothesis 4c) was partially supported (path coefficient = 0.25 with p = 0.091, f2 = 0.10, q2 = 0.03). Despite the non-significant path, the size of the path coefficient combined with the closeness of the significance with the 0.05 threshold value, and added to the low sample size, tends to suggest that some further investigation would be needed to gain some additional insights about the possible existence and size of the interaction effect. The computation of simple slopes resulted in finding a significant simple slope of .589 (p < .01) for high habit levels (with a non-significant β coefficient of −.062 for low habit levels).
Finally, no evidence was found to support the hypothesized effects of compatibility on habit as well as on knowledge sharing. Nonetheless, the moderating effect of habit on the link between compatibility and knowledge sharing was found to be strong and significant (path coefficient = 0.33***, f2 = 0.14, q2 = 0.10). Further computations revealed that the interaction effect accounted for an incremental variance of 8% in the dependent variable. The computation of simple slopes resulted in finding a significant simple slope of .627 (p < .001) for high habit levels (with a non-significant β coefficient of −.016 for low habit levels). Hypothesis 4b is thus supported.]]>
</section>

    <section name="Discussion" category="discussion">
        <![CDATA[
6. Discussion
This section presents a discussion of the main findings alongside with the limitations of the study and contributions to theory and practice.

6.1. Summary of findings
The use of social-collaboration technologies is often perceived as the miracle solution to address the global business trend that consists of distributing business processes across firms and geographies, leading to the development of globally distributed teams. Besides, social-collaboration technologies have also been considered as a way to tackle the widespread email inefficiency question that has been increasingly jeopardizing employee productivity and thus overall firm performance. This research helps understand that the reality on the field is a lot more subtle as the use of social-collaboration technologies in replacement of deeply entrenched work behaviors is inherently disruptive for workers. In other words, using social-collaboration tools is not necessarily synonymous of increased collaboration and knowledge sharing. ]]> <h target="2" match="full">This research goes a step further into exploring this gap through the investigation of the role played by the notion of habit in influencing the relationship between the perceived positive attributes about social-collaborative tools and the actual impact on knowledge sharing capability.</h><![CDATA[ Past information systems research has often sought to understand how users come to adopt a particular information system. However, aside from a technological breakthrough, social-collaboration represents a paradigm shift in the way people feel, think, and behave at work (Castells, 2013). In this context, adoption is a necessary but not a sufficient condition as firms are more interested in long-term viability, success, and continued use of social collaborative tools (Bhattacherjee, 2001); collaboration becoming a new mindset and part of the organization's culture.
A research model was developed hypothesizing a direct effect of three perceived attributes: relative advantage, perceived ease of use, and compatibility, on habit and knowledge sharing. Subsequently, habit was hypothesized to moderate the relationship between all three attributes and the dependent variable, knowledge sharing. The model explained 51% of the variance of habit and 38% for knowledge sharing. The goodness-of-fit (GoF) score of 0.56 provided extra confidence in the overall quality of the model. Alternative models were also tested: a baseline model excluding all moderating effects as well as a model testing the direct effect of habit on the dependent variable. The superiority of the research model was demonstrated.

The findings revealed that habit was positively influenced by relative advantage and perceived ease of use while relative advantage was found to positively impact knowledge sharing. ]]> <h target="4" match="full">Habit was found to moderate the relationships between all three attributes (relative advantage, perceived ease of use, and compatibility to a lesser extent) and knowledge sharing. </h> <![CDATA[ This result suggests that succeeding in implementing collaborative tools in organizations depends on the extent to which usage habits are triggered and developed by management when implementing a collaborative platform. The quicker individuals get into the habit of using collaborative tools, the faster an organization will establish a collaborative culture and will in turn benefit from the development of knowledge sharing behaviors among employees.

6.2. Implications for theory and research
]]> <h target="5" match="part">This research first provides additional evidence about the actual complexity of the relationship between perceptions, intention, and behavior in the technology adoption context (Limayem et al., 2007; Warshaw and Davis, 1984; Warshaw and Davis, 1985a,b).  As a consequence, assuming that intention automatically leads to actual usage when studying technology acceptance is a highly simplistic view, especially in the context of technologies engendering a drastic change in working behaviors. This paper also contributes to the body of knowledge initiated by Limayem and Hirt (2003) and Limayem et al. (2007) who went further into the investigation of the complexity of the relationship between intention and behavior by exploring the role of habit and its antecedents in the context of continued IS usage.</h> <![CDATA[
Going along this line of thought, we purport that our findings shed some new light on research conducted in the past on the adoption and acceptance of collaborative technologies in the Enterprise 2.0 context. Indeed, it is believed that beyond the use of collaborative technologies lay an in-depth work paradigm shift, collaboration, discarding work behavior principles that used to be set in stone for more than a century. As a consequence, caution shall be employed when using widespread IS adoption/acceptance theories and models. ]]> <h target="4" match="part">Adding habit as a moderator is a first step towards better understanding the relationship between the perceived attributes towards collaborative tools and actual knowledge sharing activities. </h><![CDATA[ Future research should continue to explore the nature of this link in order to explain additional variance of the knowledge sharing capability construct. We encourage additional types of perceptions and attributes to be investigated.

Finally, this research assumed that the formation of habits happens in an identical way across the various functions and hierarchical levels of organizations. Lindbladh and Lyttkens (2002) reflected upon the idea that “people in lower social positions are more inclined to rely on their habits and are accordingly less likely to change their behavior” (p. 451). Such insights could lead to an interesting continuation of this research by investigating whether different habit types exist across organizational levels and functions and also whether habits form and develop along different patterns.
6.3. Implications for practice
This study provides recommendations for program managers who are willing to engage in a social-collaboration initiative. It demonstrates by extension from our case that habits play a key role in the success or failure of this type of projects. Managers should expect that breaking from old habits while enabling the development of new ones will require continuous change management efforts. Managers should first focus on breaking old habits by creating a sense of urgency for change (Kotter, 1996). As habits start forming around new collaboration principles, establishing and communicating a change vision will help ensure users to not revert back to past behaviors. Management shall also consider the incentivization of habit development through direct usage monitoring in the system and/or by using employee surveys/interviews. This research also provides indication on how the success of social-collaboration initiatives shall be measured. In this regard, implementing KPIs that capture how efficiently knowledge is created, shared and retrieved across the organization would be a good starting point. Indeed, by extension of our case on distributed teams, we can anticipate that social-collaboration tools provide a promising solution for improving knowledge-exchange processes in organizations. Our research has design implications for social-collaboration media as well. Given the prominence of habit formation around these tools, it is important to provide features that will reinforce continuous usage (e.g., gamification features).
6.4. Limitations
While this research paper brings several contributions to research and practice, there are a number of opportunities to improve upon and extend this study in future research. First, the aim of this study is to explore the impact of social-collaborative technologies on the knowledge sharing capability of employees, and thus of the overall firm. However, there are barriers to knowledge sharing, such as a lack of incentives (Yao, Kam, & Chan, 2007) or a maladapted organizational climate (Schepers & Van den Berg, 2007) that may impede knowledge sharing behaviors. Our knowledge sharing measure is not behavioral but rather intentional because it focuses on an individual's perceived knowledge sharing capability. This decision was motivated by the consideration that beyond being reflected in a set of work behaviors, the essence of collaboration is within the employees' mind. Once collaboration is engrained into an individual's mindset, then collaborative behaviors will follow and spread across other employees. Nonetheless, extending our research using a more objective and quantifiable knowledge sharing measure would help demonstrate the causal link between collaborative mindset and work behaviors. Measures based on user data generated on the collaborative platform could be envisaged.
Second, habits require a stable context to develop (Limayem et al., 2007) as this facilitates the propensity to perform repeated behaviors with minimal cognitive monitoring (Wood et al., 2002). The disruptive nature of the no-email initiative may have altered the stability required for habits to form. Moreover, habits require time to develop. Although, the social-collaboration toolset had been available for about one year before the study took place, it was initially seldom used by the members of the incident unit. We can assume that a more stable context as well as a different data collection time would provide complementary results. Continuing along this line of thought, a longitudinal methodology relying on data collected across several phases of the usage process, would bring additional insights about how habits develop and evolve over time (Limayem et al., 2007).
Finally, the purpose of this study was to investigate the special role played by habits in implementing a collaboration-based culture within organizations, more specifically in the context of no-email initiatives. The choice of a case study methodology was motivated by the intention to gain an in-depth understanding of the phenomenon and thus to focus on a single case that had high theoretical relevance (no-email initiatives being still rather scarce among organizations). The preference for a quantitative case study in lieu of more conventional qualitative case study methodologies was justified by the desire to derive findings that were applicable and valid within the boundaries of the entire organization; the overall objective being to investigate the importance of work habits in firms in the process of adopting social collaborative tools in a no-email context. Future research could aim at replicating this study in other organizations that are at the same but also at prior or post implementation stages. Cross-sectional research designs are also needed to extend the validity of the findings.

The conclusions derived in this research paper may trigger a broader reflection on the predominant role of habits in the adoption and continuous use of disruptive technologies. It is hoped that the advances made in this paper will stimulate such future research efforts.]]>
</section>

</publication>