<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="gai shuangshuang">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 6, Part B, December 2016, Pages 1320-1327</time>
International Journal of Information Management
    <title>An analysis of the utilization of Facebook by local Korean governments for tourism development and the network of smart tourism ecosystem</title>
    <author>Ji Hoon Park.</author> Author links open the author workspace.a. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Cheolhan Lee.</author> Author links open the author workspace.b. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Changsok Yoo.</author> Author links open the author workspace.c. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Yoonjae Nam.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspacec. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
School of Media and Communication, Korea University, Republic of Korea
b
Department of Advertising and Public Relations, Dongguk University, Republic of Korea
c
<![CDATA[Department of Culture & Tourism Contents, Kyung Hee University, Republic of Korea]]>
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.05.027</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">We investigate the utilization of Facebook by local Korean governments for tourism development.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">Most local Koran governments actively manage Facebook to promote tourism with public.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">The level of local government affects the level of SNS use for tourism.</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">Korean local governments’ Facebook pages are co-related as part of a smart tourism ecosystem.</highlight>
    <highlight id="5">The smart tourism ecosystem is associated with governmental utilization of Facebook for activating local tourism.</highlight>

<abstract>
Abstract
    <h target="1" match="full">This study investigated the utilization of Facebook by local Korean governments for the purposes of tourism development.</h> <h target="2" match="full">The results indicate that most local Korean governments actively manage online tools such as Facebook, to communicate with the public and offer a wide range of information to promote tourism.</h> <h target="3" match="full"> A notable finding is that the level of local governmental could affect the level of social networking site use for tourism.</h> It is claimed that the varying level of social networking site use is because the scale of the tourism industry and the level of information and communication technology innovation could vary with different types of municipalities.  <h target="4" match="full">Through network analyses, the study also shows that Korean local governments’ Facebook pages are co-related in the Facebook system as part of a smart tourism ecosystem,</h> <h target="5" match="full">and that the smart tourism ecosystem facilitated by Facebook offerings is associated with governmental utilization of Facebook for activating local tourism.</h> 
</abstract>
    
    <keywords>Local governments</keywords>
    <keywords>Smart tourism</keywords>
    <keywords>Facebook</keywords>
    <keywords>Ecosystem</keywords>
    <keywords>Network analysis</keywords>
    
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction"><![CDATA[
1. Introduction
The use of advanced information and communication technology is ubiquitous in most business sectors. The tourism industry is no exception. The tourism experience has never been this ‘smart.’ Thanks to the GPS and augmented reality functions of smartphones, visitors are updated with real-time information on dining options, weather, currency rates, accommodations, and nearby points of interest. A travel guide application that runs on smartphones operates in several different languages and offers a variety of services such as audio guides, interactive street maps and transportation information such as real-time bus schedules and bus fares.

In correspondence with the ever increasing ‘smartness’ of the tourism experience, the concept of smart tourism has gained currency recently in academia as well as in the tourism industry. What is intriguing is the role of state and local governments in promoting smart tourism. Most notably, China and Korea have been driving the smart tourism agenda forward by funding initiatives to build infrastructure and develop interactive digital technologies, all of which constitutes the foundation of a so-called smart tourism ecosystem (Gretzel, Koo, Sigala, & Xiang, 2015; Gretzel, Sigala, Xiang, & Koo, 2015; Koo, Shin, Kim, Kim, & Chung, 2013). For instance, the Korean Tourism Organization has both domestic and international Smart Tourism Departments which oversee the development and operation of multiple platforms, including multilingual websites and smartphone applications like Korea Everywhere and Visit Korea, which offer location-based information about tourist destinations and local events (Koo et al., 2013).
Social media, social networking sites (SNSs), take a central place in smart tourism by local governments. Social media are more than just a cost-effective marketing tool that can instantly reach millions of people; they can also be used to create a hub that brings together local governments, tourism agencies, industry partners, and other institutions interested in developing business relationships in this sector. Increasingly it is not uncommon to see local governments, e.g. recently the Welsh government, create LinkedIn business pages to build networks of different players in the tourism industry. Social media can offer support to tourism businesses by providing information about investment opportunities, tourism industry research results, PR opportunities, and travel trade opportunities. Furthermore, the social media strategies of many local governments can facilitate sustainable growth for other multimedia sectors because audio and video have become increasingly important as marketing tools. Lee (2012) recommends a more innovative use of social media, “social media marketing podcasting,” by proposing that Korean local governments produce a podcast called “Korean Tourism 100,” which includes not only conventional tourist information but also special lectures, seminars, storytelling, and forums. Recently, the number of shared video posts on Facebook exceeded those of YouTube (O’Reilly, 2014). Given the growing importance of video posts in social media, this visual material can go viral and be seen by millions, making it an ideal platform for promoting local tourism.
Among various aspects of smart tourism, this study pays attention to the ways in which local governments utilize SNSs to promote tourism. ]]> <h target="1" match="full">More specifically, this study investigated how local governments in Korea utilize Facebook for the purposes of tourism development. </h> <![CDATA[ In a country well-known for cutting-edge mobile, smart technologies, Korean governments have taken active roles the tourism initiatives, developing a variety of tour-related services (Koo et al., 2013). While this study is specific to the use of Facebook by Korean local governments, it more generally provides insights into both theoretical and practical implications of smart tourism.
This exploratory study first identifies the characteristics of smart tourism. Then the study discusses how local governments can take an active role in smart tourism and contribute to a larger smart tourism ecosystem.]]><h target="2" match="full"> With Korean local governments in focus, this paper explores the degree to which local governments actively manage Facebook as an online tool to communicate with the public and promote tourism.</h>  <h target="4" match="full">Through network analyses, the study suggests that Korean local governments’ Facebook pages are co-related in the Facebook system as part of a smart tourism ecosystem, </h> <h target="5" match="full">and that the smart tourism ecosystem facilitated by Facebook offerings is associated with governmental utilization of Facebook for activating local tourism.</h><![CDATA[

1.1. Conceptualizing smart tourism
Smart tourism is a slippery term that has a wide range of meanings in academic research, corporate settings, and government sectors. While the term smart tourism abounds in popular discourse, a sheer dearth of academic work exists regarding the identification of its key characteristics. Although the term is used inconsistently, this study attempts to identify three popular usages of smart tourism based on observations of a variety of documents and popular websites.1 First, smart tourism can be defined as intelligent services that intend to satisfy the needs of tourists by helping them make the most out of their visits to unknown destinations. With the rapid increase in domestic and international tourism, particularly FITs (free and independent travelers), the demand for customized tourism services has increased. One can easily find online travel agencies (e.g., globallysmart.com) developed with the intention of producing smart and intelligent tourists. Smart tourism agencies offer more than just traditional services like organizing flight tickets and hotel bookings. They also offer comparison services, customized travel packages, and an online space where travelers can share their own experiences. For instance, Smart Tourism Marketing Group, a travel agency based in New Zealand, provides guests and visitors with personalized itinerary services. This smart service allows its users to “create tourism,” which Epstein and Vergani (2006) identify as the process whereby tourists become active producers of their tourism experiences rather than passive consumers. As Molz (2012) notes, smart tourism develops “open-ended adventures that allow tourists to create their own narrative trajectory through a city (p. 57).”
Second, smart tourism is concerned with tourism-related corporations’ marketing services, including tourism marketing strategies, online marketing (e.g., social media strategies), and promotional campaigns. Also included in this category are digital service interface development and project management platforms such as the development of tourism-related websites and smartphone applications. Trento Rise in Italy, for example, is a company that has developed a “smart tourism platform” for enhanced and innovative tourism management. Likewise, Smarttourismwebsite.com offers web marketing solutions for tourism businesses.
Finally, smart tourism refers to the combination of technology and tourism. Apparently, web-based tour services such as hotel reservations, food, transportation, and healthcare are not new. The application of information and communication technology (ICT) to the tourism sector has a long history. Technological innovation in this industry can be traced back to the 1950s when airlines developed computerized reservation systems (CRSs) for scheduling and booking (Alt & Zimmerman, 2015). The global distribution system (GDS) and the World Wide Web (WWW) revolutionized the tourism sector and have facilitated the development of a globally operating, internet-based tourism environment (Smith, Macleopd, & Robertson, 2010). As early as the 1980s, scholars like Poon (1988) began to discuss the implications of adopting new technologies to improve the organization, management, and distribution of tourism services. How then is the current notion of smart tourism different from the traditional concept of information technology in tourism? Does smart tourism represent a significant departure from the e-tourism of the past? While smart tourism can be seen as an advanced form of e-tourism, it distinguishes itself from earlier form of tourism. Gretzel, Koo et al. (2015), Gretzel, Sigala et al. (2015) have outlined the differences between e-tourism and smart tourism in six different fields.
Central to smart tourism is the advancement of mobile technologies (Buhalis & Law, 2008; Wang, Park, & Fesenmaier, 2012). Between 2013 and 2017, mobile phone penetration is expected to rise from 61.6% to 69.4% of the global population (eMarketer, 2014). The development and spread of personal smart devices and ICT infrastructure are expected to have a profound impact on the tourism industry and to stimulate smart tourism practices. The Organization for Economic Co-operation and Development (OECD) defines smart as “an application or service able to learn from previous situations and to communicate the results of these situations to other devices and users” (Guest Author, 2013). For instance, mobile-device GPS functions and Quick Response (QR) codes enable a variety of location-based, real-time interactive touristic services such as interactive street maps, augmented reality features, and access to transportation information in different languages. Location-aware mobile applications offer otherwise invisible place-based information tools that enhance tourists’ experiences. Molz (2012) defines smart tourism as multi-sensuous since it “opens up possibilities of touching, smelling, feeling, tasting and gazing as tourists inhabit and move through a city” (pp. 57–58). A smart tourism project entitled SMART (Scotland’s Museums Augmented Reality Tourism) at the University of St Andrews aims to provide visitors with a digital-physical experience where overlaid, personalized, multi-lingual text and rich audiovisual information are presented when a visitor maintains his or her focus on a specific artifact in a museum.
Smart tourism emerged in the context of revolutionary advancement in communication infrastructures and interactive digital technologies, widely referred to as the “smart revolution” (Yoo, 2012). The smart revolution has opened up the possibility of profound transformation in the ways that individuals and organizations behave, operate, and connect to one another. Elliott and Urry (2010) claim that “the emergence of a complex global mobility system involves the creation of new forms of mobile social life, new kinds of daily experience, and new forms of social interaction” (p. 5). Therefore, smart tourism must be seen as a shift in tourism ecology in that it transforms traditional tourism practices and facilitates the creation of new business models for tourism-related industries, including the disintermediation of the tourism industry and the emergence of tourism e-mediaries (Buhalis, 2003; Buhalis & Licata, 2002)
Scholars generally agree that there are three characteristics unique to smart tourism. First, smart tourism represents a convergence between conventional tourism industries and ICT (Gretzel, Koo et al., 2015; Gretzel, Sigala et al., 2015; Hunter, Chung, Gretzel, & Koo, 2015). Wireless internet, mobile smartphones, portable computers, connected hotspots, and social networking sites are integrated into a converged platform of travel information and services that tourists have ubiquitous access to. What used to be a solid boundary between different businesses and media has now become blurred because both travel agents and smartphones perform the same booking functions—both allowing tourists, for example, to buy train tickets and reserve hotels. Travelers have become both consumers and producers of tourist knowledge since the emergence of travel blogging, for instance, which allows tourists to share travel knowledge.
Second, smart tourism is social in that it removes barriers (e.g., language and access) to sociable interaction among and between tourists and locals, thus enhancing social opportunity (Koo et al., 2013). By alerting tourists when other tourists are nearby, location-aware mobile media can facilitate connections and interactions between tourists (Molz, 2012). Capitalizing on social media, Sol Wave Hotel in Spain encourages guests to interact with one another by allowing them to share pictures, send private messages, see other guests online, and share their locations inside the hotel. Furthermore, an increasing number of tourists become active players or prosumers in the tourism industry by sharing their journeys, reviews, and experiences with geographically dispersed tourists via blogs and social networking sites (SNSs), thereby creating a virtual community.
The third characteristic of smart tourism is connectedness, in that it brings together relevant tourism stakeholders including government, tourism industry participants, IT specialists, device manufacturers, universities, and research sectors. According to Buhalis and Amaranggana (2014), dynamically connected stakeholders are defining characteristics of smart tourism. Smart tourism facilitates the symbiotic relationships that transportation, accommodation, restaurants, and cultural activities have with various technological media, including social media, the Internet, and applications (STRC, 2014). As noted in Table 1, compared with the earlier form of tourism, smart tourism promotes public-private-consumer collaboration—by creating information, citizens and consumers can take on the roles of governments or businesses (Gretzel, Koo et al., 2015; Gretzel, Sigala et al., 2015).
Table 1. Smart Tourism vs. e-Tourism (Gretzel, Koo et al., 2015; Gretzel, Sigala et al., 2015, p. 182).
e-Tourism	Smart Tourism
Sphere	digital	bridging digital & physical
Core technology	websites	sensors & smartphones
Travel phase	pre- & post-travel	during trip
Lifeblood	information	big data
Paradigm	interactivity	technology-mediated co-creation
Structure	value chain/intermediaries	ecosystem
Exchange	B2B, B2C, C2C	public-private-consumer collaboration
It is noteworthy that government organizations have often supported the development of solutions that enhance the technological base or infrastructure of the tourism sector. In order to facilitate the mobility of international tourists, government representatives from the tourism sectors of Peru, Colombia, and Ecuador have agreed to collaborate on a smart visa electronic system in the region that will replace traditional visa procedures. Taiwan’s Board of Science and the Institute for Information Industry worked together with the Taipei City Government, the Taipei Computer Association, the External Trade Development Council, and Chunghwa Telecom Co. to establish “Smart Tourism Taiwan,” a web platform that can be synced across multiple platforms such as smartphones and web browsers. Government sectors often work in tandem with universities and research institutions to enhance the competitiveness of their tourism sectors. In Korea, government-led Brain Korea 21 Plus supports research programs in Korean universities to promote the government’s creative economy policy, which includes the development of smart tourism. ETRI (Electronics and Telecommunications Research Institute), a non-profit and the largest government-funded research institute, developed Korean-English interpretation applications, which boast over an 80% success rate in real-life situations.

While states and local governments have taken active roles in smart tourism, very little empirical research has been carried out to identify how they use social media and/or advanced mobile technologies to provide information to the public, and whether they can serve as central agents of the smart tourism ecosystem. The following sections discuss how local governments utilize social media, such as Facebook, and how such utilizations are associated with the smart tourism ecosystem.<![CDATA[ 

1.2. Local governments and smart tourism
Local governments, especially in less developed regions, have actively pursued the development of tourism. Government involvement in tourism has many forms, such as investing resources, planning policies, and promoting tourist attractions. Previous studies have shown that economic concerns are the main impetus for local governments to become involved in tourism. Residents expect that the development of tourism will result in an improvement in the local economy, better employment opportunities, infrastructure improvements, and more investment opportunities (Nunkoo & Ramkissoon, 2011). In addition, a successful tourism sector also provides opportunities for cultural exchange and increases entertainment opportunities for local residents (Besculides, Lee, & McCormick, 2002). For example, a local government’s investment in a tourist attraction such as a national park might lead to the provision of additional economic development and to sources of funding to maintain the park’s value. In order to achieve these positive effects of tourism, local governments often play a significant role in funding and operating tourist activities and attractions.
The competitiveness of tourist destinations often relies on the cultural or natural environment. It is ironic that the economic success of a tourist attraction might lead to negative environmental consequences such as population pressures, land use intensification, air pollution, traffic congestion, vandalism, and environmental damage. In other words, uncontrolled tourism has the potential to seriously damage both the environment and the tourist prospects of a given area (Nunkoo & Smith, 2013). For example, the negative impacts resulting from tourism development in New Zealand have included the loss of some parts of the country’s natural environment that had been relatively unspoiled, as well as the loss of amenity values from incremental development. This can also affect the quality of life of a country’s citizens and put pressure on infrastructure, resulting in significant costs to local communities (Connell, Page, & Bently, 2009). If excessive development is permitted, tourism can damage the very essence of a tourist attraction’s competitiveness. These negative effects can also force local governments to become involved in tourism development and to seek sustainable modes for promoting tourism.
For travelers, the information provided on government tourism websites or SNSs are often the best places to obtain credible information—even better, these can be accessed 24 a day from anywhere in the world. Furthermore, the personalization of social media can bring a tourist attraction to life. For example, the City of Abbotsford in Canada uses Mrs. Abbotsford as a Twitter persona, which helps create the sense that residents and visitors are communicating with a person and not an organization, thus increasing credibility through friendly, personal feedback. Travelers visit tourism websites or SNSs to gather information, which might lead to repeated visits to tourism destinations and eventually increase the odds of success for small tourist attractions (Lin & Huang, 2006). An interactive design is a critical factor for tourist websites, as this allows tourist organizations to identify consumers’ interests and boost their participation (Doolin, Burgess, & Cooper, 2002). The provision of virtual experiences using graphics, photos, and videos on local government websites or SNSs is also important. These features can tempt online visitors enough to prompt a real-world visit to the promoted area (Rosen & Purinton, 2004). Exposure to tourism information on social media is positively associated with people’s attitudes towards a place. According to the 2014 Incheon Tourism Social Media Satisfaction Survey, 88% of the 200 respondents who consumed tourism information through Incheon Tourism’s SNS reported more favorable attitudes toward Incheon Metropolitan City (Lee, 2015).
In this context, this study hypothesizes that Korean governments will actively use their Facebook pages as communication tools to attract potential visitors and promote their tourism industry. In addition, according to Larsson (2013), differences between municipalities, mirroring various aspects of a rural-urban dichotomy, can influence the spread of social media utilization.]]> <h target="3" match="full"> This study also suggests that the level of local government could affect the level of SNS use for tourism since the scale of the tourism industry and the level of ICT innovation could vary with different types of municipalities, </h><![CDATA[leading to the following research questions:
RQ1

Do Korean local governments actively use their Facebook pages to provide tourism information to users for developing tourism?

RQ2

Do the level of Facebook utilization in the implementation of Korean local governments’ smart tourism agenda vary according to local government type?


1.3. Smart tourism and ecosystem
Through the development of smart tourism, a complex business and information ecosystem that creates and supports the exchange of touristic resources and the co-creation of the tourism experience can be established (Gretzel, Koo et al., 2015; Gretzel, Sigala et al., 2015). Governmental use of social media for local tourism can provide a map of information ecology, which refers to the interrelationships between relevant online sites. The concept of information ecology focuses on interrelationships between people, enterprises, technologies, and the surrounding information environment (Nam, Lee, & Park, 2013). Among these, human beings are situated at the core of the information ecosystem, which is composed of information strategies, information-seeking behaviors, information management, and information architectures (Feather & Sturges, 2003; Nam et al., 2013). In a service ecosystem context, all social and economic actors interact through institutions and technology in order to co-produce service offerings, exchange service offerings and resources, and co-create value (Spohrer, Maglio, Bailey, & Gruhl, 2007; Vargo, Maglio, & Akaka, 2008). Thus, through examining smart tourism ecosystems, we can describe how smart tourism’s business actors are dynamically interconnected, collaborating, and seamlessly exchanging resources with stakeholders.
This study focuses on information disseminated via SNSs. On an SNS, users visit local governments’ pages to obtain more information about what the government is doing and what is happening in that location. Local governments also interact with users and share information through these networks. Governments can also link content from other organizations, or from mass media outlets, to their sites. More importantly, enriched by Web 2.0 or 3.0 technology, local governments’ sites are now intertwined with other local governments’ sites through link functions such as “likes” on Facebook and “re-tweets” on Twitter. Furthermore, in a smart tourism ecosystem, by using SNSs governments become more open and technology-focused as providers of infrastructure and data. In addition, consumers can also create and offer value as well as monitor, thereby taking on business or governance roles (Gretzel, Koo et al., 2015; Gretzel, Sigala et al., 2015).
A network analysis is a set of research procedures that focuses on the relationships between social entities such as “who provides information to whom” and “who is linked with whom” and explores the patterns of these relationships, including how these entities “collaborate with,” “subcontract with,” and engage in “joint ventures with” each other (Barnett, Danowski, & Richards, 1993; Monge & Contractor, 2003; Rogers & Kincaid, 1981; Wasserman & Faust, 1994). With this in mind, the present study attempts to examine the network structure of local Korean governments’ Facebook pages and the organizations “liked” (or linked) by them as part of a smart tourism ecosystem and how the ecosystem is associated with governmental utilization of Facebook for activating tourism. <![CDATA[The following research questions are posed:
RQ3

How are Korean local governments’ Facebook pages co-linked as part of a smart tourism ecosystem?

RQ4

How is the smart tourism ecosystem facilitated by Facebook offerings associated with governmental utilization of Facebook for activating local tourism?

]]></section>

    <section name="Methods" category="methods"><![CDATA[
2. Methods
2.1. Sample
Korea has 279 local governments, including those of metropolitan cities, provinces (or states) (-do), cities (-si), counties (-gun), and city districts (-gu). Metropolitan cities and provinces are higher-level local governments consisting of 7 metropolitan cities (Seoul, Busan, Incheon, Daegu, Daejeon, Gwangju and Ulsan) and 9 provinces (Gyeonggi-do, Gangwon-do, Gyeongsangbuk-do, Gyeongsangnam-do, Chungcheongbuk-do, Chungcheongnam-do, Jeollabuk-do, Jeollanam-do, Jeju-do), which basically serve as intermediaries between the central and lower-level local governments. And, each metropolitan city has their lower-level of local governments (city districts) and a province has cities (a population of roughly over 150,000) and counties. Gyeonggi-do, which surrounds Seoul, usually has been called “Seoul-capital area”.

Then, it was determined whether they have an official website or SNS presence or not. Among these 279 local governments, 196 have and manage official Facebook pages, and, of these, only 133 local governments “like” the pages of other organizations. Therefore, this study examined those 133 local governments’ Facebook pages since it is assumed that they are interconnected with third-party stakeholders with regard to the smart tourism ecosystem.

2.2. Data and variables
For this study, the number of “total postings,” “tourism-related postings,” “policy-related postings,” and “total responses to users’ postings” over a seven-day period were collected in preparation for content analysis. For inter-coder reliability, two coders were assigned, and there was 95.4% agreement between them, which is a satisfactory level of reliability.

The relationships among Korean local governments’ Facebook pages and their co-liked Facebook pages are presented as a network data. However, a network based on these relationships is a 2-mode network because it has two different sets of entities: (1) Korean local governments’ Facebook pages, and (2) co-liked Facebook pages. If the rows and columns in a matrix index represent different sets of entities, the matrix is 2-mode matrix (Borgatti & Everett, 1997). In this context, a class of entities is called by the term “mode.” The 1-mode case represents members that have social ties with other members, whereas the 2-mode case represents members that have social ties with members of another class.
Most social network analysis is concerned with the 1-mode case, in which the basic network data set is an n × n matrix S, where n equals the number of nodes in the network. A node might be an individual or a higher-level component such as an organization or a nation from which the system is composed. Each cell, sij, indicates the strength of the relationship among nodes i and j. In communication research, this relationship is generally the frequency of communication among the nodes (Barnett et al., 1993; Nam, 2015; Salisbury & Barnett, 1999).
The 2-mode case arises when researchers collect relations between classes of actors such as persons and events, or companies and organizations. In this case, the study collected data on which companies in the list of Korean local governments’ Facebook pages belong to which co-liked Facebook pages. This type of data is often referred to as affiliations. Co-memberships and co-link relationships with other organizations can be thought of as providing opportunities for social relationships among Korean local governments as actors and also as the consequences of pre-existing relationships for tourism.

Thus, this study obtained data on how Korean local governments jointly linked via certain organizations. The primary data used are explicitly presented outlinks contained in Korean local governments’ Facebook pages. For examining more central local governments in a Facebook network, a two-mode affiliation network was analyzed. This study used a 279 × 4393 matrix (each local government listed × each organization “liked” by the governments’ Facebook pages), where each cell was coded “1” for linked (“liked” by local governments) and “0” for non-linked. The primary data set was pre-multiplied by its transposition to form a 133 (local governments) × 133 matrix of joint affiliation of governments in the Facebook network. Then, using UCINET 6 (Borgatti, Everett, & Freeman, 2002), two types of centrality were calculated to determine which governments or organizations play a significant role in the Facebook network: (1) degree centrality and (2) eigenvector centrality. First, degree centrality in this study indicates the number of co-affiliated organizations between two local governments. To obtain a higher degree of centrality, a local government should be linked with other local governments that are affiliated with many other organizations. Degree centrality in this study indicates that the number of co-affiliated organizations between two companies or the number of co-affiliated global companies between two organizations. The higher number of like-relationships does not simply increase the degree centrality score. Rather, to obtain higher degree-centrality score, Korean local governments’ Facebook pages should be linked with some organizations’ pages which are co-liked with many other Korean local governments’ pages. In other words, how the Korean local governments build their relationships with the core co-related organization which are multi-affiliated with Korean governments are crucial for positioning themselves at the center of smart tourism ecosystem. Second, eigenvector centrality considers the strength of ties and indirect social ties among nodes (Barnett, Danowski, Feeley, & Stalker, 2010). More central local governments could boost their centralities due to the inherent circularity involved in the calculation of eigenvector centrality (Nam, Barnett, & Kim, 2014). In this two-mode case, the total number of co-links with a given local government was considered rather than the one-way links between an organization and a government. Therefore, eigenvector centrality determines how central (or peripheral) a local government is, based on its loading on the largest eigenvector of the network’s sociomatrix.

]]></section>

    <section name="Results" category="results"><![CDATA[
3. Results
3.1. RQ1 and RQ2
The content analysis indicated that 23.1% of total postings on the Korean local governments’ Facebook pages were related to local tourism and relevant tourist information. The ANOVA test showed that the provincial government’s Facebook page had the highest average number of total postings within seven days. This was statistically significant among types (F[4,128] = 4.37, p < 0.01). Metro cities and provinces posted the most tourism-related postings, and there was statistical significance for this finding as well (F[4,128] = 3.17, p < 0.05). Results also indicated that the metro cities had the most “likes” on their tourism postings, and there was a significant difference in the number of “likes” between levels of government. On the other hand, there was no significant difference across the levels of government in terms of the number of policy-related postings and the “likes” on them (Table 2).
Table 2. Utilization of Facebook for tourism development.
No. of postings on Tourism <7 days**	No. of Likes on Tourism postings <7days**	No. of Total postings <7 days**	Like on Policy postings	Like on Tourism postings**
    M	SD	% of posting	M	SD	M	SD	M	SD	M	SD
    Metro (n = 7)	3.0	2.1	34.9	467.4	471.2	471.2	303.3	471.2	303.3	8.6	3.6
    District in Metro (n = 46)	1.1	1.3	19.3	12.7	23.8	23.8	12.0	23.8	12.0	5.7	4
    State (n = 7)	3.0	2.3	30.9	100.9	118.6	118.6	101.6	118.6	101.6	9.7	4
    City in State (n = 47)	1.4	1.8	17.9	221.9	104.7	104.7	922.4	104.7	922.4	7.8	5.3
    County in State (n = 26)	1.7	2.4	40.5	35.4	44.5	44.5	29.9	44.5	29.9	4.2	4.1
    Total (N = 133)	1.5	1.9	23.1	141.5	96.5	96.5	590.5	96.5	590.5	6.5	4.7
    **
    p < 0.01.
    3.2. RQ3
    Network analyses were conducted to reveal which local governments were more central in the Facebook network. Results showed that states, metros, districts in metros and cities in Seoul metropolitan area (cities in Gyeonggi provinces) were highly ranked in the network. Seoul (metro) had the highest degree (4381) and eigenvector centrality (0.272), followed by Gyeonggi Icheon-si (2nd, city in Seoul metropolitan area), Gyeonggi Goyang-si (3rd, city in Seoul metropolitan area), Gyeonggi Bucheon-si (4th, city in Seoul metropolitan area), Seo-gu in Daejeon (5th, district in metro), Joong-gu in Daegu (6th, district in metro), Jeonranam-do (7th, province) and Gwangju-si (8th, metro) (Table 3).
    Table 3. Centralities of Korean local governments’ Facebook pages.
    Types	Degree	N Degree	Eigenvector	N Eigenvector
    Seoul	Metro	4381	33.189	0.272	38.461
    Gyeonggi Icheon	City in State (Seoul-capital area)	3823	28.962	0.237	33.531
    Gyeonggi Goyang	City in State (Seoul-capital area)	3783	28.659	0.234	33.03
    Gyeonggi Bucheon	City in State (Seoul-capital area)	3548	26.879	0.198	28.039
    Daejeon Seo-gu	District in Metro	3536	26.788	0.18	25.46
    Daegu_Joong-gu	District in Metro	3432	26	0.197	27.888
    Jeonranam-do	Province	3316	25.121	0.175	24.785
    Gwangju	Metro	3259	24.689	0.195	27.538
    Gyeongnam Jinju	City in State	3137	23.765	0.172	24.332
    Gyeonggi-do	Province	3124	23.667	0.172	24.368
    Gyeonggi Euijeongbu	City in State (Seoul-capital area)	3117	23.614	0.156	22.036
    Seoul Yangcheon		3094	23.439	0.165	23.35
    Gyeonggi Suwon	City in State (Seoul-capital area)	3093	23.432	0.165	23.374
    Gyeonggi Pocheon	City in State (Seoul-capital area)	2989	22.644	0.188	26.535
    Gyeongbuk Pohang	City in State	2800	21.212	0.155	21.933
    The results of the network analysis are represented graphically in Fig. 1. The graph was constructed by plotting the first two dimensions from a multidimensional scaling of the network—such that the closer the local governments are to each other, the more similar their relationships are with other organizations.
    Fig. 1
    Download high-res image (1MB)Download full-size image
    Fig. 1. Network visualization of local Korean governments’ Facebook pages.
    3.3. RQ4
    Pearson correlations were computed to examine whether the extent of the centralities in the Facebook network were associated with the local governments and the level of Facebook utilization for tourism promotion and information, including local population, the financial independence rate (2013), the number of tourists (2013), and the extent of their Facebook interaction with users for tourism purposes.
    
    Centralities were positively and significantly correlated with population (degree centrality: r = 0.33, p < 0.01; eigenvector centrality: r = 0.34, p < 0.01), financial independence rate (degree centrality: r = 0.32, p < 0.01; eigenvector centrality: r = 0.33, p < 0.01), the number of “likes” on the page (degree centrality: r = 0.30, p < 0.01; eigenvector centrality: r = 0.33, p < 0.01), the number of “likes” on tourism-related posts (degree centrality: r = 0.41, p < 0.01; eigenvector centrality: r = 0.47, p < 0.01). The results showed that the number of Facebook fans was significantly correlated with the number of incoming tourists (r = 0.51, p < 0.01) and postings on tourism (r = 0.31, p < 0.01). The actual number of incoming tourists was positively and significantly associated with the number of total postings (r = 0.26, p < 0.01) and postings on tourism (r = 0.33, p < 0.01) (Tables 4).
    Table 4. Correlations.
    Degree centrality	Eigenvector centrality	Population	Finance	#Likes	#Tourist	#Tourism-postings	#Total-postings	#Likes on Tourism
    1	–	0.992**	0.331**	0.317**	0.295**	0.074	0.071	0.077	0.407**
    2		–	0.355**	0.325**	0.326**	0.074	0.083	0.078	0.469**
    3			–	0.412**	0.586**	0.575**	0.267**	0.185*	0.481**
    4				–	0.312**	0.032	0.136	0.413**	0.343**
    5					–	0.512**	0.310**	0.209*	0.743**
    6						–	0.331**	0.275**	0.191
    7							–	0.505**	0.158
    8								–	0.067
    *
    p < 0.05.
    **
    p < 0.01.
    Lastly, quadratic assignment procedure (QAP) correlations between two pairs of different networks were calculated by UCINET 6 to find similarities in relational patterns among the five networks of organizations linked with different levels of local government (County in province, city in province, district in metro, province and metro). The results indicated that all networks were significantly correlated with each other network of organizations. In particular, the network of organizations linked with cities in province was the most strongly related to that of organizations linked with districts in metro (r = 0.326), the network of organizations linked with counties in province was the less strongly related to that of organizations linked with metro (r = 0.091). Also, QAP results suggested that a governmental unit and its sub-governmental unit were interconnected with organizations in terms of tourism development, since the networks of both provinces and their cities (r = 0.276) and the networks of both metros and their districts (r = 0.252) were relatively highly correlated (Table 5).
    Table 5. QAP correlations.
    County in State	City in State	District in Metro	State	Metro
    1	–	0.175*	0.182*	0.119*	0.091*
    2		–	0.326*	0.276*	0.207*
    3			–	0.209*	0.252*
    4				–	0.124*
    *
    p < 0.05.
    
    ]]></section>
    
    <section name="Discussion" category="discussion"><![CDATA[
    4. Discussion
    ]]> <h target="1" match="full">This study investigated the utilization of Facebook by local governments for the purposes of tourism development.</h> <h target="2" match="full">The results indicated that most local Koran governments actively manage online tools, including Facebook, to communicate with the public and promote tourism. </h> <![CDATA[Based on our research, we can foresee that social media are likely to be further integrated into the ecosystem of smart tourism in Korea.
    
    ]]> <h target="4" match="full">Network analyses have been used to show how Korean local governments’ Facebook pages are co-related in the Facebook system as part of a smart tourism ecosystem.</h> <![CDATA[ Governmental uses of social media can provide a map of web-ecology, which refers to the interrelationships among relevant online sites. The results of this study indicate that metropolitan cities, their districts, and local cities in the Seoul-capital area were highly ranked in the network, which meant they had more co-“liked” organizations in the Facebook system. This suggests that they would utilize Facebook more actively and have a wider scope of governmental activities than the governments of counties and local cities in other areas. Further, the metropolitan cities’ and provinces’ Facebook pages had more Facebook fans, more updated tourism-related information, and more user responses to tourism postings. The analysis also showed that more central governments, with regard to the Facebook co-“liked” network, have more “likes” on both policy- and tourism-related postings and responded more interactively with their public.
    
    This study suggests that the use of SNSs by local governments not only benefits local residents but is also beneficial to potential tourists who live outside the area, as the local governments’ web-based promotion of tourism has been identified as an important factor in successful tourism development. The involvement of local governments in tourism promotion has been specifically significant for current cultural tourism efforts. Compared to tourism products that rely on the natural or physical environment, cultural tourism requires more contextual information and sensitivity when promoted to tourists unfamiliar with the cultural background of a given area. In order to promote these local tourism opportunities, local governments should operate tourism websites and SNSs with the expectation that tourists seek out information about their potential destinations. Compared to other advertising media such as television or newspapers SNSs are relatively inexpensive and are among the most efficient promotion tools for regional tourism. In addition, through SNSs governments can showcase and store a large amount of information while also retrieving web-ecology data consisting of interconnected users’ informational behaviors on SNSs.
    
    Finally, it is suggested that the ecosystem built by smart tourism will be of benefit not only to the tourism industry but also to other sectors at the national level. The significance of smart tourism achieved via social media suggests that broadband telecommunication infrastructure is a prerequisite for the ecosystem of smart tourism. In recognition of the role of ICT infrastructure in building an outstanding system of tourism information services, many local governments have made financial commitments to enhance Wi-Fi, mobile, and Internet access in their regions. Since 2008, British Columbia, for instance, has invested $6.83 million to build a province-wide infrastructure that brings high-speed Internet services to more than 210 new locales so that travelers (and residents) are provided with up-to-date, accurate information. The successful integration of ICT into the tourism sector will enable more accessibility, visibility of information, availability of products, and tourist satisfaction (Bethapudi, 2013). In addition, it is intriguing to note that social media can become a useful vehicle through which to generate big data to be used for tourism research and policy implementation. As an example, Haeundae (a district in Korea’s Busan Metropolitan City) has organized a “big data analysis team” whose research outcomes contribute to tangible tourism strategies and policies. The team conducted a keyword analysis of 38,500 tweets; blogs; and other social media postings during a five-month period and discovered several factors leading to tourist dissatisfaction (e.g.; heavy traffic and complicated bus routes). This type of data about tourists’ actual experiences gathered via social media can help local districts improve tourist services and develop tourism products. Likewise; Jeju City invested approximately $300,000 to construct a big data-based tourism service platform that offers interactive services to visitors; tourism agencies; and other tourism businesses. When completed; the platform will provide visitors with real-time information about the operation hours of tourist destinations; admission fees; the number of tourists in a specific location; how to get to the location; and local weather forecasts via social media.
    The main contribution of this study is that it presents a broad picture of the recent use of SNSs in Korea by local governments for the purposes of tourism development. Nevertheless, we acknowledge that this study has limitations, the biggest of which is that it is a specific study that focuses only on one SNS, Facebook. Therefore, we invite further empirical investigation, including the use of larger datasets from other SNSs, more sophisticated variables, and international studies. Second, there could be a problem of correlation and dependence in observed statistical data and network variables, although this study used network data from whole relationships among all of Korean local governments’ Facebook pages rather than from those among samples. In addition, in-depth interviews with public servants in local government settings could contribute to a better understanding of social media uses for tourism development. Thus, future research may provide more accurate insights by combining content analysis with a larger sample set and with in-depth interviews with practitioners.
    ]]></section>
</publication>