<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="gai shuangshuang">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 3, June 2016, Pages 360-373</time>
International Journal of Information Management
    <title>Predicting positive user responses to social media advertising: The roles of emotional appeal, informativeness, and creativity</title>
    <author>Jieun Lee.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspace<author>Ilyoo B. Hong.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspace
College of Business and Economics, Chung-Ang University, Republic of Korea
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.01.001</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">Informativeness and advertising creativity were the key drivers of favorable behavioral responses to an SNS ad.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">Perceived herd behavior had an indirect impact on intention to express empathy.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">Privacy concerns negatively influenced user intention to express empathy for an SNS ad.</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">Attitude and subjective norm were positively related to user intention to express empathy for the given SNS ad.</highlight>
    <highlight id="5">Intention to express empathy positively influenced purchase intention.</highlight>

<abstract><![CDATA[
Abstract
As social network services become more pervasive, social media advertising emerges as an attractive vehicle for augmenting advertising effectiveness. To leverage this new means of marketing, one must understand what engages SNS users in a favorable online behavior (i.e., overtly indicating personal interest in, or support for, the exposed message by clicking the Like or Share button in Facebook), thereby resulting in an effective advertising campaign. This research conceptualizes SNS ad effectiveness as a concept encompassing emotional appeal, informativeness and creativity that all have a potential to contribute to a positive online behavior. It empirically investigates the antecedents of positive user behavior for a SNS ad based on the theory of reasoned action, the social influence theory, and a persuasion theory. It proposes and tests a conceptual model of the formation of online user’s behavioral responses with regards to SNS advertising. ]]> <h target="1" match="full">The results of our empirical tests of the model reveal that informativeness and advertising creativity were key drivers of favorable behavioral responses to an SNS ad and that intention to engage in favorable user responses was positively associated with purchase intention.</h> <![CDATA[ Based on these findings, the paper suggests further research directions and offers implications for harnessing the full potential of the new SNS advertising platform.
]]></abstract>
    
    <keywords>Social media advertising</keywords>
    <keywords>Social networking site</keywords>
    <keywords>Empathy</keywords>
    <keywords>Social influence</keywords>
    <keywords>Viral behavior</keywords>
    
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction"><![CDATA[
1. Introduction
In recent years, the increasingly widespread use of social networking sites (SNS) has gradually shifted the advertisement platform used by business firms from traditional media to social media. Strong growth in mobile advertising is expected to increase the use of digital ads, which represented up to 30% of all U.S. ad spending in 2014 (eMarketer.com, 2014). Social media marketing enables word-of-mouth (WOM) advertising campaigns, inducing brand awareness and increasing sales revenue (Godes & Mayzlin, 2009; Kumar & Mirchandani, 2012), and also promotes a firm’s relationships with prospects, which makes it easy to accurately target consumers. Social media marketing has thus attracted much attention from businesses seeking to generate increased consumption of their commercial offerings (Wikipedia.org, 2015b).
One challenge facing marketing professionals considering campaigns on SNS is ensuring that the social network ad in question serves its goals effectively. Many marketing professionals find it difficult to measure the effectiveness of social media campaigns because tracking their outcomes is hard. However, the extent to which a social media advertisement is producing the intended benefits can be gauged by examining the interactions (e.g., the number of “Likes” or “Shares”) among social network users to assess their perceptions of the ad (Burg, 2013). The bottom line is that in order for a SNS ad to be considered effective, it should be able to lead a user to favorably respond to the ad (e.g., publicly expressing his/her support for the ideas conveyed by, or for the mood generated by, the ad). User’s positive responses on a social network are likely to help spread the advertisement message among the users, contributing to the increased awareness of the featured brand. According to a related research report (Gustin, 2012; Lipsman, Aquino, & Kemp, 2012), not only ‘exposed fans’ but also ‘friends of fans’ were found to spend more after viewing ads on Facebook. Presumably, ads that can induce positive perceptions and responses among social network users would likely create the WOM effect, and thus result in greater sales yielding high return on investment in SNS ad campaigns.
In this regard, present research has been motivated by two research questions (RQ): what are the qualities of a SNS ad that help produce positive user responses (RQ1), and is positive user behavior with regards to a SNS ad a predictor of positive purchase behavior (RQ2)? Extant research has not systematically addressed these issues. Research identifying desirable qualities of a SNS ad will provide useful implications for producing positive user responses, and hence intended business benefits of the ad. A few studies (Ducoffe, 1996; Gao & Koufaris, 2006; Logan, Bright, & Grngadharbatla, 2012; Taylor, Lewin, & Strutton, 2011) have examined the predictors of user attitudes to SNS advertising, but they offer little assistance in predicting attitudes to the positive user responses that help improve the brand awareness on a social network. It is imperative to understand what drives users’ favorable online behavior (e.g., clicking the Like or Share button for a SNS ad) if a firm is to increase the potential effectiveness of an ad campaign. In this research, we use the term ‘positive user behavior’ to refer to a user’s behavioral responses associated with disclosing and spreading the user’s personal interest in, and/or support for, a SNS ad.
The main purpose of this paper is to identify the antecedents of the behavioral intention to engage in positive user behavior for an SNS advertisement and propose a conceptual model of how positive user responses to an advertisement are formed on a SNS. The conceptual model is built around the theory of reasoned action, the social influence theory, and a persuasion theory. We thus gain insight into the predictors of viral behavioral intention with respect to SNS advertisement and the impact of these predictors (e.g., attitude, subjective norm, herd behavior, privacy concerns, etc.) on consumers’ behavioral responses including purchase intention. Predictors believed to play a sizable role in forming users’ behavioral responses will be drawn from the related literature. The findings of this research will offer useful implications for firms seeking a favorable return on investments from their SNS campaigns.

The rest of the paper is organized as follows. First, we review the related literature to gain a basic understanding of underlying concepts that will be used to construct a theoretical model and hypotheses. The literature on empathy expression, advertising effectiveness, social influences, and privacy concerns would provide insights into potential antecedents to the viral behavioral intention. Next, we introduce the data collection method, sample, and measures used to test the model. Then, we present the results and discuss the key findings of the study. Finally, we provide implications as well as limitations and future research directions.

]]></section>

    <section name="Theoretical background and hypotheses" category="background"><![CDATA[
2. Theoretical background and hypotheses
One theoretical backbone that underlies the present research is the theory of reasoned action (Fishbein & Ajzen, 1975). The theory of reasoned action (TRA) posits that an individual's behavior is conceptualized as a consequence of the behavioral intention that is affected by both the individual's attitude concerning the behavior and the subjective norm concerning it (Fishbein & Ajzen, 1975). Over the last decade, numerous studies have modeled user behavior on SNS based on the TRA. However, these studies have focused on either SNS use (Kwon & Wen, 2010; Pelling & White, 2009; Sledgianowski & Kulviwat, 2008) or continued SNS use (Choi, 2013) with little attention paid to user behavior concerning SNS ads. In our research, we use the TRA to model the user’s online behavior associated with a SNS ad. The TRA provides a powerful model to predict consumer’s volitional behavior and intentions based on salient information and beliefs about the likelihood that performing a particular behavior will lead to a specific outcome (Madden, Ellen, & Ajzen, 1992). And user’s online behavior including revealing personal reaction to a SNS ad is regarded as a type of volitional behavior that can be adequately modeled and predicted using information and beliefs about the use of a SNS. Specifically, a positive user response to a SNS ad is viewed as a behavioral outcome jointly formed by the user’s attitude toward the user response and the subjective norm about that user response. It is presumed further that the user's attitude is determined by beliefs a consumer may have as to the effectiveness of a SNS ad, such as emotional appeal.
Meanwhile, user behavior associated with SNS ads may also be explained from the perspective of the social influence theory. SNS advertising differs from conventional advertising in the way the advertising content spreads among the individuals whom the ad is targeted at. Electronic word of mouth (eWOM) enabled by a SNS accelerates the dissemination of the advertising message over a social network. Interpersonal influence that exists in a SNS serves as a driving force for users’ engagement in eWOM so that SNS users’ online dissemination behavior including opinion giving, opinion seeking and pass-along responses tend to be driven by the acts of peer users (Chu, 2009). While the TRA includes a social influence construct called subjective norm that denotes an individual’s perception of the pressure to conform to the expectations of important others, the theory is not extensive enough to incorporate the bandwagon effect that refers to the tendency that the probability of individual adoption increasing with respect to the proportion who have already done so (Colman, 2014; p. 77). It is important that both dimensions be taken into consideration to assess the social influence.
In summary, the TRA and the social influence theory represent two prime theories used in this research to predict the user’s positive responses to a SNS ad. The theoretical framework underpinning the present research encompasses both internal and external drivers of the behavioral intention to express empathy (e.g., to click the Like or Share button) with regards to a SNS ad. Internal drivers are a user’s own evaluations of the outcome of a given behavior, while external drivers are the user’s perceptions of other people’s behavior or evaluations such as social pressures inducing the user to perform that behavior. The TRA provides both an internal driver (i.e., attitude) and an external driver (i.e., subjective norms). However, the external driver incorporated into the TRA is not comprehensive in that it only includes normative social pressure without paying attention to informational social pressure. Thus, we combined the TRA with the social influence theory so as to include both informational and normative social influences. The resulting research model now incorporates relevant internal and external drivers that are likely to influence the intention about empathy expression.

In addition to the two theories mentioned above, this research employs a theory of persuasion called elaboration likelihood model (ELM) to illuminate the influence of emotion on attitude change. Petty and Cacioppo (1986) view persuasion as a process in which the success of influence depends chiefly on the way the receiver makes sense of the message. They state that ELM introduces two distinct pathways that one can use when trying to persuade others. Central route is associated with cognitive processing of the message content, while peripheral route relies more on peripheral cues (e.g., speech tones, credibility of the persuader, etc.) for a short cut than on the content itself. The ELM theorizes that peripheral messages appealing to a given peripheral cue can enable powerful influence especially when message receivers are either uninterested in, or unable to process, the content (Petty & Cacioppo, 1986). Given peripheral route processing, emotional appeals may make a positive impact. Thus, the ELM will provide a theoretical guideline in hypothesizing the relationship between emotional appeal and attitude toward empathy expression.
Given the aforementioned research aim, it was imperative that we identify key constructs that play a role in leading to a positive user evaluation of the empathy expression behavior. A review of the literature resulted in the research model shown in Fig. 1, which outlines the antecedents and their impact on behavioral intention to express empathy about the given ad. Hypotheses H1, H6, H7 and H9 involve the relationships between the behavioral intention to express empathy and its antecedents. As the TRA posits, the behavioral intention is influenced by attitude and subjective norm. The model incorporates the positive impact of social influences (i.e., perceived herd behavior and subjective norm) as well as the negative impact of privacy concerns on the behavioral intention. Perceived herd behavior, a construct of informational social influence, denotes the tendency for individuals to mimic the actions, whether rational or irrational, of a larger group. And privacy concerns refers to an individual’s concerns over the possible exposure of private information. As hypotheses H6, H7 and H8 depict, perceived herd behavior is likely to both directly and indirectly affect intention to express empathy; note that subjective norm plays the mediating role between perceived herd behavior and intention to express empathy. Next, the three hypotheses including H3 through H5 encompass relationships between attitude and the related attitudinal beliefs. Relating these hypotheses to the research questions presented earlier, hypotheses H1 and H3 through H8 will help address the RQ1, whereas hypothesis H2 is expected to find an answer to RQ2. In the following subsections, we will present the individual hypotheses.
Structural model
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Structural model.
2.1. Behavioral intention to express empathy
2.1.1. The empathy expression concept
It would be worthwhile to first introduce the concept of empathy expression. SNS users who have been exposed to an ad generally go through an evaluative phase where a user develops an affective evaluation response (for example, good, bad, angry, sad, etc). And most SNS including Facebook and Twitter provide an affective evaluation mechanism, known as ‘one-click social plugins’, whereby the user can express his or her affective response in the form of positive evaluation (e.g., like) or negative evaluation (e.g., dislike). One-click social plugins (e.g. Like, Google +1, Retweet, and Share) are buttons placed on social media or other sites through which users can share their interest or convey their attitude about various content (Swani, Milne, & Brown, 2013). In case of Facebook, the affective response can be expressed only as positive evaluation (i.e., like), and thus, no expression will be regarded as either negative or neutral evaluation of the given ad. The positive affective evaluation is, in nature, virtual empathy that a user has about the ad message (Rosen, 2012). Empathy is generated from the perspectives of a user when he or she merges with others’ feelings involuntarily (Escalas & Stern, 2003). Psychologists conceptualize empathy as “an emotional response that stems from another’s emotional state or condition and that is congruent with the other’s emotional state or situation” (Escalas & Stern, 2003; p. 567). Empathy in a social network context captures empathic reactions that a user develops to a SNS ad. Hence, for our research, empathy is defined as the user’s ability to sense and understand the emotions, moods, and temperaments of others with regards to an ad that has been exposed on a social network, coupled with the ability to imagine what others might be thinking or feeling about that ad. Once the empathy is experienced on an online social network, it is expressed via a social plug-in. A Facebook Like is an example of empathy expression; by clicking the Like button, users show that they understand and share in the emotional state or context of the user who posted the message (Rosen, 2012). Users presented with an appealing advertisement on a SNS are likely to be driven by a social need to share in the emotional state of the users who have already clicked the Like button. Thus, a Facebook user who has positive affective evaluation of a SNS ad may choose to explicitly reveal his or her own empathy by clicking on Like.
2.1.2. Attitude toward empathy expression vs. attitude toward advertising
In this research we took a unique approach by adopting as a construct the attitude toward empathy expression associated with an ad, rather than the attitude toward advertising that is commonly examined by most related studies. The advertising literature defines attitude toward advertising (AAD) as “a predisposition to respond in a favorable or unfavorable manner to a particular advertising stimulus during a particular exposure occasion” (Lutz, 1985). So the AAD concept specifically addresses the evaluations of a given ad.
On the other hand, attitude toward empathy expression (AEE) is conceptually rooted on AAD, but the concept is tied to a SNS context. On a SNS, a user exposed to an ad will first evaluate the given ad (e.g., “It is an interesting ad”), and then evaluate the empathy expression behavior with regards to the ad (e.g., “It is worth clicking the Like or Share button”). The SNS user’s viral behavior will be directly contingent upon the nature of the ad. That is, determinants of evaluative perceptions of his empathy expression behavior are largely determinants of evaluative perceptions of the ad. For example, if a user perceives that an ad exposed to him is out of ordinary and heart-touching, then no doubt he is likely to click “Like” or “Share” on a social network so that his acquaintances will be informed of his view of the ad.

It incorporates a SNS user’s attitude toward the viral behavior (i.e., the behavior of overtly indicating and spreading his or her personal reaction to a given ad). As Alhabash and McAlister (2014) note, online content on a social network like Facebook or Twitter becomes viral as it is communicated and disseminated in a digital form creating the WOM effect. Thus, for our research we define AEE as “a user’s evaluations of the behavior of disclosing and spreading his or her positive reactions to a SNS ad.” In this regard, AEE can influence the effectiveness of an advertising campaign, since the WOM advertising success is dependent on users’ AEE and viral behavior.
As we can see in Table 2, this construct measures a user’s overall attitude about both the SNS advertisement and the behavior of empathy expression with regards to that ad. Since one-click social plugin (e.g., the Like button) available on a SNS encourages more frequent WOM behavior (Swani et al., 2013), SNS users would be generally inclined to express their affective evaluation of the SNS ad to their social network acquaintances, contributing to the brand awareness. Thus, the attitude toward empathy expression would be a more appropriate construct to examine for our research than the attitude toward advertising.
Table 2. Measures for the research model.
Construct	Definition	Measure items	Sources
Emotional appeal	The extent to which emotional responses are triggered when exposed to a SNS ad	—After seeing this ad, I had intense feelings
—I was emotionally attracted by the key message of this ad
—The emotional aspect of this ad leads me to like the ad	Davis (1983);
Escalas and Stern (2003)

Informativeness	The degree to which a SNS ad offers information users perceive as useful	—Information obtained from the SNS ad would be useful
—I would learn a lot from using the SNS ad
—I think the information obtained from the SNS ad would be helpful	Logan et al. (2012);
Pavlou et al. (2007)

Advertising creativity	The extent to which an SNS ad is original and unexpected	—The SNS ad is unique
—The SNS ad is really out of ordinary
—The SNS ad is intriguing
—The SNS ad is surprising	Haberland and Dacin (1992)

Privacy concerns	Perceived negative consequences that may result from disclosing personal information to others on a SNS	—I am concerned that my online usage behavior might be known to others while I use the Internet
—I am concerned that my Facebook usage details might be known to other Facebook users
—I am concerned that my acquaintances might learn about my liking the SNS ad	Buchanan et al. (2007)

Perceived herd behavior	Perceived social pressure to conform to the behaviors of others as a consequence of exposure to their online behaviors on a SNS	—My decision to click “Like” for this ad is likely to be influenced by the number of “Likes” for this ad
—If I find that many of my Facebook acquaintances “Liked” this ad, then I would be more willing to click “Like” for this ad
—The more “Likes” this ad attracts, the more preferable it is to click “Like” for this ad
—It is wise to adopt the choice of other Facebook users when deciding whether to click the “Like” for this ad	Huang and Chen (2006);
Yoo et al. (2008)

Subjective norm	Perceived social pressure to comply with a behavior expected of a user by important referents	—My Facebook acquaintances would find it reasonable for me to click “Like” for this ad
—My Facebook acquaintances would find it necessary for me to click “Like” for this ad
—My Facebook acquaintances would find it worthwhile for me to click “Like” for this ad
—My Facebook acquaintances would expect me to click “Like” for this ad.	Ajzen and Fishbein (1980)

Attitude toward empathy expression	Predisposition to respond in a favorable or unfavorable manner about clicking Like for a SNS ad	—I feel good about clicking “Like” for this ad
—I feel positive about clicking “Like” for this ad
—I feel favorable about clicking “Like” for this sort of ad
—My overall attitude toward this ad is positive	Holbrook and Batra (1987)

Intention to express empathy	Perceived likelihood that a user will engage in the behavior of clicking Like for a SNS ad	—I find it wise to click “Like” for this ad
—I am inclined to click “Like” for this ad	Alhabash et al. (2013);
Eckler and Bolls (2011)

Purchase intention	Perceived likelihood that a user will buy a given service in the near future	—I might purchase this service
—It is worth purchasing this service	MacKenzie, Lutz, & Belch (1986)
2.1.3. How attitude relates to intention about empathy expression
There exists little research delving into the relationship between attitude and intention in the context of empathy expression. The TRA theory postulates that the intention to perform a behavior is determined by the attitude to performing it as well as subjective norm (Fishbein & Ajzen, 1975). Attitude refers to the degree to which a person has a favorable or unfavorable evaluation or appraisal of the behavior in question (Ajzen, 1991). Behavioral intention is the cognitive representation of a person’s readiness to perform the behavior.
With our research, the behavior under consideration is a user’s expression of empathy about an SNS ad. Hence, intention to express empathy is defined as a user’s cognitive representation of his readiness to express empathy about a given SNS ad. Provided that a user has a positive disposition about the behavior of empathy expression, he or she is likely to develop a strong intention toward that behavior. In their study on Facebook users' motivation for the Like-clicking behavior, Chin and Lu (2015) found that there was a significant positive relationship between attitude and intention under consideration. The formation of the user’s positive attitude may reply on his or her values or beliefs that a solid view or opinion that he or she comes up with about a matter of concern should be communicated to or exchanged with others. If he strongly feels that it is desirable to show support for an interesting ad by clicking Like, then with no doubt he is likely to have an inclination to click it without hesitation so that his reaction may be shared with his acquaintances. Likewise, it can be posited that an individual experiencing intense empathy will have a favorable attitude toward the expression of empathy and be highly inclined to express empathy by clicking Like for the SNS ad too. Accordingly, the following hypothesis is proposed:
H1

Attitude toward empathy expression is positively related to the intention to express empathy.


Before examining how intention to express empathy is related to purchase intention, it would be worthwhile to understand how the number of likes is related to sales amount. The relationship between Facebook Likes and sales is controversial. While Facebook-based marketers claim that the more Likes a Facebook ad is given, the greater sales the ad is likely to generate, some say that there are many companies today offering to sell ‘cheap fans’ and therefore the number of likes may not reflect the true purchase intention of potential buyers (Rubin, 2012). Nevertheless, a single click on a Facebook Like for a daily deal was associated with 4.5 additional voucher sales, equivalent to an increase in revenue of $468 (Li & Wu, 2013) and one click to Like is estimated to create at least $8 in revenues (Chompon.com, 2011). Thus, a positive relationship can be established between the number of Likes and sales volume.
Then would intention to click Like as an empathic reaction to a SNS ad lead to intention to buy? In their empirical study on a company-hosted Facebook community, Pöyry, Parvinen, and Malmivaara (2013) found that both browsing and contribution by community members were positively related to intentions to purchase a community product. Their finding implies that active user behaviors on Facebook ad pages can translate into purchase intention. Liking captures the user’s affective reaction to a page (Gerlitz & Helmond, 2011). When a user is inclined to click the Like for an ad after experiencing a positive empathic reaction to the ad, the user’s Like is likely to represent personal support for the ideas or theme embedded in the ad. Thus, the user will now have an elevated interest in the product or service featured in the SNS ad. And when the time comes to make a purchase, the user is more likely to choose that brand than others. Therefore, the intention to purchase a product or service featured in an SNS ad may be a consequence of positive user responses on a social network (e.g., intention to engage in positive affective evaluation of an SNS ad). Almost 25% of consumers participating in one survey replied that they had intention to purchase the brand that their friends liked (eMarketer.com, 2012). If a user learns that his or her friends liked a SNS ad, he or she will be motivated to click the Like button, thereby increasing the user’s intention to purchase that brand. Thus, persuading consumers to like would be a useful strategy for marketers who try to augment advertising effectiveness. Based on these theoretical grounds, we propose the following hypothesis:
H2

Intention to express empathy is positively related to purchase intention.


2.2. Advertising effectiveness
Research on advertising effectiveness highlights advertising creativity (Reinartz & Saffert, 2013), informativeness and entertainment (Ducoffe, 1996; Gao & Koufaris, 2006), irritation (Logan et al., 2012), and social cues (Liu, 2014) as antecedents of consumer attitudes to an advertisement. A review of the related literature indicates that informativeness and entertainment as well as advertising creativity are recognized as key sources of advertising effectiveness (Ducoffe, 1996; Taylor et al., 2011). While these related studies are designed to determine antecedents of attitude toward advertising, our research focuses on identifying antecedents of attitude toward empathy expression. As we mentioned earlier, attitude toward empathy expression is a construct newly created specifically for the SNS setting. Since the construct is based on the attitude toward advertising concept, it would make logical sense to choose among the antecedents of attitude toward advertising. At the same time, it would be necessary to take into considerations potential determinants of a SNS user’s attitude toward the viral behavior (i.e., empathy expression) with regards to the ad.
We argue that both informativeness and advertising creativity often emphasized in the advertising literature importantly affect the user’s behavior in a SNS environment.  SNS users are more interested in advertising that has informative value and creative content (Reinartz & Saffert, 2013; Taylor et al., 2011). On the other hand, while the existing studies emphasize entertainment as a key determinant of attitude toward advertising, users on a SNS react more favorably to a persuasive message or other online content if it has greater emotional appeal (Alhabash, McAlister, Quillam, Rifon, & Richards, 2013). Thus, the present research argues that SNS advertising effectiveness should be evaluated via emotional appeal instead of entertainment; emotional appeal is an integrative concept inclusive of entertainment, as it encompasses a wide range of emotions including fun. Therefore, we determine that the constructs relevant to our research questions are emotional appeal, informativeness, and advertising creativity, which are believed to play key roles in the formation of behavioral responses to SNS advertising (please see Section 3.2 for the procedure used to derive these dimensions).
2.2.1. Emotional appeal and attitude
Emotional appeal is a method of persuasion designed to create an emotional response to a message by using emotional content (e.g., horror movie, sad story, triumphant music, etc.). As the ELM predicts, emotional appeals will more effectively persuade an individual who has little motivation or little ability to cognitively process a message (Petty & Cacioppo, 1986). Emotional appeal deals with the ways in which emotional responses are triggered as a function of the message’s motivational relevance to individuals (Alhabash et al., 2013). Emotion is a person’s state of feeling in the sense of an affect. Emotion can be either positive (e.g., love, joy) or negative (e.g., fear, anger, sadness). Related studies in the field of communication recognize emotion as a vital element that can importantly affect the effectiveness of a message (Xie, Donthu, Lohtia, & Osmonbekov, 2004). In their empirical study on social network WOM, Swani et al. (2013) found that emotional content in an advertising content generates more WOM; for example, their study revealed that a message containing emotional content generated 16 estimated mean Facebook Likes, whereas 8 estimated mean Likes were observed without emotional content. When a persuasive message is received, affective responses (i.e., feelings and moods evoked by the ad) are combined with cognitive responses (i.e., rational evaluation of the ad) to form the attitude toward the message (Batra & Ray, 1986). Messages with strong emotional appeals have been found to be more likely to be shared online (Alhabash et al., 2013). Thus, the related studies suggest that the stronger emotional appeals a SNS ad possesses, the more positive attitude a user is likely to develop toward the ad.
H3

Emotional appeal is positively related to attitude toward empathy expression.


2.2.2. Informativeness and attitude
Informativeness is defined as the “ability to inform users about product alternatives that enable them to make choices yielding the highest value” (Rotzoll, Haefner, & Sandage, 1990). Informativeness is a perceptual construct that is measured via self-reported items (Pavlou, Liang, & Xue, 2007). And it encompasses rational appeal due to its ability to help a consumer make an informed judgment about the acceptance of the message, and therefore is conceptually distinct from ‘emotional appeal.’ In their early study on information content in television advertising, Resnik and Bruce (1977) stated that an informative ad enables a consumer to make a more intelligent buying decision. Consumers will find an advertisement valuable, if it gives accurate portrayals of products (Andrews, 1989; Taylor et al., 2011). Studies have found informativeness to be important in the formation of consumer attitudes to electronic commerce websites (Gao & Koufaris, 2006) as well as to television advertising (Resnik & Bruce, 1977) and to SNS advertising (Taylor et al., 2011). Informative advertising messages on a SNS will draw users’ attention and motivate them to associate the ad with a positive image and at times to drive them to spread the messages to friends over the social network volitionally. Overall, the related literature agrees that informative SNS ads provide a user with the ability to make an informed judgment for a future purchase, and that the user’s perception of this favorable aspect of the ad leads to the formation of a positive attitude toward the viral behavior as well as toward the ad. Based on the above theoretical grounds, we propose the following hypothesis.
H4

Informativeness is positively related to attitude toward empathy expression.


2.2.3. Advertising creativity and attitude
Advertising creativity is the extent to which an ad is original and unexpected (Haberland & Dacin, 1992). Divergence and relevance are known to be the leading characteristics of advertising creativity; divergence is associated with elements that are novel, different or unusual, whereas relevance is concerned with elements that are meaningful, appropriate, useful, or valuable to the audience (Smith, MacKenzie, Yang, Buchholz, & Darley, 2007). Creative messages grab more attention and lead to positive attitudes about the featured products (Reinartz & Saffert, 2013). Furthermore, a “euro invested in a highly creative ad campaign had, on average, nearly double the sales impact of a euro spent on a noncreative campaign” (Reinartz & Saffert, 2013, p. 5). In their experimental study, Smith et al. (2007) found that creative ads increase motivation to process the ad and improve the attitude toward the ad and that the positive affect transfers to the brand. Thus, advertising creativity is strongly linked to the effectiveness of an ad. On the above theoretical grounds, we propose the following hypothesis:
H5

Advertising creativity is positively related to attitude toward empathy expression.


2.3. Social influences
Research on social influence suggests that there are two psychological needs that lead humans to conform to the expectations of others: the need to be right (informational social influence) and the need to be liked (normative social influence) (Deutsch & Gerard, 1955). Informational social influence is “the influence to accept information obtained from another as evidence about the true state of some aspect of the individual’s environment,” whereas normative social influence is “the influence to conform to the expectations of another person or group” (Burnkrant & Cousineau, 1975; Deutsch & Gerard, 1955).
Social influence can affect an individual’s attitudes and behaviors. Kelman (1958) states that changes of attitudes produced by social influence may occur through three different processes including internalization, compliance, and identification. Internalization is the adoption of induced behavior because it is congruent with his value system and can help attain his goals. Compliance is a change in behavior but not necessarily attitude (e.g., obedient behavior). Finally, identification is the change of attitudes or behaviors due to the influence of someone respected or liked (e.g., a celebrity) (Kelman, 1958). In the buying context, these three processes are associated with the Deutsch and Gerard’s social influence types. Internalization would occur if a consumer determines that information from others (e.g., product reviews) helps achieve the cost reduction goal; hence the internationalization process will be involved when one accepts informational social influence. On the other hand, compliance and identification are applicable to the normative social influence situation. Compliance is likely to occur when an individual decides to behave according to the expectations of his acquaintances (i.e., his subjective norms). For example, a consumer may decide to adopt a mobile instant messaging system because his online acquaintances strongly expect him to. Meanwhile, identification would be involved when a consumer decides to purchase a bicycle featured in an ad depicting a renowned sports hero using the product. This consumer’s behavioral change can be described as a consequence of identifying himself with the sports hero appearing in that ad.
We shall show below how these two forms of social influence, informational and normative, are related to each other as well as to behavioral intention to express empathy on a social network.

2.3.1. Perceived herd behavior and intention to express empathy
Informational social influence refers to “the pressure to accept information from another as evidence of reality” (Deutsch & Gerard, 1955) and is commonly known as “informational cascades” or “herd behavior.” Informational influence operates through the process of internalization in which an individual takes information from others if it increases his or her knowledge needed to reduce uncertainty (Bearden, Netemeyer, & Teel, 1989; Kelman, 1958). The consumer behavior literature suggests that product evaluation is a typical setting in which informational social influence is likely to operate (Cohen & Golden, 1972). A product presentation would be internalized only if it is perceived as providing useful information about the product (Burnkrant & Cousineau, 1975). Thus, under uncertainty, consumers observe the actions of others and then follow their behavior without regard to their own information. In this research, we define perceived herd behavior as the perceived social pressure to conform to the behaviors of others as a result of exposure to their online behaviors.
Users exposed to a social network ad who find that many people have liked it are likely to click the Like button just to “hop on the bandwagon.” The social psychology literature defines the bandwagon effect as the social phenomenon whereby the rate of uptake of beliefs, ideas, fads and trends increases the more that they have already been adopted by others (Colman, 2014). When a SNS user observes that the behavior of expressing empathy about a message presented on a SNS like Facebook has become pervasive, he or she will be inclined to be part of this fad. In particular, the numbers of Likes and Shares are signals to viewers about the quality of the message and whether it is worth viewing (Alhabash et al., 2013). Thus, the stronger social pressure the user perceives to accept the widespread Like-clicking behavior of others on a social network, the more intense the intention to express empathy. Based on the above logical grounds, we propose the following hypothesis.
H6

Perceived herd behavior is positively related to intention to express empathy.


2.3.2. Subjective norm and intention to express empathy
Meanwhile, normative influence can affect an individual’s attitudes, norms, and values (Burnkrant & Cousineau, 1975). According to Bearden et al. (1989), normative social influence is divided into value expressive and utilitarian influences, depending on which of Kelman’s processes of attitude change it is related to. Value expressive influence is motivated by a desire to enhance self-image by association with a referent like a sports hero; hence, it operates through referent identification (Bearden et al., 1989; Kelman, 1958). On the other hand, utilitarian influence is manifested in an individual’s need to comply with the expectations of others to achieve rewards or avoid punishments (Burnkrant & Cousineau, 1975; Kelman, 1958).
Normative influence has been frequently studied as the “subjective norm” within the general framework of the TRA (Fishbein & Ajzen, 1975). Subjective norm is the perception or opinion about what important others believe an individual should do (Ajzen & Fishbein, 1980). Therefore, from the perspective of Kelman’s theoretical framework, subjective norm would likely accompany the compliance process, and it reflects utilitarian influence.
Related studies on technology acceptance have found that subjective norm plays an important role when a user decides on the acceptance of a new information system; for example, it positively affects the behavioral intention to adopt B2C e-commerce (Crespo & Bosque, 2008) or instant messaging (Lu, Zhou, & Wang, 2009). Likewise, subjective norm is expected to play an even larger role in determining the intention to use a SNS, another form of information system, since a user’s online usage behavior including posting a comment or clicking the “Like” or “Share” button tends to be quite transparent to other users on the social network. In particular, the reward that motivates the user to comply with the expectations of these acquaintances is often the maintenance of a favorable relationship with a referent group. Hence, a user who learns that many acquaintances have already clicked the Like button for a given Facebook ad will perceive intense pressure to click “Like” for the ad as well, and comply with the expectation to become part of the referent group who clicked “Like” for the ad. Based on this line of reasoning, we propose the following hypothesis:
H7
Subjective norm concerning empathy expression is positively related to intention to express empathy.


2.3.3. Perceived herd behavior and subjective norm
Cohen and Golden (1972) argued that both informational and normative influences in a product evaluation situation are present under the following two conditions: (a) quality is somewhat ambiguous because of a lack of clear standards, and (b) one’s own ability to discriminate is not thought satisfactory. Thus, perceived herd behavior and subjective norm can both play a role in shaping a user’s online behavior.
Perceived herd behavior conceptualized as informational influence operates through internalization where the chief motivation is to obtain knowledge from a credible source and reduce uncertainty. A lack of information, an ambiguous situation, or premature demands for action or decision lead the person to substitute seemingly competent information from others for his own search for direct evidence (Cohen & Golden, 1972). When a user is first exposed to a SNS ad, he or she would be unsure as to what is the most appropriate behavioral response to the ad on a social network. To resolve the uncertainty, the user would observe the statistics—e.g., how many Likes or Shares there are. If the user found high figures, the user would likely perceive strong herd behavior and no doubt click Like or Share to imitate the behavior of the referent group.
Whereas perceived herd behavior is based on a basic, low-level motivation (i.e., reducing uncertainty and attain an individual’s goal), subjective norm is associated with an advanced, high-level motivation (that is, maintaining a favorable relationship with a referent person). One will likely choose to accept influence either to establish or enhance a favorable reward-punishment relationship with a certain individual or because of a desire to identify with such an individual (Cohen & Golden, 1972; Kelman, 1958). If a user perceives that herd behavior occurs intensely, the user is quite likely to comply with expectations of his online friends. In their study on virtual communities, Bagozzi and Dholakia (2002) found that the attitude and behavior of a community member were apparently influenced by referent groups within the community. SNS messages are disseminated among a larger number of “friends” on a social network much faster than on an offline network. Thus, the WOM process will be facilitated.
In sum, the basic need to jump on the bandwagon to reduce uncertainty and achieve a user’s personal goal is likely to trigger the advanced need to comply with the norms established by the referent group. Thus, a user who has accepted influence of herd behavior associated with expression of empathy will likely accept influence of subjective norm as well. Based on the above grounds, we propose the following hypothesis.
H8

Perceived herd behavior is positively related to subjective norm concerning empathy expression.


Issues of privacy on a SNS are becoming an increasing concern. Some studies have reported that concern about privacy was the main reason why some SNS users closed their SNS accounts (Stieger, Burger, Bohn, & Voracek, 2013). Privacy concern was found to have a negative impact on self-disclosure, meaning that the higher the users’ concern for privacy, the less information the user will disclose on SNSs (Zlatolas, Welzer, Hericko, & Hölbl, 2015). Furthermore, SNS users’ private information accumulated on the server in the course of system use (including conversations, profiles, affective evaluations, and so forth) are illegally collected and used for unintended purposes such as surveillance or monitoring. For example, some employers use SNS to gather negative information about job candidates that may be subsequently used to reject a candidate (Bowers, 2008). Our social media “audience” is bigger than we actually know; our followers or friends are not the only ones that can see information about us (Wikipedia.org, 2015a). For that reason, those concerned about the possibility that others might learn about their ad likes and infer their character, values or preferences from them are likely to refrain from clicking the Like button. Furthermore, existing research has found that privacy concerns are negatively related to attitude to SNS advertising (Taylor et al., 2011). Therefore, we hypothesize the following:
H9

Privacy concern is negatively related to intention to express empathy.

]]></section>

    <section name="Research method" category="methods"><![CDATA[
3. Research method
3.1. Data collection and sample
An online survey was conducted using the Google Forms tool to collect data for empirical analysis. Our research employs a self-reported data collection method based on experimental design. An experimental design is designed to collect data by applying a treatment (or a stimulus) and observing the response. In our research, a Facebook ad page has been presented to the experiment participants as a treatment, and a questionnaire has been used to capture the perceptions of our participants after they had been exposed to the Facebook ad page.

A total of 420 undergraduate students at a major university in Korea, took part in this survey for course credit. The survey lasted for the period of one week, and an additional week was given to induce the non-respondents to participate. College students were deemed appropriate as participants because Facebook has become popular by solely catering to college students. The percentage of U.S. college-aged adults (i.e., aged 18–24) who use Facebook constituted 92.4% in October 2014 (McDermott, 2014). Besides, a recent survey found that Facebook is the most popular SNS in Korea and that young adults (i.e., aged 18–34) represented 65% of all Korean Internet users in 2011 (Socialbakers, 2011). In this study, participants ranged from 20 to 30 years old (M = 23.86, SD = 2.03). Males comprised 63.6% of the respondents. The relatively high proportion of males is attributed to Korea’s corporate culture where business firms still hire more males than females. The Korean firms’ employment practice seems to have affected the gender composition of college students majoring in business administration. Five invalid responses were removed, leaving 415 responses for analysis. The respondents’ profile is shown in Table 1.
Table 1. Demographic profile of the sample.
Attribute	Value	Frequency	Percentage (%)
Gender	Female	151	36.4
Male	264	63.6

Age	20–23	185	44.6
24–26	184	44.3
27–30	46	11.1

Facebook membership in years	Less than 6 months	41	9.9
6 months to one year	14	3.4
One to two years	86	20.7
More than two years	274	66.0

Facebook usage frequency	Daily	237	57.1
Weekly	109	26.3
Less often	69	16.6

Average duration of Facebook use	Less than 30 min	308	74.2
30 min to one hour	74	17.8
More than one hour	33	8.0
The stimulus used for our experiment was a captured still image of a recent Facebook ad posted by a carpool service company named Tikle. Tikle is a Korean sharing-economy company founded in 2012 to concentrate on carpool brokering services based on internet. The participants were provided via e-mail with a link to a web-based page including this image and the online questionnaire. On this web page, they were instructed to answer the online questions based on the still image. The image included a message urging drivers to share vacant automobile seats and save gas expenses. The advertising copy reads “Try our carpool service for yourself. You can share vacant seats and save money. The number one carpool company, Tikle” (see Appendix A).
Unlike their Western counterparts, a majority of Korean college students tend to use public transportation like subway trains, buses or taxis for their routine trips, and hence rarely own an automobile. For that reason, they are increasingly interested in emerging carpool services that not only provide comfortable rides for affordable costs, but also help save fuel expenses. Thus, we determined that it was a suitable SNS ad for our study. In addition, this carpool ad has been chosen from a pool of existing ads on Korean Facebook website (http://ko-kr.facebook.com), based on its relatively high figures of “Likes” and “Shares”.
The stimulus chosen for this study is measurable in each of the dimensions of advertising effectiveness. First, the stimulus has a potential to generate a sense of guilt (i.e., a type of emotion) on the part of some respondents, while individuals may experience different emotions depending on their values and background. Many Korean cities have a severe traffic congestion issue while fuel prices are unusually high. The ad image portrays multiple drivers who each have no passenger in a car. The situation presented by the image is against the social norm that people should help save the limited energy resource. A respondent viewing the Facebook ad would likely have guilty feelings if he or she were in the driver’s place, since these solo occupants are not taking into considerations economic or environmental impact of their behavior. Based on the ELM theory, it may be inferred that users viewing this ad will take a peripheral, rather than central, route to processing the message such that the sense of guilt aroused by the ad will leave an intense impression about the ad. Second, the present stimulus is informative enough to provide useful information that would help a consumer make a right purchase decision. For example, it informs that the use of a carpool service can help save expensive fuel costs through a more efficient utilization of empty seats. Furthermore, it shows that carpool services can be used not only for daily commuting but also for special occasions such as weekend leisure trips, ski trips, etc. It also tells that Tikle is the leading player in the domestic market that attracts a large number of drivers who look for rides to lower their fuel expenses. Finally, the advertising stimulus chosen for this study is creative to some extent. It shows two contrasting situations in one still image: one where the road is packed with cars and the other where the road is occupied by the same number of drivers as the cars. Such an unusual image will likely bring to the viewer senses of uniqueness, unexpectedness and extraordinariness. In summary, because of the emotional, informative and creative aspects embedded in the ad image, this ad is likely to succeed in capturing some attention of those whom the ad is exposed to.

3.2. Measures
First, interviews were conducted using a focus group to gain insight into how users like Facebook advertising. A total of 17 college students who use Facebook regularly were chosen and assigned to the focus group. Questions were asked to learn what aspects of a SNS ad lead them to give a positive user response, such as clicking Like or Share on Facebook. Answers to the questions included impressiveness, eye-catching appeal, relevance, extra-ordinariness, heart-touching potential, among others. ]]> <h target="1" match="full">Then, based on the focus group interview results and the related literature, key factors likely to lead to the positive user response to a SNS ad were identified as emotional appeal, informativeness, and advertising creativity.</h><![CDATA[

Measurement items were mainly adapted from the related prior studies to fit the context of SNS advertising. Advertising effectiveness is comprised of three dimensions. First, emotional appeal refers to the extent to which emotional responses are triggered when exposed to a SNS ad, and the items are based on Davis (1983) and Escalas and Stern (2003). Davis (1983) proposed a multi-dimensional measure of empathy consisting of Perspective Taking (PT), Fantasy (FS), Empathic Concern (EC), and Personal Distress (PD). Of these four scales, EC and PD deal with emotional reactions, and EC is particularly relevant to our emotional appeal construct. Our emotional appeal scale is also rooted on the Ad Response Empathy (ARE) scale developed by Escalas and Stern (2003) to capture the empathic reaction to a television commercial. Second, informativeness denotes the degree to which a SNS ad offers information users perceive as useful, and the scale was adapted from Logan et al. (2012) and Pavlou et al. (2007). Finally, advertising creativity refers to the extent to which an SNS ad is original and unexpected, and the scale was adapted from Haberland and Dacin (1992). The privacy concerns construct (Buchanan, Paine, Joinson, & Reips, 2007) was measured using a scale customized to capture the aspects of privacy associated with a user’s sensitive information (e.g., political or ideological or social views) that may be revealed to others when they click the Like or Share button. The items used to measure perceived herd behavior were taken from previous research (Huang & Chen, 2006; Yoo, Kim, Moon, & Choe, 2008) and modified for this study. The scale for subjective norms was adapted from Ajzen and Fishbein (1980), and was used to measure perceived social pressure to comply with a behavior expected of a user by important referents. The scale for attitude toward empathy expression was modified from Holbrook and Batra (1987) to measure a predisposition to respond in a favorable or unfavorable manner about clicking Like for a SNS ad. Intention to express empathy refers to perceived likelihood that a user will engage in the behavior of clicking Like for a SNS ad. The scale to measure intention to express empathy was adapted from Alhabash et al. (2013) and Eckler and Bolls (2011). All items were measured on a five-point Likert-type scale, ranging from “strongly disagree” (1) to “strongly agree” (5). Table 2 lists the survey items used to measure the constructs and their operational definitions.

]]></section>

    <section name="Results" category="results"><![CDATA[
4. Results
4.1. Measurement model
We conducted a confirmatory factor analysis using AMOS 21.0 to test the measurement model. Goodness of fit was tested using six common model-fit measures, and all the indices indicated a good fit between the hypothesized model and the observed data (x2/df = 1.77, RMSEA = 0.043; NFI = 0.924; CFI = 0.965; TLI = 0.958; RMR = 0.050, SRMR = 0.043). The overall fit for the measurement model was acceptable according to conventional cutoff criteria (Kline, 2005).
The measurement model was assessed for reliability and validity. The reliability of the constructs was assessed using Cronbach’s alpha and composite reliability (CR) values. As shown in Table 3, the Cronbach’s alphas for the constructs were between 0.756 and 0.909 and the CR coefficients were above 0.716, all exceeding the 0.70 threshold proposed by Fornell and Larcker (1981). Therefore, the constructs used in this study represented acceptable reliability.
Table 3. Statistics of Construct Items.
Factor loadings	Cronbach’s α	Composite reliability	Average variance extracted	Mean (S.D.)
Emotional appeal		0.756	0.716	0.508	2.47
EMO1	0.727				(0.899)
EMO2	0.626				
EMO3	0.777				

Informativeness		0.816	0.821	0.609	2.97
INFO1	0.841				(0.855)
INFO2	0.663				
INFO3	0.826				

Creativity		0.903	0.878	0.686	2.52
CREA1	0.788				(0.967)
CREA2	0.785				
CREA3	0.878				
CREA4	0.859				

Perceived herd behavior		0.889	0.865	0.650	2.51
HERD1	0.864				(1.038)
HERD2	0.895				
HERD3	0.763				
HERD4	0.686				

Subjective norms		0.909	0.912	0.718	2.51
SN1	0.827				(0.882)
SN2	0.892				
SN3	0.895				
SN4	0.771				

Attitude to empathy expression		0.841	0.870	0.557	3.25
ATT1	0.716				(0.728)
ATT2	0.637				
ATT3	0.754				
ATT4	0.862				

Privacy concerns		0.841	0.801	0.664	2.54
PC1	0.778				(1.032)
PC2	0.959				
PC3	0.685				

Intention to express empathy		0.889	0.830	0.801	2.79
INT1	0.905				(1.217)
INT2	0.885				

Purchase intention		0.802	0.751	0.670	2.58
PI1	0.798				(1.061)
PI2	0.839				
X2 = 595.004 (p = 0.000, df = 337); RMSEA = 0.043; NFI = 0.924; CFI = 0.965; TLI = 0.958; RMR = 0.050; SRMR = 0.043.

Next, convergent validity and discriminant validity were tested. First, convergent validity was assessed by examining factor loadings of each observed variable. All factor loadings were significant and exceeded the recommended 0.50 threshold (Hair, Black, Babin, Anderson, & Tatham, 2006). Convergent validity was further assessed by examining CR and average variances extracted (AVE) values. CR values were above 0.70 and AVE values were above 0.50, indicating that both CR and AVE values exceeded the corresponding cutoff criteria (Hair et al., 2006). CR values of the constructs ranged from 0.716 to 0.912 and AVE values ranged from 0.508 to 0.801. This demonstrated fair convergent validity (see Table 3). Furthermore, the square root of AVE obtained for each construct was larger than was the correlation of the construct with each of the remaining constructs (see Table 4), confirming discriminant validity (Fornell & Larcker, 1981). Therefore, convergent and discriminant validity as well as reliability proved to be adequate for the measurement model.
Table 4. Correlations between constructs (AVE and squared correlations).
EMO	INFO	CREA	HERD	ATT	SN	PC	INTL	PI
EMO	0.713*								
INFO	0.529	0.780*							
CREA	0.510	0.459	0.828*						
HERD	0.325	0.299	0.261	0.806*					
ATT	0.343	0.414	0.390	0.219	0.746*				
SN	0.467	0.527	0.473	0.318	0.507	0.847*			
PC	−0.023	−0.103	0.010	−0.150	0.068	−0.025	0.815*		
INT	0.429	0.474	0.442	0.238	0.559	0.562	0.098	0.895*	
PI	0.455	0.558	0.348	0.238	0.432	0.442	0.059	0.612	0.819*
EMO—emotional appeal; INFO—informativeness; CREA—ad creativity; HERD—herd behavior; ATT—attitude toward empathy expression; SN—subjective norm; PC—privacy concerns; INT—intention to express empathy; PI—purchase intention.


*
The numbers in the diagonal row are square roots of the average variance extracted.

The data used for this study was gathered based on the self-reported perceptions of the respondents. There is potential for common method bias for all self-report data. So before examining the hypothesized model, common method bias was assessed. To assess the severity of common method bias, Harman’s single-factor test (Podsakoff & Organ, 1986) was performed. For the Harman’s single-factor test, all the variables data in our model were entered into an unrotated exploratory factor analysis. Results from this test showed that the most covariance explained by one factor was 33.81% which was below the 50% threshold, meaning that common method biases are not a severe concern for this study (Podsakoff & Organ, 1986). Furthermore, an additional test was performed to examine the common method bias in the data set using the technique of unmeasured common latent factor, as demonstrated in Podsakoff, MacKenzie, Lee, and Podsakoff (2003) and Liang, Saraf, Hu, and Xue (2007). We conducted this test using AMOS. It was found that differences between standardized coefficients without a common latent factor and standardized coefficients with a common latent factor were less than 0.2. Therefore, common method bias is not a major concern in our data set.
Last, a multi-collinearity check was conducted. A review of the statistics literature indicates that we can use variation inflation factor (VIF) to determine if there exists an overlap between two variables (If VIF exceeds 10, then the items in the two variables have overlaps). We conducted the VIF analysis, and the resulting figures were 1.070 (the minimum) and 2.052 (the maximum), which suggests that there is no overlap. That is, there is no issue with multi-collinearity which refers to a situation when variables are so highly correlated with each other that it is difficult to come up with reliable estimates of their individual regression coefficients.

4.2. Structural paths and hypothesis tests
We constructed a structural equation model to test hypotheses. The hypothesized causal paths were estimated using AMOS 21.0. The resulting indices indicated a good model fit (x2/df = 1.78, RMSEA = 0.043; NFI = 0.920; CFI = 0.963; TLI = 0.957; RMR = 0.071; SRMR = 0.058) when evaluated against cutoff criteria in the literature (Kline, 2005). Fig. 2 displays the standardized path coefficient, path significance, and explained variance (R2) for each path. Seven hypotheses were supported while two were rejected. The results of the structural model illustrated the vital role of informativeness and advertising creativity in determining users’ attitudes to empathy expression. Informativeness (β = 0.31, p < 0.001) and advertising creativity (β = 0.21, p < 0.01) were both found to have a significant positive effect on attitude to empathy expression. However, the effect of emotional appeal on attitude proved insignificant (β = 0.16, p = 0.11). Thus, H4 and H5 were supported while H3 was not. Meanwhile, the results revealed that perceived herd behavior had a significant positive effect on subjective norm (β = 0.32, p < 0.001). ]]> <h target="2" match="part"><![CDATA[ However, perceived herd behavior was not significantly related to intention to express empathy (β = 0.06, p = 0.17). ]]></h> <h target="4" match="part"> <![CDATA[ Subjective norm (β = 0.40, p < 0.001) and privacy concern (β = –0.10, p < 0.05) were significantly associated with intention to express empathy. Thus, H8 and H9 were supported, whereas H7 was not. Attitude to empathy expression had a significant positive effect on intention to express empathy, supporting H1 (β = 0.45, p < 0.001). ]]> </h> <h target="5" match="full"> <![CDATA[Finally, a positive relationship was observed between intention to express empathy and purchase intention (β = 0.69, p < 0.001), supporting H2.]]></h><![CDATA[ It was revealed that 54% of the variance in intention to express empathy was explained by a combination of emotional appeal, informativeness, advertising creativity, perceived herd behavior, attitude, subjective norm, and privacy concerns. Emotional appeal, informativenss, and advertising creativity were found to explain 35% of the variance in attitude toward empathy expression.
Hypotheses testing
Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Hypotheses testing. X2 = 625.553 (p = 0.000, df = 352); RMSEA = 0.043; NFI = 0.920; CFI = 0.963; TLI = 0.957; RMR = 0.071; SRMR = 0.0584; *p < 0.05; **p < 0.01; ***p < 0.001.

]]></section>

    <section name="Discussion and implications" category="discussion"><![CDATA[
5. Discussion and implications
5.1. Discussion
This research sought to develop a theoretical model specifying the antecedents of positive user responses to an advertisement on a SNS and to test the proposed model using structural equation modeling. Our findings empirically support the proposed model.

The results of this study reveal two significant predictors of attitude toward empathy expression: informativeness and advertising creativity. The role of informativeness can be understood from the instrumental, or utilitarian, perspective. Muk and Chung (2014) found that utilitarian values of advertising on social networks enhance users’ positive attitudes toward brand pages. In our research, information about the utilitarian aspects of a product or service can strongly support consumers’ functional needs (Khan, Dhar, & Wertebroch, 2005). The quality information presented in SNS ads, such as a product’s benefits, can therefore help consumers make optimal purchases. Meanwhile, the importance of advertising creativity is associated with the fundamental human need to consume something new, original, out of the ordinary, and imaginative (Haberland & Dacin, 1992). A creative SNS ad will capture consumers’ attention, driving them to express their positive affective evaluation of the ad. Specifically, we found that the more informative and creative users perceive an SNS advertising message to be, the more positive their attitude to empathy expression is. ]]> <h target="1" match="full">Thus, users are likely to develop a positive attitude to the expression of favorable affective evaluation of a SNS ad when the ad provides information that addresses their functional needs (e.g., making an optimal choice of product/service) and when it is creative enough to provide hedonic value.</h><![CDATA[
Contrary to our expectations, emotional appeal failed to influence user attitudes toward empathy expression. In forming a positive user attitude toward empathy expression for a SNS ad, emotional appeal is less likely to play a substantial role. That is, emotional appeal may be important in itself, however it is not expected to be influential enough to generate a positive attitude toward empathy expression. Another possible explanation for this insignificant relationship is that the SNS advertisement chosen for this study (i.e., the carpool service ad) features a utilitarian (i.e., functionally driven) service, and therefore, emotional appeal appears to be less important, hardly giving rise to empathy in average users. Instead, rational aspects (e.g., informativeness) are likely to play a larger role in forming user attitude for utilitarian services than emotional aspects. This suggests that the product category may moderate the relationship between emotional appeal and user attitude.

The perceived herd behavior construct was designed to examine perceptions of informational social pressure. ]]> <h target="2" match="full">It was found that, while perceived herd behavior has an indirect impact on intention to express empathy,</h><![CDATA[ it is positively related to subjective norm, which is in turn positively related to intention to express empathy. This finding implies that users who recognize that many people appear to like a given SNS ad will be likely to perceive that important others expect them to like the ad as well, ultimately leading them to intend to like the ad. Theoretically, a user who decided to reduce uncertainty associated with SNS usage by following the herd behavior (i.e., adopting the prevailing viral behavior on Facebook) is likely to move on to maintain favorable relationships with his Facebook friends by complying with their expectations concerning the behavior of clicking “Like” or “Share” as a reaction to a SNS ad. Thus, top priority is given to uncertainty reduction and the next to social relationship management.]]> <h target="4" match="part"> Furthermore, as the TRA predicts, subjective norm positively affects intention to like the ad, implying that one may intend to like an SNS ad, not just because many people have liked it but because one's acquaintances expect one to like it.</h><![CDATA[

]]> <h target="3" match="full">As expected, privacy concerns negatively influenced a user’s viral intention for a SNS ad.</h><![CDATA[ When a SNS user strongly perceives that his privacy might be severely violated in the event that his friends make inferences about his ideology, character or preferences from the user’s viral behavior, the user is less likely to intend to express empathy. Meanwhile, this finding appears to be somewhat compatible with the finding of another study (Chen & Kim, 2013) that examined the effect of privacy concerns on SNS usage. Chen and Kim (2013) found that privacy concerns is not likely to entirely thwart a user’s intense desire to use an SNS, but to limit the user’s online usage to the extent that it may misrepresent or expose his private matters to other users on a social network. The respondents in our study may have perceived that their act of clicking Like for a SNS ad could be observed by their Facebook friends and would give them the impression that they supported for-profit commercials. If such a perception grows strong, an individual will most likely avoid any overt behavior that is believed to invade his or her privacy.]]>
    <h target="4" match="part">This research also found that the more positive a participant’s attitude toward empathy expression and the more strongly participants perceive the social pressure to express empathy, the greater their intention to express empathy for the given SNS ad.</h> <h target="5" match="part">Moreover, SNS responses such as intention to express empathy were found to influence purchase intention.</h> <![CDATA[

5.2. Implications
Our findings provide useful insights into what contributes to the formation of user attitudes to empathy expression and behavioral intention to express empathy with regards to a SNS ad. As we shall see below, they offer theoretical and practical implications for social media advertising.

The first theoretical implication is that it enhances our understanding about advertising effectiveness in a SNS context by proposing a new construct called attitude toward empathy expression (AEE), a concept extended from attitude toward advertising (AAD) traditionally studied in the marketing domain. We argue that AEE may have better predictive power in explaining the viral behavioral intention characterized by the SNS environment. Even though we did not empirically analyze the relationship between the two constructs (i.e., AAD and AEE), the findings suggest that AEE appears to be a suitable construct in a SNS advertising context. Second, the results demonstrate that the TRA and social influence theory are robust theories that can help researchers predict the factors influencing users’ positive viral responses (e.g., clicking Like or Share) and a subsequent marketing response (e.g., purchase intention). These two theories are complementary in that they together provide a comprehensive perspective on user behavior on a SNS by enabling us to consider both personal and social factors. Third, while the relationship between perceived herd behavior and intention to express empathy expression proved insignificant, the relationship was mediated by subjective norms. Our results helped enhance our understanding of the theoretical relationships among these two forms of social influences and intention to express empathy.

On the other hand, our research results also point to practical implications. First, the finding on the relationship between intention to express empathy and purchase intention provides a key implication for advertisers and marketers; Positive SNS responses (e.g., a user’s viral intention and behavior) can help generate a direct marketing response (e.g., purchase intention), thereby helping to augment the sales. Users will be inclined to purchase a good or service featured in an SNS ad when they have a strong intention to engage in a viral behavior for a given ad, suggesting that a well-formulated advertising strategy focused on increasing the number of likes and shares will eventually pay off. Second, our results determined three antecedents of behavioral intention to express empathy about a SNS ad; namely, attitude toward empathy expression, subjective norm, and privacy concerns. In particular, informativeness and advertising creativity were found to be significant predictors of attitude toward empathy expression while emotional appeal was not. Therefore, to increase the likelihood that users will react favorably to an ad, advertisers and marketers should make their advertising messages more informative and creative to the extent that such messages will effectively induce users to express their empathy. However, the insignificant relationship between emotional appeal and attitude toward empathy expression appears to be attributed to the product/service class used in this study. So marketers and advertisers need to pay attention to the product or service class to be featured in their SNS ad when creating an advertising campaign, since emotional appeal may or may not contribute to positive user responses depending on the product/service category.

]]></section>

    <section name="Limitations and research directions" category="conclusion"><![CDATA[
6. Limitations and research directions
Though this research contributes to the literature by identifying the antecedents of user responses to SNS advertising and subsequent marketing responses, it has a few limitations. First, the predictors we used in our model may not be exhaustive. Further research is needed to explore other factors that may lead to favorable responses to SNS advertising. Second, college students in their 20s are active SNS users but may not be representative of the consumer population. Future research may investigate and test the nomological relationships in our model using a sample consisting of real-world consumers. Third, it would be worthwhile to replicate this study using a motion picture (e.g., a YouTube video) instead of a still picture. A recent study found that media type may affect attitudes to an advertisement on a mobile device and that a video ad leads to a more positive attitude to advertising than does a still-image ad (Sung & Cho, 2012). Fourth, this study did not include the ‘behavior’ construct in the research model, because it focused on understanding the relationships between intention and its antecedents. However, the incorporation of the construct as a dependent variable would have enabled far-reaching implications for practitioners as well as academics. Moreover, with such a model setup it would have been possible to examine the moderating role of privacy concerns in the relationship between intention and behavior, rather than merely illuminating the direct effect of privacy concerns on intention. Fifth, while the present research focuses on ‘liking’ as a user’s behavioral response to a SNS ad, it would be desirable to examine alternative responses such as sharing and writing posts which are regarded as more active user behavior than liking. Finally, future research may examine the moderating role of product category in the relationship between emotional appeal and user’s attitude toward empathy expression. It may be posited that hedonic products or services involve greater impact of emotional appeal on attitude, whereas utilitarian counterparts involve minimal or insignificant impact. Findings of such research will augment our understanding of the factors affecting the formation of positive user behavior with regards to a SNS ad.
]]></section>
</publication>
