<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication maker="liu bin">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 6, Part B, December 2016, Pages 1350-1359</time>
International Journal of Information Management
    <title>What keeps the mobile hotel booking users loyal? Investigating the roles of self-efficacy, compatibility, perceived ease of use, and perceived convenience</title>
    <author>Ahmet Bulent Ozturk.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Anil Bilgihan.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Khaldoon Nusair.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacec. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Fevzi Okumus.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
Rosen College of Hospitality Management, University of Central Florida, 9907 Universal Blvd., Orlando, FL 32832, USA
b
Department of Marketing, Florida Atlantic University, Boca Raton, FL, USA
c
College of Economics and Political Science, Sultan Qaboos University, Al Khoudh, Muscat 123, Oman
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.04.005</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">Convenience, compatibility, and PEOU are positively associated with MHB loyalty.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">Ccompatibility significantly influences PEOU and perceived convenience.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">PEOU has a significant impact on perceived convenience.</highlight>

    <abstract><![CDATA[
Abstract
With the advancements in mobile technologies, mobile hotel booking (MHB) has become an important distribution channel for hotels and online travel agencies (OTAs). Understanding MHB users’ loyalty intentions toward this technology has become equally important for MHB service providers, as it is essential for them to retain their customers. However, existing literature in the context of mobile booking has mainly focused on the adoption and acceptance of this technology. The purpose of this paper is to empirically test a research model that incorporates antecedents of mobile shopping loyalty in a hotel booking context. The proposed model was tested through structural equation modeling (SEM) by using empirical data collected from 396 MHB users. ]]><h target="1" match="full"> Study results revealed that convenience, compatibility, and perceived ease of use (PEOU) had a significant impact on the users’ loyalty intentions toward MHB technology.  </h> <h target="2;3" match="full;full">In addition, compatibility significantly influenced PEOU and convenience and PEOU had a significant impact on loyalty and convenience.</h><![CDATA[ Study results provide valuable theoretical and practical implications for various players in the hotel and travel industry including hoteliers, OTAs, mobile app developers and hospitality technology vendors.
]]></abstract>

    <keywords>Mobile shopping</keywords>
    <keywords>Mobile booking</keywords>
    <keywords>Loyalty</keywords>
    <keywords>Convenience</keywords>
    <keywords>Compatibility</keywords>
    
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction"><![CDATA[
1. Introduction
Online distribution of services, including hotel rooms, flights, travel packages, attraction tickets, cruises, and car rentals has been on the rise due to the benefits that both travelers and companies perceive (Bilgihan & Bujisic, 2015). The Internet is amongst the most important channels for hotel room distribution. Therefore, adopting an effective e-commerce strategy is a key matter for the lodging industry (Law, Buhalis, & Cobanoglu, 2014). On the other hand, the shift from e-commerce to mobile commerce (m-commerce) is accelerating as more consumers use their mobile devices to shop online. It was reported that more than 70 percent of people own a smartphone in the U.S. (Nielsen, 2014) and smartphones have become the staple of everyday life as nine out of ten smartphone users use their devices daily (Okumus & Bilgihan, 2014; Okumus, Bilgihan, & Ozturk, 2015).
The pervasive diffusion of mobile technology is transforming the lodging industry (Tussyadiah & Zach, 2012: Xiang, Tussyadiah, & Buhalis, 2015). Mobile devices have introduced both convenience and easiness to contemporary travelers. With this technology, it is possible to complete variety of transactions including shopping on-the-go for travel related products and services. One of the facilities provided is the convenience to book hotel rooms via mobile devices. It is expected that mobile booking will become the predominant distribution channel for the lodging industry (Tode, 2014). Hotel brands are optimistic about the future of mobile booking and they believe that more travelers will adopt their mobile devices to make hotel reservations.
Just as the Internet changed lodging in the late 1990s, the transition to the mobile is expected to have similar effects for the lodging industry as it is transforming the guests’ experiences. Hence, in order to stay competitive and increase booking revenues, hospitality practitioners need to focus on m-commerce. This can be achieved both by offering effective mobile booking strategies (Wang & Wang, 2010) and by ensuring customer loyalty (Kandampully, Zhang, & Bilgihan, 2015). First generation hotel mobile sites provided hotel information such as location, amenities and facilities, now hotel mobile sites and mobile applications (app) not only allows travelers to access hotel information and services but also enable travelers to book their rooms on-the-go.
Mobile technologies grant customers powerful influences in the world of travel business (Morosan, 2014). In the lodging industry, customer loyalty is shrinking. It is expected that the mobile platform will play a key role not only in the distribution of the rooms but also in establishing and strengthening customer relationships and brand loyalty (Anuar, Musa, & Khalid, 2014). Kandampully et al. (2015) highlight the effect of mobile channels on customer loyalty and lists the “impact of mobile Web solutions and app experiences on customer loyalty” (p. 401) as a research priority for the lodging industry.
Even though initial acceptance is essential for the dissemination of an innovation, acceptance does not assure continued usage of the innovation (Hong, Thong, & Tam 2006; Hsieh, Rai, & Keil 2008). Also, it is important to consider the fact that most mobile users are willing to download specific travel apps (e.g. hotel app, OTA app) onto their devices, however, about half of those are deleted later (Linton & Kwortnik, 2015). This statistic calls for further research in mobile loyalty. Furthermore, Wang and Wang (2010) state that it is critical for both practitioners and academics to understand the factors that influence the usage of MHB. Creating and maintaining loyalty help firms develop long-term, mutually beneficial relationships with customers (Pan, Sheng, & Xie, 2012). In addition, it is known that loyal customers are willing to pay more, express higher purchase intentions, and resist brand switching (Evanschitzky et al., 2012).
Prior studies related to mobile booking have mainly focused on the adoption and acceptance of this technology and examined instrumental beliefs (e.g., PEOU, perceived complexity, service quality, and technical barriers) as the antecedents to behavioral intention toward it. However, understanding customer loyalty in MHB is a complex task that extends beyond the aforementioned factors. Therefore, this study builds on the previous research and considers other constructs that play a critical role in user loyalty including, personal differences (such as compatibility and self-efficacy) and system characteristics (such as convenience).

Convenience is related to creating time and place benefits for users (Kim, Mirusmonov, & Lee, 2010) and it has been recognized as one of the most important factors in the context of m-commerce (Xu & Gutierrez, 2006). Considering the key futures of MHB technology, we can determine convenience as one of the primary characteristics of MHB (Kim et al., 2010). Furthermore, MHB services’ compatibility with users’ needs and lifestyle play an important role in their continued use intentions (Kim et al., 2010). In addition, users’ self-efficacy levels in the context of mobile computing may be different from a desktop computing. For example, as mobile devices have different input components such as touchscreens, accelerometers, and gravity sensors, users may require different skills to navigate compared to a web-based environment that tend to use mouse and keyboard (Keith, Babb, Lowry, Furner, & Abdulatt, 2015). In this regard, users with high Internet self-efficacy or computer self-efficacy does not necessarily mean that they will have high level of mobile computing self-efficacy. Therefore, understanding MHB users’ compatibility, self-efficacy and convenience in relation to their behavioral intentions is crucial for MHB service providers, as it is essential for them to retain their customers. In sum, the purpose of this study is to investigate the determinants that influence users’ behavioral intentions towards MHB technology. More specifically, this study aims to develop and test a theoretical based model to answer the following research questions: (1) Do compatibility, PEOU and convenience positively influence users’ loyalty intentions toward MHB technology? (2) Does compatibility positively influence PEOU and convenience in MHB (3) Does PEOU positively influence convenience in MHB? (4) Does self-efficacy positively influence users’ PEOU of MHB technology?

]]></section>
    
    <section name="Literature review;Theoretical background" category="background"><![CDATA[
2. Literature review
2.1. Mobile hotel booking technology
Hotel mobile apps and mobile websites are means that travelers use to navigate and book hotel rooms. Such apps and mobile websites generate a small portion of total hotel bookings, but their acceptance and popularity are increasing exponentially as more people are moving away from desktops and getting comfortable with booking their travel reservations on mobile devices. Mobile apps and mobile websites no longer are new, but the current round of investments increasingly are shifting the initial focus from basic mobile self-service tools to online booking engines. In other words, they are shifting from an added amenity to an online distribution channel.

MHB technology in this study refers to “a location based online distribution information system that enables customers worldwide to reserve hotel rooms anytime, anywhere through the use of the wireless Internet, and global positioning system (GPS) on their mobile devices” (Wang & Wang, 2010). MHB technology is designed to provide hotel reservation support for mobile devices through mobile websites and mobile apps. Mobile devices have smaller screen sizes and their computing power is lower than personal computers, thus, websites that are designed for personal computers can be very difficult to read and navigate on mobile devices making the booking process relatively time consuming. On the other hand, mobile optimized websites and apps make the booking procedure more accessible and easy for consumers. Since the content of mobile booking sites and apps are optimized for smaller touch screens, users can be guided through the search and booking process allowing them to complete their reservations within a few and easier steps (Wang & Wang, 2010). Additionally, GPS enables mobile devices to search for hotels nearby, if the user prefers, the site or the app only lists the hotels close to the user’s geographical location.
3. Theoretical background
The theoretical foundations and research constructs for this study are derived from the Technology Acceptance Model (TAM) (Davis, 1989), Social Cognitive Theory (Bandura, 1986), Technology Task Fit Theory (Goodhue, 1995) and Self-Determination Theory (Ryan & Deci, 2000b). Using TAM in the MHB context is important as this preeminent model explains how users come to accept and use a technology. TAM suggests that when users are presented with a new technology (e.g. MHB), PEOU of the technology will influence their decision whether they will use it or not. The impact of PEOU on technology acceptance has been investigated extensively. However, initial acceptance of an innovation does not assure continued usage of it (Hong et al., 2006; Hsieh et al., 2008). Therefore, even though users initially decide to use a technology, they may stop using it at any time if they believe that they are putting too much effort to use it. Next, Social Cognitive Theory explains that people’s belief in their capacity to execute behaviors influences their behaviors. The model includes the construct of self-efficacy, which is the extent, or strength of one's belief in one's own ability to complete tasks and reach goals, in this case using the mobile device to make a hotel reservation. It is an important construct for behavioral intentions in innovation adoption research. Following, Technology Task Fit theory was deployed because it asserts that a technology is more likely to be used if the capabilities of the technology match the tasks that the user must perform. In other words, in order to use and to continue using MHB, the user should feel that the system and action fit into his/her lifestyle. Finally, Self-Determination Theory was considered as it concerns with the motivation behind choices people make without external influence and interference. Self-determination theory considers convenience as related to users’ perceived belief that a technology/system is helpful to their task completion (Chang, Yan, & Tseng, 2012). Convenience has been recognized as one of the most important factors in the context of m-commerce (Xu & Gutierrez, 2006) as it is related to creating time and place benefits for users (Kim et al., 2010). In sum, we integrated aforementioned theories to capture technology-related, social-related, and self-related constructs to develop a theoretical based model that investigates the role of self-efficacy, compatibility, PEOU, and convenience to explain users’ loyalty intentions toward MHB technology (Fig. 1).
Fig. 1
Download high-res image (246KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Research model.
3.1. Self-efficacy
Self-efficacy is rooted in social cognitive theory (Bandura, 1986). It affects what behaviors people choose to perform, the amount of effort they are ready to use, and the amount of time they will persist to overcome obstacles (Bandura, 1982; Bandura, 1986). Self-efficacy is the belief an individual maintains as to how well he/she can perform a task (Huffman, Whetten, & Huffman, 2013). According to Bandura’s theory, individuals with high self-efficacy are more likely to view difficult tasks as something to be mastered rather than something to be avoided. Self-efficacy is defined as the “generative capability in which cognitive, social and behavioral sub-skills must be organized into integrated courses of action to serve innumerable purpose” (Bandura, 1982).
Self-efficacy in general is related to actual behavior (Bandura, 2012). Technology self-efficacy is the personal belief that the person has the adequate and accurate aptitudes and skill set to succeed when dealing with a technology related task (McDonald & Siegall, 1992). Based on Luarn and Lin (2005) mobile banking service study, current research focuses on whether individuals believe that they have the necessary knowledge, skill or ability to use MHB technology. Consequently we define perceived self-efficacy as the judgment of one’s ability to use MHB technology.
3.2. Compatibility
According to the Technology Task Fit Theory, the technology’s compatibility with users’ existing values and beliefs, previously introduced ideas, and needs are important (Chen, Gillenson, & Sherrell, 2002; Goodhue, 1995). Compatibility is the degree to which the innovation is perceived to be consistent with the potential users’ existing values, previous experiences, and needs. High compatibility leads to preferable adoption of mobile systems (Wu & Wang, 2005). We define compatibility as the degree to which MHB technology fits the lifestyle and experiences of individuals. Compatibility has effects on both behavioral intention to use through perceived usefulness, and actual use through behavioral intention to use (Wu & Wang, 2005). It is a key factor in consumers’ attitude towards online shopping (Chen et al., 2002), as Wu and Wang (2005) highlight that the compatibility had the most significant influence on behavioral intention in a mobile shopping context. It is also an important construct in users’ mobile device activities (Koenig-Lewis, Palmer, & Moll, 2010). Ewe et al. (2015) highlight that in order to increase the usage of mobile banking, the system should create an impression that mobile banking is easy to use and is compatible with users’ lifestyles. Finally, it is a construct that has been used in recent TAM studies and found to be a key precursor of perceived ease of use (Akturan & Tezcan, 2012). Thus, the inclusion of compatibility construct in the research model is reasonable as greater compatibility results in a faster rate of technology adoption.
3.3. Perceived ease of use
PEOU is a key component of technology adoption and usage behavior. Davis (1989) defined perceived ease of use as “the degree to which a person believes that use of a particular system would be free of effort i.e. easy to comprehend or use (Jen & Hung, 2010). It is a prominent construct in tourism information systems research (Bilgihan, Barreda, Okumus, & Nusair, 2016). It is associated with users’ evaluation of the effort involved in the progression of utilizing a technology (Venkatesh, 2000). PEOU positively affects the intention to use smartphone apps (Okumus & Bilgihan, 2014). In this study, we adopt Davis’s definition and defined PEOU as the degree to which an individual considers that MHB technology is easy to use.
3.4. Convenience
Convenience is amongst the most common incentives for consumers to shop online (Chen et al., 2002). Customers’ perceived online shopping convenience as one of the crucial determinants of success of online businesses (Jiang, Yang, & Jun, 2013). The favorable aspects of mobile convenience directly and positively influence mobile value (Lin & Lu, 2015) and enhances user satisfaction, and further increases the value for users. In online tourism contexts, purchasers enjoy convenience when comparing rates, accessing more flexible rates, saving time, and reducing both costs and negotiation time in front of their screens (Wu & Chang, 2005).
The self-determination theory proposes two principal motivations for technology acceptance, namely intrinsic (doing an activity for its own sake) and extrinsic motivation (doing an activity for a consequence separable from the activity itself) (Roca & Gagné, 2008). Intrinsic motivations are related to enjoyment whereas extrinsic motivations refer to pursuit of a reward or the avoidance of a punishment (Ryan & Deci, 2000a). The self-determination theory depicts convenience as related to users’ perceived belief that a technology/system is helpful to their task completion (Chang et al., 2012). Prior research utilized convenience as an antecedent of technology usage intention in modified Technology Acceptance Models (e.g. Hossain & Prybutok, 2008; Yoon & Kim, 2007).
The concept of convenience has distinct dimensions including time (i.e. product may be provided at a time that is more convenient for the customer), place (i.e. product may be provided in a place that is more convenient for the customer), acquisition (i.e. firms may make it easier for the customer, financially and otherwise, to purchase their products), use (i.e. product may be made more convenient for the customer to use) and execution (i.e. the most obvious convenience is simply having someone provide the product for the consumer) (Brown, 1990). While Brown (1990) proposed five dimensions for the concept of convenience, we define convenience as the degree of convenience toward time, place and execution. Both acquisition convenience and use convenience have been eliminated from our study as in the former concept it is not necessarily relevant to using technology, while in the latter one it is not easy to distinguish use of convenience from ease of use (Yoon & Kim, 2007). In the context of MHB, time and place dimension refers to the degree of perception held by individuals that they can use MHB technology to accomplish their booking at a time and place that is more convenient for them. Finally, execution dimension refers to the degree of perception held by individuals that they find the MHB technology convenient in the process of booking a hotel room.
3.5. Loyalty
Loyalty is conceptualized as customers' favorable attitude towards a brand (Keller, 1993). Creating and maintaining customer loyalty, helps companies develop long-term, mutually beneficial relationships with customers (Pan et al., 2012). Loyal customers exhibit attachment and commitment toward the company, and are not attracted to competitors offerings (So, King, Sparks, & Wang, 2013). The term e-loyalty is specified as consumers' intention to revisit a website or purchase again from an online vendor (Reichheld & Schetter, 2000; Flavian, Guinaliu, & Gurrea, 2006). Developing e-loyalty is essential to resist brand switching (Barreda, Nusair, Okumus, & Bilgihan, 2013). Traditionally, e-loyalty is derived from the ease of ordering, product information and selection, on-time delivery, customer confidence, adequate privacy policies, online resources, e-commerce quality, trust, and commitment (Bilgihan & Bujisic, 2015; Wolfinbarger & Gilly, 2003). In alignment with the studies in the context of e-commerce, mobile loyalty (m-loyalty) also depends on consumers' intention to revisit a mobile website resulting in repeat purchasing behavior (Cyr, Head, & Ivanov, 2006). In this study, loyalty is defined as users’ behavioral intentions to continuously use MHB technology and recommend it to other users.

]]></section>

    <section name="Research model and development of hypotheses" category="research model and hypotheses"><![CDATA[
4. Research model and development of hypotheses
4.1. Self-efficacy and perceived ease of use
Self-efficacy affects users’ system anxiety, which eventually affects PEOU and perceived usefulness of the system (Igbaria & Iivari, 1995). Prior research focused on examining the effects of self-efficacy on PEOU (e.g. Venkatesh & Davis, 2000; Venkatesh, 2000;Yi & Hwang, 2003;Ozturk, 2016). Agarwal , Sambamurthy , & Stair (2000) highlight the strong relationship between self-efficacy and ease of use. This designates that users regard the system easier to use when their conviction in their own efficacy regarding the target system. Consequently, we relate MHB-specific self-efficacy to ease of use in the model and hypothesize that:
H1

Self-efficacy has a positive effect on PEOU in MHB.


4.2. The impact of compatibility on perceived ease of use, convenience and loyalty
Prior literature support that compatibility has a positive influence on attitudes towards online shopping, perceived usefulness, and ease of use of online purchasing (Crespo, de los Salmones, & del Bosque, 2013). Research also shows that compatibility positively and directly influences both perceived usefulness and behavioral intention to use (Wu & Wang, 2005). Compatibility was found to be a primary determinant of consumer attitude towards using online stores (Chen et al., 2002). Koenig-Lewis et al. (2010) found that compatibility is a significant indicator for the adoption of mobile banking. Compatibility is also an important antecedent for PEOU (Akturan & Tezcan, 2012). Therefore, based on the arguments above we posit the following hypotheses:
H2

Compatibility has a positive effect on PEOU in MHB.

H3

Compatibility has a positive effect on loyalty in MHB.

H4

Compatibility has a positive effect on convenience in MHB.


4.3. Convenience and loyalty
With the advancement of mobile technologies, travelers can gain unlimited access to the information they require and enjoy a wider range of choices. Sustaining high levels of online shopping convenience has increasingly become a key driving force for brands, with the aim of enhancing customer loyalty (Jiang et al., 2013). For many years, travelers have been using their desktops and laptops for convenience purposes. When similar products and services exist, convenience can be an important factor in users’ acceptance because the basic technology and service have already been tested and standardized (Yang, Lee, Park, & Lee, 2014). Therefore, convenience should be an important factor for MHB. In MHB, especially for return users, technology stores user preferences and recalls these preferences and payment information at the time of booking making the booking process progress smoothly and less time consuming. Enabling users to make reservations quickly and easily on a mobile device yields to a high convenience. This is expected to increase the loyalty towards MHB. Based on the arguments above, we propose:
H5

Convenience has a positive effect on loyalty in MHB.


4.4. The impact of perceived ease of use on convenience and loyalty
The ‘ease of use’ is a determinant of the convenience (Yoon & Kim, 2007). Convenience is a key advantage of online shopping, and difficulties with site navigation and the checkout process are the factors that consumer abandon shopping online. Therefore, PEOU is expected to have a positive influence on user’s perception of convenience in their interaction with MHB technology. On the other hand, when users believe that a technology is easy to operate, they are more likely to have a favorable attitude towards the technology, which in return increases their willingness to utilize it in the future (Davis, 1989; Rosen, Whaling, Rab, Carrier, & Cheever, 2013). Furthermore, usability, the key aspect of ease of use, is the driver of loyalty for online shopping (Jackson, 2006). Similarly, users are more likely to remain loyal when they find the technology usable (Lee, Moon, Kim, & Yi, 2015). Individuals may decide to use MHB technology for many reasons. For example, an unexpected change in travel plan may force individuals to utilize MHB technology to book a hotel. However, if the users find MHB technology exhausting and hard to operate, then they may prefer not use it for the next time, which also may affect their intention to recommend it to others. Therefore, based on the discussion provided above, we propose the following hypotheses:
H6

PEOU has a positive effect on convenience in MHB.

H7

PEOU has a positive effect on loyalty in MHB.’

]]></section>

    <section name="Methodology" category="methods"><![CDATA[
5. Methodology
5.1. Survey instrument
A web based survey was developed to collect the empirical data for this study. The questionnaire consisted of two parts. In the first part, respondents were asked to indicate their level of agreement to the statements regarding the research constructs. The second part of the questionnaire included questions regarding respondents’ demographic characteristics such as age, gender, education and income level. An explanation of MHB technology with examples was included at the beginning of the questionnaire to make sure that the respondents have a clear idea of MHB technology. All scales were adapted from previous research and they were all measured using seven-point Likert scale ranging from ‘strongly disagree’ to “strongly agree”. Minor modifications were made to ensure that the scales reflect the MHB context. Self-efficacy was measured with three items adapted from Compeau and Higgins (1995). Compatibility were adapted from Chen et al. (2002) and measured with two items. Convenience was measured using a total of three items developed by Yoon and Kim (2007). PEOU was measured with 3-item scale adapted from Davis (1989). Finally, loyalty was measured with three items adapted from Lin and Wang (2006) (Table 2). A pilot test was carried out on the questionnaire to ensure its clarity and comprehensiveness. The questionnaires were distributed to a total 30 participants including 20 students and 10 faculty members who had previous MHB experience. Based on the comments and feedback obtained from the participants, some modifications were made on the wording of the questionnaire.
5.2. Data collection and preliminary analysis
A web based survey was used to collect data in this study. A marketing company (Qualtrics) was used to collect data. Target population of the study was U.S. travelers who booked a hotel room via their mobile devices at least once during the previous six months. A screening question was utilized to ensure that only those respondents who had previous MHB experience participated in the survey. The screening question used in the survey was “after considering the information provided about MHB technology, have you booked a hotel room in the last 6 months using a mobile device such as a smartphone or a tablet (e.g., iPhone, iPad, Samsung Galaxy Smartphone or Tablet, Windows Phone, Blackberry, etc.)”. The marketing company distributed the link to 8000 randomly selected panel members in the U.S. A total of 410 questionnaires were obtained with a response rate of 5%. Fourteen questionnaires were discarded due to incomplete responses. A total of 396 questionnaires were used for data analysis.

The data was first checked for outliers and missing values. Missing values were imputed by utilizing an expectation maximization method. A nonresponse biased test was conducted to compare early and late respondents on the variables of interests (Ary, Jacobs, & Razavieh, 1996). ANOVA results indicated no significant differences between early and late respondents demonstrating that nonresponse bias was not an issue for the sample used in this study. In addition, an examination of skewness and kurtosis values of the variables indicated that the sample did not violate normal distribution as the values were all in the acceptable range of −2 and +2 (George & Mallery, 2010). The demographic characteristics of the participants are presented in Table 1 Fifty percent of the respondents were male. Forty one percent of the participants were between the ages of 26–35 and nearly 37% of the respondents had a bachelor’s degree. Finally, 24% of the participants’ household income was between $50,000 and $75,000 (Table 1).
Table 1. Definition and origin of constructs.
Constructs	Origin	Definition
Self-efficacy	Compeau and Higgins (1995)	The judgement of one’s knowledge, skill or ability to use MHB technology
Compatibility	Chen et al. (2002)	The degree to which MHB technology fits the lifestyle and experiences of individuals
Perceived Ease of Use	Davis (1989)	The degree to which an individual considers that MHB technology is easy to use
Convenience	Yoon and Kim (2007)	The degree to which individuals find MHB technology convenient in the process of booking a hotel room and believe that they can use it to accomplish their booking at a time and place that is more convenient for them
Loyalty	Lin and Wang (2006)	Users’ behavioral intentions to continuously use MHB technology and recommend it to other users
Table 2. Respondents’ demographic characteristics.
Demographic Characteristics	N	%
Gender
Male	201	50.8
Female	195	49.2
Total	396	100

Age		
18–25	71	17.0
26–35	164	41.4
36–45	79	19.9
46–55	44	11.1
56–65	34	8.6
66 or older	4	1.0
Total	396	100

Education
Below High School	0	0.00
High School	40	10.1
Associate’s Degree	36	9.1
Some College	91	23.0
Bachelor’s Degree	146	36.8
Master’s Degree	61	15.4
Doctorate Degree	22	5.6
Total	396	100

Income
$25,000 or less	32	8.1
$25,001–$50,000	80	20.2
$50,001–$75,000	96	24.2
$75,001–$100,000	90	22.7
$100,001–$150,000	44	11.1
$150,001–$200,000	34	8.6
$200,001–$250,000	8	2.0
$250,001 or more	12	3.0
Total	396	100

]]></section>
    
    <section name="Results" category="results"><![CDATA[
        
6. Results
6.1. Measurement model analysis
AMOS 21.0 was utilized to analyze the collected empirical data. A standard two step approach was followed: (1) a measurement model analysis including a confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) to assess the measurement model and the validity of the multi-item scales and (2) a structural equation modeling (SEM) to test the study hypotheses. To examine the overall measurement model fit, a series of absolute and relative fit indexes were used. The chi-square statistics were significant as the ratio of chi-square value to degree of freedom was less than the cut of point of 3 (χ2 = 179.987, df = 67), which was an indicative of good fit. The Root Mean Square Error of Approximation (RMSEA) was calculated at 0.06 which was well below the recommended value of 0.08 (Browne & Cudeck, 1993). In addition, other goodness-of-fit statistics including Comparative Fit Index (CFI = 0.96), Goodness of Fit Index (GFI = 0.94), Tucker-Lewis Index (TLI = 0.97), Normed Fit Index (NFI = 0.93), Relative Fit Index (RFI = 0.95), and Incremental Fit Index (IFI = 0.96) demonstrated an acceptable model fit (Hair, Anderson, & Tatham, 1998).
Composite reliability (CR) estimates were used to assess the reliability of the measurement scales. As can be seen on Table 2, the CR values were above 0.8 which illustrated a support for construct reliability (Fornell & Larcker, 1981). To evaluate the convergent validity, Average Variance Extracted (AVE) values were used. The AVE values ranged from 0.87 to 0.90 exceeding the recommended value of 0.5, thus indicating good construct validity (Fornell & Larcker, 1981). In addition, the square roots of AVE scores were compared with the correlations between constructs to assess the discriminant validity. The results delivered supportive evidence for discriminant validity since the squared correlations between pairs of constructs were less than the AVE values (Table 4). Finally, multicollinearity was checked for by calculating variance inflation factor (VIF) scores for each predictor. The results indicated that all VIF scores were in the range of 1.00–2.70 well below the cut-off value of 10 (Neter, Wasserman, & Kutner, 1989), indicating that there is no cause for concern about the multicollinearity (Table 3).
Table 3. Validity and Reliability of Measurement Model.
Constructs	Standardized Loadings	Construct Reliability	AVE
Self-Efficacy		0.90	0.87
1. I could use MHB if only there is a built in-help facility for assistance.	0.87		
2. I could use MHB if someone else had helped to get started.	0.96		
3. I could use MHB if someone showed how to do it first.	0.91		

Compatibility		0.93	0.91
1. Using MHB fits my lifestyle.	0.91		
2. Using MHB fits well with the way I like to book or search hotel information.	0.91		

Perceived Ease of Use		0.90	0.90
1. Learning to operate MHB is easy for me.	0.89		
2. It is easy for me to become skillful at using MHB.	0.93		
3. Overall, I find MHB easy to use.	0.86		

Convenience		0.92	0.89
1. I can book my hotel at any time via mobile booking.	0.88		
2. I can book my hotel at any place via mobile booking.	0.89		
3. I feel that mobile booking is convenient for me to complete my hotel booking process.	0.85		

Loyalty		0.92	0.89
1. I will continue to use MHB	0.88		
2. I will recommend others to use MHB	0.93		
3. I will use MHB in the future.	0.88		
Table 4. Discriminant validity matrix.
CR	AVE	MSV	ASV	1	2	3	4	5
1. Convenience	0.908	0.767	0.621	0.440	0.876				
2. Self-efficacy	0.939	0.836	0.007	0.003	0.013	0.914			
3. Compatibility	0.905	0.826	0.667	0.482	0.770	0.085	0.909		
4. PEOU	0.924	0.801	0.661	0.452	0.740	0.024	0.813	0.895	
5. Loyalty	0.925	0.805	0.667	0.472	0.788	0.054	0.817	0.773	0.897
Note: AVE: Averance Variance Extracted; MSV: Maximum Shared Squared Variance; ASV: Average Shared Squared Variance (ASV). The square roots of AVEs are highlighted in bold.

6.2. Structural model analysis
The second step of the data analysis involved SEM analysis, which allowed testing the hypotheses of the study. In accordance with prior studies in technology adoption in general (Ozturk and Hancer, 2012) and mobile adoption in particular (Bigne, Ruiz, & Sanz, 2005; Wang, Xiang, Law, & Ki, 2015) MHB users’ demographic characteristics (i.e., age, gender, education, and income) were included to the model as control variables. To assess the overall model fit; the same goodness-of-fit measures were used as in the CFA. Chi-square to degrees of freedom ratio was equal to 2.20 which was below the cutoff point of 3 (χ2 = 249.038; df = 113) thus indicating a good model fit. In addition, other fit indices for the research model were in acceptable range with RMSEA of 0.05, CFI of 0.97, GFI of 0.93, TLI = 0.96, NFI of 0.95, RFI of 0.93 and IFI of 0.97 (Hair et al., 1998). Study results for testing the hypotheses illustrated that all of the hypotheses were supported in their proposed directions with the exception of H1. ]]><h target="2" match="part">The three predictors (i.e., PEOU, convenience, and compatibility) of loyalty explained a total 75% of variance with compatibility being the strongest one.</h> <![CDATA[ In addition, the variance explained for PEOU was 66% and the variance explained for convenience was 64% (Fig. 2).
Fig. 2
Download high-res image (329KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Results for structural modeling analysis.
*p<0.1; **p<0.05; ***p<0.01; n.s. non-significant; bold: varience explained

    ]]></section>
    
    <section name="Discussion and conclusions" category="conclusion"><![CDATA[
        
    7. Discussion and conclusions
    The aim of the current study was to develop and test a theoretical model that investigates the determinants of users’ loyalty intentions toward MHB technology. In this regard, the impacts of compatibility, PEOU, and convenience on MHB users’ loyalty intentions were examined. In addition, the impacts of compatibility on PEOU and convenience were investigated. This study further analyzed the influence of self-efficacy on PEOU and the impact of PEOU on convenience. The study results related to H1, which states that self-efficacy was positively related to PEOU was not significant (path coefficient = −0.036). This finding indicates that MHB users’ PEOU does not differ based on their self-efficacy. In other words, users’ confidence level on their ability to use MHB technology does not affect their perception of how easy MHB will be to use. The finding of H1 contradicted the results of past studies. This is possibly due to the fact that nearly 78 percent of the sample are less than 45 years old; a market segment that is tech-savvy and have the knowledge and the skills in MHB. From this perspective, the results are logical. Study findings associated with H2, H3 and H4, which state that compatibility is positively associated with PEOU, loyalty and convenience respectively, were all significant (H2 path coefficient = 0.816; H3 path coefficient = 0.391; H4 path coefficient = 0.506). These results were consistent with prior studies (Akturan & Tezcan, 2012; Crespo et al., 2013) indicating that when users believe that using MHB technology fits well their lifestyle and fits well the way they like to book a hotel room, then they find MHB convenient and easy to use and thus are willing to continuously use MHB and recommend it to others. This is a key finding that highlights the predominant role of compatibility in m-commerce. Rogers (2003) describes compatibility as the degree to which an innovation (mobile booking in this context) is perceived as consistent with the existing values, past experiences, and needs of potential adopters. Innovations that are perceived as being compatible with potential users’ values are more likely to be adopted. Previous studies investigated the compatibility of MHB from the hotel’s perspective. Wang et al. (2016) investigated the factors affecting hotels' adoption of mobile booking systems. They report that compatibility has a significant effect on hotels' adoption of a mobile booking technology. Our results, on the other hand, investigated the MHB phenomenon from the users’ perspective, and yet offered similar insights.
    Consistent with the previous literature (Jiang et al., 2013), study results demonstrate that convenience was also an important antecedents of loyalty (H5 path coefficient = 0.325). This result illustrates that when users have positive perceptions toward the convenience of MHB technology, then their loyalty level increases. This finding is similar with a recent Cornell Hospitality Report that reports travelers want to use mobile devices to gain convenience (Linton & Kwortnik, 2015). Due to high level of importance in convenience, providers should focus on features that makes the app or the mobile website more convenient for the customers. Finally, the study results revealed that PEOU positively influence convenience and loyalty (H6 path coefficient = 0.319 and H7 path coefficient = 0.210). These findings confirmed that PEOU is still an important construct in information technology research that positively affects convenience and loyalty. On the other hand, it is important to note that, when standardized path coefficients were compared, we can conclude that compatibility is the most important factor affecting MHB users’ loyalty intentions.
    7.1. Theoretical implications
    This study contributes to the user m-commerce adoption literature by investigating factors affecting users’ loyalty intentions toward MHB technology. In modern society, more and more people are discovering mobile shopping, and some are making very good use of m-commerce. Previously, companies have enthusiastically used e-commerce as a key marketing tool and sales vehicle for their products and services (Smith, 2008). Now, more companies are using the mobile as a marketing tool and hotel brands are no exception. An increasing number of guests are booking their hotel rooms using their mobile devices. Motivated by the steadily increasing popularity of mobile booking, the present study has aimed to explore the key antecedents of the user loyalty of MHB. For that purpose, the current research developed and tested a multidisciplinary model.
    This study contributes to the literature in information systems and services marketing in several ways. As suggested by Wang and Wang (2010), users’ behavioral intentions toward MHB cannot be entirely explained by the existing technology adoption models. This current study has developed and tested a multidisciplinary theoretical model that is rooted in four theories namely; Technology Acceptance Model (Davis, 1989), Social Cognitive Theory (Bandura, 1986), Technology Task Fit Theory (Goodhue, 1995), and Self-Determination Theory (Ryan & Deci, 2000a) and links important constructs (i.e. self-efficacy, compatibility, PEOU, convenience, and loyalty) of MHB technology.
    7.2 It is important to integrate aforementioned theories to investigate users’ loyalty intentions toward MHB technology. Such integration enhances our understanding about the roles of technology-related, social-related, and self-related constructs that drive customer loyalty in the context of MHB technology. There is a robust literature on the antecedents of loyalty, however not much is known about how mobile loyalty drivers are different from other contexts (e.g. e-commerce). The relationships among constructs may vary with the type of technology. Knowing how these constructs are different for the mobile technology is crucial. In this regard, the study findings confirm that users' behavioral intentions have two principal motivations; convenience as an intrinsic motivation (doing an activity for its own sake) and compatibility as an extrinsic motivation (doing an activity for a consequence separable from the activity itself). To the authors’ best knowledge, there has been no research conducted to examine MHB in terms of users’ compatibility and convenience perceptions and their relations to users’ behavioral intentions. In this regard, this study conceptualizes compatibility and convenience in the context of MHB and confirms that they are both critical factors that significantly influence MHB users’ loyalty intentions
    
    In addition, most of the prior studies utilized instrumental beliefs as the antecedents to behavioral intention toward mobile services. This research theoretically builds on the previous research and considers supplementary constructs that play a critical role MHB loyalty. More specifically, in current research, along with PEOU, personal differences such as compatibility and self-efficacy and system characteristics including convenience were also included in the research model as they are developing relevance in MHB due to the critical role they play in user behavioral intentions. In this regard, amalgamation and validation of these constructs offer valuable theoretical contribution to the general body of knowledge in information technology and services marketing.
    
    7.2. Practical implications
    The research findings of the study also provide valuable practical implications for various players in the lodging and travel industry including hoteliers, OTAs, mobile app developers and hospitality technology vendors. Mobile devices have introduced both convenience and easiness to contemporary travelers. Mobile booking is the fastest growing segment of online booking. Therefore, all hotels should consider this important and growing channel as IT applications can lead to competitive advantage for hotels (Bilgihan, Okumus, Nusair, & Kwun, 2011). Designing a convenient and easy to use environment of MHB is an essential for hotel brands. In the face of severe competition and continually rising customer expectations, hotel brands have become interested in creating loyal guests. Users behave differently on each platform (desktop, tablet, mobile) and may have different needs from different platforms. For that reason, it was important to inform practitioners regarding the needs of the growing mobile segment.
     ]]><h target="1" match="part"> The study results indicate that compatibility, PEOU, and convenience are successful in explaining the MHB loyalty. </h><![CDATA[Therefore, MHB service providers should focus on the utilitarian interface design elements when aiming for user loyalty. In addition, MHB technology should be designed and implemented with the convenience on mind. Accessibility of information and simplicity of the transaction processes are important antecedents to the successful completion of transactions in mobile booking. A convenient MHB website and app should provide a short response time, facilitate fast completion of a transaction, and minimize customer effort. Because of the nature of the medium itself, mobile customers have come to expect fast and efficient processing of their booking transactions.
    
    In other words, our results confirm that customers seek easy online navigation and a convenient experience. Mobile shopping marketers should focus on easy to use, intuitive shopping experience and commerce competencies that address convenience for customer loyalty. Creating intuitive user interfaces is a critical goal. Visually, the user interface of the mobile platform should provide clues that indicate what it is going to do. We advise the MHB marketers and developers to design and built in-help facility for assistance. For example, MHB should demonstrate a booking experience when users first open the app/website and they should be able to ask any questions they might have during the booking process.Also, the interface should deliver the expected and consistent results. Users should perform the choosing the location and dates, paying and booking the room with a minimum amount of effort. Further, the interface should provide clear and immediate feedback. In order to increase the convenience, mobile platform developers should make the most from the mobile device features. For instance, using Bluetooth, the smartphone could be used as a room key to increase convenience after the booking process. Also, the mobile platform can use the location of guests’ phone to help them discover places in their immediate area. To further increase the convenience, the mobile platforms could consider linking social media (e.g. Tripadvisor for hotel reviews) to the apps. Therefore, guests can read reviews of places, and they can post their own without leaving the app.
    
    Convenience is also related to creating a one-on-one relationship with customers. The mobile platform should offer personalized experiences based on previous booking trends and preferences. Mobile alerts, Uber integration to call for transportation, mobile payment, mobile check-in, keyless entry, and ordering room service are all examples of features that hotels can tie into their mobile websites and apps to take the user experience to the next level.
    
    A MHB technology that is logical and convenient to use will also minimizes the likelihood that customers make mistakes and will make their shopping experience more satisfying. Such outcomes are likely to enhance customer loyalty (Srinivasan, Anderson, & Ponnavolu, 2002). Customers driven by the need for convenience are less likely to inconvenience themselves by repeatedly searching for new service providers. Therefore, they are more likely to exhibit higher levels of loyalty (Anderson & Srinivasan, 2003). The findings of the study suggest MHB service providers to emphasize the main features that the users need. For instance, once the customer completes the booking, they should see an on-screen confirmation and directly receive an SMS confirmation. Guests should be able to locate the hotel on a map and choose to get directions on foot or by road using MHB technology. MHB technology should include convenience features such as enabling customers to access reservations when they are offline as well. Also, it should save credit card details for both ease of use and convenience for future reservations. Other features such as mobile check-in and using the phone as a room key and ordering room service via apps are convenient options for the users. For example the Conrad Concierge app from Hilton Worldwide acts as a full-service concierge, it allows users order room service, book hotel spa treatments, choose what kinds of bath amenities they want stocked in their bathrooms and arrange airport transportation.
    Consumers are using mobile technology in every aspect of daily life from connecting with friends to banking, and they’re increasingly showing a preference to make travel transactions through mobile apps and/or mobile-optimized websites. When users believe that using MHB technology fits well their lifestyle and the way they like to book a hotel room, they would be more likely to continuously use and recommend it to others. Due to the importance of the compatibility construct, we recommend online hotel marketers to make sure that the MHB sites and apps they implement fits well their guests’ lifestyles. They are advised to offer more personalized user experiences. Hotel brands and OTAs are also advised to tailor search results to specific user behavior and location. Furthermore, since PEOU was found to be still an important construct, MHB sites and apps should be designed in a way that they make the booking process easy by integrating the ability to login and select previously used payment information. Developers and marketers are advised to bear in mind that browsing on a mobile device is different from browsing on a computer because screens are smaller and it is more difficult to type information, thus, MHB apps and MHB sites are advised to retrieve information.
    
    7.3. Limitations and future research
    There are a few limitations of this research that should be considered when interpreting its findings. First of all, the data of the study was collected from U.S MHB users only. Future research involving data collection in other countries may offer important information for comparing cultural differences in MHB users’ loyalty intentions. In addition, since the sample size was relatively small, the results of this study may not be generalizable to different generational groups including Generation X, Generation Y and baby boomers and senior citizens. Therefore, through user segmentation with a larger sample, future research might investigate if similar results would be found in other segments of the MHB market.
    
    In this research, we did not differentiate among the various segments of the hotel industry (e.g., luxury, upscale, midscale, economy, and budget). In addition, we did not consider the booking time (e.g., last minute bookings, advance bookings). Also, there might be some potential moderating variables such as mobile coupon codes, user’s experience with m-commerce, and age. Some methodological issues can be further improved in future studies (e.g., the response rate and sample size). Future studies may deploy experimental designs to examine important constructs such as engagement, interactivity, flow, and personalization.
    
    Even though TAM is a preeminent model in explaining the acceptance of new technologies, future research may investigate the antecedents of MHB loyalty using different theoretical frameworks such as the unified theory of acceptance and use of technology (UTAUT) model. Moreover, future models are advised to include other antecedents that fit into MHB. Finally, just like any other theoretical model, the proposed model in this study does not include all potential variables that affects the endogenous variable. While it attempts to draw from diverse theories to explain the phenomenon of MHB loyalty, there certainly might be other important exogenous variables that significantly impact MHB loyalty. For instance, social norms play an important role in mobile technology adoption. People tend to use some technologies (e.g., mobile apps) just because they feel like their social environment expects them to use those technologies. In addition to social norms, value of use and security related factors may also play important roles in users behavioral intentions toward MHB technology. Future studies are advised to include such variables to increase the wholeness of the model.
    ]]></section>
</publication>