<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="gai shuangshuang">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 3, June 2016, Pages 403-413</time>
International Journal of Information Management
    <title>An empirical study of the rise of big data in business scholarship</title>
    <author>Julie Frizzo-Barker.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspace<author>Peter A. Chow-White.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspace<author>Maryam Mozafari.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspace<author>Dung Ha.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspace
GeNA Lab, School of Communication, Simon Fraser University, 8888 University Drive, Burnaby, BC V5A 1S6, Canada
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.01.006</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">Big data is a fragmented emerging domain of research theoretically and empirically.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">We identify 8 different concepts of big data from 41% of studies that defined it.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">Focus on tools, how-to, and conceptual papers indicates early stage of development.</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">Top benefits included unprecedented potential to measure and manage predictively.</highlight>
    <highlight id="5">Top challenges are lack of skillset for big data use, and privacy concerns.</highlight>

<abstract><![CDATA[
Abstract
Big data has captured the interests of scholars across many disciplines over the last half a decade. Business scholars have increasingly turned their attention to the impact of this emerging phenomenon. Despite the rise in attention, our understanding of what big data is and what it means for organizations and institutional actors remains uncertain. In this study, we conduct a systematic review on “big data” across business scholarship over the past six years (2009–2014). We analyzed 219 peer-reviewed academic papers from 152 journals from the most comprehensive business literature database. We conducted the systematic review both quantitatively and qualitatively using the data analysis software NVivo10. Our results reveal several key insights about the scholarly investigation of big data, including its top benefits and challenges. ]]> <h target="1" match="full">Overall, we found that big data remains a fragmented, early-stage domain of research in terms of theoretical grounding, methodological diversity and empirically oriented work.</h> <![CDATA[ These challenges serve to improve our understanding of the state of big data in contemporary research, and to further prompt scholars and decision-makers to advance future research in the most productive manner.
]]></abstract>
    
    <keywords>Big data</keywords>
    <keywords>Systematic review</keywords>
    <keywords>Data practices</keywords>
    <keywords>Disruptive innovation</keywords>
    
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction"><![CDATA[
1. Introduction
Over the last five years, there has been a remarkable increase in scholarship on big data across various academic disciplines including management, business and information systems. As big data technologies emerge in our networked society, a new synthesis of real-time, user-generated information and communication creates a constant flow of potential new insights for business, government, education and social initiatives. Digitally-savvy organizations are already using big data in a variety of strategic ways: to do what they have always done but better; to do something differently; to do something completely new; to co-create value with customers, or to monetize data (Petter & Peppard, 2013). But the vast majority of large and mid-sized organizations are still struggling to integrate big data into their organizational cultures. Big data represents a significant shift in thinking about data infrastructure, business intelligence and analytics, and information technology strategy, which are all key areas of impact for business and management scholars (Bharadwaj, El Sawy, Pavlou, & Venkatraman, 2013; Chen, Chiang, & Storey, 2012).
Mayer-Schönberger and Cukier (2013) argue big data is all about predictions, connections, and relationships amongst vast data sets. Beyond bigger, better, networked information, big data is chiefly defined by its novel applications. There are plenty of examples in the pages of business journals, industry magazines, and financial media. Sentiment tracking of Twitter posts has been shown to predict stock market indicators (Bollen, Mao, & Zeng 2011). Smartphone data is used to determine supply chain management and highway traffic alerts for corporate chains (Demirkan & Delen, 2013). Search query tracking has been used to predict sickness prevalence through Google Flu Trends (Lazer, Kennedy, King, & Vespignani 2014). While the term big data has become rapidly incorporated into the lexicon of industry, academia, science, and medicine, it remains an uncertain and ambiguous concept in terms of scholarship and practice.
Big data is a buzzword with a number of meanings. Some refer to big data as very large sets of data that are impossible to analyze by hand or through traditional methods, such as a spreadsheet. Massive amounts of data are generated from various sources including genomics, social media, professional sports, and weather sensors, just to name a few. Data is also moving, analyzed, and utilized at a faster and faster pace. This popular definition is called the 3 Vs: volume, variety, and velocity definition of big data (Laney, 2001; McAfee, Brynjolfsson, Davenport, Patil, & Barton, 2012). Others point out big data is more than the sum of its technical parts. It represents a social movement or cultural shift in organizations to data driven decision making (Chow-White & Green, 2013). Despite this explosion of interest the concept is uncertain and ambiguous and the applications are wide and varied.
According to the Gartner (2015) Hype Cycle methodology, once an important new technology is introduced, it progresses through a sharp peak in visibility and inflated expectations, followed by a downward slope into disillusionment, and eventually stabilizes back upwards through enlightenment and ultimately widespread productivity. The concept of big data has moved through the initial hype and disillusionment phases in public discourse, and is still in the preliminary stages of the disillusionment stage in academic research across a wide range of disciplines. This is a predictable trend based on academia’s lengthy process of review before publishing.
We explore the state of research about big data in business scholarship to understand how scholars are defining big data, where they are investigating it, and what they are finding so far. Big data is the newest example of a ‘disruptive innovation’ (Christensen, 1997, 2016; Christensen & Raynor, 2003; Hwang & Christensen, 2008) across all sub-fields of business and this creates a lot of noise. The academic literature is the space to separate scholarly signals from popular noise to understand what big data is, who is using it, and what benefits, opportunities, and risks does it present to organizations and firms? In this study, we describe the process and findings of our systematic review of big data research within business literature from 2009–2014. Systematic reviews are a form of meta-analysis designed to “summarize in an explicit way what is known and not known about a specific practice-related question” (Briner, Denyer, & Rousseau, 2009, p. 19). The field of business has been at the forefront of experimenting with big data technologies and techniques, and this study is designed to support leaders, scholars and decision-makers in thinking about the benefits, risks and gaps in our current knowledge to do with big data.
1.1. The need for a systematic review
Research-based studies of big data’s impact on business are beginning to proliferate. However, each study in this rapidly developing area is inevitably limited in scope and reflective of diverse findings. This poses a risk to the accumulation of knowledge and the integration of findings among business leaders and researchers (Briner et al., 2009). Beyond the few data-rich giants such as LinkedIn, Facebook and Google, leaders of most large and mid-sized companies remain perplexed by the highly fragmented landscape of big data technologies now available (Goes, 2014). Systematic reviews are a powerful way of addressing fragmentation as a “means of evaluating and interpreting all available research relevant to a particular research question or topic area or phenomenon of interest” (Kitchenham, 2004, p. iv). Systematic reviews are most commonly used in the medical domain. However, scholars have recently been adopting them across business, marketing and management studies as a tool for bridging the “research-practice gap” (Rousseau, 2006). We rigorously gathered, assessed, and analyzed relevant empirical studies on big data in the business literature, in order to conduct an objective synthesis of the results, which may be integrated into professional practice (Sackett et al., 2000). Our research found these relevant discussions in the journals increasing rapidly over the last six years. The research articles we review are a systematically collected set of primary studies. Our subsequent analysis of these papers is a valuable secondary study offering a more holistic view and new insights on the latest uses of big data technologies in the field of business.

]]></section>

    <section name="Methods" category="methods"><![CDATA[
2. Methods
We conducted a systematic review—an in-depth investigation of the existing knowledge about big data across the business literature. There are a number of steps involved in conducting a systematic review: (1) research design, (2) data collection, and (3) coding and analysis.

In phase 1 (research design) we developed 10 research questions (see Table 1) to guide our analysis. These include: How does the literature define (or not define) big data? What is the ratio of conceptual papers to empirical papers? What types of big data tools are represented in the studies? Which types of organizations, industries, business divisions, and countries are represented in the studies? What are some of the main benefits and challenges of big data for firms?
Table 1. Research questions.
RQ1	How does the literature define (or not define) big data?
RQ2	What is the relative proportion of conceptual and empirical papers?
RQ3	What is the relative proportion of quantitative, qualitative and mixed-method studies?
RQ4	What types of big data tools are represented in the research?
RQ5	Which types of organizations are represented in the research?
RQ6	Which industries are represented in the research?
RQ7	Which countries are represented by the research?
RQ8	What is the overall sentiment of each study?
RQ9	What are some of the top benefits of big data for business?
RQ10	What are some of the top challenges of big data for business?
Our reference: JJIM 1481.

Article reference: IJIM_2016_57.

Article title: An Empirical Study of the Rise of Big Data in Business Scholarship.

To be published in: International Journal of Information Management.


In phase 2 (data collection), we consulted several business scholars and business librarians to identify the top business databases. Our search term was simply “big data.” We first conducted an advanced search within Business Source Complete (BSC), which allowed us to narrow the search to journal articles from 2009–2014, yielding 552 results. BSC is considered one of the most comprehensive databases with 5117 journals and magazines indexed and abstracted. Next we consulted the Journal of Citation Reports (JCR) for the top business journals as of 2013, as a cross-reference to ensure we had captured results from the top journals as ranked by impact factor. There were 111 journals listed in JCR and we searched them individually. We chose the starting point of January 2009 as it coincided with the emergence of the first few scholarly papers on big data. We collected published peer-reviewed, English-language, academic journal articles in business. Our final data-set included 219 papers sourced from 152 different journals, published from 2009 to 2014 (see Figs. 1 and 2). We collected the data from 2009 to 2013 in September and October of 2014, and did a secondary search for the data from 2014 in March 2015 to ensure we captured everything published up to December 2014.
Fig. 1
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Number of publications on big data per year (Total: 219).
Fig. 2
Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Number of publications and journals publishing research on big data per year.
Prior to coding and meta-analysis, four researchers including an associate professor, a doctoral candidate, and two masters students, reviewed the extensive search results and manually assessed the papers for relevant papers (intercoder reliability score: 96.9%). Any disagreements were discussed and reconciled prior to analysis. Any articles we could not agree on were removed from the sample. Our main criterion for inclusion was the use of the term “big data” as the core technology analyzed or part of the core argument developed in the paper, typically evidenced by its emphasis in the title, abstract and/or keywords. In a few exceptional cases; papers did not explicitly mention big data in those areas yet included a substantial discussion of the topic within the paper itself; and thus were included in the sample population. From BSC; we identified 184 papers that fit our criteria; and from JCR we identified 35 additional papers beyond those that were cross-listed in both databases. We identified 184 unique papers in BSC and an additional 35 unique papers in JCR for a total of 219 papers in our population.

It should be noted that we experimented with using a big data approach to our search process, grappling with the new challenges of big data for conducting systematic reviews. But the proliferation of databases and the emergence of data warehouses like Google Scholar pose a number of problems for capturing an entire disciplinary population. First, as we found by cross-referencing just two databases, disciplinary scholarship can be spread across a number of new databases. Second, catch-all databases such as Google Scholar can produce results too large and too impractical for human coders to properly assess. Third, one of the problems we found when consulting Google Scholar for a trial run of our search was the problem of sorting out large amounts of “dirty” data. Ultimately, established traditional databases, in this case Business Source Complete and Journal of Citation Reports, offered a rigorously reviewed, comprehensive collection that we could confidently search for a systematic review.

In Phase 3 (coding), we coded and analyzed the articles in our population. We used the data analysis software NVivo10 to create a database of the articles, code them, and analyze them. We created a coding scheme which we used to classify the articles in accordance with each of the research questions. Next, we conducted iterative rounds of quantitative and qualitative analysis on each of the results. For instance, after calculating how many of the papers defined big data, we then went on to graph the trend of whether more or less papers were defining big data over time, and to sub-categorize the types of definitions. The use of NVivo10, a progressive big data tool in itself, offered a greater capacity to identify key shifts, trends and relationships amongst our data in order to perform a rigorous systematic review.

]]></section>

    <section name="Results" category="results"><![CDATA[
3. Results
3.1. RQ1: How does the literature define (or not define) big data?
Across the timeframe analyzed (2009–2014), 41% of papers defined big data, while the remaining 59% did not (Fig. 3). In addition, we found an increasing number of papers defined big data over time (Fig. 4). Scholars tend to define new terminology more frequently as it first emerges in the literature, and less so over time as the diversity of definitions crystallize and diffuse into common use. For instance, social media is rarely defined in common use or in the literature anymore, where it might have been a decade ago. We find that many papers continue to define big data in different ways throughout the period, which confirms our expectation that a common understanding of big data remains in flux in the earliest phases of research. As key concepts such as big data become institutionalized over time, these variations become more uniform, so there is less need to define them.
Fig. 3
Download full-size image
Fig. 3. Total percentages of articles defining big data.
Fig. 4
Download full-size image
Fig. 4. Number of publications that defined big data by year.
Big data has rapidly emerged as a nebulous term with a variety of definitions, in both popular discourse and scholarly research. The majority (59%) of papers do not define big data, but simply use the terminology in context.]]> <h target="2" match="full"> We found an array of definitions in 41% of the articles (see Table 2).</h><![CDATA[ The most well-known definition is the “3Vs” of big data: volume, variety and velocity (Laney, 2001). Volume is big data’s most obvious attribute. Variety describes the diversity of structured and unstructured data that can be collected. Velocity refers to how quickly data can be made available for analysis. Other papers in our population cited the “4Vs” definition which includes veracity, or the quality of data. One paper cited the “5Vs” which also adds value to the growing list of Vs, to measure the usefulness of data for an intended purpose.
Table 2. Types of definitions of big data.
Total
Size of data (rapid growth in heterogeneous massive data)	28
Business tool (extracting commercial value from data, uncovering new patterns of customer behavior)	25
3 Vs (Volume, Variety, Velocity)	23
IT Tools//New tools needed for managing huge size of data	18
Shift in architecture//New approach to understanding data	13
4 Vs (Volume, Variety, Velocity, Veracity)	8
Interplay of Technology, Analysis and Mythology (cultural, social, scholarly phenomenon)	8
5 Vs (Volume, Variety, Velocity, Veracity, Value)	1
]]> <h target="2" match="full">Table 2 also shows eight types of definitions we found among the papers that defined big data, and the number of times each definition occurred.</h><![CDATA[ Beyond the lists of Vs outlined above, we found that big data was also characterized as a business topic, an information-technology tool, a shift in architecture or new approach for collecting and using data, or simply a massive amount of data. Finally, a small group of papers identified cultural or social aspects of big data as an interplay of technology, analysis, and mythology.
3.2. RQ2: What is the relative proportion of conceptual and empirical papers?
We analyzed the relative proportion of conceptual and empirical papers to investigate research and study design in big data scholarship. Empirical papers focus on observable or measurable big data activities and processes through a variety of methodological approaches. Conceptual papers discuss ideas, applications, theories, benefits, and challenges of big data but do not collect primary data or analyze secondary data. From our total population of 219 papers we analyzed, 72% (n = 158) were conceptual in nature, and 28% (n = 61) were empirical (see Fig. 5).
Fig. 5
Download full-size image
Fig. 5. Total percentage of conceptual vs. empirical articles.
In our longitudinal analysis of the relative proportion between conceptual and empirical papers (see Fig. 6), ]]> <h target="3" match="part">we can see that the earliest years (2009–2010) included only a few conceptual papers and no empirical papers.</h><![CDATA[ However, it should be noted that the first two years of the data collection period account for only 2.2% of all 219 papers. 2011 marked the first appearance of empirical research, a survey and interview-based study conducted by MIT Sloan Management Review and the IBM Institute for Business Value (LaValle, Lesser, Shockley, Hopkins, & Kruschwitz, 2011). 2012 marked the start of a progressive increase in both conceptual and empirical papers, with conceptual papers continuing to outnumber empirical studies across each of those years (2012–2014).
Fig. 6
Download full-size image
Fig. 6. Conceptual vs. Empirical publications by year.
Within scholarship of emerging phenomenon, we observe that conceptual studies tend to precede empirical studies. New concepts typically diffuse into the literature beginning with exploratory discussion around broader ideas, predictions, opportunities and drawbacks to do with a new phenomenon, which are later tested, observed and measured empirically in practice. The conceptual papers offer useful commentary, frameworks, theories and critique of big data from a particular point of view. At the same time, the proliferation of conceptual papers indicates the newness of the field. Some of these articles rely chiefly on personal opinion, anecdotal evidence or armchair hypothesizing, which contributes to the conflicting landscape of big data research at the present. For instance, one conceptual paper states that it “represents a snapshot in time and is intentionally opinionated to reflect our teams' experiences on the ground helping clients solve their most pressing problems” (Thoughtworks, 2012). Another conceptual paper outlines various examples and applications exemplifying the big data paradigm, the technologies enabling the upsurge of big data, and the challenges involved in facilitating their widespread adoption (Adolph, 2014). These perspectives lay the groundwork for big data diffusion through the experiential accounts of early adopters.
Overall, our findings demonstrate that big data scholarship remains in the earliest phases of development, both conceptually and especially empirically, in the field of business. The next section looks more closely at our findings on empirical big data research.

3.3. RQ3: What is the relative proportion of quantitative, qualitative, and mixed-method studies?
We measured the methodologies used to identify the relative proportion of qualitative, quantitative, and mixed-method studies in the articles with empirical methods (n = 61). Overall, this sub-group of our total population was comprised of 50% qualitative studies, 39% quantitative studies and 11% mixed-method studies (see Fig. 7). Both research paradigms are equally valuable when conducted skillfully. Quantitative research provides deductive, numerical and thematic analysis, while qualitative research provides inductive, interpretive insights that enhance meaning and understanding. The empirical studies we analyzed used methodological tools such as surveys, interviews, case studies, policy analysis, social media analysis, news media analysis, and literature reviews.
Fig. 7
Download full-size image
Fig. 7. Types of Empirical Studies.
As noted above, the first empirical paper in our population appeared in 2011 (LaValle et al., 2011). The mixed-method study conducted by MIT Sloan Management Review and IBM investigated how big data and analytics can facilitate greater business insights, through a survey of nearly 3000 executives, managers and analysts from 30 industries and 100 countries, as well as in-depth interviews with leading researchers. Following this in 2012, we see the emergence of qualitative, quantitative and mixed-method empirical studies, with each category increasing in numbers to 2014 (see Fig. 8). Qualitative studies were the most popular type of empirical study in 2012 and 2013, but by 2014, quantitative studies made up the majority of empirical studies for the first time. Mixed method studies made up the smallest proportion of the studies in each year they appeared.
Fig. 8
Download full-size image
Fig. 8. Types of empirical publications by year.
The qualitative studies used research methods such as interviews, case studies and policy analysis. For example, Goyal, Hancock, and Hatami (2012) interviewed 120 sales executives about big data’s role in uncovering lucrative new micromarkets. Russell and Bennett (2014) present several case studies that illustrate how big data can improve talent management decisions and ultimately organizational performance. Gopaldas (2014) used interviews as primary data and media analysis as secondary data in order to understand marketplace sentiments, highlighting the role of human input in big data sentiment analysis. And Truyens and Eecke (2014) analyze European legislation to clarify the legal aspects of text mining.
The quantitative studies used methods such as surveys, social media analysis, web traffic analysis, text mining and behavioral experiments. For instance, He, Zha, and Li (2013) conducted a social media competitive analysis of the Facebook and Twitter sites of three top pizza chains to understand how they used social media in practice. Others predicted hotel demand via big data, by analyzing a destination marketing company’s web traffic (Yang, Pan, & Song, 2014). Scholars also used text mining to analyze 350,000 web-based consumer reviews, measuring dimensions of quality such as validity, valence, optimality and heterogeneity (Tirunillai & Tellis, 2014). As a final example, one of the studies we analyzed was the first empirical study to track the longitudinal effects of problem-solving customer participation in a peer-to-peer problem-solving community of 2542 B2B customers (Bone, Fombelle, Ray, & Lemon, 2014).
3.4. RQ4: What types of big data tools are represented in the research?
Big data’s volume, velocity and variety creates new challenges for aggregating, classifying, storing, and deciphering value out of data. Cloud computing, new programming models, and scalable high-performance databases, are emerging as big data’s core technologies. A host of diverse big data tools are referenced across 50 of studies we reviewed (23% of the sample population). We categorized them into tools focused on (1) programming models, (2) data collection, processing and storage, (3) data extraction and monitoring, and (4) data management, modelling, and analytics (see Table 3).
Table 3. Big data tools.

Some of the most important big data tools are MapReduce, a programming paradigm for large-scale, massively parallel data access, and Hadoop, an open-source software based on MapReduce designed to process and store huge datasets (terabytes or petabytes) in a scalable way through a distributed file system (Adolph, 2014). Hadoop is rooted in the open-source, tech start-up markets led by Cloudera and Hortonworks, even though top commercial database vendors such as Oracle, Microsoft and IBM have also since adopted it (Asay, 2013). Other free and open-source big data platforms include MongoDB, Spark and Storm.
Another category of big data tools we identified focus on data extraction and monitoring. With the rise of social media, customer review forums, blogs and wikis, more and more companies are using these web 2.0 platforms to provide services and interact with customers. Businesses can monitor, analyze and assess the competitive landscape for a given industry using data mining, text mining and sentiment analysis techniques, gaining insights from vast amounts of user-generated content. Software such as SocialMention, Technorati, and Radian6, are designed to interpret a company’s reputation in real time, in order to react swiftly as a socially engaged enterprise.

Data management, modelling, and analytics represent another important category of big data tools. As Chen et al. (2012) have noted, business intelligence and analytics 3.0 will require the techniques and tools to assess big data analytics in tandem with text, web, network and mobile analytics. Predictive analytics can be used to forecast consumer demands and flag exceptions, allowing companies to optimize supply chains and manage risk.
3.5. RQ5: Which types of organizations are represented in the research?
As expected, many of the papers in our sample population addressed big data in terms of how it can be used to increase organizational success. We investigated which studies in our population addressed big data in relation to organizations. Among the studies that referenced organizations, we also noted whether they were large, mid-sized, or small businesses.

We found that only 28% of the papers in our sample population overtly discussed big data in relation to particular types of organizations. Fig. 9 shows the breakdown of these of studies. Most of the studies in this group (40%) referenced big data in relation to organizations in general, without mentioning a particular company, or size of organization. For instance, some of these focus on big data in the context of real-time enterprises (RTE) or zero-friction organizations with the ability to capture and deliver “on-time data” to the right decision-makers within the organization (Habbal, 2014).
Fig. 9
Download full-size image
Fig. 9. Types of Organizations using big data.
The second largest category we identified (38%) was large organization and multi-national corporations. Most are well-known, large cap firms such as Walmart, Macy’s, Amazon, Google, Universal, Sony BMG, IBM, Hewlett-Packard, and Warner. For example, one study notes that Walmart processes over 1 million transactions per hour, generating 2.5 petabytes of customer data, or the equivalent of 167 times the books in the Library of Congress (Johnson, 2012). Another study highlights the use of social media app FourSquare to geo-target and monitor check-ins at eateries and retailers in New York City through mobile technologies, in order to analyze customer patterns at Shake Shack, Starbucks, Chipotle, and other shops (Banerjee, Viswanathan, Raman, & Ying, 2013).
Another 15% of these studies referenced big data in relation to companies of various sizes, as seen in phrases such as: “Organizations of all sizes and purposes are seeking to take advantage of the big data tsunami and the opportunities it presents” (Gabel & Tokarski, 2014). This poses a significant area for research, as big data is often associated with large corporations and big budgets. Yet, as Melo (2014) observes, “Every organization – from startups to multinationals – can achieve this analytic sophistication as cloud-based solutions allow access to advanced analytics and decision management for organizations of all sizes.”
Finally, 7% of these studies focus on small and medium enterprises (SMEs). Big data poses both a unique challenge and opportunity for these businesses. According to Lopez, “It is not uncommon to see small and midsize organizations with just a few hundred employees struggling to keep up with growing data volumes and shrinking batch windows, just as large enterprises do” (2012, p. 17). And yet, these businesses can gain significant ground by utilizing big data and its related technologies to differentiate and market themselves. For instance, one study examined the social media presence of medium-sized companies, and found that they had an average of 178 social accounts, “separate ‘voices’ speaking to communities throughout the social ‘cloud’ translating to significant business-related influence (Hlavac & Schaefer, 2013).
3.6. RQ6: Which types of industries are represented in the research?
Big data technologies are now being applied across a wide range of industries in contemporary society, from healthcare to education and sports. We were interested to see which industries were most prominently represented in the business literature, and where the gaps remained. We classified each study to determine those that related to various aspects of business operations in general, as well as more specific areas of focus such as finance and management, information technology, law, and other areas.

Since our sample population was drawn from the Business Source Complete (BSC) database, we expected to see most papers address various aspects of business. This was indeed the case, with the majority of papers (37%) highlighting various aspects of general business activities, from the organizational design challenges of big data (Galbraith, 2014) to big data and management (George, Haas, & Pentland, 2014). Other studies in this category address big data in relation to innovation, computing technologies, analytics, social media, marketing, inventory management, talent management, and customer experience.
We found that the remaining papers address big data in the context of a specific industry (see Fig. 10). Of these studies, the most popular sector researched in conjunction with big data was finance and management (22%), including various studies on banking and accounting (Bennett, 2013). The next most popular was law and governance (17%), with studies on the military, policy-making, and national security (Bertot, Gorham, Jaeger, Sarin, & Choi, 2014). Information technology (IT) was another sector represented (13%), covering topics such as data analysis, technical platforms, crowdsourcing, and information systems strategy (Whittington, 2014). Healthcare represented 2% of studies, including studies on genomics, medicine, hospitals and drug administration (Miller & Tucker, 2014). Education also represented 2%, examining big data in relation to higher education, research and libraries (Radenković, Despotović-Zrakić, Bogdanović, Barać, & Labus, 2014). Finally, a diverse group of “other” industries were identified (7%), including studies on trade and manufacturing, agriculture, music and entertainment, insurance, media, non-governmental organizations, and the environment.
Fig. 10
Download full-size image
Fig. 10. Types of Industries using big data.
3.7. RQ7: Which countries are represented by the research?
We identified the country of origin associated with each of the articles in our population in order to assess global contributations to big data research. The vast majority of scholarship on big data focuses on the U.S. context (see Fig. 11). North American scholarship accounts for 86% of the total big data research papers published since 2009 (n = 189). The United States in particular produced most of these (n = 187), with two Canadian studies making up the total number. Again, we searched for English-only studies within Business Source Complete (BSC), the world’s definitive scholarly full-text business database. We acknowledge that scholarship in other databases or other languages may reflect a different breakdown.
Fig. 11
Download full-size image
Fig. 11. Countries of origin represented in the literature.
European research represented the second-largest hub of big data scholarship, producing 12% of the total population analyzed. Within Europe, the top contributors were various countries within the European Union (EU), including studies from Serbia, Romania, and Switzerland (n = 11) and the United Kingdom (n = 10). In one article, for example, the Berlin Commissioner for Data Protection and Freedom of Information explores the benefits and concerns of a major proposed reform to the EU’s data protection rules, which would harmonize 28 separate legal frameworks, affecting Europe’s economy, innovation and civil rights (Dix et al., 2013).
The third continent represented in our population was Asia, including studies from Singapore, Hong Kong, and India, accounting for less than 1% of the total population (n = 3). For instance, one paper outlined how DBS Bank in Singapore is implementing big data analytics to enhance customer service (Ng, 2012). Overall these country-based findings demonstrate that although big data has attracted tremendous attention from a variety of scholars and practitioners, it remains limited in terms of international perspective and global diversity. There are noticable global ‘holes’ in the research agenda such as Africa and South America.
3.8. RQ8: What is the overall sentiment of each study?
We used sentiment analysis to illuminate shifting perceptions of big data across the timeframe analyzed (Fig. 12). In the broader context of public discourse on big data, we have already observed the pendulum swing: following a frenzy of excitement, predictions and news headlines, big data was voted as the ”most hated buzzword of 2013” by business executives (Datoo, 2014). In terms of academic scholarship, the lengthier timelines of research and publishing result in the slightly delayed circulation of big data knowledge. In order to assess how the field is developing and maturing, we coded our sample population to decipher the general tone toward big data in each study, whether positive or negative.
Fig. 12
Download full-size image
Fig. 12. Overall sentiment about big data.
We found that the vast majority of the studies in our sample population (85%) treated big data with a highly positive sentiment. This was often easily identified from the tone of the headlines themselves, such as, ”Making Advanced Analytics Work for You” (Barton & Court, 2012), ”CFOs Take Notice: Big Data may be your new Best Friend” (Clayton, 2013), and ”Mining the Past to see the Future” (Cokins, 2014). ]]> <h target="5" match="part">To clarify, many of these positive papers address challenges to do with big data, yet the challenges are framed as obstacles to overcome in order to achieve the desired outcomes of using big data as a tool for business success. </h> <![CDATA[ In that sense, the overall sentiment towards big data remains positive.
The remaining studies (15%) explore negative, cautious, or doubtful sentiments. In this category, we coded those studies that focused mainly on concerns, skepticism or major drawbacks to do with big data. The papers generally explore technical difficulties, privacy, and ethical issues, as evidenced in titles such as, ”How Big Data Enables Economic Harm to Customers” (Newman, 2014), ”Can Big Data Deliver on its Promise?” (Durand, 2012), and ”Critical Questions for Big Data” (Boyd & Crawford, 2012). Papers focused on these big data pitfalls first emerged in our sample population in 2011.
The emergence of skepticism is not necessarily an indication that big data is less valuable than originally predicted. Rather, it indicates the start of an important phase of critical research, awareness, and embeddedness as well as a shift to empirically oriented research. According to Gartner’s hype curve, big data’s transformational impact will only start to become clear over the next several years (Heudecker, 2013). Earlier this year, Gartner VP distinguished analyst Betsy Burton (2015) explained why Gartner has recently retired the big data hype cycle: it has ”quickly moved over the peak of inflated expectations, and become prevalent in our lives, as well as part of a number of other hype cycles.” This is reminiscent of the Internet itself, which emerged as a disruptive technology in the marketplace, and subsequently became a foundational element of modern business. As big data tools become more widely used in the market, organizations will become more well-versed and realistic about how to best use these technologies.
3.9. RQ9: What are some of the top benefits of big data for business?
Businesses have historically turned to large amounts of data and analytics to inform strategy and decision making, so why is big data making such an impact right now, and what are some of the top benefits? Firstly, data itself has become easier to collect, through web clicks, RFID tags, sensors, loyalty cards and barcodes. Secondly, data has become cheaper to store and analyze through some of the big data tools outlined above, and the volume capacity and performance quality of these tools is steadily increasing. This means more businesses than ever have the opportunity to tap into new insights.

At a foundational level, one of the most powerful benefits of big data is simply the greater availability, visibility, and transparency of information. As businesses collect and analyze both structured and unstructured data, decision-makers can gain a clearer picture of employee performance, product supply chain, service quality, customer satisfaction, and the competitive landscape (Fanning & Grant, 2013; Milliken 2014; Tirunillai & Tellis, 2014). When the inner workings of an organization are brought to light, there is the potential for problem-solving and optimization. Data analysts and data-mining techniques can find new patterns and connections at a more granular level than was previously possible by virtue of the fact that this type of data is collected and made available for analysis.
]]> <h target="4" match="full">Another one of the most resounding benefits we found across the population, is big data’s unprecedented potential to help businesses measure and manage predictively.</h><![CDATA[ This is made possible by sophisticated, real-time analytics that can increase the speed and accuracy of decision-making. For instance, banks can manage delinquency levels more effectively, auto manufacturers can forecast which parts of vehicles may be most prone to break down and offer preventative maintenance, and retailers can predict which customers will stop shopping and offer them incentives to return (Melo 2014; Shu, 2014).
Big data also enables businesses to market products and services in a new way. Marketers can map consumer purchase paths through social media monitoring, campaign-tracking data, clickstream analysis, and product review forums, to ascertain which methods are the most effective (Spenner & Freeman, 2012). Crowdsourcing through big data can spark improved product development or identify customer needs to create new businesses. This type of data allows firms to better understand customer heterogeneity, or personal preference, and to spend marketing budgets in more targeted ways that increase return on investment
3.10. RQ10: What are some of the top challenges of big data for business?
]]> <h target="5" match="part">As with any disruptive technology, big data technologies introduce new challenges and problems to overcome, alongside the benefits they produce. The two most prominently discussed in our sample population are the lack of skillsets or tools required to carry out big data strategies, and concerns about privacy and surveillance, followed by various disruptions of conventional methods, labour, and legality.</h> 

        <h target="5" match="part"><![CDATA[The most prevalent challenges reflected in the literature center on exactly how to take advantage of the unprecedented scale of available data. This includes the new need for data scientists and programmers versed in big data applications, as well as the integration of new technical tools required to collect, store, analyze and use big data (Dobre & Xhafa, 2014).]]></h> <![CDATA[For instance, since tools and techniques for extracting data have proliferated more quickly than analytical tools, many companies are overwhelmed by the sheer volume of data they’re able to collect, but unable to identify the truly valuable pieces of information from the flood, which in turn slows down the very processes they were intended to sharpen (Gobble, 2013). Beyond talent and technology issues, the desire to incorporate big data into business challenges organizational structures themselves, as new workflows and incentives must be designed to prioritize data-driven decision-making (Fanning & Grant, 2013).]]>
        <h target="5" match="part"><![CDATA[The second most prevalent challenge of big data relates to the risk of data privacy and ethical infringements, which cut across the whole big data lifecycle from collection and combination to analysis and use (Cumbley & Church, 2013).]]></h><![CDATA[ As data becomes more valuable and more prevalent, illegal markets for lucrative personal data also emerge (Pasquale, 2015). Increases in computing power and data linkages fuel fears of identity exploitation, massive online data breaches and automated identification technologies (Knight & Saxby, 2014). As consumers become more aware of these potential risks, they are less inclined to embrace products and services involving tracking technologies such as cookies or GPS trackers to collect personal data. In legal terms, big data innovation has raced ahead of existing policy, so organizations will need to address risks related to security, intellectual property and liability, before they become public relations crises.
Other concerns reported in the literature include the cost versus benefit of using big data for decision-making, the validation and integrity of collected data, and the complexities of dealing with highly distributed data sources (McNeely & Hahm, 2014). The excitement around big data has sparked the urgent notion to get on board with the latest technologies, or risk getting left behind the competition. But with a wide variety of concerns and obstacles to overcome in order to use big data in an effective, lucrative, and ethical way, recent scholarship on big data challenges is perhaps some of the most valuable information in our population.

]]></section>

    <section name="Conclusion" category="conclusion"><![CDATA[
4. Conclusion
Although the field is in its earliest stages of scholarly development, we found clear evidence of the energy and increasing interest focused on big data studies in business. Several key conclusions warrant further discussion in order to track the advancement of big data research. Despite the newness of the big data domain, a rapidly proliferating body of scholarship is evident across the field of business. Yet our data shows that this scholarship remains in the preliminary stages of investigating a new phenomenon. This is evident from the relative proportion of conceptual to empirical papers (72–28% respectively, see Fig. 5 and RQ3 above). Particularly within academic domains that reflect a nexus of many different disciplinary influences, such as big data, methodological diversity is to be expected. We found that empirical studies on big data are increasing year on year, and tracking the results of these types of studies over the next few years will be a good indicator of the growing maturity of the field.
Another reflection of the newness of this scholarship is its general orientation toward certain topics of interest and blind spots toward others. For instance, we identified a focus on big data tools, which we found included in nearly a quarter of the studies we reviewed (23%). This theme indicates one of the practical concerns of the emerging phenomenon at hand: what tools, processes and infrastructure do organizations need to develop or augment to capitalize on the benefits of big data? This finding also reflects one of the blind spots we identified: much of the literature is more focused on the what or how type questions around integrating big data into business, but far less on whether or even if all organizations or their stakeholders will benefit from using big data. These gaps in the literature are typical limitations of early growth in any burgeoning field. According to our findings on sentiment, only 15% of studies focused on critical, ethical or socio-economic aspects of big data. There is also a growing literature outside of business focused on the politics of big data algorithms. This would be a productive direction to further develop in the field of business, based on some of the good examples highlighted in our study above (Newman, 2014; Durand, 2012; boyd & Crawford 2012).
In this systematic review, we noted the limitations in the literature relating to small and medium enterprises (RQ5), and the lack of global diversity (RQ7). Big data represents a disruptive innovation for both organizations smaller than corporations, as well as the global community. Future empirical work is necessary to determine what types of data-driven best practices are most useful for diverse users − whether small data, better data, or big data turn out to be the best solutions.

Based on these conclusions, according to the Gartner Hype Cycle (2015), big data research within business scholarship has progressed through the first phase, the peak of inflated expectations, and is beginning to engage in the second phase, the trough of disillusionment. Further empirical research on big data in business will help to establish consistent concepts and conventions, and propel the domain through the final stages of the Hype Cycle and toward increased usefulness: the slope of enlightenment and the plateau of productivity. Based on the growing trend of empirical studies, we expect to see more studies in the near future with an eye toward which big data techniques work and which do not, in the context of practical application.
]]></section>
</publication>