<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="gai shuangshuang">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 5, October 2016, Pages 686-699</time>
    <title>An empirical investigation of information sharing behavior on social commerce sites</title>
    <author>Libo Liu.</author>Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Christy M.K. Cheung.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Matthew K.O. Lee.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacec. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
Department of Business Technology and Entrepreneurship, Faculty of Business and Law, Swinburne University of Technology, Australia
b
<![CDATA[Department of Finance & Decision Sciences, Hong Kong Baptist University, 8/F The Wing Lung Bank Building for Business Studies, 34 Renfrew Road, Kowloon Tong, Kowloon, Hong Kong]]>
c
Department of Information Systems, City University of Hong Kong, 83 Tat Chee Avenue, Kowloon Tong, Hong Kong
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.03.013</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">This study highlights the role of directed social network and examines its impact on information sharing behavior.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">The model was test by analyzing data collected with both subjective and objective approaches in a longitudinal setting.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">This study examines customer information sharing behavior in a new social media context – social commerce sites.</highlight>
Abstract
    <abstract>Social commerce sites (SCSs), a new model of social media, provide fertile ground for customers to communicate their opinions and exchange product- or service- related information. Given the significant opportunities related to the use of social media data for customers’ insight, we explore the factors driving information sharing behavior on SCSs. In this paper, we propose and empirically test a comprehensive theoretical model for customer information sharing behavior through analysis of online survey data as well as network and behavioral usage data of over four months from 1177 customers in a SCS.  <h target="2" match="full">The research model was empirically validated with the use of both subjective and objective data in a longitudinal setting.</h> <![CDATA[ Our results show that customer information sharing is influenced by both individual (i.e., reputation and the enjoyment of helping others) and social capital (i.e., out-degrees’ post, in-degrees’ feedback, customer expertise and reciprocity) factors. ]]> <h target="1" match="full">This study contributes to the existing literature by highlighting the role of directed social network in customer information sharing behavior on SCSs.</h><![CDATA[ We believe that the results of our study offer important insights to the IS research and practice.]]></abstract>
Keywords
    <keywords>Customer information sharing behavior</keywords>
    <keywords>Social commerce sites</keywords>
    <keywords>Directed social network</keywords>
    <keywords>Social mediaSocial capital</keywords>
    <keywords>Panel data</keywords>
    <keywords>Survey</keywords>
    <keywords>Longitudinal study</keywords>
    <section name=" Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
Social commerce sites (SCSs) become popular online social venues in which customers communicate their opinions and exchange product- or service- related information (Hajli, 2015; Kim & Park, 2013; Olbrich & Holsing, 2011; Pagani & Mirabello, 2011). On sites such as Pinterest.com, Svpply.com, and TheFancy.com, users can share their favorite products, create collections, and interact with other users. Such sites connect users, and let them browse, share, recommend, and rate products. Social commerce sites are growing at amazing rates. For example, Pinterest.com attracted 70 million global users as of July 2013 since its launch in 2010 (Horwitz, 2013), and has more than 100 million active users as of September 2015 (Issac, 2015), making it as one of the fastest growing sites. Prior literature confirmed that online shared product or service opinions and experiences have a significantly influence on customers’ purchasing decisions (Cheung & Thadani, 2012; Zhu & Zhang, 2010). In 2013, Nielsen Company1 revealed that nearly 85% of consumers reviewed online user-generated context before conducting online or offline transaction. To date, the behavior of information sharing on SCSs received limited attention in the Information Systems (IS) literature. Given that SCSs have the potential to transform the way customers acquire and process product- or service- related information, it is of unavoidable importance for academics and practitioners to understand information sharing behaviors of customers on this new form of social media. In particular, it is crucial to understand the reasoning behind customers’ willingness to spend their time and effort to contribute and exchange information on SCSs.
Information sharing on SCSs is different from traditional customer reviews in the sense that it focuses on social networks, whereas traditional customer reviews are shared with unknown online crowds. Marsden (2009) revealed that 83% of online customers are willing to share product- or service- related information with their friends, and 67% of online customers are more likely to make their purchase decisions based information provided by social network communities. Trusov, Bucklin, and Pauwels (2009) reported that user-generated content on SCSs is seen as a reliable and valuable asset that has significant influence on purchase decisions. Therefore, it is important to understand the factors that influence the willingness of customers to share product- or service- related information on SCSs. Such insights into customers' information sharing behaviors will help us to better understand the popularity of this phenomenon of social commerce, and also assist businesses to develop and improve their social media marketing strategy.
The knowledge management literature (Chai, Das, & Rao, 2011; Chang & Chuang, 2011; Chiu, Hsu, & Wang, 2006; Wasko & Faraj, 2005) acknowledged the importance of social capital in information sharing behaviors on social network sites. Most studies examined the impact of social capital (i.e., cognitive, relational, and structural dimensions) on information sharing in online communities. In this study, we attempt to better understand the influence of directed network structure and other individual factors on customer information sharing behavior on SCSs. Relative to traditional e-commerce sites, SCSs integrate social media functionalities that lead to development of relationships among individuals and groups of customers. Specifically, customers can “follow” other customers and/or “being followed” by others on SCSs. More important, the role of directed network structure has been examined in various contexts, such as inter- and intra- firm networks of formal or informal nature (Rindfleisch & Moorman, 2001) and collaborative group networks (Burt, 2009; Grewal, Lilien, & Mallapragada, 2006). However, the correlation between directed social network structure and customer information sharing behavior on SCSs remains unknown. ]]> <h target="1" match="full">We draw on social capital theory to examine the role of directed social networks as well as individual factors in customer information sharing behavior on SCSs.</h> <![CDATA[
We also notice that most of the existing studies on information sharing behaviors used a subjective approach to explore how and why individuals contribute knowledge to online communities (Chiu et al., 2006; Hennig Thurau, Gwinner, Walsh, & Gremler, 2004; Wasko & Faraj, 2005). In other words, prior studies mainly obtained data from surveys or case studies that are considered to be subjective in respect to the nature of data. These data collection approaches do not take into account the actual usage data that measures information sharing behavior on social media sites. Furthermore, prior studies on information sharing in online communities mostly utilized cross-sectional data collection (Boughzala & Briggs, 2012; Chiu et al., 2006; Ma & Agarwal, 2007; Sun, Fang, & Lim, 2012; Wasko & Faraj, 2005). To address the identified gaps in the literature, we combine subjective (i.e., survey) and objective (i.e., network data and actual usage data) methods to explore the impact of social capital and other individual factors on customer information sharing behavior on SCSs. Moreover, the current study considers a longitudinal design to empirically illustrate the relationship between key antecedent variables and customer information sharing.
To summarize, we believe this study makes four significant contributions. First, previous work has primarily focused on information sharing in traditional online communities.]]><h target="3" match="full"> This study examines customer information sharing behavior in a new social media model—SCSs. </h> <h target="1" match="full"> Second, we consider the directed social network structure and examine its impact on customer information sharing behavior on SCSs.</h> <![CDATA[ Third, the evidence found in most of the previous studies was derived from data collected through a subjective approach (e.g., surveys or case studies).]]> <h target="2" match="part"> In this study, we empirically test our research model by analyzing data collected with both subjective (i.e., an online survey study) and objective (i.e., network and behavioral usage data from a real SCS) approaches. Finally, we also empirically validate the research model in a longitudinal setting.</h><![CDATA[

We have organized the rest of this paper as follows: In the first section, we present the theoretical background and literature. Then, we provide a conceptual model for customer information sharing on SCSs. After describing our data source, we explain our empirical strategy and present the results of our data analysis. Finally, we conclude with a discussion of the implications for theory and practice.]]></section>
    <section name="Theoretical background and literature review" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Theoretical background and literature review
The literature has provided us with a rich theoretical foundation on which to build our research model that explains customers’ willingness to share information in online communities. In this section, we first elaborate on the distinctive social media features of SCSs, we then introduce the theoretical foundation of our study. Finally, we review relevant literature on customer information sharing behavior.

2.1. Social commerce sites
Social commerce is defined as “a subset of e-commerce that involves using social media to assist in e-commerce transactions and activities” (Liang & Turban, 2011; p. 6). Enabled by ubiquitously accessible and scalable communication techniques, social commerce has substantially changed the way customers and retailers communicate. Particularly, the linkage of online shopping and social networking sites initiate a new form of communities, namely SCSs (Hajli, 2015; Olbrich & Holsing, 2011). Social commerce includes various social elements into its core functionalities, which is the main difference in relation to traditional e-commerce. SCSs integrate social functionalities such as customer ratings and reviews, user recommendations and referrals, social shopping tools and online communities. These social functionalities create a trusted environment in which friends, family, and acquaintances dynamically interact and contribute content to the referral and promotion of products or services through positive, negative feedback, reviews, ratings, and testimonials. In other words, the traditional research and purchase cycles of online shopping behaviors are shortened through the establishment of a single destination powered by the collective intelligence (Bai, Yao, & Dou, 2015; Laudon & Traver, 2009). Being brought about by the integration of Web 2.0 technologies, e-business opportunities, and online communities, social commerce has several representative functionalities. The success of social commerce lies in the critical mass of buyers and sellers that in turn benefit from the network effects of interactions and contribution. Consequently, users can add personal information on their profiles that is displayed on the home page. They can add self-disclosure tags about styles they like, hobbies and interests. They can also post personal and vision statements. Social commerce leverage algorithmic data management and customer self-service to reach diverse customer segments. Thus, a primary functionality of SCSs is sharing favorite products or services. Users can upload product images or post product or services links. Users can also add tags and descriptions to products or services and organize the same in collections. Most SCSs embed social networking functions. A user can subscribe to another user’s sharing by “following” him/her. The following relationship does not need mutual consent, nor has to be reciprocal. The number of followings a user has indicates his/her immersion in the community and attention paid to others’ sharing. The number of followers a user has indicates his/her popularity in the community and others’ attention paid to his/her product or service sharing. Furthermore, social networking features in SCSs enable customers to observe following customers’ behaviors (i.e., out-degrees’ post) as well as to obtain feedback and appreciation from follower customers (i.e., in-degrees’ feedback).
In SCSs, customers exchange information about products and services, and get advice from trusted individuals (Leitner & Grechenig, 2009) so that they will make more accurate purchase decisions. Previous studies have emphasized the important role of trust in social commerce (Hsiao, Lin, Wang, Lu, & Yu, 2010; Kim & Park, 2013). Hsiao et al. (2010) proposed a framework for investigating the effects of trust in product referrals and trust in websites on the intention to purchase products in social shopping. Kim and Park (2013) indicated that trust is a key factor in social commerce. They further investigated that reputation and size of the s-commerce site, safety controls, and cost benefits can play critical roles in fostering this trust. Zhou, Zhang, and Zimmermann (2013) provided a review of social commerce research and practice in light of the wide attention it has drawn in the industry. They proposed a research framework with an integrated view of social commerce that consists of four key components: business, technology, people, and information to understand the development of social commerce research and practice to date. In summary, previous studies in SCSs focused on how social commerce influence customer purchase decision. In this study, we will explore SCSs from another perspective to explore the factors driving information sharing behavior on SCSs.
2.2. Social capital theory and information sharing behavior
Social capital has been primarily defined as a set of social resources embedded in relationships (Loury, 1998). Coleman and Coleman (1994) espoused a broader definition of social capital, including not only social relationships but also associated values. Social capital is concerned with the aspect of social structure that creates value and facilitates actions of individuals within a social structure (Coleman & Coleman, 1994). Based on a comprehensive review of relevant studies, Nahapiet and Ghoshal (1998, p. 243) defined social capital as “the sum of the actual and potential resources embedded within, and derived from the network relationships possessed by an individual or social unit”. Social capital is used to describe the resources embedded in social networks that are accessed and used by actors for social interactions (Lin, 2002).
Social capital was initially cited in community studies, as crosscutting long-standing personal relationships that represent basis for trust, cooperation, and collective action (Jacobs, 1961). Nahapiet and Ghoshal (1998) regarded social capital as an integrative framework for understanding information sharing in organizations. They suggested that information combination and exchange is facilitated when: (1) structural links or connections exist among individuals (structural capital); (2) individuals have the cognitive capability to understand and apply knowledge (cognitive capital); and (3) their relationships have strong and positive characteristics (relational capital). These forms of social capital constitute the combination and exchange of knowledge among individuals within a social structure. Moreover, Wasko and Faraj (2005) identified three key dimensions of social capital: cognitive, structural, and relational. Authors further explored the roles that these dimensions play in information sharing on electronic networks of practice. Nahapiet and Ghoshal’s model focused on group-level social capital factors, whereas that of Wasko and Faraj focused on individual-level information sharing. The results of these two studies suggest that social capital is widely recognized as exhibiting a duality: (1) at the group level, social capital reflects the affective nature and quality of relationships; (2) at the individual level, it facilitates customers’ actions and reflects their access to resources (Coleman & Coleman, 1994; Lin, 2002).
2.2.1. Structural capital
Structural dimension of social capital refers to the overall pattern of links between actors (Nahapiet & Ghoshal, 1998). The manifestations of structural dimension are network ties and network configuration (See Table 1). Network ties include strong and weak ties. Strong ties are typified as being close and by having intensive interaction, while weak ties are typified as being distant and by having infrequent interaction (Granovetter, 1973). Granovetter (1973) theorized that the weak ties were more likely to be sources of novel information, because strong ties tended to be connected to others who were close with the seeker that the information possessed by them is already well known by the seeker. Subsequent research on the importance of weak ties has demonstrated that weak ties can be instrumental, such as in finding a job, diffusion of ideas (Rogers, 1995), disclosure of public information (Uzzi & Lancaster, 2003), and finding technical advice (Constant, Sproull, & Kiesler, 1996). On the other hand, strong ties have been reported to be important because the strong-tie friends are more accessible and willing to be helpful (Krackhardt, 1992). Further, many studies have shown that strong ties are important conduits of useful knowledge (e.g., Hansen, 1999; Uzzi, 1996). The most frequently mentioned structural capital development is the accumulation of ‘weak ties’ and maintaining of ‘strong ties’. Some researchers suggest that the maintaining of ‘strong ties’ in an online environment is much less used than the accumulation of ‘weak ties’, because individuals’ strong ties maintain their social capital through several channels so that the communication in one particular type of online site is not that necessary (Haythornthwaite, 2005). For the accumulation of ‘weak ties’, empirical results indicate that online social network sites could increase the number of weak ties because these ties are cheaply and easily maintained (Steinfield, Ellison, & Lampe, 2008). Ellison has found that the intensity of Facebook usage is positively associated with both weak tie and strong tie social capital among college students (Ellison, Steinfield, & Lampe, 2007).
Table 1. Social capital factors facilitating information sharing in online communities.
Structural Capital	Construct	Facilitate Information Sharing	Source
Network ties	Network structure	Decentralized network facilitate information distribution.	Robert et al. (2008)
Network configuration	Centrality	High levels of network centrality enable individuals to share more information	Wasko and Faraj (2005)
Social interaction	Social interactivity	Opportunity to interact and communicate with other members	Phang, Kankanhalli, and Sabherwal (2009)
Social interaction ties	A cost-effective way of assessing a wider range of information sources	Chiu et al. (2006)
Social interaction	Actor that is central in a network of social interactions likely has greater potential to combine and exchange resources with other actors in the network	Tsai and Ghoshal (1998)
Relational Capital	Construct	Facilitate Information Sharing	Source
Trust	Trust	Trust creates intrinsic motivation to share information	Chiu et al. (2006)
Norms	Norms of reciprocity	Participants expect mutual reciprocity which can justify their effort in information sharing actives	Chiu et al. (2006)
Wasko and Faraj (2005)
Identification	Identification	Sense of belonging and positive feeling toward community	Chiu et al. (2006)
Perceived identity verification	Similar identity helps to build relationships with each other	Ma and Agarwal (2007)
Obligations	Commitment	Commitment to a collective conveys a sense of responsibility to help others	Wasko and Faraj (2005)
Cognitive Capital	Construct	Facilitate Information Sharing	Source
Shared codes	Knowledge tracking fulfillment	Systems supported ability to track information activities	Phang et al. (2009)
Shared language	Shared language	Facilitating common understanding of collective ways of acting in virtual community	Chiu et al. (2006)
Sun et al. (2012)
Shared value, vision	Shared vision	Common goals and interests that members of a virtual community share will help them see the meaning of information	Chiu et al. (2006)
Sun et al. (2012)
Tenure	User Tenure	Facilitating information sharing practice	Wasko and Faraj (2005)
Expertise	User Expertise	Facilitating information sharing skills and capability	Wasko and Faraj (2005)
2.2.2. Relational capital
Relational dimension of social capital refers to the assets created and leveraged through relationships such as respect and friendship, which bond the actors together and influence their behavior (Nahapiet & Ghoshal, 1998). The most important factors are: (1) trust and trustworthiness, (2) norms and sanctions, and (3) identity and identification (Nahapiet & Ghoshal, 1998) (See Table 1).
The trust literature (Schoorman, Mayer, & Davis, 2007) provides considerable evidence that trusting relationships lead to greater knowledge exchange: when trust exists, people are more willing to give useful knowledge (Levin & Cross, 2004). According to Lewicki, McAllister, and Bies (1998), trust is defined as the trustor’s confident positive expectations regarding the trustee’s conduct. In fact, this definition has been quoted for many times by other researchers (Tomlinson & Lewicki, 2006). There is also a popular definition of trust, which is the willingness of a party to be vulnerable to the actions of another party (Mayer, Davis, & Schoorman, 1995). There are three main trust research streams: personality-based trust, institutional-based trust and cognition-based trust, which can partially explain trust (McKnight, Cummings, & Chervany, 1998). Each research stream includes some factors: personality-based factors, institutional-based factors and cognition-based factors, which would influence trust. The object of institution-based trust is a specific context and that of cognition-based trust is one person or vendor (McKnight, Kacmar, & Choudhury, 2004), from which we can find that institution-based trust represents the macro level trust and cognition-based trust represents the micro level trust. Findings are consistent that social norms are antecedents to information sharing behavior (Bock, Zmud, & Lee, 2005; Hsu & Lin, 2008).
2.2.3. Cognitive capital
Cognitive dimension of social capital refers to those resources that provide shared representative actions, interpretations, and systems of meaning among parties. The most representative facets include: (1) shared language and codes, and (2) shared narratives (Nahapiet & Ghoshal, 1998) (See Table 1). Shared language and codes, and the shared narratives could promote information sharing. (1) The communication among individuals is more effective due to the shared understanding (Cabrera & Cabrera, 2005). (2) Shared codes and narratives could exclude others (Johnson, Lorenz, & Lundvall, 2002) in order for the cohesion of the community to be enhanced. Since shared language and codes can provide the basis for a response to the problem of co-ordination and make the combining of knowledge easier, the organizational learning capability is enhanced so that the information sharing outcomes will be better. Cognitive capital development relates to the enhancement of shared language, codes, and narratives. One of the online social shopping communities’ features is appreciate others’ posts (e.g., “liking”, “comments” and “forwards”). Such activities can promote the publicity and diffusion of posts, and thus direct other customers to view the same narratives.
2.3. Social network theory
Social network refers to a set of nodes (actors) and the set of ties representing relationship or absence of a relationship between the nodes (actors). The actors and the corresponding set of ties can be depicted in the form of a network diagram. There are three types of social networks: whole networks, personal networks and partial networks. The whole network is to describe the characteristics of a complete network within a clearly demarked population. Personal network has tended to examine the differences in the size, structure, and patterns of personal networks. Partial network is the result of using snowballing sampling techniques, where not all the actors in a network will be captured but the analysis goes beyond the comparison of personal networks towards the identification of important actors and strengths of ties between actors.

Social network theory is to understand how social networks facilitate and constrain the flows of information and resources between actors, and hence cognitions, opportunities, and behaviors (Tindall & Wellman, 2001). It emphasizes the importance of the structure of the network and interactions between actors within the network (Caniëls & Romijn, 2008). Social network theory has been developed and applied across a variety of research domain, including global economy (Scott, 1997), and health (Fowler & Christakis, 2008). Researchers also have been able to explain variance in traditional organizational outcomes (i.e., individual satisfaction or performance) by using social network perspective. A social network perspective is employed to model the structure of a social group, how this structure influences other variables, or how structures change over time. The study of these structures uses methods in social network analysis to identify influential nodes, local and global structures, and network dynamics.
2.4. Directed social network
Many organizational studies attempted to use social network perspective to explain the patterns of interactions and exchange within social units (Borgatti & Foster, 2003). Prior studies suggested the important role of social interaction structures in determining the accessibility of valued resources (Brass, 1992; Ibarra, 1993a, 1993b). The social network structure of social commerce is significantly different from one of e-commerce. Specifically, customers can subscribe to another customer by simply “following” him/her. Customer also can “be followed” by other customers. It is so called following and follower on social media. Followings, followers and focal customers form the directed social network (as shown in Fig. 1). The directed online social network structure of SCSs has two types of network ties: following (out-degree tie) and being followed (in-degree tie). All ties in SCSs have direction (i.e., relationship on Twitter) rather than mutual relationship (i.e., relationship on Facebook). The network structure of SCSs is directed in nature. Thus, the relationship between the structure of directed online social networks and customer information sharing behavior is worthy for study. Furthermore, social features in SCSs enable customers to observe following customers’ behaviors (e.g., through following other customer) as well as to obtain feedback and appreciation from follower customers (e.g., through being followed by other customer) (Chen, Wang, & Xie, 2011). The impact of these key features of SCSs on customer information sharing behavior can be explained through the structural capital in directed social network.
Fig. 1
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Ego centric directed social network.
One of the central themes in social capital theory is that “who you know” affects “what you know”. The fundamental proposition is that network ties provide access to resources. However, for structural capital, the previous literature focuses more on the network tie than network resource. Research on structural capital often focuses on the social network structure (Wasko & Faraj, 2005), as opposed to social interaction. Like Wasko and Faraj (2005) limited the measure of structural capital to the centrality of network. They only measured the linkage between actors instead of social interaction embedded within linkage. It has been argued that topological studies of networks often neglect the resource flowing between actors and focus on the network structure perspectives (Lin, 2002). Although these authors agree on the significance of relationships as resource for structural capital, they lack consensus on a precise measurement of structural capital. Other studies took social interaction into account to measure structural capital, like Chiu et al. (2006) and Sun et al. (2012). However they used perceived social interaction to measure structural capital. Straub, Limayem, and Karahanna-Evaristo (1995) argued that actual behavior and perceived behavior were not always congruent. It is not precise to use perceived social interaction to measure actual social interaction behavior.
Therefore, we bridge the gap between the network tie and social interaction views by showing that actual social interaction can generate more precise measurement for structural capital. Measuring the actual social interaction inside a network is difficult, because it is hard to have a direct observation of the individual’s browsing information. To the best of our knowledge, actual social interaction behavior has not been widely used before. In this study we adopt the view and define structural capital as the sum of the actual social interaction derived from the network of relationships possessed by an individual. It is measured by actual social interaction behavior embedded in directed social network structure including: out-degrees’ post (i.e., followings’ post) and in-degrees’ feedback (i.e., followers’ comments). Out-degrees’ post measures how much information an individual’s get from social network. In-degrees’ feedback is related to how much response an individual get from the social network.

2.5. Customer information sharing behavior
Information sharing has been an important area of IS research for nearly two decades (Alavi & Leidner, 2001; Jarvenpaa & Staples, 2000; Ma & Agarwal, 2007; Nunamaker & Briggs, 2011; Sambamurthy & Subramani, 2005; Cheung, Liu, & Lee, 2015). Given the increasing proliferation of the Internet, individuals from diverse organizational, national, and cultural backgrounds are able to easily exchange information with other in online community (Nunamaker & Briggs, 2011; Sen, Raghu, & Vinze, 2010; Wenger, 1998). In recent years, considerable research efforts were directed to understand how and why customers post their opinions, comments, and reviews of products or services on social media (see Appendix). Some researchers (Cheung & Thadani, 2012; Dellarocas, Gao, & Narayan, 2010; Hennig Thurau et al., 2004) associated these behaviors with electronic word of mouth (eWOM), and explained it from a motivational perspective with an emphasis on perceived benefits and costs. For example, Hennig Thurau et al. (2004) identified five motivational categories of customer information sharing behaviors: focused-related utility, consumption utility, approval utility, moderator-related utility, and homeostasis utility. In our study, we pay attention to the directed network structure of SCSs and explore the role of social capital in customer information sharing behavior.
Most studies (Cheema & Kaikati, 2010; Lee, Cheung, Lim, & Sia, 2006; Wu & Sukoco, 2010) relied on subjective data, which was collected through survey and case study, to explain why customers participate in online communities. However, Straub et al. (1995) argued that actual and perceived usage are not always congruent. In our study, we use both subjective (i.e., online survey data) and objective data (i.e., network data and actual usage data) to test our research model and hypotheses. We also noticed that some studies (Cheung & Lee, 2012; Hennig Thurau et al., 2004) used a cross-sectional approach to collect data. In the current study, we use a longitudinal study to validate our research model and hypotheses.]]></section>
    <section name="Research model and hypotheses" category="research model and hypotheses" >
        <![CDATA[
3. Research model and hypotheses
In our study, we explore the reasons behind customers’ willingness to share information on SCSs. Wasko and Faraj (2005) regarded social capital as an integrative framework for understanding information sharing behavior. Based on Wasko and Faraj’s theoretical model (Wasko & Faraj, 2005), we develop several hypotheses that investigate the influence of individual motivations, cognitive capital (i.e., customer tenure and customer expertise), structure capital (i.e., out-degrees’ post, in-degree feedback) and relational dimensions (i.e., reciprocity) on customer information sharing behavior (see Fig. 2). In addition, we use out-degrees’ post, in-degree feedback to represent structural capital because SCSs rely on directed social network structure, which is different from traditional social network structure.
Fig. 2
Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Research model.
3.1. Individual motivations
Based on the theoretical model proposed by Wasko and Faraj (2005), we develop hypotheses to examine how individual motivations are related to customer information sharing behavior on SCSs. Individual motivations include reputation and enjoyment of helping others (Wasko & Faraj, 2005).
3.1.1. Reputation
Researchers from the fields of psychology, sociology, economics, and political sciences assume that all human actions are ultimately directed toward self-interest. Rewards and avoidance are the most obvious self-benefits that encourage individuals to act for public good. As rational beings, humans look for returns (e.g., prizes, reputation and recognition) by maximizing their benefits and minimizing their costs in the process of information exchange with others (Lakhani & Von Hippel, 2003). This perspective has been widely adopted in previous customer information sharing studies (Cheung & Lee, 2012; Hennig Thurau et al., 2004; Liu, Ray, & Whinston, 2010; Sun, Youn, Wu, & Kuntaraporn, 2006) in which reputation has been recognized as a key driver of content contribution in social media. Individuals share and contribute their knowledge to gain informal recognition and establish themselves as experts (Constant, Kiesler, & Sproull, 1994; Constant et al., 1996). Thus, reputation is especially an important antecedent of customer information sharing. Thus:
H1: Customers who perceive that information sharing will enhance their reputations are more likely to share information on SCSs.

3.1.2. Enjoyment of helping others
Individuals may receive intrinsic benefits from sharing information. Self-evaluation is an important intrinsic motivation that drives engagement in activities, relative to other external rewards (Albert Bandura, 1986). Individuals who feel good when helping others are more willing to share information online without expecting direct rewards in return. Wasko and Faraj (Bai et al., 2015; Wasko & Faraj, 2005) suggested that individuals are motivated intrinsically to share information with others because they enjoy doing it. This enjoyment of helping others has been considered as an intrinsic motivation that explains individuals’ willingness to share knowledge in online social spaces (Hennig Thurau et al., 2004; Kankanhalli, Tan, & Wei, 2005). Based on this line of research, we expect that:
H2: Customers who enjoy helping others are more likely share information on SCSs.

3.2. Structural capital
Structural capital refers to the distributed pattern of social interactions among members of a network (Wasko & Faraj, 2005). Wasko and Faraj (2005) have empirically validated that individuals who are centrally embedded in a collective are more likely to have a developed habit for cooperation and thus have greater potential to share knowledge with others in an electronic networks of practice. However, the social network structure of SCSs is significantly different from the one of the traditional online communities. Specifically, the network structure of SCSs is directed in nature, which means there are two different types of network ties (i.e., in-degree and out-degree ties). In-degree tie refers to the number of ties from other actors to a focal actor, whilst out-degree tie refers to the number of ties from a focal actor to other actors. In our study, we attempt to explore how structural capital embedded in the specific network structure affects customer information sharing behavior.
Milton and Westphal (2005) found that a higher level of centrality within an identity confirmation network is positively related to cooperation and performance. Network centrality is related to the individual’s degree of involvement in assisting others with exchanges (Mossholder, Settoon, & Henagan, 2005). Nahapiet and Ghoshal (1998) argued that network ties provide access to resources. In SCSs an individual with a large out-degree tie have more access to resources. Chiu et al. (2006) provided empirical support for the influence of social interaction ties on knowledge sharing. Based on the social exchange theory, an individual who obtains more information from a social network is more likely to benefit from other individuals in that network. Prior studies demonstrated that the more social interactions undertaken by exchange partners, the greater the intensity, frequency, and breadth of information exchanged (Ring & Van de Ven, 1994). Customers can easily observe what out-degrees have posted on SCSs by following them. The following relationship indicates that focal customers prefer to read information from out-degrees’ posts. Hence, customers are more likely to cognitively absorb the information from out-degrees’ posts (Agarwal & Karahanna, 2000). In other words, the more customers read, the higher the chances that they will encounter the information they are interested in. Thus, their level of engagement in SCSs increases, resulting in sharing more information. In addition, based on social influence theory, customers are more likely to share information when they notice that the people they like share information. Therefore, we posits:
H3: Customers who have access to more out-degrees’ post are more likely to share information on SCSs.

Customers with higher in-degree tie tend to be more attractive because more incoming links suggest greater popularity within the network. Previous studies found that an individual with high in-degree tie is more likely to benefit from a social network (Stephen & Toubia, 2009). An individual with many followers can attract a larger audience. SCSs allow customers to provide feedback to and express appreciation of other customers’ posts. For instance, they can respond to others’ posts by leaving comments or feedback. Feedback becomes a key incentive or motivator for their future action. Individuals who receive feedback on their prior contributions would continue to contribute (Bandura & McDonald, 1963; Bandura, 1977; Liu, Cheung, & Lee, 2016). In SCSs, customers are able to receive feedback from in-degree members (i.e., followers’ feedback). Thus, this study assumes that customers who receive more feedback are more motivated to contribute to the community.
H4: Customers who get more in-degrees’ feedback are more likely to share information on SCSs.

3.3. Cognitive capital
Cognitive capital refers to the resources that create shared interpretations and meanings in a collective (Wasko & Faraj, 2005). It is usually nurtured through continuous social interactions over a period of time (Nahapiet & Ghoshal, 1998). A customer’s cognitive capital is nurtured as he/she interacts with other community members over time (Nahapiet & Ghoshal, 1998). A certain level of shared understanding between community members allows them to accumulate hands-on experience over time (Chou & He, 2011). IS researchers empirically demonstrated that members with longer tenure and expertise are more likely to engage in information exchange in online communities (Wasko & Faraj, 2005). Wasko & Faraj (2005) indicated that individuals with longer tenure in the shared practice are more likely to understand how their expertise is relevant, and are thus better able to share information with others. In the context of SCSs, we expect that customer tenure and customer expertise reduce the amount of cognitive effort of customers in the community required to achieve a reasonable understanding and anticipation, and thus customers are more likely to find the interactions and information sharing meaningful and effective. They will be more willing to spend their own time and effort to post and exchange product information with other customers in the community. Compared with customers with fewer community experiences, customers with longer tenure have a better understanding of whether their posts (i.e., sharing views and experiences) are relevant and valuable (Wasko & Faraj, 2005). Thus, we hypothesize:
H5: Customers who have a longer tenure are more likely to share information on SCSs.

The cognitive dimension of social capital develops through existence of shared language and vocabulary, and exchange of collective narratives that facilitate social interaction processes (Nahapiet & Ghoshal, 1998). Wasko & Faraj (2005) further suggested that language is the means individuals engage in communication and provides a frame of reference for interpreting the environment. Shared language mastery is typically indicated by an individual's level of expertise. Members who share common language better understand each other, avoid misunderstandings in communication, and readily anticipate similar values or visions. In organizational studies (Orr, 1996), researchers argued that a shared vision and/or a set of common values facilitate individual and group actions that have organization wide benefits. In online communities, language indicates an individual’s level of expertise. Individuals with a higher level of expertise may have a better understanding of the context in which their knowledge is relevant. As the customer’s expertise increases over time, he/she can more accurately and easily assess the benefits and costs of a SCS. Therefore, we expect:
H6: Customers who have higher levels of expertise are more likely to share information on SCSs.

3.4. Relational capital
Relational capital has been empirically proven to enhance knowledge exchange (Bouty, 2000; Robert, Dennis, & Ahuja, 2008; Tsai & Ghoshal, 1998). Relational capital exists when individuals have a strong identification with the collective because they are more willing to help each other when everyone is part of the accepted collective (Hajli, 2015; Leana & Van Buren, 1999). Prior studies examine relational capital using commitment and reciprocity (Chiu et al., 2006; Wasko & Faraj, 2005). We examine the relational dimension of social capital using reciprocity. Reciprocity refers to knowledge exchanges that are mutual and perceived as fair (Chiu et al., 2006). Reciprocity is an internalized social norm that is conceived as a benefit to individuals engaging in social exchanges (Perugini, Gallucci, Presaghi, & Ercolani, 2003). Previous research has found that individuals who share information in online communities value reciprocity (Chiu et al., 2006; Wasko & Faraj, 2005) that drives them to participate and share. An individual, who has received the appreciation from other members for his/her valuable contribution, becomes even more motivated to continue contributing within the community. Individuals usually reciprocate the benefits they receive from others, which spurs ongoing supportive exchanges (Shumaker & Brownell, 1984). Therefore:
H7: Customers who are guided by a norm of reciprocity are more likely to share information on SCSs.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Research method" category="methods">
        <![CDATA[
4. Research method
4.1. Research setting
The data for this study was collected from Meilishuo (www.meilishuo.com) that is a popular SCS. Launched in November 2009, Meilishuo is now one of the most popular websites in China with more than 32 million registered members. As of February 2015, the site ranked 863 in China in terms of its traffic.2 The daily user sharing volume is around 3.4 million and the daily page views amount to 164 million. Meilishuo is an online platform where customers share pictures and information about their favorite products (e.g., product price, tags, and retailers). Customers are able to purchase their favorite products by simply clicking the hyperlinks that are available on the shopping site. This SCS also possesses a set of social network structure functionalities that facilitate individual customers to interact with other fellow customers. For instance, individual customers can “follow” other customers in the community, and interact with them by giving “likes” to their posts. They can also be followed by other customers and obtain feedback and appreciation from them. In this sense, each individual customer has his/her own social network in the community and is regarded as an ego actor in the social network. This platform provides rich data that allowed us to empirically explore how social capital influences customer information sharing behavior on SCSs.
4.2. Data collection procedure
The study used a multi-method approach and collected data at two different points of time (see Fig. 3). In the first phase of the data collection, we collected subjective data through an online survey. Then based on the respondents’ customer ID we crawled their network data. In the second phase of the data collection, we crawled the actual usage data of the respondents in Phase 1. The data collection period was four months, from November 2012 to February 2013. To determine the length of the time window, we needed to ensure that the time window was not too short or was not truly reflecting users’ behavior changes. In the meanwhile, we also needed to make sure that the time window was not too long or was not accumulating too many unrelated activities (Collins & Graham, 2002; Xia, Huang, Duan, & Whinston, 2012).
Fig. 3
Download full-size image
Fig. 3. Time window illustration.
In Phase 1 (November 2012), we conducted an online survey and invited members of Meilishuo to fill in an online questionnaire. In order to improve the response rate and sample quality, we employed a market research firm for the survey data collection. The market research firm used IP addresses to prevent double-counting of survey respondents. Customers were identified by their network IP addresses at the time of connection for the online survey questionnaire. To ensure the sample include only active customers, we selected customers who have started posting before November 2012. A total of 1177 completed responses were obtained. Among the 1177 respondents, 91.3% were females and 8.7% were males. The majority of our respondents (81.5%) were aged between 20 and 29, and 76.4% of our respondents had an education level of the university or above. Also the majority of our respondents (88.9%) used computer to login to the SCSs (see Table 3).
Table 3. Demographic statistics.
Variables	Levels	Percentage
Gender	Male	8.7%
Female	91.3%
Age	< = 18	5.2%
19–23	42.1%
24–28	39.4%
29–35	10.8%
36–42	2%
>42	0.6%
Education	High school	5%
Junior college	17.5%
Undergraduate or above	76.4%
Platform	Mobile Device	10.9%
Computer	88.9%
Others	0.2%
In the same period (November 2012), based on the respondents’ customer ID we crawled the network data for each of the 1177 respondents from the Meilishuo community. Specifically, we collected the “following” and “follower” customers’ lists and built an ego-centric network for each respondent of this study.

In Phase 2 (February 2013), based on the 1177 respondents’ customer ID we crawled their actual usage data from the Meilishuo community. More specifically, we collected the posts’ full text and date of publishing. A total of 218,516 posts were collected from the 1177 respondents that were used to generate a profile of customer information sharing behavior history.

4.3. Operationalization of constructs
The constructs included in the research model are operationalized as follows. In the first phase (November 2012), we collected subjective data through an online survey. The measures of these independent constructs (i.e., reputation, enjoyment of helping, and reciprocity) were borrowed from the prior literature’s scales that have been proven as reliable and valid. The measurement of reputation, reciprocity, and enjoyment of helping were adapted from Wasko and Faraj (Wasko & Faraj, 2005) (see Table 4). All items with minor wording modifications were applied to fit our research context. All constructs were measured using multi-item perceptual scales and were carried out by a seven-point Likert scale, ranging from strongly disagree (1) to strongly agree (7).
Table 4. Construct measurement.
Constructs	Items	Factor Loading	Composite Reliability	AVE	Cronbach’s α
Reputation (REP)	REP 1: I feel that my participation in meilishuo.com improves my status in the profession.	0.93	0.94	0.85	0.91
REP 2: I participate in meilishuo.com to improve my reputation in the profession.	0.94			
REP 3: I earn respect from others by participating in meilishuo.com.	0.89		

Enjoyment of helping (EOH)	EOH1: I like helping other members in meilishuo.com.	0.94	0.94	0.84	0.91
EOH2: It feels good to help others other members in meilishuo.com.	0.87			
EOH3: I enjoy helping other members in meilishuo.com.	0.94			

Reciprocity (RC)	RC1: When I share my knowledge through meilishuo.com, I believe that I will get an answer for giving an answer.	0.78	0.91	0.72	0.87
RC2: When I share my knowledge through meilishuo.com, I expect somebody to respond when I'm in need.	0.87			
RC3: When I contribute knowledge to meilishuo.com, I expect to get back knowledge when I need it.	0.87			
RC4: I know that other members in meilishuo.com will help me, so it's only fair to help other member.	0.86			
In this phase, we also crawled objective network data, customer tenure and expertise from the 1177 respondents in the Meilishuo. We collected out-degree members and in-degree members for each customer to form directed social network (as shown in Fig. 4). In particular, we focused on two key social interaction for the directed social network structure, out-degrees’ post and in-degrees’ feedback on SCSs.
Fig. 4
Download full-size image
Fig. 4. Illustration of directed social network on SCSs.
A customer can follow other customers he/she like which is out-degree members. As the provision of post is optional, not everyone that a member follows would have posts. Therefore, out-degrees post is operationalized as the total number of posts provided by all out-degree members (i.e., following).
A customer can be followed by other customers which are in-degree members. Customers are able to receive feedback from in-degree members (i.e., followers’ feedback) As the provision of post is optional, not followers provide feedback to focal customer. Therefore, in-degrees feedback is operationalized as the total number of feedback provided by in-degree members (i.e., followers).
The SCS provides statistics on the number of recommendations that a member receives on the sharing messages s/he has posted to the SCS. As a member whose posts receive a large number of recommendations from other members is likely to be an expert of the brand. Therefore, customer expertise was operationalized as the total recommendation score that a customer received in the SCS until November 2012.
Customer tenure was operationalized as the total number of days a customer joined in the community until November 2012.

In the second phase (February 2013), based on the respondents’ customer ID, we crawled their actual usage data that represents the customer information sharing behavior on Meilishuo community. This dependent construct of the research model was operationalized as the total number of information a customer has posted in the community from November 2012 till February 2013.]]></section>
    <section name=" Data analysis" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
5. Data analysis
5.1. Validation of the measurement items
Reliability and validity tests were conducted for verification of the measurement model. The reliability was tested using Cronbach’s α and composite reliability (CR). Cronbach’s α and CR should be at least 0.70. It implies that a construct retains internal consistency. In our study, the two conditions of reliability were satisfied in data sample by having the CRs ranging from 0.78 to 0.94, and the Cronbach’s α from 0.87 to 0.91 (see Table 4).
The convergent validity and discriminant validity of the constructs in the model were also examined. Convergent validity was tested using three criteria for all constructs: (1) the composite reliability (CR) should be at least 0.70 (Chin, 1998), (2) the average variance extracted (AVE) should be at least 0.50 (Fornell & Larcker, 1987), and (3) all item loadings should be greater than 0.70. The three conditions of convergent validity were satisfied in data sample by having the CRs ranging from 0.91 to 0.94, and the AVEs from 0.72 to 0.85. The item loadings were all higher than the 0.70 benchmark (see Table 4). Descriptive statistics of data are shown in Table 5.
Table 5. Descriptive statistics.
Mean	Std. Dev.	Min	Max
REP	5.15	1.25	1	7
EOH	5.79	1.03	1	7
PMP	2055.32	22126.60	0	574509
PMR	54.14	594.33	0	17458
TEN	152.05	87.14	1	756
EXP	8381.15	100293.02	0	2525677
RC	5.22	1.22	1	7
CISB	186.50	1255.49	0	21202
Discriminant validity is the degree to which the measures of two constructs were empirically distinct. Discriminant validity between constructs can be verified if the square root of the AVE for each construct was greater than the correlation between constructs (Fornell & Larcker, 1987). The square root of AVE for each construct was greater than the correlations between the constructs and all other constructs. Therefore, the results suggested adequate discriminant validity (see Table 6).
Table 6. Discriminant validity.
REP	EOH	PMP	PMR	TEN	EXP	RC	CISB
REP	0.92							
EOH	0.45	0.92						
PMP	0.07	0.04	1.00					
PMR	0.01	0.03	0.03	1.00				
TEN	0.08	0.02	0.12	0.09	1.00			
EXP	0.03	0.06	0.22	0.09	0.12	1.00		
RC	0.49	0.39	0.06	0.02	0.02	0.05	0.85	
CISB	0.04	0.01	0.27	0.14	0.20	0.56	0.05	1.00
5.2. Data analysis technique
As described in the previous section, customer information sharing behavior is measured by adding all the posts in a post list. As it is a count variable, Poisson regression and negative binomial regression are appropriate statistical approaches to analyze our data set. However, a Poisson regression model has a very restrictive assumption that the mean of the dependent variable equals the variance (Cohen, Cohen, West, & Aiken, 2003). If the variance is greater than the mean, the data is said to be over-dispersed, which can lead to the inflation of the goodness of fit chi-square test and the overestimation of predictor significance (Cohen et al., 2003). One approach to over-dispersion is to use a negative binomial regression model (Cohen et al., 2003). Table 5 summarizes the descriptive statistics (mean, standard deviation, minimum and maximum) for the variables used. In the current study, the data is over-dispersed. The variance of customer information sharing behavior is greater than its mean value (i.e., variance of customer information sharing behavior = 1576255.14, mean of customer information sharing behavior = 186.50). Therefore, we adopted a negative binomial regression (with the use of SPSS software) to test the hypothesized effects in our research model.
5.3. Research model testing
We summarize the Omnibus test results, coefficients, Wald statistic, associated degrees of freedom and significance level of each of the predictors (see Table 7). A negative binomial regression analysis was performed for customer information sharing behavior as dependent variable and reputation, enjoyment of helping, out-degrees’ post and in-degrees’ feedback, customer tenure, customer expertise and reciprocity as independent variables. The Omnibus test revealed that the full model significantly predicts customer information sharing behavior (Likelihood Ratio Chi-Square = 3857.649; df = 7; p < 0.0001). The results supported most of our hypotheses. Particularly, with the exception of the relationship between enjoyment of helping and customer information sharing behavior, all of the other hypotheses are statistically significant.
Table 7. Results of binomial regression analysis.
Parameter	Customer Information Sharing Behavior
β	df	Sig.
Individual Motivations	H1	Reputation	0.102**	1	0.043
H2	Enjoyment of Helping	0.003	1	0.932
Structural Capital	H3	Out-degrees’ post	0.597***	1	0.000
H4	In-degrees’ feedback	3.366***	1	0.000
Cognitive Capital	H5	Customer Tenure	1.185***	1	0.000
H6	Customer Expertise	0.464***	1	0.000
Relational Capital	H7	Reciprocity	0.167***	1	0.000
Omnibus Test Customer information sharing behavior: Likelihood Ratio Chi-Square = 3857.649 (df = 7, p < 0.0001).
DV: Customer information sharing behavior.


**
p < 0.05.
***
p < 0.001.
Reputation is significantly related to customer information sharing behavior (β = 0.102, p < 0.050) that supports H1. From a structural capital perspective, out-degrees’ post exerts a significant positive effect on customer information sharing behavior (β = 0.597, p < 0.0001) that supports H3. In-degrees’ feedback is significantly related to customer information sharing behavior (β = 3.366, p < 0.0001) that supports H4. From a cognitive capital perspective, customer tenure has a positive effect on customer information sharing behavior (β = 1.185, p < 0.0001) that supports H5. Moreover, customer expertise has a significant effect on customer information sharing behavior (β = 0.464, p < 0.0001) that supports H6. From a relational capital perspective, reciprocity shows a significant positive effect on customer information sharing behavior (β = 0.167, p < 0.0001) that supports H7. Surprisingly, our results indicate that enjoyment of helping does not exhibit any significant effect on customer information sharing behavior.]]></section>
    <section name=" Discussion and conclusions" category="conclusion">
       <![CDATA[
6. Discussion and conclusions
]]> <h target="1" match="full">The purpose of this study was to explore the factors driving customer information sharing behavior on SCSs and examine how the directed online social network structure of this new social media affect customer information sharing behavior.</h> <![CDATA[  We found that social capital and individual motivations are the key antecedents of information sharing behaviors on SCSs. We adopted an empirical analysis approach and collected subjective survey and objective behavioral data from a SCS. Our results generally support the theoretical model and our hypotheses. Both individual motivations and social capital influence customer information sharing behavior in SCSs.
6.1. General discussion
6.1.1. Individual factors
Our results indicate that individual motivators are important factors that determine customer information sharing behavior on SCSs. Consistent with the literature, reputation is a strong motivator of active participation (Wasko & Faraj, 2005). In our study, we found that customers want to enhance their reputation by sharing information on SGSs. Our results show that enjoyment of helping does not have any significant effect on customer information sharing, as suggested by prior research examining knowledge contribution in electronic networks (Chiu et al., 2006; Wasko & Faraj, 2005). One possible explanation is that customer information sharing behavior in this new platform is driven by customer themselves (i.e., reputation) instead of helping each other. Information sharing in SCSs is more concerned about the successful functioning, and growth rather than the benefits that will provide to others (Chiu et al., 2006). The results may indicate that extrinsic rewards may be more important than intrinsic returns to motivate information sharing in the context of SCSs.
6.1.2. Social factors
Apart from the individual motivations, our results provide evidence that social capital plays an important role in explaining customer information sharing behavior. All three social capital dimensions (structural, cognitive, and relational) have a significant impact on customer information sharing behavior. For instance, our results showed that customers who connect to a large number of other customers are more likely to share information. Customer expertise and tenure are also important predictors of customer information sharing behavior. Finally, the relational dimension of social capital, reciprocity, has a significant impact on customer information sharing behavior. These findings support our argument that social capital factors play important roles for customer information sharing behavior in the context of SCSs.

6.2. Research implications
As previously highlighted, we believe that this study contributes to the information sharing literature in four major ways.]]> <h target="3" match="full"> First, existing information sharing studies focus on traditional online communities, whereas this study enriches the literature by examining customer information sharing behavior in a new social media, namely SCSs. </h> <![CDATA[ This study provides strong empirical support for the information sharing model, which indicates that individual motivation and social capital have a significant effect on customer information sharing behavior.

Second, customer information sharing behavior is complex and involves a variety of underlying causal mechanisms. Although numerous psychological factors have been identified as the antecedents of knowledge sharing behavior in the context of virtual communities, previous studies have only examined information sharing behaviors from the perspective of individuals rather than groups. In this study, we consider the directed online social network structure and use social capital theory to explain customer information sharing behavior in the context of SCSs. We examine how the directed online social network structures of SCSs affect customer information sharing behavior. By identifying facets of social capital as determinants of customer information sharing behavior, relationship among customers (network structure) are characterized as valuable customer information sharing resources. The results of this study enhance our understanding of directed online social network structures on SCSs (i.e., out-degrees post and in-degrees feedback positively influences customer information sharing behavior). This indicates that the new directed online social network structures provided by SCSs present a new social commerce value.

Third, our study extends the existing research in terms of the method we adopted for this investigation. Previous studies have primarily been derived from data collected through a subjective approach (e.g., through survey or experimental design). In this study, we test our research by analyzing data collected through subjective (i.e., online survey study) and objective (i.e., network and usage data) approaches. With the use of different data source, common method bias can be reduced.

Finally, we empirically illustrate the influence of individual motivations and social capital in a longitudinal setting. To the best of our knowledge, this study is one of the first to demonstrate the longitudinal implications of customer information sharing behavior in the context of SCSs.

6.3. Managerial implications
The findings of this study are also useful to SCSs, which represent a new type of social media platform. Many community administrators are still finding ways to improve their community features to attract and retain members. As such, they must identify ways to motivate members to share and, more importantly, to continue sharing within the community. This study will help them understand their customers’ behavior. Our results showed that reputation, out-degrees’ post and in-degrees’ feedback, customer expertise, customer tenure and reciprocity are the critical factors that encourage customers to share and contribute on SCSs. Therefore, we have the following recommendations: First, to encourage more customers to share their information, SCSs should apply reputation-tracking mechanisms that will allow them to recognize contributors. Apart from the number of contributions, publicly visible cues such as length of membership and membership status should be incorporated into the platform design. Second, SCSs should pay attention to the three dimensions of social capital. From a structural perspective, managers should focus on directed online social network structure development to enhance information exchange through social network structure. For example, managers should develop strategies that encourage the frequency of interaction and the strength of the relationships among customers. Particularly, we find that the following-follower feature has played an important role in the continuance of customer information sharing behavior. Both out-degrees’ post and in-degrees’ feedback have an important impact on customer information sharing behavior in SCSs. As such, the more posts a customer can access from his/her following, the higher the chance that he/she will contribute. Thus, community designers should add features that encourage members to continue to follow others. For instance, they might add “Friends you may know” or “Your Friends are also following this person” functions to expand members’ social networks and enhance their exposure to posts. From a relational perspective, managers can encourage customer reciprocity by using extrinsic motivations such as rewards for customer information sharing behavior. From a cognitive perspective, maintaining a set of core and expertise customers plays an important role in sustaining a successful SCSs. Managers should also target customers with longer tenure in their practices.

6.4. Limitations and future research direction
This study has limitations that must be noted and require further examination and additional research. First, given that our data were collected from a SCS, our samples were primarily female. Thus, a gender bias certainly exists. Future studies should test our model with a gender neutral data sample. Second, the generalizability of our results may be limited because we examined only one SCS that specifically focused on fashion. Future studies should examine whether other social media exhibit similar dynamics and compare the impact of individual motivations and social capital across different social media platforms. In addition, future studies should include other factors (including commitment) to improve the variance explained.

6.5. Conclusion
In this study, we use social capital theories to explain how individual motivations and social capital affect customer information sharing behavior in SCSs. Unlike other studies on information sharing, we extended the existing framework by introducing the directed online social network structure of SCSs into our investigation. ]]> <h target="2" match="full">In addition, we empirically tested our research model and hypotheses using combined method (subjective survey data, objective network data and behavioral usage data) in a longitudinal setting.</h> <![CDATA[ We hope that our study will bring new insights to researchers with a strong interest in understanding customer information sharing behavior in social media.]]></section>

Acknowledgement
This research was supported by Faculty Research Grant (FRG 32450) from Faculty of Business and Law, Swinburne University of Technology in Australia.
</publication>
