<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="zhouzhichao">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 3, June 2016, Pages 425-432</time>
    <title>The applications of social commerce constructs</title>
    <author>Mohana Shanmugam.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Shiwei Sun.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Asra Amidi.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacec. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Farzad Khani.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaced. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Fariborz Khani.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacee. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
College of Information Technology, Department of Information Systems, University Tenaga Nasional, Selangor, Malaysia
b
<![CDATA[Department of Aviation & Supply Chain Management, Raymond J. Harbert College of Business, Auburn University, Auburn, AL 36849, USA]]>
c
Department of Information System, University Putra Malaysia (UPM), 43300 Serdang, Selangor, Malaysia
d
Azad University, Tehran, Iran
e
University of Science and Culture, Tehran, Iran
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.01.007</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">This study investigates the social support constructs during trust-building from both emotional and informational perspectives separately.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">The findings that social commerce constructs has more significant effect on emotional support than that on informational support.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">Results indicate that social commerce constructs can lead to greater emotional and informational support</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">This study extends social support theory and trust literature.</highlight>
Abstract
    <abstract><![CDATA[Social commerce has evolved quickly in practice and gained attention in the IS discipline. However, trust has remained a vital component and is dominantly worth investigating. ]]><h target="1" match="part">The purpose of this study, therefore, is to examine the roles of social commerce constructs and social support constructs (i.e., emotional support and informational support) in establishing trust on online community platforms.</h><![CDATA[ The study will apply the theoretical foundation of social commerce constructs proposed by Hajli. In order to provide a detailed understanding of the proposed model, a quantitative study involving a survey data gathered from online communities in Malaysia, including Facebook, Trip Advisor and LinkedIn was conducted. The data was analyzed and hypotheses were tested with structural equation modeling (SEM). Our results shed some lights on social commerce literature. ]]><h target="2" match="part">The findings show that there are significant effect of social commerce constructs on social support, namely the emotional and informational support, and in turn, on trust- building.</h></abstract>
Keywords
    <keywords>Social commerce</keywords>
    <keywords>Social commerce constructs</keywords>
    <keywords>Emotional support</keywords>
    <keywords>Informational support</keywords>
    <keywords>Trust</keywords>
    <section name=" Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
The rise of social networking sites (SNSs) has led to a novel electronic commerce known as social commerce (Hajli, Mohana, Powell, & Love, 2015). This novel paradigm is mediated by social media. With the advancement of social media and Web 2.0 technologies, social commerce has developed the way how individuals communicate with their peers on social platforms. These platforms include online communities and other social networking sites. In a social commerce context, consumers aside communicating also rate other products, review others’ opinions, participate in forums, share their experiences and recommend products and services (Hajli, 2015). Through this mechanism, consumers have an advantage over the influence of other consumers (Hajli, Lin, Featherman, & Wang, 2014) which supports them in their decision making, and additionally the level of trust is increased (Hajli, Lin, Featherman, & Wang, 2014).
Security and trust is an essential factor in an online platform (Featherman & Hajli, 2015; Hajli & Lin, 2014). Research has shown that trust is indeed a challenging subject in e-commerce (Gefen, Straub, & Boudreau, 2000) as it involves individuals. Individuals are prone to execute the transaction only in conditions of existing trust. In fact, research from Hajli (2015) has affirmed that trust is a vital component in online community. In addition, research has empirically proven that social commerce constructs influence trust which results in a significant intention to buy (Hajli, 2015). However, a predominant cursor of the social perspective in social commerce climate which spurs trust has been overlooked in past research. Therefore, it is crucial to study the constructs that build trust in an online community context.
Drawn on Hajli’s social commerce constructs (Hajli, 2015) a research model developed here identifies the constructs that affect trust. The author proposes a model to investigate the social commerce constructs influence on social support in explaining trust. Specifically, this research looks into the dimensions of social commerce constructs; forums, communities, ratings, reviews, recommendations and referrals that affects social support constructs which in return results in positive effect on trust in online community. Social support construct comprised of the emotional and informational constructs refers to the social interaction of people in a domain and their feelings being attended to.
]]><h target="1" match="part">This research, therefore, investigates the role of social commerce constructs and social support from the social psychology discipline in order to establish trust in online community platforms.</h><![CDATA[ First, the social commerce constructs; forums, communities, ratings, reviews, recommendations and referrals (Hajli, 2015) are hypothesized to drive the social support constructs. Second, the emotional support and informational support constructs of the social support construct is hypothesized to have a positive result on trust in an online community context. Through this extension, the present study addresses these research questions: (1) do social commerce constructs influence social support measured by emotional and informational constructs? (2) Does social support measured by emotional and informational constructs influence trust?
The rest of the paper is organized as follows. The next sections review social commerce, social support theory and trust. The resulting model acts as the theoretical foundation of this paper. The research framework and a series of testable hypotheses are presented before the methodology is provided. The data collected were then analyzed and interpreted. The implications are discussed and recommendations are provided before concluding the paper.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Theoretical foundation of research" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Theoretical foundation of research
2.1. Social commerce and social commerce constructs
Social commerce, a relatively new business model capitalized on social media application allows dynamic interaction between users and the platform they are engaged in. This is in contrast with the classic e-commerce. By definition, social commerce is a division of e-commerce (Stephen & Toubia, 2010) and uses social networking sites to associate social interaction and collaboration among users online to accommodate e-commerce (Kim & Park, 2013).
With the proliferation of Web 2.0 technologies, social commerce elevates online business with consumers being directly involved in the acquisition process through the sharing and dissemination of information. In other words, social commerce produces information-driven consumers where consumers create their own content, rate and review service and products and leave their comments on the Internet (Hajli, 2014a). This integration of social network elements into social commerce produces value for business through texts produced by consumers (Hajli, 2015). In the marketing discipline, social commerce is classified a vital component (Hajli, 2015) because consumer involvement is a key strategic factor (Do-Hyung, Jumin, & Ingoo, 2007).
Social commerce constructs is defined as the constructs that are derived through social commerce such as online forums, ratings, communities, reviews and recommendations (Hajli, 2015). The information produced by these social commerce platforms or communities can affect consumers’ purchasing intention or behavior. More and more scholars have begun to study social commerce constructs. For instance, in a recent study by Hajli (2015), it is shown that consumers refer and recommend products or services through social commerce constructs, namely forums, communities, ratings, reviews, recommendations, and referrals. These constructs are the facet to successful social commerce transactions. Consumers are more inclined to participate in an online deal or service when these social commerce constructs are present. Research also has shown that rating, a particular construct of the social commerce adds value for members of a community (Heinonen, 2011; Keller, 2009) aside reducing or increasing ambiguity (Nambisan, 2002). Online communities, on the other hand, gather people of the same or diverse interest within a dedicated network to share interest and acquire knowledge (Chen, Xu, & Whinston, 2011).
2.2. Social support and trust in online communities
Social support is produced when communication between individuals are undertaken in a dynamic platform such as the online communities. This is evident when individuals are supportive over their peers through emotional and informational support (Hajli, 2014a, 2014b), a multi-dimension of the social support construct. Social support is defined as social resources that are available or provided by individuals of a network (Gottlieb & Bergen, 2010) which nurtures sense of warmth, care and sense of belonging (Ali, 2011) aside leading to approving consumer attitudes (Hassanein & Head, 2007).
The emotional support is affective and sentimental in nature (Hajli, Mohana, Powell, & Love, 2015). In particular, the emotional support involves listening and showing sympathy or trust (House, 1981). The informational support is practical in nature and denotes advice, referrals or teachings (Hajli, Mohana, Powell, & Love, 2015). Social support is a constructive element in online communities as it cultivates trust in an individual over a decision. This is apparent as past research has reported that social interaction and support dedicated online initiates trust (Hajli, Lin, Featherman, & Wang, 2014). It is also reasoned that these support leads to trust on the online environment (Hajli, Lin, Featherman, & Wang, 2014).
An individual is inclined to participate in an online community platform only when they feel safe because there are bound to be risks and uncertainty in an online context (Pavlou, 2003). This is apparent in the e-commerce context especially when risks are perceived to be high (Mutz, 2005). With social support mechanism in place, individuals are likely to have a high level of trust because of the positive influence from other individuals of the same network (Casaló, Flavián, & Guinalíu, 2008).
Trust is therefore seen as a deriving value obtained when social support is primed. Trust is vital in online community (Hajli, 2015) and has been the key issue for successful online businesses (Salam, Iyer, Palvia, & Singh, 2005). In point of fact, Gefen et al. (2000) Gefen, Straub, and Boudreau (2000) in their study concluded that trust is one of the most significant factors in influencing the success of an online commerce. As trust is sustained by knowledge transfer (Zhao & Lavin, 2012), social support aids individuals in gaining that required information on a particular product or service before executing a task. A recent research has also found that the emotional and informational support from the social support construct increase trust (Hajli, 2014a, 2014b). In addition, Crocker and Canevello (2008) argued that the availability of social support offer trust to individuals participating in an online community. The presence of social contact, as a result, enhances consumers’ trust in this online platform.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Research model and hypothesis development" category="research model and hypotheses">
        <![CDATA[
3. Research model and hypothesis development
3.1. The effect of social commerce constructs on social support constructs
Users interact in social commerce platforms in a collaborative online environment (Curty & Zhang, 2011). Social commerce constructs are social platforms which allow the sharing of the idea of consumers to peers of the same group or network. Forums, communities, ratings, reviews, recommendations and referrals are instances of social commerce constructs (Hajli, 2014a, 2014b) which are essential to social support in online communities. In addition, experience gained from these social platforms prepares an avenue for online social support where individuals can look up to. It is argued that online communication of consumers in social commerce constructs provide social support (Crocker & Canevello, 2008).
Past research has shown that online users join social commerce platforms because of the value social support imparts to them (Ridings & Gefen, 2004). This social support includes the informational and emotional support (Hajli, 2014a; Ridings & Gefen, 2004) derived from the social psychology domain. Social support has become of interest and relevance after the emergence of Web 2.0 technologies, with the tardy booming of Twitter and Facebook. Through social commerce constructs, consumers are expected to receive social support which aids them into making informed decisions involved when executing a transaction. It is argued that social commerce constructs produce both informational and emotional support in online communities (Hajli, 2014a). Therefore, the interconnectivity of member on the community through social commerce constructs can develop emotional and informational support. We can, therefore, hypothesize that:
 ]]><h target="2" match="part">H1a: Social commerce constructs have a positive effect on emotional support.

H1b: Social commerce constructs have a positive effect on informational support.</h><![CDATA[

3.2. The effect of social support constructs on trust in online communities
Social support, a notion from psychology is defined as the social interaction of individuals in a network that are cared for, answered to and supported (Ali, 2011). This network includes online communities such as discussion boards, chat rooms and other social networking sites like the Facebook and Twitter (Daneback & Plantin, 2008; LaCoursiere, 2001).
There are a number of established studies based on social support theory in online community studies particularly looking into the health domain (Ballantine & Stephenson, 2011; Obst & Stafurik, 2010). In the health sector, social support is key essential to trust because individuals attempt to deal with their medical conditions based on advice and information provided by people of the same network. Additionally Ridings and Gefen (2004) affirmed that the main reason individuals join online communities is for social support aside exchanging relevant information. Social support comes in a multi-dimensional construct and can be categorized with emotional and informational construct. Which are deemed significant in an online community context (Coulson, 2005; Huang, Nambisan, & Uzuner, 2010; Madjar, 2008). Strong social support makes a user feel connected to friends as well as builds trust with those friends (Crocker & Canevello, 2008; Weber, Johnson, & Corrigan, 2004). Trust is an on-going issue in social commerce. This concern is of rising importance among consumers as social commerce platforms like Facebook become more widespread (Hajli, 2013). Many researchers argue that trust is a key element in online environment (e.g., Gefen, Karahanna, & Straub, 2003; Mutz, 2005; Pavlou, 2003). Trust is further increased by social support (Gefen, Karahanna, & Straub, 2003). Reychav and Weisberg’s (2010) studies show that social context or social support do influence trust.
Many researchers argue that trust is a key element in online environment (Gefen, Karahanna, & Straub, 2003; Mutz, 2005; Pavlou, 2003). Trust is further increased by social support (Gefen, Karahanna, & Straub, 2003). A recent work (Hajli, 2014b) asserts that social support raises trust among users of online communities. This is legit because trust is known to ensue from social support. In fact, a handful of research argues that the presence of online social support augments consumers’ trust (Crocker & Canevello, 2008; Hajli, 2014a). Online community is to deliver both emotional and informational social support while informational support could provide interpretation, solutions and plans, emotional support emphases on articulating one’s concerns and hence indirectly help in problem-solving. These two types of messages are the main support mechanisms for social interactions in online communities. Strong social support makes a user feel connected to friends as well as builds trust with others in online community (Crocker & Canevello, 2008; Weber, Johnson, & Corrigan, 2004). These arguments are summarized with the following two hypotheses:
H2a: Emotional support has a positive effect on trust in online communities.

H2b: Informational support has a positive effect on trust in online communities.

3.3. Research model
Trust can be considered as a function of the degree of risk inherent in a certain situation (Koller, 1988). Studies on trust in the context of e-commerce have been receiving increased attention (e.g., McKnight, Choudhury, & Kacmar, 2002). A good understanding of trust building is essential to explain interpersonal behavior during economic exchanges. Consistent to the context of e-commerce in which trust is needed between buyer and seller, trust also plays a fundamental role in social commerce. Trust can greatly improve the effectiveness of the social commerce. According to previous studies (e.g., Ba & Pavlou, 2002; Coleman, 1990; Williamson, 1993), three sources of trust, including familiarity, calculativeness, and values, are essential in the business world. Familiarity is achieved by repeated interaction. Calculativeness is a calculation of the other party’s costs and benefits of cheating. Values are institutional structures that drive trustworthy behavior.
During the context of social commerce, the support from others’ information or emotions can make the interactions easily happen, and in turn, produce trust. The conceptual model, presented in Fig. 1, is formulated, based on the preceding discussions, in building trust.
Fig. 1
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Research model.]]>
    </section>
    <section name=" Methodology" category="methods">
        <![CDATA[
4. Methodology
4.1. Data collection
The survey method was employed to collect primary data from online communities in Malaysia, including Facebook, TripAdvisor, and LinkedIn. To be eligible for the study, all participants were required to have at least one social commerce account in regular use. A pilot study was conducted on 8 respondents which included face validity testing and content validity testing. The questionnaires were distributed from December 20, 2013, to January 20, 2014.

Overall, 300 participants completed the survey. A total of 208 questionnaires were returned. Excluding the same- answer and too much missing data surveys, we used 175 for our data analysis work. Out of the 175 subjects, 48% were male and 52% were female. Participants were asked to indicate their education status, 6% received a Doctorate degree, 18% received a Master degree, 26% were in graduate school, 28% received a Bachelor degree, and 22% were in college or less. The age range of the sample was predominately under 30 (62%), with relatively few subjects who were over 30 (38%).

4.2. Preliminary analyses
Prior to starting the empirical analysis, we conducted an examination of a dataset, including missing data analysis and two checks for the bias (i.e., non-response and common method).

4.2.1. Missing completely at random
Using Little’s MCAR test, we tested our data set to determine whether it meets the assumption of missing completely at random (MCAR). The results (χ2 (214) = 244.274, p = .076) showed that the data are missing completely at random. In order to preserve the maximum number of cases, we substituted a simple mean for the missing data (Little & Rubin, 1987).
4.2.2. Non-response bias
This aspect was assessed by comparing early (those who responded to the first mailing) with the late respondents (those who responded after the reminder). The results showed no statistically significant difference between these two groups. We thus determined that non-response bias did not present an issue for this study.

4.2.3. Common method bias
To reduce common method bias, Podsakoff, MacKenzie, Lee, and Podsakoff (2003) suggest use procedures during the design of study and data collection processes. Following the guidelines, we protected respondent–researcher anonymity, provided clear directions to the best of our ability, and proximally separated independent and dependent variables (Podsakoff et al., 2003). We then tested for bias statistically. Harman’s one factor test (Brewer, Campbell, & Crano, 1970; Greene & Organ, 1973; Harman, 1960) was used to determine if common method bias is a threat to the validity of this study’s results. The unrotated factor solution indicates the largest factor accounts for 35.868% of the variance, which is below 50%. The result also suggests that common method bias is not a significant threat to the validity of our study.
4.3. Measures
All items are adapted from literature and modified as needed for this study, as shown in Table 1. All items used a seven-point Likert scale (ranging from 1 = “strong disagree” to 7 = “strong agree”). Social commerce constructs was measured using Hajli (2014a, 2014b)’s 4-items scale. The social support (SC) construct looks at both the emotional and informational dimensions of social support theory. It was assessed using the Hajli (2014a, 2014b)’s simplified 7-items scale that includes the dimensions of emotional support and informational support. Trust was evaluated using the Gefen, Straub, and Boudreau (2000)’s 3-items. For the measurement, we asked participants to rate the extent to which they trust on the online communities.
Table 1. Summary of measurement scales.
Construct	Item #	Scale items and EFA factor loadings	Source
Social commerce constructs	SCIS1	I will ask my friends on forums and communities to provide me with their suggestions before I go shopping for a new product. (.609)	Hajli (2014a, 2014b, 2015)
SCIS2	I am willing to recommend a new product that is worth buying for my friends on this online community. (.683)
SCIS3	I am willing to share my own shopping experience of a new product with my friends on forums and communities or through ratings and reviews. (.719)
SCIS4	I would like to use people’s online recommendations to buy a new product. (.671)

Emotional support	SE1	When faced with difficulties, some people on this online community are on my side with me. (.782)	Hajli, 2015
SE2	When faced with difficulties, some people on this online community comforted and encouraged me. (.686)
SE3	When faced with difficulties, some people on this online community listened to me talking about my private feelings. (.846)
SE4	When faced with difficulties, some people on this online community expressed interest and concern in
my well-being. (.818)
Informational support	SI1	On this online community, some people would offer suggestions when I needed help. (.742)
SI2	When I encountered a problem, some people on this online community would give me information to help me overcome the problem. (.689)
SI3	When faced with difficulties, some people on this online community would help me discover the cause and provide me with suggestions. (.612)

Trust	T1	The performance of this online community always meets my expectations. (.840)	Gefen, Straub, and Boudreau (2000)
T2	This online community can be counted on as a good online community. (.841)
T3	This online community is a reliable online community. (.586)]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Results of measurement model testing" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
5. Results of measurement model testing
Given our research model and objectives, structural equation modeling (SEM) has some advantages over other analysis techniques such as linear regression because SEM can examine proposed causal paths among constructs (Gefen, Straub, & Boudreau, 2000; Gefen, Karahanna, & Straub, 2003; Rigdon, 1998). We analyzed the data using IBM Amos 22.
5.1. Descriptive statistics, reliability and validity
Table 2 presents the means, standard deviations, Cronbach’s alphas, AVEs and the construct correlations. The Cronbach’s alphas (ranging from .673 to .801) indicate a satisfactory degree of internal consistency reliability of the measures, except the construct of discomfort presents poor but acceptable reliability (Bollen & Lennox, 1991).
Table 2. Descriptive statistics and correlation.
Variable	Mean	S.D.	α	CR	1	2	3	4
SCIS	5.207	.884	.673	.953	.837			
SE	4.539	1.012	.733	.804	.355**	.509		
SI	5.130	.912	.801	.803	.516**	.592**	.577	
T	5.150	.856	.735	.753	.310**	.435**	.452**	.508
Note: N = 175; α: Cronbach’s alpha; CR: composite construct reliabilities; AVEs on diagonal
*p < 0.05, **p < 0.01, ***p < 0.001.

Construct reliability was assessed based on the composite construct reliabilities (CR) computed with the formula: ρ =  (Σli) 2/ ((Σλi) 2 + Σθi), where λi refers to the ith factor loading and θi refers to the ith error variance (Hair Jr. et al., 2010, p. 687). As shown in Table 2, CRs range from 0.803 and 0.953, with greater than the commonly accepted cutoff value of .70 (Gefen, Straub, & Boudreau, 2000; Hair Jr. et al., 2010), which demonstrates adequate reliability of the measures. Discriminant validity was first assessed by examining the factor correlations. Although there are no firm rules, inter-construct correlations below |.7| provide evidence of measure distinctness, and thus discriminant validity (Ping, 2003). No factor correlation is greater than .7, which demonstrates discriminant validity (see Table 2). Another way to examine discriminant validity is to compare the average variance extracted (AVE) to the squared inter-construct correlation. When the AVE is larger than the corresponding squared inter-construct correlation estimates, it suggests that the indicators have more in common with the construct they are associated with than they do with other constructs, which again provides evidence of discriminant validity (Kline, 2010). The data provided in Table 2 suggests adequate divergent validity of the measures.
An exploratory factor analysis with varimax rotation for all constructs was conducted to test construct validity. Factor loadings for each constructs are shown in Table 1. The results indicated that all factor loadings were greater than 0.5, showing a good convergent validity. The results confirmed the existence of four observed constructs with eigenvalues greater than 1.0, meaning a good discriminant validity in this study.
5.2. Measurement model
First, we analyzed a measurement model to assess the measurement quality of constructs by using a confirmatory factor analysis (CFA). The measurement model consists of four latent factors and 10 indicators. The range of loadings for the social commerce constructs factors is from .609 to .719. The ranges of loadings for the two social support factors are as follows emotional support, .686–.846; informational support, .612–742. The range of loadings for the trust is from .586 to .841.

The model chi- square is statistically significant (χ2 (73) = 205.660, p < .001), which indicates that the exact fit hypothesis is rejected. However, this test is highly sensitive (Jöreskog & Sörbom, 1989). We, therefore, examined other measures of goodness-of-fit. The comparative fit index (CFI) is .837 which exceeds the cutoff value of .80 (Browne & Cudeck, 1993; Hair, Anderson, Tatham, & Black, 2009). The two fit indices are satisfactory but not higher as expected. This might be affected by the sample size (Bollen, 1990). The root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA) is .086 which is less than .1 (Byrne, Pitts, Wilson, & Steiner, 2012). Thus, we conclude that our data adequately fit the measurement model.
5.3. Structural model
After confirming adequate fit for the measurement model, we assessed the fit of our structural model. The goodness-of-fit of the structural model was comparable to that of the previously described CFA model. The hypothesized model appears to fit the data well, as shown in Fig. 2. We did not conduct post-hoc modifications because of the good fit of the data to the model. With evidence of acceptable fit, we proceeded to test our hypotheses.
Fig. 2
Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Structural model.
Note: *p < .05, **p < .01, ***p < .001.
Model fitness: χ2 (df) = 205.660 (73), p < 0.001, CFI = .837, GFI = .863; IFI = .841; NFI = .773; NNFI = .717; RMSEA = .086.
5.4. Hypothesis testing
The four hypotheses presented earlier were tested using the structural equation modeling (SEM) approach. The three latent variables were linked as hypothesized. Model estimation was done using the maximum likelihood technique. We chose maximum likelihood parameter estimation over other estimation methods (e.g., weighted least squares, two-stage least squares) because the data were fairly normally distributed (Kline, 2010). The results are shown in Table 3. All the partial paths are significant at least .05 level.
Table 3. Estimation results structural model.
Relationships	β	t-value	p-value	Conclusion
SCIS → SE	.716	4.636	<.001	H1a supported
SCIS → SI	.838	5.638	<.001	H1b supported
SE → T	.315	2.372	<.05	H2a supported
SI → T	.321	2.543	<.05	H2b supported
Note: *p < .05, **p < .01, ***p < .001.
Legend: SCIS: social commerce constructs; SE: emotional support; SI: informational support; T: trust.


]]><h target="3" match="part">Hypothesis 1a posited that the higher social commerce constructs will result in greater emotional support. Our results support Hypothesis 1a. Similarly, the higher social commerce constructs will also lead to greater informational support (Hypothesis 1b). Our results indicate that Hypothesis 1b is also supported.</h><![CDATA[ Hypotheses 2a and Hypotheses 2b stated the greater emotional support and informational support will increase participants’ trust on online community. The results showed that the two hypotheses are both significant.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Discussion" category="discussion">
        <![CDATA[
6. Discussion
This study introduces a theoretical framework that integrates the social commerce constructs and the emotional and informational support from the social support to test trust-building. To be specific, it investigated the constructs that affect trust in an online community context by conducting a quantitative study. Precisely, a research model that integrates the social commerce constructs and the constructs of social support; emotional and informational support and how they build trust on an online community is proposed and evaluated in this study. The empirical evidence supports two key findings as hypothesized, ]]><h target="3" match="full">(1) the presence of social commerce constructs lead to greater emotional and informational support;</h><![CDATA[ and (2) the effect of social support measured by emotional and informational support increases participants’ trust in online communities. These findings highlight that the model emphasized the role of social commerce constructs into generating a higher sense of emotional and informational support hence increasing the level of trust a participant possess when participating in an online community context.

With the development of Internet and social media, more and more consumers are becoming information sources and information seekers. As is widely acknowledged, acquiring as much as information is one of the prerequisites before making an order online. Trust has always been seen as a vital component when considering an online transaction. Trust is central in an online community platform as it defines an individual’s act of obligatory. It is therefore central to investigate the constructs that can increase trust in an online community context. Consistent with previous studies, the role of trust is highlighted in this study. The findings can increase an understanding of trust-building in social commerce. Specifically, the results of this research indicate that social commerce constructs can lead to greater emotional and informational support, and the effect of social support measured by emotional and informational support can increase participants’ trust in online communities.]]><h target="3" match="part">Empirical investigation significantly supports the assertion that social commerce constructs increase both the emotional and informational support leading to an increase in trust on online community platforms.</h>From the study findings, we can also have more knowledge of how to build trust. <h target="1" match="part">Unlike other previous studies simply viewing social support as a second-order construct, we use social commerce constructs as the antecedent and test its role on social support from emotional and informational perspectives.</h> <h target="4" match="part">This extends past research. Consist with previous studies (e.g., Hajli, 2014a), we can clearly find that social commerce constructs positively influence social support.</h> <h target="2" match="full">However, the results indicate that the effect on emotional support is more significant than that on informational support.</h><![CDATA[ The findings of our research reflect upon the second order construct of the social support construct separately which is one contribution of this research. In addition, findings of our research empirically report an increase in participants’ trust with the integration of both the emotional and informational constructs. There is a positive ascent from 28% of trust in past research by Hajli, 2015 to 32.4% in our research when social commerce constructs are integrated with the social support constructs. This study therefore develops a theoretical foundation for social commerce by integrating the social commerce constructs and the social support constructs, namely emotional and informational support, in building trust. ]]><h target="4" match="part">Thus, the findings extend social support theory and trust literature by unraveling the relationships among social commerce constructs, emotional support, informational support, and trust.</h><![CDATA[
From a practical perspective, this study emphasizes the importance of integrating social commerce constructs alongside with social support constructs because this can lead to a higher level of trust. The results serve as a mechanism to e-vendors as to how social commerce constructs and social support constructs can be used as a trust-building means in influencing online participants’ trust when engaging in an online community whether or not a purchase or online transactions are involved. It indicates that in order to build trust through social commerce constructs, e-vendors should create an environment with social support.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Limitations and future research direction;Conclusion" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
7. Limitations and future research direction
There are several limitations of this study. First, the generalizability of the empirical results is limited. In this study, we just tested our model with the data collection in some specific online communities. Therefore, the results may not be applicable to others in other social commerce contexts. Future studies should look into other social networking sites or online communities. Second, the representativeness of the sample is also limited. In this study, the participants were from Facebook, Trip Advisor, and LinkedIn in Malaysia. Thus, a larger sample and different geographical locations for data collection work are needed to improve the study bias. This is to ensure the findings can be generalized to a larger population. Third, there might be some other potential factors that might be considered for model testing work. The role of social support is emphasized in this study. However, other factors in developing trust in social commerce can also be very important, which also deserves investigating. This can be a future research direction to explore trust-building work in social commerce. Last, the age of the participants is also a limitation. It might be a moderator on the social support. Future research might take it into the model when collecting larger data for analysis.
8. Conclusion
Trust in social commerce has caused scholars’ great attention. To investigate how the trust is built in social commerce, we proposed a framework and made hypotheses development based on social support theory and previous literature. Following that, we used a survey approach and collected data from online communities in Malaysia. The data were analyzed to test our model with structural equation modeling. The findings highlight the role of social support in building trust. The results of this research indicate that social commerce constructs lead to greater emotional and informational support. The effect of social support, including emotional and informational support, increases participants’ trust in online communities. Because of the limitation of the generalizability and contexts, future studies with a larger sample and different geographical location are encouraged to investigate how our findings can be generalized to larger populations. Future research should also look into testing the model with other online communities as it will be interesting to find the diversity that exists in various other groups mediated by the Web 2.0 technologies. Overall, this study investigates the social support constructs during trust-building from both emotional and informational perspective and hence arrives at some novel findings. To conclude, our results shed some lights on social commerce literature and trust theory.]]>
    </section>
</publication>