<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="zhouzhichao">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 3, June 2016, Pages 322-332</time>
    <title>The user multifaceted expertise: Divergent effects of the website versus e-commerce expertise</title>
    <author>Muhammad Aljukhadar.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Sylvain Senecal.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace1. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
King Abdulaziz University, Faculty of Economics and Administration, Jeddah 21589, Saudi Arabia
b
HEC Montreal, Marketing Department 3000 Côte Sainte-Catherine, Montreal, QC H3T 2A7, Canada
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2015.11.006</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">Site expertise and e-commerce expertise differently impact cognitive effort, site adaptation, and acceptance.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">Site expertise determined the user cognitive effort, while e-commerce expertise did not.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">Site expertise and e-commerce expertise had divergent effects on the site adaptation and acceptance.</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">These results were replicated in a different culture.</highlight>
Abstract
    <abstract><![CDATA[Expertise is a key factor in user’s adaptation and evaluation of the IT artifact. To date however, research has widely disregarded the notion that expertise is multifaceted and, consequently, its effects should vary according to the facet measured. To address this gap, the present research shows the effects of a facet of expertise rarely studied – expertise with the artifact such as an e-commerce site (website expertise) – besides the effects of expertise with the artifact class (e-commerce expertise).]]><h target="1;3" match="part;part">It is stipulated that site expertise shapes the site use and acceptance differently and more profoundly than e-commerce expertise.</h><![CDATA[  The results show that users with low (vs. high) site expertise perceived the site as less easy to use, and their site acceptance was more (less) strongly influenced by the site information quality. Alternatively, e-commerce expertise played a different moderating role in the acceptance process, and users with low e-commerce expertise did not perceive the site as less easy to use. ]]><h target="4" match="full">The results were replicated in a second study conducted in a different culture.</h>The findings support the research main thesis that expertise is multifaceted and, therefore, considering the different facets is necessary to understand the process of user acceptance of the IT artifact.</abstract>
Keywords
    <keywords>User expertise</keywords>
    <keywords>Expertise dimensions</keywords>
    <keywords>Ease of use</keywords>
    <keywords>Website expertise</keywords>
    <keywords>E-commerce expertise</keywords>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
Studying the process of user acceptance of the artifact is vital because it helps predict IS outcomes (Kock, Lynn, Dow, & Akgün, 2006). Little quantitative research however has examined how users adapt and accept the IT artifact. Many of the conceptual frameworks proposed in the relevant literature have adapted reductionist models such as TAM; moreover, they generally have not theorized or empirically examined the acceptance behaviour (Benbasat & Barki, 2007). Concomitantly, whereas research has studied several factors influencing user acceptance and attitude toward the IT artifact, it has not adequately theorized about the role of user expertise.
The e-commerce website is an example of a frequently encountered IT artifact. Online shoppers in the United States are expected to spend $371 billion in 2016 (excluding travel), up 41% from 2013; accordingly, online retail will account for 11% of total retail sales in 2016 (Forrester, 2015). The growing popularity of Internet shopping drives companies to focus on designing websites that perform better. Research suggests that the perceived ease of use (EOU) of a website and other site-related factors influence its acceptance. Johnson, Bellman, and Lohse (2003) showed that websites that are easier to learn how to use show higher rates of purchasing. A website that is easier to use and that delivers a compelling experience motivates visitors to use and return to it—i.e., to accept it (Kwon & Lennon, 2009).
The user level of expertise is a key factor in user’s acceptance and evaluation of the artifact. The likelihood of an optimal experience is dependent on the interplay between the person, the task, and the artifact (Finneran & Zhang, 2003). Expertise was considered a central factor that should be accounted for when studying user online behaviour (Novak, Hoffman, & Yung, 2000). To date however, research in general has underestimated the role of expertise. Importantly, research has widely disregarded the notion that expertise is multifaceted and, consequently, its effects on the acceptance process should vary according to the facet considered.
Expertise is a construct that continues to gain prominence due to development in the cognitive psychology and artificial intelligence fields (Chi, Glaser, & Farr, 2014). Expertise (at times referred to as prior knowledge, familiarity, and skill) has been widely considered unidimensional. In their seminal work however, Alba and Hutchinson (1987) indicated that product expertise is multifaceted. Considering expertise in user studies, and differentiating between its facets, is thus vital. Disregarding contextual and user-related factors results in poor external validity for models developed in experimental settings (Gallivan, 2001). Furthermore, applied research showed the importance of considering expertise. Paris (1988) discussed how a model that considers user expertise to generate personalized answers outperforms other models. Nonetheless, the little research that showed the influence of online expertise has resulted in inconclusive results (e.g., Chang, Cheung, & Lai, 2005).
In order to respond to the question of whether user expertise is a critical, multifaceted factor in acceptance and usage studies, the current research (1) theorizes and empirically examines the role played by the artifact-specific expertise (website expertise) versus generic expertise (e-commerce expertise), (2) shows how user adaptation and acceptance of the artifact can be better understood by considering the different facets of expertise, and (3) discusses the importance of taking into consideration the multifaceted nature of expertise and the need to develop measures to capture its facets in future work.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Theoretical background;The effects of expertise on artifact adaptation and acceptance" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Theoretical background
2.1. Underlying conceptual framework
The Technology Acceptance Model (TAM) focuses on the influence that perceived usefulness and perceived EOU have on the artifact acceptance; TAM is considered to be one of the most influential theories in organizational research (Benbasat & Barki, 2007). Although TAM is based in part on the Theory of Reasoned Actions (TRA; Fishbein & Ajzen, 1975), the two approaches differ in that TAM takes into consideration only two salient user beliefs concerning a given artifact: usefulness and EOU. Building on TRA and TAM, we propose that artifact-related factors influence ease of use and attitude toward the artifact. Attitude, in turn, drives behavioral intentions.
By applying this theory to the context of the commercial website, we advance that site-related factors should influence the EOU and attitude toward the site (Fig. 1). Website information quality, interactivity, aesthetics, and trust are well established site-related factors that have been found to correlate with the site attitude and behavioural intentions (Dickinger & Stangl 2013; Kim, Williams, & Lee, 2004; Lee & Kozar, 2006; Poddar, Donthu, & Wei, 2009; Appendix A for the definition and measure of each construct).
Conceptual framework
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Conceptual framework.
The main effects in Fig. 1 have been established in research. Kim et al. (2004), for instance, suggested that there are positive relationships between the information quality, trust, aesthetics, and EOU of a site with the user attitude toward that site. Nonetheless, little work has focused on the potential moderators to the acceptance process. A main thesis of this paper is that the facets of user expertise differently affect site acceptance and, therefore, considering the multifaceted nature of expertise is vital to shed light on the process of user adoption and acceptance of the IT artifact. The expertise facets are hypothesized to differently moderate the model’s main effects.
An examination of the factors that moderate the relationships between EOU and attitude and their antecedents is pivotal as it helps reveal boundary conditions and contributes to an in-depth understanding of the acceptance process. As suggested by Benbasat and Barki (2007), studies that examine the antecedents of the two salient beliefs comprising the TAM (EOU and usefulness) will help establish guidelines for the design of better IT artifacts. Elie-Dit-Cosaque and Straub (2011) discussed how the user acceptance and adaptation of the IT artifact has been treated as a black box. They extended the Coping Theory, as developed by Beaudry and Pinsonneault (2005), to explain the user adaptation phase of technology. Nonetheless, this and other research in the domain have underestimated or overlooked the expertise factor.
2.2. Role of expertise
The mitigating role of expertise has been shown in various contexts. Level of expertise was found to influence product evaluation. Expertise was found to affect the evaluative responses to product information (Sujan, 1985). Bettman and Sujan (1987) found that in a choice of comparable alternatives, priming an attribute such as reliability affected novices’ choices but not those of experts. When product information was unambiguous, low expertise consumers based their evaluations on country of origin, while high expertise consumers based their evaluations on attribute strength (Maheswaran, 1994). Users with less expertise perceive a higher risk in decision making (Heilman, Douglas, & Gordon, 2000). Research also investigated the impact of expertise on information acquisition and retrieval. For instance, men’s use of online reviews depended on their level of expertise (Kim, Mattila, & Baloglu, 2011).
The importance of studying expertise stems from the essential challenge/skill balance factor (Csikszentmihalyi, 1988), which measures a user’s perception of how challenging the task is compared to how skillful the user is in performing the task. Perceived ease of use is actually the user’s perceived skills relative to the challenge posed by the artifact (Venkatesh & Davis, 2000). The Person-artifact-Task model, proposed by Finneran and Zhang (2003), underscores the importance of user’s expertise and attitude in shaping artifact usage. To evaluate a computer, experts focus on technical attributes, whereas novices focus on simple benefit information (Maheswaran & Sternthal, 1990). These authors, however, measured expertise by objective knowledge. Focusing as well on objective knowledge, Moreau, Lehmann, and Markman (2001) indicated that the effect of expertise on the adoption of a new product is complex.
Mandel and Johnson (2002) showed that expertise moderates product search behaviour. Navarro-Prieto, Scaife and Rogers (1999) studied cognitive strategies in searching the Web. They found that expert searchers plan ahead, while novice searchers do not have a clear plan and are more driven by external representations (what is experienced on the screen). Klein and Ford (2003) focused on objective and subjective expertise to study online information search. They found that high expertise users perform more information search than users with a moderate level of expertise, but less information search than users with low expertise.
Lucassen and Schraagen (2011) considered domain expertise and showed that trust judgments of domain experts (vs. novices) are influenced (not influenced) by accuracy. In an e-learning context, Lin (2011) highlighted that perceived ease of use has a stronger effect on the intention of the novice user, whereas perceived usefulness has a stronger effect for the expert user. Lin also found that the impact of satisfaction on intention is stronger for the novice user. Indeed, expertise was shown as a significant moderator within the Unified Theory of Acceptance and Use of Technology UTAUT (Venkatesh, Thong, & Xu, 2012).
2.3. E-Commerce expertise and the website expertise
The multifaceted nature of expertise has been underscored. In the marketing context, Alba and Hutchinson (1987) indicated that product expertise has five dimensions (cognitive effort, cognitive structure, analysis, elaboration, and memory). Kadan, Madureira, Wang, and Zach (2012) differentiated between two facets of an analyst’s expertise (within-industry expertise versus across-industry expertise). Dane, Rockmann, and Pratt (2012) focused on domain expertise and showed how it contributes to intuitive decision-making effectiveness. Sedera and Dey (2013) studied expertise from a contemporary information systems perspective. They underscored the multidimensional nature of expertise and suggested that prior approaches to measuring expertise are incomplete and outdated.
In the context of Web search, the study of Hölscher and Strube (2000) is perhaps the first trial to show the relevance of different facets of expertise. These authors viewed Web expertise as the general knowledge and skills necessary to utilize the Internet effectively to solve information search problems, while domain-expertise is the knowledge of searching in a specific field. As hypothesized, the two facets of expertise differently affected search effectiveness (Hölscher & Strube, 2000).
Moreau et al. (2001) indicated that researchers have studied three types of expertise: objective expertise (accurate information of the artifact stored in memory), subjective expertise (self-assessed or self-efficacy perceptions), and artifact-related expertise (the number of encounters with the artifact). Importantly, their work suggests that artifact expertise (target expertise) is different from expertise with the artifact class (base expertise), and that both facets of expertise should differently impact adoption behaviour.
We build on the above theory in differentiating between the level of expertise with the artifact (site expertise; i.e., user’s level of expertise with a specific website; e.g., Murray & Häubl, 2007) and the level of expertise with the artifact class (e-commerce expertise; i.e., user’s level of expertise with e-commerce sites and applications; e.g., Page, Robson, & Uncles, 2012). Importantly, we stipulate that each facet of expertise has unique effects on site acceptance.
3. The effects of expertise on artifact adaptation and acceptance
3.1. Effects of expertise facets on user’s cognitive effort
Suppose that a user who has a low (vs. high) level of expertise is trying to achieve a task on a given website. Will this user perceive a low level of the site EOU? Will the user need more time to accomplish the task? In other words, will this user devote more cognitive effort than a user with a high level of expertise to accomplish the same task? At first sight, the answers to these questions look straightforward. However, the existence of different facets to user expertise makes the answers far less direct.

Expertise shapes use behaviour by means of different processes. First, computer anxiety should be affected by computer skill deficit (Simonson, Maurer, Montag-Torardi, & Whitaker, 1987). Less expertise means higher anxiety. Computer anxiety was associated with the perceived EOU (Venkatesh, 2000). Alternatively, perceived control reflects the degree to which the user feels in control in using an artifact. The expertise level should also positively affect the user’s perceived control, which is detrimental in defining user performance. Finneran and Zhang (2003) explained that:
“In computer-mediated environments, activity needs to be broken down into the task (main goal of the activity) and the artifact (tool for accomplishing the activity). The mastering of artifacts within CMEs cannot be taken for granted due to the complex and dynamic nature of the artifacts (computers). For example, calculating travel expenses with a spreadsheet is a much different activity than doing it with pencil and paper. When a person uses pencil and paper to calculate travel expenses, it is assumed that the person has no problem with using pencil and paper; thus, they are transparent or not noticed. This assumption does not necessarily hold when the person uses a spreadsheet. Depending on the person’s experience with the spreadsheet, it can be transparent (a skillful user) thus the person focuses on calculating travel expenses, or cumbersome (a novice user) thus the person struggles with the spreadsheet and it interferes with his/her primary task of calculating travel expenses.”


In effect, the site expertise should enhance perceived ease of use. Some research has measured perceived EOU using four items (clear and understandable interaction with the particular artifact, easy to become skillful with the artifact, easy to get the artifact to do what I want, and interacting with the artifact does not require a lot of mental effort; Venkatesh, 2000). While some of these items relate to the artifact per se, several items relate to the level of site expertise. For instance, a user that is expert with a site will find it easier to get the site to do what he or she wants. Therefore, this user will perceive and report high EOU levels.
Empirical evidence is in favor of the viewpoint advanced above. Johnson et al. (2003) found shoppers to change their behaviour according to their site visit history. They found shoppers to spend more time during the initial visits, and less time in later visits to accomplish a purchasing task. The cognitive effort and time associated with achieving a task on a site should diminish as users become more expert in using the site. The time spent to achieve a task is an objective proxy of the cognitive effort a user dispenses. As they became more expert in using the site, users should perceive the site as more easy to use and should require less time to perform their tasks.
H1a: users with high (vs. low) level of site expertise will perceive the site as easier to use.
H1b: users with high (vs. low) level of site expertise will require less time to achieve their online tasks.
The ensuing and more challenging question is: what is the role of generic expertise on the cognitive effort to use the artifact? Will a user who is more expert with e-commerce sites find it easier to get a site to do what he or she wants? Stated differently, is the expertise with the artifact class automatically transferable to the artifact? While this question is relevant and has several implications, the literature review reveals that no decisive answer has been found.

The knowledge transfer paradigm, used in analogical learning, offers a base for distinguishing between the roles of the different facets of expertise on the adaptation behaviour (Gentner, Rattermann, & Forbus 1993). By enabling knowledge transfer from the artifact class (e-commerce sites) to the artifact (a certain site), users should more quickly learn how to use the artifact and, thus, be able to perform a task with less cognitive effort. When the site shares several similarities with the ensemble of e-commerce sites, access to generic knowledge should automatically occur (Gentner et al., 1993), and the user should benefit from e-commerce expertise to achieve a task with less cognitive effort.
Given the wide variety of the design, structure, and end-product of e-commerce sites, it is unlikely for a website to share many similarities with the ensemble of e-commerce sites. Access to generic knowledge is less likely to happen, and the user should not broadly benefit from the accumulated e-commerce expertise. Armstrong and Hardgrave (2007), building on the Theory of Mindshift Learning, reached supportive conclusions. They suggest that expertise in a certain artifact does not necessarily lead to better efficiency in accepting a new, similar artifact. More specifically, they found experts to achieve better results only if they perceive the new artifact as being novel or having carryover, but not as changed.
H2a: users with high (vs. low) level of e-commerce expertise will perceive the same level of the site ease of use.
H2b: users with high (vs. low) level of e-commerce expertise will require the same time to achieve their online tasks.
3.2. Effects of expertise facets on the acceptance process
Expertise should impact how users evaluate and accept the IT artifact. Evaluative criteria were shown to change as consumers gain more product expertise (Alba & Huchinson, 1987). The acceptance of an artifact should take place in the light of the experiences accumulated in memory (Mason & Bequette, 1998). As the main thesis of this paper indicates, and because the accumulated expertise can be specific (site expertise) or generic (e-commerce expertise), the role played by each facet on acceptance behaviour should considerably vary.
Facets of expertise, thus, are hypothesized to affect the acceptance process depicted in Fig. 1. This proposition is relevant because it implies that user’s needs with regard to site-related factors are dynamic rather than static and because it contemplates the multifaceted nature of expertise. Empirical evidence is in support of this expected role for expertise. In developing a measure of website service quality, Parasuraman, Zeithaml, and Malhotra (2005) found that the determinants of the site’s perceived quality were different for users with routine versus users with non-routine encounters with the site.
The effect of generic over specific expertise on the acceptance process can be understood using the categorization approach (Fiske, 1982). According to this approach, if a new website is categorized by a user as belonging to a defined category, the expertise associated with the category can be quickly retrieved and applied. This is because one’s prior experience with the category (i.e., category schema) usually serves as a guide to evaluations. In such a situation, the site acceptance should be based less on the site-specific factors and more on the accumulated experiences. Alternatively, if the categorization attempt failed (e.g., because the closest category implied that some attributes were inconsistent with those of the target site), the user will evaluate the site in a “piecemeal mode” (Fiske, 1982). Given that e-commerce sites widely vary in their design, structure, and the end-product they offer (as implied by H2), the “piecemeal mode” is the one predicted for most users. User acceptance should be derived directly from the site-related factors, and the facets of expertise should thus act as moderators.
3.2.1. Moderating role of site expertise
Detailed and precise information on the site should increase its EOU particularly for users with low site expertise. This is because these users are willing to spend more effort to get acquainted with the site compared to users with high site expertise (Power Law of Practice applied by Johnson et al., 2003). Users with low site expertise will, thus, benefit more from quality information. Therefore, the impact of information quality on site acceptance (i.e., on the site EOU and site attitude) should be stronger for users with low level of site expertise.
Alternatively, while the impact of trust on attitude has been shown (Kim et al., 2004), we stipulate that this impact should intensify with the site expertise. High site expertise reflects more site visits. Trust increases with experience (Blau, 1964). Trust also increases with interaction frequency (Gefen, 2000). Users with more interactions with a website better recognize its security features and privacy policy (Yoon, 2002), which leads them to trust the site more. Therefore, the effect of trust on site acceptance (i.e., on the site EOU and site attitude) should be stronger for users with high site expertise. Site expertise is not predicted to moderate the other main effects in the model.
H3a: the effects of site information quality on the site acceptance will be stronger for users with low (vs. high) site expertise.
H3b: the effects of site trust on the site acceptance will be stronger for users with high (vs. low) site expertise.
H3c: the effects of the other site-related factors on the site acceptance will be equivalent (i.e., invariant) for users with high and low site expertise.
3.2.2. Moderating role of e-commerce expertise
Users with high artifact-class expertise should be able to accurately assess the artifact EOU and be more affected by this key factor. Moorthy, Ratchford, and Talukdar (1997) indicated that as users gain expertise, they evaluate product qualities more accurately. In addition, high expertise users were shown to focus on the technical or core attributes (Bell, Auh, & Smalley, 2005).
As users gain e-commerce expertise, converting them to loyal users becomes more difficult. Indeed, e-commerce experts would have learned and used several e-commerce sites. Because they can better benchmark sites with regard to their usability and can select from a variety of sites (Moorthy et al., 1997), users with high e-commerce expertise should be more reluctant to accept a site that is relatively hard to use.
Following the same reasoning, users with high e-commerce expertise should better benchmark sites with regard to their aesthetics. Mandel and Johnson (2002) manipulated aesthetic elements on the site and found that the manipulation had a direct impact on the choice of users with high expertise. By gaining more e-commerce expertise, users’ preferences grow in sophistication. These users will appreciate more the hedonic features of a website such as its aesthetics. Therefore, the effects of the site aesthetics on the site acceptance should be stronger for these users. Alternatively, e-commerce expertise is not predicted to moderate the other main effects in the model.
H4a: the effects of site ease of use on the site acceptance will be stronger for users with high (vs. low) e-commerce expertise.
H4b: the effects of site aesthetics on the site acceptance will be stronger for users with high (vs. low) e-commerce expertise.
H4c: the effects of the other site-related factors on the site acceptance will be equivalent (i.e., invariant) for users with high and low e-commerce expertise.]]>
    </section>
    <section name=" Methodology" category="methods">
        <![CDATA[
4. Methodology
4.1. Data collection and design
A large-scale study was performed in collaboration with a leading market research company in Canada. The company had a consumer panel of over 350,000 participants at the time of data collection. The company builds its consumer panel mainly through its own website. Potential panel members enter their personal data and contact information and are given the chance to win monthly monetary prizes; their chances of winning increase when they participate in a given study.

To improve the ability to generalize from the findings and reduce the effects of sector-related and organization-related factors such as organization loyalty and site awareness (Kwon & Lennon, 2009; Yoon, 2002), websites representing a number of organizations in a variety of sectors were included in the study. Appendix B reports the sample size and the websites included in each of the two studies.
An email list corresponding to the randomly selected panel members was used to send these members an invitation to participate in the study. The response rate was close to those of previous research projects conducted by the market research company (approximately 20%). Upon receiving the invitation email, panel members could choose to participate by clicking on the provided hyperlink. The link opened a window that contained an interactive link to the company’s website and provided an explanation of the task to be performed and a link to the randomly assigned website.

Because e-commerce users are generally goal-oriented (Wolfinbarger & Gilly, 2003), and because this study was focused on goal-oriented environments, each participant was assigned a task to perform on a randomly assigned site. The assigned tasks were identical within each sector, had comparable levels of complexity, and consisted of retrieving a piece of information on the assigned website. Assigning a task would also ensure sufficient interaction with the website, and hence better measurements of the site-related variables.
After completing the task (one task on one website for each participant, i.e., between-subject design), the participant returned to the initial window and clicked the “continue” button to respond to the study questionnaire.

4.2. Replication study
To show the external and predictive validity of the model and to replicate the results concerning the moderating roles of expertise facets, a second study was performed using a different population. The same steps were followed in the second study. However, the samples were selected from a panel of French-speaking consumers (residing in the predominantly French-speaking region of Canada). In this study, the tasks and measurements were administered in French. In addition, participants were given the link to the French version of the website and several websites active in the French-speaking region were added (Appendix B).
Pooling the data sets for the sectors resulted in a final sample of 7253 responses for the first study (the English-speaking participants) and an additional 5882 responses for the second study (the French-speaking participants).

4.3. Measures
In the questionnaire, the first item asked the participant to respond to a question concerning the task. The difference in task completion time (interchangeably termed task time) for participants who succeeded in entering the correct task response and those who did not was small and insignificant (3.40 vs. 3.25 min.; F = 1.57, NS). We concluded that, whether or not they successfully responded to the tasks, the participants spent enough time on the websites and that, while retrieving the required information, they expended equal effort in using the sites.
The next set of items reflected the latent variables. The site-related factors’ subscales were identical or similar to those in the literature (Bressolles & Nantel, 2008; Loiacono, Watson, & Goodhue, 2007; Wolfinbarger & Gilly, 2003; Yoo & Donthu, 2001) and were pretested (all α’s >0.90; items used are reported in Appendix A).
Three items reflected the site attitude (I like this website; I think this is a good website; I think it is a pleasant website; α = 0.96; Chen & Wells, 1999) and three items reflected positive behavioral intentions toward the site (I will visit this website again in the future; This website is my reference for my needs of…; I will recommend visiting this website to a friend, family member, or colleague; α = 0.92; Bart, Shankar, Sultan, & Urban, 2005; Chen & Wells, 1999).
Site expertise was measured by the binary item (Was this your first visit to the website?). That is, for site expertise, we split the sample into low site expertise (participants who reported that they never encountered the site that was assigned to them in the experiment) and high site expertise. We followed this classification based on the power law of practice, which predicts that the difficulty to use a technology application significantly falls after the first encounter with the technology (Johnson et al., 2003). In the first study, 5151 (71.8%) of the respondents were first-time users of the website that was randomly assigned to them. In the second study, 4293 (73.8%) of the respondents were first-time users of the website that was randomly assigned to them.
For e-commerce expertise, because our literature review did not find a validated measure of this variable, we consider this facet of user expertise to be a generic form of expertise as indicated in the above sections. More specifically, we consider a user to have low e-commerce expertise if he or she (1) has not purchased goods using the internet or (2) has not been engaged in active searching of products and services on the web. This is because our literature review has pinpointed the latter two activities as the most relevant indicators to e-commerce expertise (Chen, 2012). Therefore, we used the following item to reflect this expertise facet “Have you already conducted electronic commerce activities or purchased goods using the Internet?” In the first study, more than half the participants (58.8%) answered yes to this question and, thus, were considered the high e-commerce expertise group. In the second study, 55.4% answered yes and were considered the high e-commerce expertise group in that study.
Indeed, the use of one item measure has been successfully conducted in research (Wanous, Reichers, & Hudy, 1997). The use of one item measures helps to reduce the length of relatively long questionnaires while maintaining reliability. Furthermore, the two items measuring the facets of expertise were separated by several other items to improve validity. The low correlation found between the two facets of expertise (r = 0.103, p = 0.00) was anticipated and indicates good discriminant validity for their measures. The last set of items pertained to demographics (51% females). A comparison of the sample demographics with those of the government census indicates that the sample can be considered representative of the adult consumer population.
4.4. Model validation
Prior to testing the research hypotheses, the base model (Fig. 1) was tested and validated. We used confirmatory factor analysis (LISREL), which has a distinctive advantage over other methods in that it accounts for all covariance in the data, and, thus, allows simultaneous examination of correlations, shared variance, path coefficients, and their significance (Bollen, 1998). To validate the model, we randomly divided the data into two equal portions, using one half to test the model (calibration sample) and the other half for cross-validation (validation sample). The covariance matrix was used for LISREL calculations.
The discriminant and convergent validity of a latent variable is confirmed when individual items load high (>0.5) on the intended factor and low (<0.4) on other factors. All items clearly met these criteria, except one (Q14 in Appendix A, which had a loading of 0.38 on the intended factor). Because the fit indices were satisfactory, this item was retained to ensure face validity.
    The model obtained from the calibration sample showed good fit (CFI = 0.97, GFI = 0.93, AGFI = 0.90, RMSEA = 0.064 with 90% confidence interval of 0.062–0.065). The root mean square error of estimation (RMSEA) was below the cut-off value for models with acceptable fit (0.08). The chi-square index was significant and large; Bentler (1990) illustrated that this index inflates for larger samples. The average variance extracted (AVE) of each latent variable was well above the threshold value of 0.50 (Fornell & Larcker, 1981) with interactivity having the smallest AVE, at 0.66, and attitude having the highest, at 0.89.
    The latent variables showed discriminant validity as demonstrated by the AVE value of each variable being greater than the shared variance with other variables (Fornell & Larcker, 1981) and by none of the confidence intervals of variable covariance (e.g., Φ ± two standard errors) including the value of 1 (Bagozzi & Yi, 1988).
    For cross-validation (simultaneous invariance check for the calibration sample with the validation sample), the parameters should be estimated simultaneously because, in multi-group SEM models, the fitting function represents a weighted combination of model fit across groups (Bollen, 1998). The accompanying model fit the data well (CFI = 0.97, GFI = 0.93, RMSEA = 0.062 [0.061–0.063]). It was concluded that the structural model was invariant, as the change in chi-square between the constrained model (structural paths between the latent variables set to be equal) versus the unconstrained model was insignificant (Δc2 = 13.1, Δdf = 8). This result shows the model’s predictive validity. The measurement model also showed acceptable invariance (Δχ2 = 31.4, Δdf = 16). The standardized coefficients of the invariant structural paths are the ones shown in Fig. 2. Because a large sample size contributes to type-I error (high power), the model was applied on smaller randomly selected samples (with N of 350) and the same structural paths were found to be significant, as in the latter model.
    SEM results with coefficients of the significant paths (coefficients of second…
    Download full-size image
    Fig. 2. SEM results with coefficients of the significant paths (coefficients of second study in italics).
    The model parameters were significant (the significant structural paths are the ones shown in Fig. 2). The site aesthetics, information quality, and interactivity positively influenced EOU. Alternatively, trust positively influenced site attitude. EOU fully mediated the path between information quality and attitude. Attitude was predictive of behavioral intentions (Fishbein & Ajzen, 1975), explaining 81% of the variance. As TRA predicts, attitude fully mediated the relationship between EOU and behavioral intentions (Fig. 2).
    4.5. Results of H1 and H2
    H1a and H2a each test for the difference in latent variable means of EOU. As such, the difference in the structured means was examined for significance (as advised and detailed in Byrne, 1998). Furthermore, ANOVA mean tests using the mathematical averages of EOU items were performed for comparison and yielded the same results as reported below.
    The difference in the EOU structured means for users with high versus low site expertise was significant as predicted (tα = 2.6), which lends support to H1a (the same result was obtained with the mean test of EOU items; 4.59 vs. 4.98; F = 84.3, p = 0.000). As expected, task time for users with low site expertise (3.60 minutes or min) was longer than that of users with high site experience (2.51 min; F = 76.66, p = 0.000). This result lends support to H1b.
    Alternatively, H2 received support. The difference in the structured means of EOU for users with high versus low e-commerce expertise was insignificant, as predicted by H2a (tα = 0.77). This result was in line with the mean difference of EOU items (M high_exp = 4.73, M low_exp = 4.72, F = 0.04, NS). The difference in task time for users with high versus low e-commerce expertise was also insignificant, as H2b predicts (M high_exp = 3.41 min., M low_exp = 3.57 min., F = 1.18, NS).
    To examine whether the above results were mitigated by the various levels of expertise (i.e., by a potential interaction effect between the two facets of expertise on EOU or task time), full factorial ANOVA tests were performed (Tables are reported in Appendix C). The results showed no interaction effects for the expertise facets on either EOU or task time.
    4.6. Results of H3 and H4
    To test for expertise moderation effects, univariate statistical analysis was applied using LISREL (Byrne, 1998, p. 259–341). This test individually examines invariance of the model relationships across groups. In a stringent test of the hypotheses concerning relationship invariance, each group was first randomly divided into two portions (calibration and validation samples) to test relationship invariance (similar to how the base model was tested). The model solution was then obtained simultaneously for the groups’ calibration samples, and the model fit indices were examined. When the measurement model was not invariant, it was freely estimated; otherwise it was constrained equal across groups. The difference in chi-square for each structural path (freely estimated versus constrained equal; Δdf = 1) was then tested for significance at p < 0.05.
    The results provide support for H3a and H3b; the test of invariance for each hypothesized path was associated with a significant change in chi-square value. Moreover, the differences in the accompanying standardized coefficients (provided in the brackets next to the chi-square difference) were substantial and in the predicted direction (Δχ2 information-EOU = 7.2 [0.10]; Δχ2 trust–attitude = 7.4 [0.07]). Invariance tests were also performed for the remainder of the structural paths for users with low versus high site expertise to test H3c, with the following results: Δχ2 interactivity–EOU NS; Δχ2 interactivity–attitude = 6.7 [0.09]; Δχ2 aesthetics–EOU NS; Δχ2 aesthetics–attitude NS; Δχ2 EOU–attitude = 4.6 [0.05]. These results indicate that H3c received moderate support.
    Alternatively, H4a was supported (Δχ2 ease of use-attitude = 8.2 [0.09]). H4b was supported because the chi-square difference was significant for the path between aesthetics and attitude (Δχ2 aesthetics–EOU NS; Δχ2 aesthetics–attitude = 3.9 [0.06]). H4c received support; the paths trust–attitude, information–attitude, interactivity–attitude, and interactivity–EOU were invariant across users with low versus high e-commerce expertise.]]>
    4.7. Replication study
        <h target="4" match="part">The input from the second study, conducted with a French-speaking sample, was used to retest the hypotheses. Applying the same tests detailed above, the results were largely replicated (a summary of results are reported in Appendix D). First, the structural paths found significant in the first study were also significant in the second study.</h> In addition, H1 and H2 received ample support. The results of H3a, H3b, H4a, and H4b were also replicated in the second study. Alternatively, H3c and H4c received moderate support.
    </section>
    <section name="Discussion and theoretical implications" category="discussion">
        <![CDATA[
    5. Discussion and theoretical implications
    This research builds on the theory of Moreau et al. (2001), Murray and Häubl (2007), and Page et al., 2012 to underscore the multifaceted nature of expertise in an online context. The results lend support to the paper’s main thesis: user expertise is multifaceted and each facet has unique effects on the artifact adoption and acceptance. First, the expertise facets differently affect the cognitive effort required to accomplish a task using the artifact. ]]><h target="2" match="full">The cognitive effort, measured by the perceived ease of use and the time required to accomplish the task, was affected by site expertise but not by e-commerce expertise.</h><![CDATA[ This result indicates that, in the context of e-commerce sites, the expertise with the artifact class is not automatically transferrable to the artifact. This result also contributes to the theory advanced by Armstrong and Hardgrave (2007), who adapted the Theory of Mindshift Learning and indicated that generic expertise does not always lead to better efficiency when using a new artifact. These authors suggest that generic expertise is beneficial in certain cases: if the new artifact was perceived as novel or carryover, but not as changed. The above findings entice researchers to investigate how to build websites and technology applications that are able to capture the generic expertise of the user.
    Whereas researchers have been reluctant to theorize about the effect of artifact-related factors on perceived EOU and attitude, they have also been reluctant to theorize about the role of expertise in shaping the acceptance process (Benbasat & Barki, 2007). Indeed, ease of use and usefulness has been treated as a black box with little work trying to understand the artifact acceptance process (Elie-Dit-Cosaque & Straub, 2011). This paper helped to address this issue by identifying the roles played by the expertise facets in affecting users’ perceptions of site ease of use and site attitude.
    Barrutia and Gilsanz (2013) viewed expertise as an important user resource shaped by both social expertise (the social resources available to a user) and individual ability (innovativeness). They showed that a negative interaction exists between expertise and electronic service quality on perceived value, and suggested that expertise and service quality dimensions might behave as substitutes. The current research contributes to these results by underscoring the multifaceted nature of expertise. Compared to e-commerce expertise, the site expertise has unique moderating effects on the acceptance process. As predicted, the site expertise moderated the effects of the site information quality and trust on the site acceptance, while e-commerce expertise moderated the effects of the site ease of use and aesthetics. Taken together, the results show that studying the multiple facets of expertise is vital to better understand the user’s adaptation and acceptance of the IT artifact.
    As such, this paper contributes to the user expertise literature and is, to our knowledge, the only work that focuses simultaneously on site expertise and e-commerce expertise. ]]><h target="3" match="full">The findings of the two studies suggest that the different facets of expertise have significant, though divergent, effects on user acceptance of the website.</h><![CDATA[ Recent research has shown comparable results in other contexts. Sedera and Dey (2013) highlighted the multidimensional nature of expertise in an information system context. Theoretically, the results support the latter view and delineate the need to consider the multiple facets of expertise and show their influence on the artifact adaptation and acceptance.
    6. Implications for management
    The findings have a number of implications for website design and management. Perceived ease of use, a critical factor in determining the decision to use and return to an e-commerce website, is directly affected by some site-related factors (information quality, aesthetics, and interactivity). As such, the improvement of these factors should contribute to the site ease of use. The latter recommendation is particularly relevant given that user perceptions of site-related factors emanates from the actual or delivered improvements (Wu, 2005). Indeed, research has shown that increasing or decreasing the quantity of certain site design elements impacts performance (Coyle & Thorson, 2001; Hausman & Siekpe, 2009). To improve the perceived EOU, the focus should be on enhancing site information quality as well as the interactivity and personalization features, which are the factors that had the greatest impact on EOU.
    The findings also suggest that a resource-allocation approach to website management can be better achieved by taking into consideration the changes in user requirements of the site according to his or her level of expertise. Site developers should take the user expertise into consideration as the findings show significant effects for the facets of expertise on the cognitive effort and the acceptance process. Researchers have suggested several methods to account for expertise in adaptive systems (Hoffman, 2014); nonetheless, developers are invited to differentiate between the expertise facets they measure and use.
    The results, which were replicated in a second study of French speaking Canadians, showed that for users with a high level of e-commerce expertise, delivering a design that facilitates site ease of use while conserving its aesthetics should be a priority. Alternatively, for users with little site expertise, the focus should be on the site information quality. In addition, as these users perceived the site as less easy to use and needed more time to accomplish their tasks, developers should try to enhance the perceived ease of use for these users (e.g., for first-time visitors to the site) by providing a simpler design or by other means.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Limitations and future research;Conclusion" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
    7. Limitations and future research
    This paper postulated and empirically showed that facets of expertise have unique significant effects on the site adaptation and acceptance. However, more research is needed to study the multifaceted nature of expertise (i.e., the dimensions that comprise the user expertise construct at an online context) and develop reliable measures to adequately capture each expertise facet. In effect, the literature does not include a work that focused on analytically studying user expertise or on illustrating its nomological network. In addition, more work is needed to explain how people gain expertise. Indeed, people might be heterogeneous in gaining expertise; it has recently been noted that there are important differences among people in how well they acquire expertise (Chi et al., 2014). Furthermore, work that focuses on measuring online expertise and profiling users according to their expertise level is needed (Liu, Wang, Johri, Zhou, & Fan, 2014).
    This paper examined a number of site-related factors that contribute to the perceived ease of use and acceptance of the organization’s website. Nonetheless, site-related factors that are less frequented in research (such as site reliability, innovativeness, and empathy; Loiacono et al., 2007) were not studied. There were several reasons for this decision. First, we chose to focus on the site-related factors that had been adequately validated in previous studies (the most studied) and those that, theoretically, would have a substantial impact on EOU and acceptance. Second, considering all the site-related factors necessitates the inclusion of many scales in the questionnaire. The inclusion of too many scales in a self-reported measure would negatively affect the reliability of the results, because of the experimental condition (online experiment) and because of the common method bias associated with the one-method used. More research is thus needed to study the effects of the other site-related factors on the site acceptance and to show the moderating role of expertise facets.
    Data were collected using a large consumer panel. Therefore, the sample is not a convenience or student sample as it includes actual consumers. This method nonetheless has several disadvantages. First, the sample is self-selected. In addition, users who are less Internet or computer savvy might participate less in survey and testing panels, which suggests that this user segment may have been underestimated. However, the users of particular interest to e-commerce organizations are those who usually use the Internet. Similar comments apply to users with a high level of privacy and security concerns, as they would be less likely to participate in survey and testing panels.
    
    This paper examined a large number of websites spanning various sectors in order to give a reliable view of the impact of e-commerce expertise and to reduce the confounding influence of attitudes toward the organization, its brand strength and loyalty (Kwon & Lennon, 2009). Future work could be devoted to studying the role of expertise facets on hedonic (i.e., pleasure-oriented) websites and in experiential environments, such as virtual communities, social networking, and gaming sites (e.g., pinterest.com, facebook.com, yahoogames.com). The literature suggests that enjoyment would be a significant factor in shaping user’s acceptance for hedonic sites (Chen, 2012). Nonetheless, the intertwined effect of enjoyment and expertise on site adaptation and acceptance has not been studied. This topic would be another potential avenue for future research.
    8. Conclusion
    It has been stated: “over time, and at different stages of IT usage, individuals’ interactions with IT continuously evolve. Inappropriate user adaptation may contribute to or result from misalignment problems during IT implementation” (Elie-Dit-Cosaque & Straub, 2011). This paper contributes to this notion by showing how the user’s level of expertise helps to explain the IT artifact acceptance and change dynamics. By considering the multifaceted nature of expertise, researchers and practitioners should be better able to reduce misalignment problems by effectively improving the user adaptation and acceptance of the IT artifact.]]>
    </section>
</publication>