<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="zhouzhichao">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 6, Part A, December 2016, Pages 1020-1032</time>
    <title>Seniors' loyalty to social network sites: Effects of social capital and attachment</title>
    <author>Myung Ja Kim. </author>Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Choong-Ki Lee.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Michael W. Preis.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
<![CDATA[The College of Hotel & Tourism Management, Kyung Hee University, 26 Kyungheedae-ro, Dongdaemun-gu, Seoul 02447, Republic of Korea]]>
b
The College of Business, University Of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, Champaign, IL 61820, USA
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.04.019</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">Bonding social capital affects interpersonal and group attachment to SNSs.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">Bridging social capital highly influences interpersonal and group attachment.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">Group attachment is significantly influenced by interpersonal attachment to SNSs.</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">Group attachment has a strong effect on site attachment to SNSs for tourism.</highlight>
    <highlight id="5">Seniors’ loyalty to SNSs is highly influenced by site attachment to the SNSs.</highlight>
Abstract
    <abstract><![CDATA[The populations of seniors in developed countries around the world are increasing rapidly, resulting in changes in social dynamics and purchasing behaviors, specifically in information technology and tourism. T ]]><h target="1" match="part">his study analyzes relationships among bonding and bridging social capital (SC), interpersonal, group, and site attachments, and loyalty to identify what makes seniors loyal to social network sites (SNSs) for tourism.</h><![CDATA[ Results show that bonding SC affects interpersonal and group attachment and that bridging SC highly influences interpersonal and group attachment. Also, interpersonal attachment has a positive effect on group attachment, which, in turn, is highly influential on site attachment. In particular, group attachment has a strong effect on site attachment, but interpersonal attachment is not shown to affect site attachment. It is also notable that loyalty to SNSs is greatly influenced by site attachment. The findings contribute to the academic literature and provide useful information for practitioners maintaining SNSs.]]></abstract>
Keywords
    <keywords>SeniorSocial capital</keywords>
    <keywords>Attachment theory</keywords>
    <keywords>Loyalty</keywords>
    <keywords>Social network site</keywords>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
The populations of seniors in developed countries around the world are increasing rapidly, resulting in changes in social dynamics and purchasing behaviors, specifically in the tourism domain (Alén, Losada, & de Carlos, 2015; Chen & Shoemaker, 2014; Kim, Lee, Kim, & Kim, 2013). The segment of the population 50 years old and over in South Korea (hereafter “Korea”) is expected to reach 43.3% of the population by 2020, up from 33.6% in 2015 [Korean Statistical Information Service (KSIS, 2014)]. For purposes of this study, as in prior research, those 50 years old and over are defined as seniors (e.g., Anderson & Langmeyer, 1982; Kim et al., 2013). This demographic shift is important to the tourism industry because seniors are interested in travel and have ample time and income to engage in tourism (Kazeminia, Del Chiappa, & Jafari, 2015; Mahadevan, 2014). As the size of the aging population grows and information technologies continue to develop, industries must learn how to create websites that meet the preferences and needs of seniors (Mitzner et al., 2010). In response, some information technology companies are developing websites and applications specifically for this segment of the population (Lee, Chen, & Hewitt, 2011). Moreover, social network sites (SNSs) play important roles in planning for travel and sharing travel and post-travel experiences as well as in providing travel information, reservation systems, and purchase opportunities for tourism products and services (Thu, 2015).
Seniors are more interested in using SNSs than ever before (Pew Research Center, 2014; The World Ages, 2013). According to Kim (2015), in Korea, the number of seniors using SNSs grew 127.6% from 2013 to 2014, six times faster than the number of non-seniors using SNSs (21.5%). Using SNSs is beneficial to seniors in terms of keeping in touch with their families and relatives, making new friends, keeping in touch with old friends, and getting information, since seniors are likely to have plenty of time but are not as mobile as when they were young (Cohen, 2014). Seniors are one of the fastest growing population groups on social networks, actively searching on Google, browsing Facebook, and watching YouTube videos (Beese, 2013). According to the Pew Research Center (2014), 46% of those 65 years of age and over who use the Internet, accounting for 27% of this segment of the population, use SNSs (e.g., Facebook), and these social network users connect more persistently with the people they care about than non-users.
For many seniors who live alone, SNSs facilitate the formation and cultivation of relationships; those who live far away from loved ones use SNSs to bridge the geographic gap (Cohen, 2014; The World Ages, 2013). In addition, research on senior SNS users suggests that SNSs improve quality of life (Cornejo, 2010), assist those seeking relationships (VandeWeerd et al., 2014), and reduce feelings of isolation and loneliness (Fritsch, Steinke, & Silbermann, 2013). Other studies have shown that in the context of tourism, SNSs are used for information searching (Chung & Koo, 2014), customer engagement (Cabiddu, Carlo, & Piccoli, 2014), and word-of-mouth (Luo & Zhong, 2015). Despite the importance of seniors’ usage of SNSs for tourism-related activities, previous studies have not examined this important topic. Accordingly, this study examines seniors’ behavior on SNSs when used for tourism-related purposes.
Social capital (SC) is defined as “the good-will that is engendered by the fabric of social relations and that can be mobilized to facilitate action” (Adler & Kwon, 2002, p. 17). SC has two dimensions, bonding SC, which consists of internal relations, and bridging SC, which consists of external relations (Adler & Kwon, 2002). While bonding SC creates solid ties that tend to be strong and exclusive, creating social solidarity, bridging SC creates diverse networks that often yield new information and resources; such networks are considered weak ties (Ellison, Steinfield, & Lampe, 2007). An extensive body of research has examined the roles of bonding and bridging SC in usage of SNSs by all users (e.g., Chang & Zhu, 2012; Chung & Koo, 2012; Ellison et al., 2007; Lee, 2013; Maghrabi, Oakley, & Nemati, 2014; Vock, van Dolen, & de Ruyter, 2013); however, there is no research of which the authors are aware that specifically focuses on bonding and bridging SC of seniors’ using SNSs for tourism-related activities.
SC resources consist of trust, norms, and networks of associations representing any group that gathers persistently for a common purpose (Garson, 2006). SC has been demonstrated to be useful in explaining senior networks (e.g., Keating & Dosman, 2009) and SNSs for tourism-related activities (e.g., Cabiddu et al., 2014; Chung & Koo, 2014; Luo & Zhong, 2015). However, studies on seniors applying SC theory have not been conducted in the tourism domain. Since senior tourism is a growing and lucrative market (Alén et al., 2015; Chen & Shoemaker, 2014; Kim et al., 2013), such studies, applying SC, may be valuable in explaining why and how seniors are loyal to SNSs.
Other theories have also proven helpful in understanding use of SNSs. In recent years, SNSs have been widely used as communication tools by individuals (Chang & Zhu, 2012). For example, Facebook, a leading SNS tool, broadcasts messages to large audiences through chats, status updates, and wall posts (Smock, Ellison, Lampe, & Wohn, 2011). SNSs are more likely individual-oriented sites (Ellison et al., 2007) whereas online communities are more likely group-oriented sites (Ren et al., 2012). However, online communities and SNSs have many similarities in terms of the ways members communicate and interact with each other, such as chatting, updating status, searching for information, posting opinions and news, and exchanging ideas and experiences (Chung, Nam, & Koo, 2016). Online communities and SNSs also have many similarities in their methods of recruiting and retaining members, for example, by increasing users’ motivations, social capital, attachments, and loyalty to their sites (Chung et al., 2016; Ellison et al., 2007; Lee, 2013; Ren et al., 2012; Smock et al., 2011). Because of these strong similarities, this study regards online communities as being comparable to SNSs.
Attachment theory has been demonstrated to be useful in explaining SNS usage (e.g., Chung & Koo, 2012; Chung, Koo, & Park, 2012; Lee, 2013). Strong bonds created between people and between people and objects are explained by attachment theory (Ainsworth, 1989; Bowlby, 1977). Several studies have confirmed that attachment theory explains members staying connected to online communities and SNSs, resulting in the subsequent successes of associated businesses (e.g., Chung & Koo, 2012; Fiedler & Sarstedt, 2010; Ren, Kraut, & Kiesler, 2007; Ren et al., 2012). Because attachments have important roles in fundamental relationships among people, attachment theory has been demonstrated to be useful in explaining behavior of SNS users (Chung & Koo, 2012; Chung et al., 2012; Lee, 2013). Thus, this study adopts attachment theory as a theoretical framework for senior SNS users for tourism activities, along with SC theory.
Prentice, Miller, and Lightdale (1994) identified two types of groups to which individuals may belong and these two types of groups have proven useful in predicting differences in behaviors between the two types of groups. In common-identity groups individuals share a social category, for example, the same club or church (Prentice et al., 1994). Common-bond groups are composed of individuals who share interpersonal connections such as friends or acquaintances (Sassenberg, 2002). Fiedler and Sarstedt (2010), Ren et al. (2007), and Qi and Fu (2011) show that users with higher levels of attachment to SNSs have higher levels of loyalty to the SNSs. Martin and Lyday (1997) assert that seniors tend to hold feelings of loyalty that is cultivated by building relationships with other seniors. Accordingly, studies on the linkage between SC and attachment in SNSs are interesting and valuable in order to identify how to influence loyalty to SNSs. ]]><h target="2" match="part">However, there has been very little focus on relationships between bonding and bridging SC and interpersonal and group attachments to SNSs. To bridge the gap, this study utilizes SC and attachment theories to explore the relationships between SC and attachment to identify why seniors are loyal to SNSs.</h><![CDATA[
Researchers have shown the importance of SC for seniors in terms of social networks (e.g., de Donder, de Witte, Buffel, Dury, & Verté, 2012; Keating & Dosman, 2009), Internet use (e.g., Choi & Dinitto, 2013; Russell, Campbell, & Hughes, 2008), and well-being (e.g., Cramm, Van Dijk, & Nieboer, 2013; Forsman, Herberts, Nyqvist, Wahlbeck, & Schierenbeck, 2013). The construct of SC has been key in conceptualizing the social ties in seniors’ quality of life (Keating & Dosman, 2009). Scholars have demonstrated the differing roles of bonding and bridging SC for seniors in the context of SNSs (e.g., Erickson, 2011; Pfeil, Arjan, & Zaphiris, 2009), but such research has not yet been attempted in tourism areas. Thus, the purpose of this study is to examine relationships among SC (bonding and bridging), attachments (interpersonal, group, and site attachments), and seniors’ loyalty to SNSs in tourism environments. Specifically, this study seeks to answer the following research question: what makes seniors loyal to SNSs in the tourism context? To answer the research question, this study applies a multi-conceptual approach investigating how bonding and bridging SC are related to interpersonal, group, and site attachment and how these three types of attachments interact with each other in affecting loyalty to SNSs.
This current study provides valuable insights into the complex relationships of bonding and bridging SC, interpersonal, group, and site attachment, and loyalty that underlie senior SNS users' behaviors when using SNSs for tourism purposes and yields important insights that may be useful to SNS managers. Specifically, the results can potentially extend our current theoretical knowledge of the linkage of SC, attachment, and loyalty for SNSs to the context of senior tourism. A stronger understanding, such as this theoretical framework, could also offer SNS practitioners new ways to facilitate use of SNSs by seniors in the context of tourism-related activities.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Literature review"  category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Literature review
2.1. Social network sites in seniors
SNSs provide social support for seniors confronted with difficult life situations, regardless of geographical location or time (Leist, 2013). Use of SNSs by seniors has been shown to overcome loneliness, relieve stress, and raise feelings of control and self-efficacy (Leist, 2013). Seniors use SNSs to communicate with family members including children and grandchildren, revealing that SNSs have the potential to support relationships between older and younger family members (Nef, Ganea, Müri, & Mosimann, 2013). Seniors' active use of SNSs to communicate with others (as opposed to passive consumption of content) is associated with reduced loneliness and increased social role satisfaction (Hutto et al., 2015). Seniors’ networks of friends are commonly small but contain high proportions of individuals who are considered to be true friends (Chang, Choi, Bazarova, & Löckenhoff, 2015). Additionally, high numbers of Facebook friendships are related to lower levels of loneliness and social isolation (Chang et al., 2015). However, no research on seniors using SNSs for tourism purposes has been conducted. Accordingly, such research on seniors using SNSs for tourism activities is a valuable and timely study because of the expected benefits of decreasing loneliness and increasing the subjective well-being of seniors.
2.2. Social capital theory
SC is valuable to individuals because it represents a resource that the individual can use to achieve his or her interests (Coleman, 1988). SC can also be built in the context of SNSs (Chung & Koo, 2012; Lee, 2013). Putnam (2000) divides SC into bonding and bridging SC. Bonding SC is built in strongly tied relationships with families and friends (Ellison et al., 2007). Bridging SC exists in relationships in which information or new perspectives are exchanged with others with whom no prior emotional bonds exist; bridging SC is weaker than bonding SC (Granovetter, 1992).
Relationships between bonding and bridging SC and SNSs have been studied by many researchers (e.g., Chang & Zhu, 2012; Chung & Koo, 2012; Ellison et al., 2007; Lee, 2013; Maghrabi et al., 2014; Vock et al., 2013), resulting in a deeper understanding of how SC influences use of SNSs. Emotional support on SNSs is essential for the creation of bonding SC and this type of SC is only present in situations where there are close, strong ties between individuals (Maghrabi et al., 2014). Conversely, persons typically extend their relationship networks, creating wide dense networks with weak ties, representing bridging SC on SNSs (Maghrabi et al., 2014). Bonding SC is developed when SNS users generate relationships with others and share values and prospective goals, whereas bridging SC is developed when SNS users increase their social networks, such as when new people join existing networks or the users join new networks (Lee, 2013).
While many studies (e.g., Chang & Zhu, 2012; Chung & Koo, 2012; Ellison et al., 2007; Lee, 2013; Maghrabi et al., 2014; Vock et al., 2013) have established the relevance of SC to the use of SNSs, this study is the first to examine the topic of seniors’ use of SNSs in the tourism context. Bonding SC developed in the context of SNSs is the result of solid relationships that depend on interpersonal trust-based strong ties, while bridging SC reflects casual affiliations characterized by weak ties among SNS users (Lee, 2013), implying that bonding SC functions differently than bridging SC in senior networks.
2.3. Attachment theory
Attachment theory is defined as “a way of conceptualizing the propensity of human beings to make strong affectional bonds to particular others” (Bowlby, 1977, p. 201). Attachments are defined as enduring affectional or devotional bonds of substantial intensity (Armsden & Greenberg, 1987) and can be formed among individuals, groups, and online communities (Ren et al., 2012). Attachments are divided into three types: interpersonal, group, and site (Ren et al., 2012). Interpersonal attachments are defined as “the bonds between group members, the interpersonal conception of group cohesion, and the attraction of the individuals to one another (personal attraction)” (Sassenberg, 2002,p. 28). Group attachment is defined as the bonds that group members have “to the group and are dependent foremost on the identification with the group as a whole, its goals, and its purposes” (Sassenberg, 2002, p. 28). Site attachment is defined as users’ attachments to websites; site attachment can develop to online sites (Kim, Chung, Lee, & Preis, 2015a) as well as to mobile sites (Kim, Chung, Lee, & Preis, 2015b). In the context of online social network involvement, site attachment is an important mediator between antecedents (motivation) and outcomes (continued usage) in mobile tourism shopping (Kim, Lee, Chung, & Preis, 2016). As a result, seniors’ site attachment to SNSs is expected to be influenced by their interpersonal and group attachments related to the SNSs to which they belong.
Interpersonal and group attachments both influence attachment to online communities (Fiedler & Sarstedt, 2010; Ren et al., 2012). While people in common-bond groups are more likely to be attached to the individual members than to the groups, people in common-identity groups tend to be more attached to their groups than to the individual members (Prentice et al., 1994, p. 484). Ren et al. (2012) find that the stronger the attachment to a large community, the more posts individuals make, whereas the weaker the attachment to a large community, the fewer posts individuals make. The effects of bond features and identity on visit frequency are mediated by attachment to a big community so that a stronger attachment to a site causes the members to visit that site more frequently (Ren et al., 2012). According to Lee (2013), both bonding and bridging SC on SNSs, as reported by SNS users, appear to be greatest in low anxiety attachments and low avoidance attachments. Chung et al. (2012) suggest that people with strong SC tend to debate matters and discuss their problems with others, facilitating social exchange on SNSs, thus increasing common bond and identity attachments.
The strength of seniors’ attachments influences seniors’ well-being. According to Magai et al. (2001), attachment dimensions in seniors mediate health, social support, lifestyle, and the ability to cope with stress. Based on Besser and Priel (2008), there is a negative relationship between seniors' attachment security and psychological distress, including depression and anxiety. Gillath, Johnson, Selcuk, and Teel (2011) suggest that securely attached seniors maintain their social ties resulting in lower incidences of depression. Gillespie, Gottlieb, and Maitland (2011) show that greater attachment to an organization is experienced by seniors who have multiple goals for volunteering. For seniors with greater attachments, this study anticipates interpersonal, group, and site attachments are significant for senior SNS users in the tourism environment. Based on the literature review above,  ]]><h target="1" match="part">this study examines how bonding SC and bridging SC affect interpersonal and group attachments, </h><![CDATA[and, in turn, how these influence site attachment to SNSs among seniors in the tourism context.
Regarding the relationship of SC to attachment theory in the use of SNSs, bonding SC results from the use of SNSs by individuals who have developed strong ties with other individuals, whereas bridging SC results from the use of SNSs among more socially distant persons (Lee, 2013). In addition, bond- and identity-based attachments mediate between SC (both bonding and bridging SC) and dependent variables (e.g., knowledge sharing, information sharing) in the context of SNSs (Chung & Koo, 2012; Chung et al., 2016). Furthermore, the relationships between SC (both bonding and bridging) and attachments are significant in guiding social relations with both strong and weak ties on SNSs (Lin, 2015; Liu, Shi, Liu, & Sheng, 2013). Accordingly, in this study, social capital theory is integrated with attachment theory in the context of seniors’ use of SNSs.
2.4. Hypothesis development
In terms of the theoretical and practical importance of the differences between bonding and bridging SC, scholars identify various characteristics and roles of bridging and bonding SC (Adler & Kwon, 2002; Putnam, 2000). In other words, bonding SC is related to the number of followers, while bridging SC is affected by the number of followees on an SNS (Hofer & Aubert, 2013). Online SNSs provide the structural features of social capital; in the case of bonding SC, online ties are more effective in forming close networks, while bridging SC is created in the presence of weak ties (Sajuria, vanHeerde-Hudson, Hudson, Dasandi, & Theocharis, 2015). As a result, both forms of SC (bonding and bridging) may have different effects on interpersonal attachment and group attachment on SNSs when the latter are being used for tourism purposes.
Bonding SC is found between individuals in emotionally close relationships such as families and close friends from whom individuals can get emotional support (Liu et al., 2013). Intensity of SNS use is positively associated with individuals’ perceived bonding SC (Ellison et al., 2007). This is significant because bonding SC reinforces attachments on SNSs (Lee, 2013); seniors who have positive bonding SC often have stronger feelings of attachment to both their community members and communities than seniors who do not have positive bonding SC (de Donder et al., 2012). Moreover, bonding SC is associated with both common bonding based groups and common identity based groups, suggesting that bonding SC influences both interpersonal attachment and group attachment (Chung et al., 2016). Among rural residents, bonding SC is important because it represents ties to community members and communities that are significant to people who may otherwise be cut off from social contact with others (Cordes et al., 2003), implying that bonding SC has effects on the individual community members as well as the communities. Based on the literature review above, this study posits that bonding SC is positively related to interpersonal and group attachments in the context of seniors using SNSs for tourism purposes. Hence:

H1
Bonding SC has a significant effect on interpersonal attachment of seniors using SNSs for tourism.
H2
Bonding SC has a significant effect on group attachment of seniors using SNSs for tourism.


Important forms of connections also develop from weak ties, or at least weak contacts that bridge otherwise unrelated groups, and serve as the foundation of bridging SC (Adler & Kwon, 2002). The weak ties offer additional information and opportunities for group members to develop bridging SC through interacting with a broad range of people (Ellison et al., 2007). The more agreeable people are, the more they grow their weak ties and enhance their bridging SC within SNSs (Maghrabi et al., 2014). Bridging SC and attachments are strongly related on SNSs (Lee, 2013; Liu et al., 2013). When members of a community actively interact with others with whom they have bridging SC ties, the members feel stronger attachments to their communities than others who have only bonding SC ties (de Donder et al., 2012).
Based on Chung and Koo (2012), attachments (i.e., both interpersonal and group attachments) are formed from bridging SC. Since, as noted previously, both types of SC influence SNS members’ intentions to use SNSs, bridging SC has effects on both forms of attachment (i.e., both interpersonal and group attachment) (Vock et al., 2013). People with strong bridging SC are inclined to discuss matters with other users and to share problems they have encountered, helping social exchange on an SNS, thus increasing interpersonal and group attachment to the SNS (Chung et al., 2012). In line with the literature review above, this assumes that bridging SC is significantly related to both interpersonal and group attachment. Hence:
H3

Bridging SC has a significant effect on interpersonal attachment of seniors using SNSs for tourism.

H4

Bridging SC has a significant effect on group attachment of seniors using SNSs for tourism.


According to Ren et al. (2007), users’ bonds with other users on online sites strengthen users’ identities with the sites so interpersonal attachment among users is a key driver, increasing group attachment to the sites. Numerous sites that were originally common identity-based have presented features that foster social interactions between their users (Fiedler & Sarstedt, 2010), suggesting that interpersonal attachment influences group attachment. Group attachment to SNSs is leveraged by interpersonal attachment to the SNSs (Ren et al., 2012). Based on the common identity and bond theory, group attachment to an online community is created explicitly by individuals’ attachments to the online community (Grabowicz, Aiello, Eguiluz, & Jaimes, 2013). Hence:

H5
Interpersonal attachment to SNSs has a significant effect on group attachment of seniors using the SNSs for tourism.


In the context of Internet group buying sites, members’ closeness to each other is related to users’ attachment to the sites (Kim et al., 2015a). Information about individuals and their unique attributes fosters common bond attachment to individual members of the site (Ren et al., 2012). Common bond (i.e., interpersonal attachment) theory makes predictions about the causes and consequences of members’ attachments to other individual group members in online communities (Ren et al., 2007). The strength of common bond attachments predicts the strength of attachment to online communities (Fiedler & Sarstedt, 2010; Ren et al., 2012), demonstrating that interpersonal attachment can strengthen attachment to online sites. In a mobile tourism context, shoppers’ interpersonal attachment on a mobile site has a highly significant impact on reciprocal altruism with others on the site (Kim et al., 2015b), which leads us to believe that interpersonal attachment can enhance site attachment. Common bonding has a positive impact on knowledge sharing on SNSs (Chung & Koo, 2012), implying that interpersonal attachment to others on a site influences site attachment in the context of senior SNS users of tourism products and services. Hence:
H6

Interpersonal attachment to SNSs has a significant effect on site attachment of seniors using the SNSs for tourism.


People who are part of groups using mobile sites, for example mobile shoppers, are more likely than others to use the sites (Kim et al., 2015b). When individuals belong to a group using an online site, the individual members feel common identity with that group (Ren et al., 2012). People who engage in on-topic online chats and generalized reciprocity are classified as common identity groups (Ren et al., 2007). Attachment to common identity groups predicts attachment to online communities (Fiedler & Sarstedt, 2010), indicating that attachment to a group that is on a particular website can strengthen attachment to the website itself (i.e., site attachment). That is, it is presumed that attachment by an individual to a group that is itself attached to an online site can lead to the individual's site attachment to the site. Drawing on the above literature, this study proposes the following hypothesis in the context of senior SNS users for tourism activities:

            Group attachment to groups using SNSs has a significant effect on site attachment of seniors using the SNSs for tourism.


Loyalty is defined as a “deeply held commitment to rebuy or repatronize a preferred product/service consistently in the future” (Oliver, 1997, p. 392). Loyalty is “manifested in various ways, such as by expressing a preference for a company” (Zeithaml, Berry, & Parasuraman, 1996, p. 34). Loyalty is important to businesses since the costs of dealing with repeat customers are lower than the costs of constantly acquiring new customers (Oliver, 1999). The more loyal consumers are to a brand or company, the more lucrative that brand or company is likely to be (Dick & Basu, 1994). Accordingly, it is significant for SNS practitioners to understand the factors that drive user loyalty (Chiu, Cheng, Huang, & Chen, 2013).
Increased attachment to an online community leads to a set of overt behaviors, for example, longer periods of membership, more frequent visits, and more energetic participation (Ren et al., 2012). Consumer attachment to retail websites positively influences consumers’ browsing and shopping loyalty to those websites (Jiang & Dong, 2009). In addition, attachment to large online community sites increases member participation and retention on the sites (Ren et al., 2012), demonstrating that attachment to sites increases member loyalty to the sites since participation, and especially retention, demonstrate loyalty. Moreover, consumer attachment to SNSs positively affects loyalty to the SNSs (Qi & Fu, 2011). In a mobile shopping context, site attachment to a mobile site has a significant impact on reciprocal altruism on the site (Kim et al., 2015b), implying that site attachment to a site could increase loyalty to the site. In the context of tourism, buyers’ attachment to a group-buying site has a positive impact on loyalty to the site, demonstrating that attachment to a site can increase loyalty to the site (Kim et al., 2015a). Site attachment influences members’ affective connections to and caring for online communities, which in turn influences those members’ behaviors; site attachment plays a vital role in keeping users connected to online communities, resulting in greater loyalty to the site (Kim et al., 2016). Based on the literature review above, this study expects that higher levels of site attachment result in higher levels of seniors’ loyalty to SNSs when used for tourism-related activities. Hence:
H8
            Site attachment to SNSs has a significant and positive effect on loyalty of seniors using the SNSs for tourism.


Drawing on the hypotheses above, this study proposes the research model shown in Fig. 1. This model examines relationships between bonding and bridging SC, interpersonal, group, and site attachment, and loyalty among senior SNS users for tourism-related activities.
Fig. 1
Download high-res image (247KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Proposed research model.]]>
    </section>
    <section name=" Methods" category="methods">
        <![CDATA[
3. Methods
3.1. Measurements
Bonding and bridging SC, interpersonal, group, and site attachment, and loyalty to SNSs were measured using items from prior research. Specifically, five items adopted from studies by Adler and Kwon (2002) and Lee (2013) were used to assess bonding SC. Five items used to assess bridging SC were drawn from research conducted by Ellison et al. (2007) and Lee (2013). Five items used to measure interpersonal attachment were adapted from previous studies on attachment by Fiedler and Sarstedt (2010) and Ren et al. (2007). Five items for measuring group attachment were adapted from the literature (Chung & Koo, 2012; Ren et al., 2012). Five items were adapted from previous research to measure site attachment (Fiedler & Sarstedt, 2010; Ren et al., 2012). Five items were adapted from previous research to measure loyalty (Dick & Basu, 1994; Oliver, 1999). Questionnaire items were reworded to reflect the context of tourism products (Appendix A).
All of the items were measured on 7-point Likert scales that range from strongly disagree (1) to strongly agree (7). For general questions, six items related to SNSs (place for accessing, reason for accessing, length of experience, devices used, activities, and duration) were adapted from Kim et al. (2016). This study added seven items measuring demographic variables. Four academic experts in tourism, senior research, and information technology were asked to verify the content validity of the items that were initially generated from the literature. To determine whether it was necessary to add, delete, or rephrase any measurement items, four experts from SNSs were also asked to evaluate the questionnaire items. A pretest was conducted on 50 people who had used SNSs for tourism-related activities within the prior year. As a result of these three steps four of the original 43 items were deleted (i.e., each one item from interpersonal attachment, group attachment, site attachment, and loyalty), leaving 39 items in the survey. Several ambiguous items that were related to bonding and bridging SC were reworded to improve clarity of meaning.
3.2. Data collection
With the widespread adoption of the Internet, scholars in tourism have utilized Internet surveys to efficiently reach populations of interest (Kim, Chung, & Lee, 2011). Since this research examines behaviors on SNSs, use of an Internet survey is particularly appropriate. The population of interest is seniors in Korea who are users of SNSs for tourism products. To sample this population, this study employed a highly rated online survey firm (Macromill Embrain: www.embrain.com). The Internet survey was conducted from the end of August to the middle of September 2014. Quota sampling was used; quotas were based on Internet users’ ages and genders and were based on data from the Korea Internet Security Agency (KISA, 2014) and KSIS (2014). These data indicate that 52.5% of men have used the Internet whereas 47.5% of women have used the Internet. Of Internet users, 60.2% are in the age group of 50–59 years while 39.8% are in the age group of 60 and over.
The survey firm of Macromill Embrain randomly selected 10,000 seniors (50 years old and over) from their nationwide panel of 1,036,803 Internet user. Then the survey firm sent both email and SMS messages to those 10,000 seniors inviting them to participate in the survey. Of those who were sent the messages, 1183 seniors actually opened the emails containing the survey invitation. Of the 1183 seniors who opened the invitation, 964 connected to the questionnaire. To validate the identities of respondents, the survey company’s standard processes include the use of panel registration numbers to correlate online identities with personal information. Each respondent was required to write the name of an SNS on which the respondent had recently accessed tourism products. The name of the SNS provided by the respondent was then presented on the computer screen for every following question. For multiple choice items, construct and item rotation functions were employed so that every respondent had a different sequence of questions to reduce response bias (Galesic, 2005).
Embrain employs several techniques to maintain the integrity of the panel and of panelists’ responses. Questionnaires that were completed too quickly or that were completed in recurring patterns for the purpose of obtaining the incentive were identified by the system and eliminated. When multiple-choice questions are answered by clicking the same number repeatedly, respondents are automatically warned before proceeding to the next page. The survey frame is managed to prevent panel members from participating in similar surveys for a certain time period, and each respondent is tracked by his or her real name and membership identification. Respondents to surveys may try to cheat by attempting to provide correct answers to qualify for a survey in order to earn the incentive; cheating may consist of straight-lining (selecting the same response over and over on a series of questions to move through the survey more quickly) or randomly selecting response options (Grey Matter Research, 2009). The Embrain survey system checks correlations, outliers, and time taken to answer surveys to detect cheating. Respondents suspected of cheating on three surveys are removed from the panel.
The first question on the questionnaire is a screening question: “Have you used an SNS for tourism products within the past year?” From the 478 respondents who were eligible based on the screening question, 450 complete responses were collected. The response rate in this study is 94.1% based on those qualified individuals originally responding ‘yes’ to the screening question (used an SNS for tourism within the past year) (The American Association for Public Opinion Research, 2015). No responses were rejected based on the screening criteria so all 450 completed questionnaires were utilized for analysis.
This study relies on self-reported data and a one-time survey, which may lead to common method bias. Accordingly, Harman’s single factor test was used to detect common method bias (Kim, Lee, Chung, & Kim, 2014). To conduct this test the self-reported items are entered into an exploratory factor analysis (unrotated) (Liang, Saraf, Hu, & Xue, 2007; Ranganathan, Teo, & Dhaliwal, 2011). When a single factor appears or one factor accounts for more than 50% of the variance in the variables, common method variance exists (Kim et al., 2014; Podsakoff, MacKenzie, Lee, & Podsakoff, 2003). Our analysis shows that four factors appeared, with the major factor accounting for 49.0% of the variance and the remaining factors accounting for 8.4%, 6.0%, and 4.7% of the variance, respectively. For this study a test for a path model in structural equation modeling (SEM) was also conducted. When method variance is a significant problem, a single-factor model should fit the data as well as a more complex model (Kim et al., 2014; Liang et al., 2007). One model with four factors and a second model with only one factor were identified. The four-factor model yielded a better fit for the variance explained (R2) than the single-factor model; for the four-factor model is R2 = 0.487 and R2 = 0.421 for the single-factor model. Additionally, the four-factor model had lower latent variable correlations (i.e., 0.561 for the four-factor model and 0.649 for the single-factor model) while the average variance extracted (AVE) (i.e., 0.793) and composite reliability (CR) (i.e., 0.939) are the same (Kim et al., 2014). Consequently, the two statistical tests show that common method bias is not present.
3.3. Analysis
To test the hypotheses proposed in Fig. 1, the collected data were analyzed with SPSS 22.0 and AMOS 22.0 using SEM. SEM is intended to assess how well a proposed model or hypothetical construct describes the collected data (Hair, Black, Babin, & Anderson, 2010). The two-step approach proposed by Anderson and Gerbing (1992) was applied: first verifying convergent validity and discriminant validity of the measurement model, followed by assessing the structural model and hypotheses.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Results" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
4. Results
4.1. Profile of the respondents
Male respondents (52.4%) outnumber females (47.6%). A little less half of the respondents (47.6%) fall into the 60 years old or over bracket and a little more than half (52.4%) fall in the 50–59 year old bracket. These proportions approximate the proportions in the population as indicated by the KISA (2014) and KSIS (2014). Respondents attending university or who have university degrees comprise a majority of the respondents (55.8%). Married respondents (88.5%) outnumber single (3.3%), divorced (3.1%), and widow or widower respondents (5.1%). More than half the respondents (56.7%) had incomes greater than 4 million Korean won per month (US$1 is equivalent to 1050 Korean won). Homemakers represent the largest proportion of respondents (29.4%) and office workers (18.0%) and self-employed (18.0%) comprise the second and third largest proportions, respectively. The majority of the respondents accessed SNSs at home (73.1%) and for personal use (92.5%). Respondents who are from all other parts of the country (55.1%) outnumber residents of the Seoul metropolitan region (44.9%). The largest single group of respondents has used SNSs more than one but less than two years (34.2%). To access SNSs, 46.0% use smartphones, 82.4% gather information from SNSs, and 47.4% spend less than 30 min per day on SNSs. Each respondent was asked to name the SNS he/she accessed most frequently for tourism products and services. The most frequently named SNSs were Facebook (24.9%), followed by Kakao (14.9%), Naver (10.0%), Daum (5.6%), Twitter (4.9%), Korea Tourism Organization (4.4%), Coupang (3.1%), Hana Tour (2.7%), Ticketmonster (1.3%), and Google (0.9%) (see Table 1). In addition, 2.9% of respondents reported accessing blog posts.
Table 1. Demographic and general characteristics of respondents.
Characteristics	N(450)	%(100)	Characteristics	N(450)	%(100)
Gender			Residence		
Male	236	52.4	 Seoul metropolitan region	203	44.9
Female	214	47.6	 All other regions	249	55.1
Age			Length of experience with SNSs		
50–59	236	52.4	 Less than 1 year	97	21.6
60 or over	214	47.6	 More than 1 or less than 2 years	154	34.2
Educational level			 More than 2 or less than 3 years	89	19.8
Middle/high school	141	31.3	 More than 3 years	110	24.4
2-year college	58	12.9	Device used to access SNSs		
University	197	43.8	 Smartphone	207	46.0
Graduate school	54	12.0	 Tablet (e.g., iPad, Galaxy tab)	10	2.2
Marital status			 Notebook	72	16.0
Single	15	3.3	 Desktop computer	161	35.8
Divorced	14	3.1	Activities by SNSse		
Widow/Widower	23	5.1	 Posting information	152	33.8
Married	398	88.5	 Gathering information	371	82.4
Monthly household income			 Texting/Emailing	248	55.1
Less than 2.00 KRWd	50	11.1	 Leisure/Recreation activities	238	52.9
2.00–3.99 KRW	145	32.2	 Social activities	122	27.1
4.00–5.99 KRW	165	36.7	 Making reservations	213	47.3
6.00 or over KRW	90	20.0	 Making purchases	193	42.9
Occupation			 For business	20	4.4
Professional	33	7.3	 Writing reviews	2	0.4
Business person	6	1.3	Time spent on SNSs per day		
Service worker	45	10.0	 Less than 30 min	213	47.4
Office worker	81	18.0	 More than 30 but less than 60 min	173	38.4
Civil servant	9	2.0	 More than 60 but less than120 min	51	11.3
Home maker	132	29.4	 More than 120 min	13	2.9
Retiree	57	12.7	The most frequently accessed SNSs		
Self-employed	81	18.0	 Facebook	112	24.9
other	6	1.3	 Kakaoa	67	14.9
Place for accessing SNSs			 Naverb	45	10.0
Home	329	73.1	 Daumc	25	5.6
Office	106	23.6	 Twitter	22	4.9
Mobile	15	3.3	 Korea Tourism Organization	20	4.4
Reason for accessing SNSs			 Coupang	14	3.1
For personal use	416	92.5	 Blogs	13	2.9
For business use	6	1.3	 Hana Tour	12	2.7
Simply for entertainment	27	6.0	 Ticketmonster	6	1.3
Other	1	0.2	 Google+	4	0.9
a
Kakao is a free mobile instant messaging application for smartphones that allows free texting and free calling.
b
Naver, the biggest portal in Korea, has diverse online and mobile SNSs, one of which is Line, one of the largest SNSs in Korea.
c
Daum is a Korean web portal that offers many online services including web-based email and messaging.
d
US$ 1 = 1050 KRW (Korean won).
e
Results add to more than 100% because respondents were able to choose multiple responses.

4.2. Non-response bias
To estimate non-response bias, we compared the demographic profiles of early and late responders in terms of age and gender (Armstrong & Overton, 1977). The rationale for this comparison is that non-respondents tend to have characteristics similar to later-respondents (Ranganathan et al., 2011). We performed Chi-square tests for differences between the late and early respondents. No significant differences were found between early and later-respondent groups [χ2 (27.920)/df (18) = 1.551, p > 0.05]. Furthermore, the Chi-square tests based on age and gender did not indicate bias between senior respondents who had used an SNS for tourism purposes in the past year and those seniors who had not used any SNS for tourism purposes in the past year (i.e., 486 seniors who connected to the questionnaire, but were excluded by the screening question) (χ2 = 0.258, p > 0.05), implying that non-response bias is not an issue in the sample.
4.3. Measurement model
Confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) is used to revise models by dropping items with high degrees of residual variance shared with other items (Anderson & Gerbing, 1992). Two items were dropped after using AMOS to run a CFA (Babin & Boles, 1998). Fit of the measurement model was good [χ2 = 421.877, df = 237, p < 0.001, ≤3.0 (Hayduck, 1987); goodness-of-fit index (GFI) = 0.927, ≥0.9 (Bagozzi & Yi, 1988); adjusted goodness-of-fit index (AGFI) = 0.907, ≥0.8 (Scott, 1994); normed fit index (NFI) = 0.946, ≥0.9 (Bentler & Bonett, 1980); comparative fit index (CFI) = 0.975, ≥0.9 (Hair et al., 2010); and root mean square error of approximation (RMSEA) is 0.042 at the 90% confidence interval, ≤0.08 (Babin & Boles, 1998)]. Results indicate that every index surpasses its respective suggested value, showing an adequate fit of the collected data to the model.
Several tests are used to confirm convergent validity; the standardized path loading of each item must be statistically significant and greater than 0.7 (Gefen, Straub, & Boudreau, 2000), the CR and Cronbach’s α for each construct must be larger than 0.7 (Nunnally, 1967), and the AVE for each construct must exceed 0.5 (Fornell & Larcker, 1981). As shown in Table 2, the standardized factor loadings are all significant and greater than 0.7; the CR for all constructs exceeds 0.7 and Cronbach’s α for all constructs exceeds 0.7; and the AVE for each construct is greater than 0.5. Thus, convergent validity of the constructs is confirmed (Bagozzi & Yi, 1988).
Table 2. Measurement model resulting from confirmatory factor analysis.
Construct	Item	Factor loadings	Composite reliability (CR)	Average variance extracted (AVE)	Cronbach’s α
Bonding SC (BOSC)	BOSC1	0.782	0.909	0.668	0.876
BOSC2	0.787			
BOSC3	0.743			
BOSC4	0.740			
BOSC5	0.768			

Bridging SC (BRSC)	BRSC1	0.808	0.929	0.724	0.905
BRSC2	0.790			
BRSC3	0.797			
BRSC4	0.817			
BRSC5	0.834			

Interpersonal attachment (IA)	IA1	0.887	0.923	0.800	0.875
IA2	–			
IA3	0.811			
IA4	0.812			

Group attachment (GA)	GA1	0.841	0.926	0.757	0.893
GA2	0.791			
GA3	0.846			
GA4	0.813			

Site attachment (SA)	SA1	–	0.906	0.764	0.845
SA2	0.773			
SA3	0.807			
SA4	0.830			

Loyalty to SNSs (LO)	LO1	0.844	0.939	0.793	0.913
LO2	0.856			
LO3	0.821			
LO4	0.884			
Note: Items IA2 and SA1 were deleted after confirmatory factor analysis.

Discriminant validity is assessed by comparing the square root of the AVE for a construct with the correlations between that construct and corresponding constructs (Bhattacherjee & Sanford, 2006). When the square roots of the AVEs are greater than the correlations between that construct and the corresponding constructs, discriminant validity is verified (Fornell & Larcker, 1981). Discriminant validity is confirmed since, as Table 3 shows, all the square roots of AVEs are greater than the correlations between the construct and the corresponding constructs.
Table 3. Discriminant validity.
Construct	1	2	3	4	5	6	Mean	S.D.
1. Bonding SC	0.817						4.205	1.000
2. Bridging SC	0.646	0.851					4.414	1.019
3. Interpersonal attachment	0.557	0.631	0.894				4.170	1.150
4. Group attachment	0.595	0.695	0.670	0.870			4.016	1.117
5. Site attachment	0.536	0.600	0.527	0.641	0.874		4.295	1.080
6. Loyalty to SNSs	0.489	0.556	0.432	0.518	0.653	0.890	4.723	1.043
Note: The diagonal elements in the correlation of constructs matrix are the square roots of the AVEs and are presented in bold type. All correlations are significant at the 0.01 level (two-tailed).

4.4. Structural model
Table 4 shows the estimates from the structural modeling. The model-fit indices for the structural model provide evidence of a good model fit (χ2 = 464.982, df = 243, p < 0.001; GFI = 0.920; AGFI = 0.901; NFI = 0.940; CFI = 0.970 and RMSEA = 0.045). Fig. 2 presents the standardized path coefficient, path significance, and R2 for the structural model. Except for Hypothesis 6, all hypotheses are supported based on the path analysis results. Hypotheses 1 and 2 postulate positive relationships among bonding SC and interpersonal and group attachments. The results of hypothesis testing show that bonding SC has positive effects on interpersonal attachment (β = 0.267, p < 0.001) and group attachment (β = 0.154, p < 0.01). Thus, Hypotheses 1 and 2 are supported. Hypotheses 3 and 4 posit structural relationships among bridging SC and interpersonal and group attachments. Bridging SC has a positive impact on interpersonal (β = 0.518, p < 0.001) and group attachments (β = 0.412, p < 0.001), thus supporting Hypotheses 3 and 4.
Table 4. Standardized structural estimates and tests of the hypotheses.
Hypothesis	Path	Path coefficient	Estimate (t-value)	Test result
H1	Bonding SC → Interpersonal attachment	0.267***	3.986	Supported

H2	Bonding SC → Group attachment	0.154**	2.690	Supported

H3	Bridging SC → Interpersonal attachment	0.518***	7.610	Supported

H4	Bridging SC → Group attachment	0.412***	6.319	Supported

H5	Interpersonal attachment → Group attachment	0.367***	6.451	Supported

H6	Interpersonal attachment → Site attachment	0.129ns	1.782	Not supported

H7	Group attachment → Site attachment	0.663***	8.466	Supported

H8	Site attachment → Loyalty to SNSs	0.749***	13.888	Supported

R2: Interpersonal attachment = 0.542; Group attachment = 0.709; Site attachment = 0.586; Loyalty to SNSs = 0.560
Note: R2 means the coefficient of determination and is the proportion of variability in the data set which is accounted for by this research model.
ns = not significant.

***
p < 0.001.
**
p < 0.01
Fig. 2
Download high-res image (303KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Path analysis results.
Note: Fit indices: χ2 = 464.982, df = 243, p < 0.001, goodness-of-fit index = 0.920, adjusted goodness-of fit = 0.901, non-normed fit index = 0.940, comparative fit index = 0.970, and root mean square error of approximation = 0.045.
Hypotheses 5 and 6 postulate positive relationships among interpersonal, group, and site attachments. Interpersonal attachment has a positive impact on group attachment (β = 0.367, p < 0.001), supporting Hypothesis 5. Since the path from interpersonal attachment to site attachment is not significant (β = 0.129, n.s.), Hypothesis 6 is not supported. Hypotheses 7 and 8 posit that site attachment is positively related to group attachment and loyalty to SNSs, respectively. Results indicate that site attachment is positively affected by group attachment (β = 0.663, p < 0.001) and site attachment has a positive impact on loyalty to SNSs (β = 0.749, p < 0.001). Thus, Hypotheses 7 and 8 are supported. For interpersonal attachment, 54.2% of the variance is explained by the direct effects of bonding and bridging SC. More than 70% of the variance in group attachment (R2 = 0.709) is explained by the direct effects of bonding and bridging SC and interpersonal attachment. More than half of the variance of site attachment (R2 = 0.586) is explained by the direct effect of interpersonal and group attachment. Also, more than half of the variance in loyalty to SNSs (R2 = 0.560) is explained by the direct effects of site attachment.
4.5. Control variables
To determine whether there are age or gender differences among seniors using SNSs for tourism purposes, we tested the data using the Chi-square statistic. The test revealed no significant difference between respondents in the 50–59 and those in the 60 and over age groups [χ2 (22.485)/df (18) = 1.249, p > 0.05]. Therefore, the findings support the argument that age does not bias the results. The test did, however, reveal a significant difference between male and female respondents [χ2 (40.461)/df (18) = 2.248, p < 0.01]. This result suggests that male and female seniors have different behaviors when using SNSs for tourism.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Discussion and conclusions" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
5. Discussion and conclusions
<!-- ]]><h target="1" match="part">This study examines relationships among bonding and bridging SC, interpersonal, group, and site attachments, and loyalty, in order to identify what makes seniors loyal to SNSs.</h><h target="2" match="part">Results show that both bonding and bridging SC have effects on interpersonal and group attachment among seniors using SNSs for tourism products and services.</h> <h target="3" match="part">Results also show that interpersonal attachment has a positive effect on group attachment,</h> <h target="4" match="part">which, in turn, has a significant influence on site attachment.</h><h target="5" match="full">It is notable that loyalty to SNSs is highly influenced by site attachment.</h><![CDATA[Contrary to prior research and this study’s expectation, interpersonal attachment is not shown to affect site attachment. With regard to the insignificant relationship between interpersonal and site attachments, the findings of this study imply that seniors using SNSs for tourism purposes are likely to be attached to the group first, which in turn strengthens site attachment, rather than attached to the site directly. The findings of this study provide contributions to academics and practitioners about senior users of SNSs in a tourism domain.-->

5.1. Theoretical implications
From the theoretical point of view, this study uses the constructs of SC and attachment to develop a research model explaining what makes seniors loyal to SNSs. Seniors join SNSs to be sociable and friendly with other users, later becoming attached to the SNSs through interpersonal and group attachment. The linkages of bonding and bridging SC, interpersonal, group, and site attachments explain user loyalty to SNSs. This study represents the first attempt to verify the relationship of SC and attachment theory with respect to seniors’ loyalty to SNSs when used for tourism-related purposes. Thus, the findings of this study have the potential to start new streams of research into SNSs, seniors, and tourism-related activities (e.g., overseas or domestic travel, accommodations, entertainment, leisure activities, eating out).

This research confirms the importance of bridging SC to interpersonal and group attachments to SNSs, which is an extension of the previous literature in the field of SC (e.g., Chang & Zhu, 2012; Ellison et al., 2007). The findings offer insights for tourism managers and academics, extending past studies on SNSs in the senior context (de Donder et al., 2012). The impact of interpersonal attachment significantly influences group attachment, indicating that interaction of interpersonal and group attachments on SNSs is an essential motivation to enhancing site attachment, expanding previous research (e.g., Ren et al., 2012). The relationship between site attachment and loyalty is highly significant, indicating that site attachment is an important element to increasing loyalty to SNSs, extending the findings of Fiedler and Sarstedt (2010) and Ren et al. (2007). Interpersonal attachment does not have a significant impact on site attachment, although it does have on group attachment to SNSs. This implies that seniors are not initially attached to SNSs directly, rather they are first attached to groups which, in turn, leads to site attachment in the context of tourism activities. Accordingly, this result represents a major step forward, building a theoretical foundation for seniors’ attachments to SNSs.
This study’s findings offer new evidence that SNSs are particularly attractive to seniors who tend to have broad ranges of relationships with weak ties (which lead to bridging SC) rather than narrow ranges of relationships with strong ties (which lead to bonding SC). Thus, the current study provides a promising first step for researchers towards understanding senior SNS users from the theoretically rich perspective of bridging SC and group attachment.

Although seniors are a large and fast growing segment of the population in Korea and elsewhere in the world, little theoretically based research has been conducted on seniors’ use of SNSs for tourism-related activities. In this respect, this study is a first attempt to identify theoretical relationships between bonding and bridging SC and attachment theory; these constructs, in turn, influence the loyalty of seniors using SNSs for tourism-related purposes. Therefore, this study has the potential to be a cornerstone of future research to create innovative ways of linking SC, attachment, and loyalty to SNSs in the context of senior tourism. Furthermore, this research offers improvements to the understanding of senior tourism in the context of SNSs.

In sum, regarding the theoretical implications, first, the most significant finding of this research is that SC theory explains increased levels of seniors’ usage of SNSs for tourism products and services. Second, attachment theory is a valuable theoretical framework for forecasting the growth of interpersonal connections among seniors in the expanding domain of SNSs for tourism purposes. Third, bridging SC is the most significant factor leading to the creation of common identity groups and casual affiliations from more socially distant people. Finally, group attachment displays greater relational importance than interpersonal attachment in explaining seniors' loyalty to SNSs.

5.2. Practical implications
From a practical perspective, it is important to first foster the bonding and bridging SC of individuals to an SNS itself in order to facilitate interpersonal and group attachment to the SNS. This study shows that the facilitation of bridging SC and interpersonal and group attachments among senior users of SNSs is associated with greater loyalty than the facilitation of bonding SC and interpersonal and group attachments. The findings of the research give SNS companies some insights into how to develop seniors’ loyalty, enabling their SNSs to succeed and thrive in the extremely competitive environment of SNSs.

Bridging SC is comparatively easier to implement than bonding SC, so practitioners should ensure their SNSs contain features that emphasize building bridging SC. Specifically, practices that help seniors feel more connected to the bigger picture, generate interest in other people, support tourism-related activities, encourage trying new things, and encourage feeling part of a larger community in their SNS, can help build bridging SC. The insights of this study could be applied to differentiated marketing strategies depending on the type of SC (i.e., bonding or bridging) and attachments (i.e., interpersonal, group, or site) being generated. For example, group attachment is important because it leads to the highest proportion of variance explained (R2 = 0.709). SNS designers should encourage seniors to join in group activities, thus increasing bonding and bridging SC as well as interpersonal attachment. SNS operators can encourage seniors to bond with other members, by creating opportunities for interactions with other group members. Therefore, this study’s findings suggest practitioners should help senior SNS users build bridging SC in an effort to create loyalty to the SNS.
Site attachment has the greatest effect on loyalty, implying that SNS companies should enhance site attachment, such as by making their websites attractive and including special offers for seniors. This research suggests that if an organization aims to increase seniors’ loyalty to the SNS, the organization will find it more effective to develop group attachment among senior members than to develop interpersonal attachment. Thus, practitioners need to make seniors feel comfortable on SNSs; this can be done by letting seniors know what typical users do on the site, encouraging seniors to engage with other members of the site, asking and answering questions, and providing reviews of products and services.

Considering the large and growing market segment of seniors, this research on senior users of SNSs for tourism purposes can be valuable to SNS marketers. The managerial implications of this research will allow SNS marketers to make more informed decisions about their marketing efforts in order to increase senior users’ loyalty to the SNSs. Furthermore, the research provides SNS operators with significant insights related to bonding and bridging SC, interpersonal, group, and site attachment, and loyalty to SNSs for tourism products and services. As a result, the findings give SNS managers some insights into how SC and attachment can lead to seniors’ loyalty for tourism activities, enabling businesses to succeed and thrive in the extremely competitive environment of SNSs.

According to KISA (2015), the proportion of senior SNS users in Korea increased by 64.8% between 2014 and 2015 (from 36.7% of seniors in 2014 to 60.5% in 2015) compared to an increase of 19.3% for the entire Korean population (from 67.8% in 2014 to 80.9% in 2015). Managers of mobile SNSs can take advantage of this growing proportion of the senior population that uses SNSs. One way to do this is for mobile SNS practitioners to strengthen interpersonal and group attachment by stimulating bonding and bridging SC on their sites. For instance, this can be done by encouraging seniors to chat with each other and to exchange ideas; it can also be done by advising and helping senior members with matters related to tourism. Also, mobile SNS marketers should apply marketing strategies designed to improve site attachment by implementing common identity based practices. By increasing seniors’ site attachment to their sites, mobile SNS marketers will increase those seniors’ loyalty to the sites. For example, site attachment can be increased by using larger font sizes on mobile SNSs, making it easier for seniors who may have weak eyesight to read postings, by having contests that only seniors are eligible to win, or by providing content that would be of special interest to seniors.
5.3. Limitations and future directions
Since this study was conducted in Korea, it is unknown whether the findings of this research are unique to Korean seniors or if they apply to seniors in other countries or different cultures. Accordingly, future research is recommended in other countries to determine whether the results are generalizable. Moreover, researchers might explore moderators of theoretical concepts, for example anxiety attachment and avoidance attachment, in order to determine their moderating effects on SC and attachment.

In order to take into account differing abilities due to the aging process, future researchers should consider differences in the cognitive abilities of seniors and differing use pattern of information technology (Freese, Rivas, & Hargittai, 2006) because physical weaknesses from aging can create difficulties for senior SNS users decoding visual and audible data on webpages. Furthermore, future studies should conduct multi-group analyses using this same model to examine potential differences in SNS usage of younger people and in online and offline contexts to refine the current theoretical framework.
This study has examined the effects of SC on loyalty, as mediated by attachments, among senior users of SNSs. Future research could provide useful information about which factors are more influential on seniors’ loyalty to SNSs and which factors are more influential on non-seniors’ loyalty to SNSs. It would also be useful to know whether there are differences between mobile users (i.e., smartphone and tablet users) and computer users on SNSs related to the research model suggested in this study.]]>
    </section>

Acknowledgements
The authors greatly appreciate the editor Dr. Teo and anonymous reviewers for insightful comments and suggestions.
</publication>