<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication market="zhouzhichao">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 5, October 2016, Pages 724-734</time>
    <title>Antecedents of privacy calculus components in virtual health communities</title>
    <author>Nima Kordzadeh.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>John Warren.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Ali Seifi.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacec. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
Department of Informatics and Computer Science, College of Business, Idaho State University, Pocatello, ID 83209, United States
b
Department of Information Systems and Cyber Security, College of Business, The University of Texas at San Antonio, San Antonio, TX 78249, United States
c
Department of Neurosurgery, The University of Texas Health Science Center at San Antonio, San Antonio, TX 78229, United States
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.04.015</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">We examined communicating personal health information (PHI) in virtual communities.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">Younger individuals are more concerned about their PHI privacy.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">Healthier individuals expect to receive less personal benefits of communicating PHI.</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">Affective commitment will increase expected outcomes of communicating PHI.</highlight>
Abstract
    <abstract>Over the past decade, social media technologies have become effective tools not only for entertainment, but also for online health communications. In virtual health communities (VHCs), the members often share their personal health information (PHI) with other members. These information exchanges provide benefits to both the information providers as well as the recipients. The PHI disclosure, however, may entail privacy concerns. <h target="1" match="part">Our study used the privacy calculus model to examine the trade-off between individuals’ expected benefits and privacy concerns when disclosing PHI in social media environments.</h> Our results showed that age, health status, and affective commitment influence the balance between the information disclosure drivers and barriers in the privacy calculus model. More specifically, we found that among members of VHCs, <h target="3" match="full">healthier people expect to receive fewer personal benefits of communicating PHI in social media environments.</h> Moreover, <h target="4" match="part">individuals who are emotionally attached to online communities expect to both receive and provide more benefits while communicating PHI in those communities.</h> We also observed that individuals who are familiar with but not members of VHCs, <h target="2" match="part">especially those who are young and healthy, are more concerned about their PHI privacy in online communities.</h></abstract>
Keywords
    <keywords>Virtual health communities</keywords>
    <keywords>Online social networks</keywords>
    <keywords>Self-disclosure</keywords>
    <keywords>Personal health information</keywords>
    <keywords>Privacy calculus model</keywords>
    <keywords>Affective commitment</keywords>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
With the rapid growth of social media technologies over the past decade, social networking websites that revolve around health and wellness topics are being increasingly adopted by individuals for health communications. For example, MedHelp.org with 17 million unique users per mo(H6) People with higher affective commitment expect to nth, and DailyStrength.org with more than 500 support groups such as those related to cancer, diabetes, and depression, are among the major health-related websites in the United States. These health-specific online communities, called virtual health communities (VHCs), (Welbourne, Blanchard, & Wadsworth, 2013) or health online social networks (Sadovykh, Sundaram, & Piramuthu, 2015), provide users with various communication platforms such as physician-rating, medicine-rating, ask-an-expert, and discussion boards (Kordzadeh & Warren, 2013). Discussion boards, for instance, enable individuals to initiate discussion threads by posting questions concerning health and wellness topics. Users of these websites post replies to the threads and share their relevant knowledge and experience with the thread initiators, as well as other users who join the threads. Thus, health consumers such as patients and their families, friends, and caregivers exchange information and emotional support with each other in a convenient yet inexpensive way (Chou, Lin, & Huang, 2016).
The results of recent national surveys have confirmed the growing adoption of social media platforms for health communications. A survey conducted by the Pew Research Center (Fox & Duggan, 2013) revealed that 26% of adult internet users in that study had gone online to look at someone else’s health-related experience in the past year. Additionally, 16% of the respondents indicated that they looked online for other individuals with similar medical conditions to theirs. The results also demonstrated that 40% of the respondents had shared their health-related experiences in online environments (Fox & Duggan, 2013). Accordingly, the user-generated health-related knowledge shared in VHCs helps the community members learn from others’ experiences to make informed health decisions such as what doctor to choose, what medication to take, and how to cope with medical conditions (e.g., cancer and alcoholism) effectively (Sadovykh et al., 2015).
A major aspect of health communications via social media platforms is communicating personal health information (PHI) such as information related to one’s medical procedures, diagnosis, symptoms, medications, test results, and one’s feelings about their medical conditions. People engage in this form of PHI disclosure because of the benefits that this behavior may provide to them (Welbourne et al., 2013). Expecting to receive better support from the community, feeling emotionally relieved, and providing more useful information to the community are among the perceived benefits of PHI disclosure in online environments (Rodgers & Chen 2005; Welbourne et al., 2013). However, sharing PHI in publicly available social media environments may entail privacy risks and concerns for information providers. For example, disclosing information about one’s medical conditions may lead to social stigma, job loss, or even criminal prosecutions in the cases such as drug abuse (Anderson & Agarwal, 2011; Beckerman & Foundation, 2008).
The trade-off between the expected outcomes and privacy concerns associated with communicating PHI in social media platforms are elucidated by the privacy calculus model (Culnan & Armstrong, 1999; Dinev & Hart, 2006). The two opposing factors in this theoretical model determines whether or not an individual engages in PHI disclosure behaviors. The privacy calculus balance between the drivers and barriers to PHI disclosure by individuals may vary. Those who are less concerned about their PHI privacy and expect to receive more benefits of PHI sharing may participate actively and share PHI more prevalently in online discussions. Whereas, those who exhibit a greater level of privacy concern may participate at a minimum level. The former group will help the community to prosper and succeed; while, the latter group may not contribute to the growth of the community. Thus, in order for community developers and providers to be able to boost user participation and enhance community growth, they need to understand the factors that impact the two opposing sides of the privacy calculus model in the context of health social media. In this research, we address this issue and investigate the potential determinants of the privacy calculus components. In particular, we examine the role of age, health status, and affective commitment.
The remainder of this article is structured as follows. The second section discusses the theoretical background of this research. The third section presents the research model and hypotheses. The fourth section describes the method. The fifth section discusses the results of our data analysis. Finally, the last two sections summarize the results and their implications, and also provide suggestions for future research.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Theoretical background: privacy calculus model" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Theoretical background: privacy calculus model
Westin (1967) defines privacy as “the claim of individuals…to determine for themselves when, how, and to what extent information about them is communicated to others. (p. 7)” The potential risks associated with personal information disclosure in different contexts makes people concerned about their privacy. However, people may still engage in personal information disclosure to gain some benefits, although they are aware of the potential risks of that. As mentioned earlier, these contrary beliefs and behaviors constitute the privacy calculus model. This theoretical notion was first introduced and discussed by Culnan and her colleagues (Culnan & Armstrong, 1999; Culnan & Bies, 2003). They argued that when faced with a privacy loss situation, individuals perform a psychological privacy calculus to decide on letting or not letting their personal information be disclosed. This perspective was later adopted in the contexts of e-commerce (Dinev & Hart, 2006), location-based services (Xu, Teo, Tan, & Agarwal, 2009), health care (Anderson & Agarwal, 2011), and online social networks (Krasnova and Veltri, 2010), to help to understand individuals’ privacy-related perceptions and behaviors in those information-intensive domains. Fig. 1 depicts a generic privacy calculus model, which we have developed based on the extant literature (e.g., Culnan & Armstrong, 1999; Culnan & Bies, 2003; Dinev & Hart, 2006).
Fig. 1
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Generic Privacy Calculus Model.
The privacy calculus model may also be adopted in the context of health social media. Health information is often sensitive information, whose revelation may expose people to privacy risks, and entail negative consequences for them (Moorhead et al., 2013; Rohm & Milne, 2004). For example, discussing one’s prior experiences of being sexually abused in VHCs may make one socially stigmatized and embarrassed, especially if they believe that there is a chance that their identity may be disclosed to the public (Angst & Agarwal, 2009). In a survey conducted by Antheunis, Tates, and Nieboer (2013), privacy concern was found to be the patients’ first barrier to health-related social media use.
If one intends to seek and provide social support in virtual environments, they may need to share health-related personal information in order to make their health communications more meaningful to others, and to gain richer benefits, such as improved health-related behaviors (Wickramasinghe, Teoh, Durst, & Viol, 2013) and psychological well-being (Batenburg & Das, 2014; Tanis, Das, & Fortgens-Sillmann, 2011). Sharing health-related information and knowledge in social media environments while publicly communicating with others will benefit the community as well. Oh (2012), found that altruism is a major driver for individuals’ replies on others’ posts in health-related social media environments. Chung (2011) found that people join VHCs and contribute within them mainly to help others, although this helping behavior will also provide personal benefits for the information provider, such as feelings of importance and self-satisfaction. Thus, privacy concerns and expected outcomes of sharing PHI in online environments for the purpose of gaining and providing help and benefits can shape the privacy calculus model in health social media.
What remains to be answered is: what are the factors that impact the privacy calculus trade-off in health social media? More specifically, what factors can decrease or increase one’s privacy concerns and/or expected outcomes of health communications via public health-related discussions? Addressing this question will advance our understanding of why some people ultimately share a large extent of PHI in virtual environments, whereas, others prefer to protect their PHI by not sharing them with others, even though they may be aware of the benefits of sharing that information.

In this study, we examine three potential antecedents of the privacy calculus trade-off including age, health status, and affective commitment. The reason for choosing these three are because they are important factors in shaping individuals’ beliefs and communication behaviors in privacy-intensive environments.

Disease-specific online communities may be used by people at different ranges of age or health status. For example, Parkinson’s disease and Alzheimer’s disease are common chronic conditions of the elderly. Whereas, obesity and sports injuries are more prevalent with younger people. Thus, understanding the differences between those groups of individuals in terms of privacy concerns and perceived benefits of PHI disclosure can help developers and administrators of VHCs to address users’ concerns more effectively and to better motivate them to actively communicate via those virtual channels. Similarly, information disclosure intentions and behaviors might be different in online communities that are focused on specific types of diseases that are associated with different levels of health status. For instance, individuals’ perceived negative and positive consequences of communicating PHI in a VHC related to prostate cancer or immune systems disorders might be different from those in a community that focuses on seasonal allergies or influenza. Therefore, it is important to shed light on the role of health status in privacy-related behaviors within VHCs. Finally, as affective commitment has been found to be a major antecedent to user participation in general-purpose online social networks (Bateman, Gray & Butler, 2011), understanding its role in VHCs can help managers of those websites to better promote communications and social support exchange activities within VHCs, by helping users make social ties to those communities and their members. In the next section, we discuss these three factors more in detail and develop hypotheses accordingly.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Research model and hypotheses development" category="research model and hypotheses">
        <![CDATA[
3. Research model and hypotheses development
3.1. Age
Several years ago, when social media technologies initially came into existence, young people were the predominant users of those technologies (Acquisti & Gross, 2006). In today’s era of social media, however, people at various ages are users of these communication platforms. Compared with elderly people, younger individuals may still use social media differently and show different privacy-related behaviors. In general, extant literature has revealed that age can play a major role in online behaviors related to privacy perceptions, beliefs, and attitudes. For example, in the context of e-commerce, prior research suggested that older people are more concerned than younger people about their information privacy when conducting online transactions (Chen, Zhang, & Heath, 2001; Janda & Fair, 2004). In a recent study, Smit, Van Noort, and Voorveld (2014) investigated coping with online behavioral advertising and found that older respondents worried more about their online privacy than younger respondents. In another study, Tufekci (2008) examined privacy concern and information disclosure behaviors in social networking sites among university students. They concluded that the tendency to reveal personal information such as political views, romantic status, and sexual orientation has a negative relationship with age. Also, in the context of health care, Laric, Pitta, and Katsanis (2009) conducted a study in the United States and Canada and observed that older individuals are more concerned about their PHI than younger ones. Health social media is also a privacy-intensive context; hence, age can shape people’s behaviors while facing with information disclosure decisions. Therefore, in line with the extant literature, we hypothesize:
(H1) Older people are more concerned about their PHI privacy in public VHC discussions.
3.2. Health status
The overall status of one’s health conditions, known as health status, has been found in prior studies to be a potential indicator of individuals’ use of, and participation in, health social media websites. Atkinson, Saperstein, and Pleis (2009) found that people with poor and fair health status are 5.98 and 3.28 times, respectively, as likely to use online support groups as those with self-reported excellent health conditions. Chou, Hunt, Beckjord, Moser, and Hesse (2009) observed that individuals with poor health status in terms of overall unhealthiness, distress, and personal cancer experience are more likely to participate in online support groups. Furthermore, other studies have suggested that poor health status may relax individuals’ privacy concern while managing their health via information technology. For example, Lafky and Horan (2011) found that people with health issues such as disabilities and chronic illnesses are less concerned about their PHI and are more willing to share this information with family members, healthcare providers, and others. Lafky and Horan (2011) concluded that “people place more value on the accessibility of their health information when they need it than on keeping it tightly controlled (p. 67)”. Collectively, these studies have demonstrated that poor health status drives participation in online communities and decreases privacy concerns associated with sharing PHI with others. Thus, in the context of health social media websites, we hypothesize:
(H2) People in poor health conditions are less concerned about their PHI privacy in public VHC discussions.
Health status may also affect one’s perceived benefits of communicating PHI in health-related virtual communities and online support groups. A higher level of participation in online communities by those with poor health status, may imply that these individuals find communities focused on their conditions and participation within them more useful (Atkinson et al., 2009; Chou et al., 2009). A potential reason for this phenomenon is that those individuals in poor health conditions might be in critical need of social support from the community. Whereas, for those with good or excellent health conditions, receiving information and emotional support may not significantly change their life. Therefore, we hypothesize:
(H3) People in poor health conditions expect to receive more benefits from communicating PHI in public VHC discussions.
Similarly, people with poor health conditions may have a greater feeling of sympathy with other users of online communities, because they (or their relatives or friends for whom they are seeking support) may be in the same situation (Coursaris & Liu, 2009). This may signify individuals’ willingness to help others in the online community via providing relevant health knowledge, which may normally include some forms of PHI. Accordingly, we hypothesize:
(H4) People in poor health conditions expect to provide more benefits to a VHC by communicating PHI in public discussions within that community.
3.3. Affective commitment
Affective commitment, also known as sense of belonging, attachment, or sense of community, is defined as one’s emotional attachment to a group, organization, or community (Ellemers, Kortekaas, & Ouwerkerk, 1999; Meyer and Allen, 1991). This construct has long been of interest to researchers in different disciplines including social psychology, organizational studies, and group sociology. More recently, this construct has been adopted in the context of online communities. Bateman et al. (2011) coined the term “affective community commitment” and defined it as “a bond between a member and a particular community that is based on the member’s strong emotional attachment to that community (p. 843).” In their study, Bateman et al. (2011) found that this construct has a significant relationship with participating in online communities in terms of posting comments and moderating online discussions within virtual communities. The positive relationship between affective commitment and participation in online communities was reconfirmed in other studies (Bagozzi & Dholakia, 2002; Chai & Kim, 2011; Chou et al., 2016; Tsai & Bagozzi, 2014; Zhao, Lu, Wang, Chau, & Zhang, 2012). Those studies collectively asserted that individuals who feel more emotionally attached to an online community such as health social media websites (Chung, 2014) are more likely to share and seek knowledge in collaboration with other members of the virtual communities. However, those studies have not clarified through what mechanisms emotionally attached individuals are more willing to contribute to online communities. One potential mechanism is the mediating role of privacy concern, such that individuals’ affective commitment to an online community can relax their privacy concern in favor of participation, knowledge contribution, and PHI sharing with other members of the community. The reason is that one’s affective commitment may have a positive relationship with one’s trust in the community (Ridings, Gefen, & Arinze, 2002) and this can decrease their privacy concerns associated with communicating with other members of those websites. Therefore, we hypothesize:
(H5) People with higher affective commitment to a VHC are less concerned about their PHI privacy while communicating in public VHC discussions.
Another potential mechanism through which affective commitment may lead to higher participation level in online communities is the role of perceived benefits or expected outcomes of this participation. In the context of health social media, those who are more attached to an online community may feel that if they provide more information about their medical conditions to a discussion thread, others will be more likely to help them with relevant information and emotional support (Stjernswärd & Östman, 2006). Furthermore, because they are highly attached to the online community, the informational aid and emotional support such as courage and sympathy received from other members would be more meaningful, compared to when there are no social ties between them and the community members. Therefore, we hypothesize:
 ]]><h target="4" match="part">(H6) People with higher affective commitment expect to receive more benefits of communicating PHI in public VHC discussions.</h><![CDATA[
Another implication of the positive relationship between affective commitment and knowledge contribution in online communities is that people who feel more attached to an online community believe that their knowledge contribution can significantly help other members of the community. In other worAdditionally, affective commitment influences personal ds, if individuals are not emotionally attached to other individuals in the online community and to the community as a whole, they may feel that their social support may not be of importance to others in the community. Accordingly, we argue that in VHCs, people with higher levels of affective commitment believe that by communicating their PHI in online discussions, they can provide valuable assistance and support to the community members. Hence, we hypothesize:

(H7) People with higher affective commitment expect to provide more benefits to a VHC by communicating PHI in public discussions within that community.
The research model, which contains the proposed hypotheses, is depicted in Fig. 2.
Fig. 2
Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Research Model.]]>
    </section>
    <section name=" Method" category=" methods">
        <![CDATA[
4. Method
To test the proposed hypotheses, we conducted a survey study and collected data from convenience samples of students, faculty, and staff at a large public university located in the southern United States. In order to enhance the diversity of the sample in terms of demographics and social media-related perceptions, beliefs, and experiences, we also collected data from a sample of visitors to clinics at a large hospital in the same area. However, the subjects from these sources were not mutually exclusive, i.e., students and faculty members might also be visitors to clinics. University staff could also take classes and be considered students. Thus, no specific border was defined between these populations.

The paper-based surveys were distributed by the principal investigator of this study to the subjects. The subjects were first asked about their level of familiarity with VHC. Those who were not familiar with VHCs were excluded from the study. Other individuals were either actual members of at least one VHC (tagged as group 1) or familiar with VHCs but not a member of any of those online communities (tagged as group 2). The group 1 subjects were asked to complete the survey based on a VHC that they were a member of. The group 2 subjects were asked to assume that they were an actual member of a VHC, then respond to the questions in the survey instrument accordingly. Moreover, because the measurement items for the construct affective commitment would not apply to the group 2 individuals, they were asked to skip those items.

In total, 127 surveys were collected from group 1 (including 74 students, 11 faculty or staff, and 42 visitors to clinics) and 108 surveys were collected from group 2 individuals (including 72 students, 9 faculty or staff, and 27 visitors to clinics). The demographic information including gender, age, and ethnicity associated with the 235 respondents is presented in Table 1.
Table 1. Demographic Characteristics of the Sample.
*Group 1	**Group 2	***Total
N	127	108	235
Gender			
Female	65 (51.2%)	54 (50.0%)	119 (50.6%)
Male	57 (44.9%)	49 (45.4%)	106 (45.1%)
Missing	5 (3.9%)	5 (4.6%)	10 (4.3%)
Age			
18–24	58 (45.7%)	58 (53.7%)	116 (49.3%)
25–34	29 (22.8%)	21 (19.4%)	50 (21.3%)
35–44	15 (11.8%)	8 (7.4%)	23 (9.8%)
45–54	13 (10.2%)	5 (4.6%)	18 (7.7%)
55–64	6 (4.7%)	10 (9.3%)	16 (6.8%)
65–74	1 (0.8%)	1 (0.9%)	2 (0.9%)
>74	1 (0.8%)	1 (0.9%)	2 (0.9%)
Missing	4 (3.1%)	4 (3.7%)	8 (3.4%)
Ethnicity/Race			
White	38 (29.9%)	43 (39.8%)	81 (34.5%)
American Indian or Alaska Native	2 (1.6%)	0 (0.0%)	2 (0.9%)
Asian	9 (7.1%)	6 (5.6%)	15 (6.4%)
African American	6(4.7%)	10 (9.3%)	16 (6.8%)
Hispanic	52 (40.9%)	41 (38.0%)	93 (39.6%)
Native Hawaiian or Other Pacific Islander	0 (0.0%)	0 (0.0%)	0 (0.00%)
Others	16 (12.6%)	4 (3.7%)	20 (8.5%)
Missing	4 (3.1%)	4 (3.7%)	8 (3.4%)
Note: *Values in parentheses: percentage of the group 1 subjects. **Values in parentheses: percentage of the group 2 subjects. ***Values in parentheses: percentage of the group 1 and group 2 subjects, combined.

In the process of preparing our survey data for analysis, we detected several incomplete or odd cases (e.g., those with ‘1′ or ‘7′ scores on all the Likert scale items in the questionnaire). After removing them from the data set, 116 surveys from group 1 and 103 surveys from group 2 were usable for further analysis (Table 2).
Table 2. Sampling Information.
Group 1	Group 2	Subtotal
Students	67	68	135
Faculty/Staff	11	9	20
Clinic Visitors	38	26	64
Subtotal	116	103	219
4.1. Instrument development
The measurement items were initially adapted from extant literature and reworded to be applicable to the context of VHCs. Except the demographic items, all other items were measured on 7-point Likert scales. After compiling an initial set of items, we conducted a content validity assessment to insure that those items appear on their surface to measure the intended construct (Boudreau, Gefen, & Straub, 2001; Kerlinger & Lee, 2000). To do so, we held three focus group sessions in which two faculty members and three PhD students from the host university in this study discussed the wording of the items. The participants in these sessions had previous experience with behavioral research in the context of information security and privacy or other relevant areas in the information systems discipline. Each session took between one hour and thirty minutes and two hours. The five expert participants in the focus group sessions exchanged several emails after each session to further discuss the potential issues and improvements related to the content validity of the items and subscales. As a result of the sessions and email exchanges, several items were removed, revised, or combined. The final set of measurement items upon which consensus was reached are provided in Table 3.
Table 3. Construct Definitions and Measurement Items.
Construct	Reference	Construct Definition	Measurement Items
PHI Privacy Concern	Xu, Dinev, Smith, and Hart (2011)	The extent to which one feels concerned about sharing his/her PHI in the public discussions within virtual health communities.	PC1: I am concerned that the health information I reveal in public discussions could be misused.
PC2*: I am indifferent that others may find my health information that I post in public discussions.
PC3: I worry about what others might do with my health information that I post to public discussions.
PC4: I am concerned about revealing my health information in public discussions, because it could be used in a way I did not foresee.
Expected Personal Outcomes of Sharing PHI	Chiu, Hsu, and Wang (2006)	One's judgment of likely beneficial consequences that his/her PHI communication in public discussions will produce to him/her.	PO1: Sharing my health information in public discussions will help me connect with people who have similar health experiences.
PO2: Sharing my health information in public discussions is good for my well-being.
PO3*: Personal benefits of talking about my health information in public discussions will be trivial.
PO4: There are advantages to me from communicating my health information in public discussions.
Expected Community-Related Outcomes of Sharing PHI	Chiu et al. (2006)	One's judgment of likely beneficial consequences that his/her PHI communication in public discussions will produce to that online community.	CO1: Sharing my health information will help other community members.
CO2: Health information that I communicate will benefit members with similar health conditions.
CO3*: Talking about my health information is worthless for this virtual community.
CO4: The health information I share is valuable to members of this virtual community.
Health Status**	Bansal, Zahedi, and Gefen (2010)	Overall status of one’s health and wellness.	HS1: Related to my health, I experience discomfort for an extended period of time.
HS2: When it comes to chronic conditions, I believe that my condition is severe.
HS3*: In general, I believe that the state of my health is excellent.
Affective Commitment	Bateman et al. (2011)	Identification with, involvement in, and emotional attachment to a virtual health community.	AC1: I feel like a part of the group at this virtual community.
AC2: I have an emotional attachment to this virtual community.
AC3: This virtual community has personal meaning for me.
AC4: I feel a sense of belonging to this virtual community.
AC5*: I feel indifferent toward this virtual community.
Note: * Items eliminated due to low factor loadings (<0.7) and/or high cross-loadings (>0.3). ** For data analysis, the scores for health status items were transformed using (8 − actual score) formula to make higher values of health status associated with better health conditions and vice versa.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Data analysis and results" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
    5. Data analysis and results
    We conducted two rounds of partial least square structural equation modeling (PLS_SEM) procedure using SmartPLS3. In the first round, we included the data collected from group 1 subjects (N = 116). In the second round, we eliminated the affective commitment construct from the model and performed another PLS-SEM using the data collected from group 2 subjects (N = 103). This would enable us to compare and contrast the results associated with those who are actual members of VHCs versus those who are merely familiar with those online communities.
    5.1. Group 1 results
    5.1.1. Measurement model
    In order to examine convergent and discriminant validity, we used factor loadings of each item and average variance extracted (AVE) for each construct. Initially, several items did not load significantly (<0.7) on their intended construct or their cross-loadings were too high (>0.3). We eliminated them and re-ran the PLS model. The final factor structure along with the square root of AVEs are presented in Table 4. Accordingly, all the items load significantly (>0.7) on their corresponding construct. Moreover, the square root of AVEs are all greater than 0.5, which means that the focal constructs explain at least 50% of the variation in their items (Fornell & Larcker, 1981; MacKenzie, Podsakoff, & Podsakoff, 2011). Additionally, the square root of AVEs exceed the correlation between each pair of constructs (Table 5). These facts indicate that the convergent and discriminant validity of the subscales are assured. We also assessed the reliability of the constructs using both Cronbach’s alpha values and composite reliability scores. The results showed that the Cronbach’s alpha values as well as the composite reliability scores for all the constructs are greater than the threshold of 0.7 suggested by Nunnally (1978). This demonstrates that the subscales are adequately reliable.
    Table 4. Convergent Validity and Reliability Assessment (Group 1 Subjects).
    Latent Construct	Indicators	Loadings	Average Variance Extracted	Composite Reliability	Cronbach’s Alpha (α)
    Privacy Concern	PC1	0.975	0.851	0.945	0.929
    PC3	0.936
    PC4	0.851
    Personal Outcomes	PO1	0.887	0.742	0.896	0.825
    PO2	0.899
    PO4	0.794
    Community Outcomes	CO1	0.886	0.843	0.941	0.907
    CO2	0.953
    CO4	0.914
    Health Status	HS1	0.904	0.798	0.887	0.747
    HS2	0.883
    Affective Commitment	AC1	0.830	0.756	0.925	0.895
    AC2	0.770
    AC3	0.909
    AC4	0.956
    Table 5. Discriminant Validity Assessment and Descriptive Statistics (Group 1 Subjects).
    Latent Construct	Privacy Concern	Personal Outcomes	Community Outcomes	Health Status	Affective Commitment	Mean	S.D.
    Privacy Concern	0.922					4.30	1.57
    Personal Outcomes	−0.196	0.861				4.17	1.18
    Community Outcomes	0.039	0.691	0.918			4.46	1.27
    Health Status	0.016	−0.208	−0.169	0.893		4.59	1.59
    Affective Commitment	−0.045	0.325	0.308	−0.111	0.869	3.17	1.36
    5.1.2. Structural model: hypotheses testing
    The estimated path coefficients along with the R-squared values are presented in Fig. 3. In order to estimate the statistical significance of the path coefficients in the structural models, we conducted Bias-Corrected and Accelerated Bootstrapping procedure with 5000 subsamples. This procedure is recommended for regular bootstrapping as “it is the most stable method that does not need excessive computing time (‘Bootstrapping,’ n.d.).” The results of the structural model demonstrated that age does not maintain a statistically significant relationship with neither PHI privacy concern nor health status (α = 0.05). Thus, H1 was not supported. The results also did not support the proposed relationship between health status and privacy concern (H2) at an alpha level of 0.05. Similarly, affective commitment did not show any significant relationship with PHI privacy concern, implying that H5 was not supported. Therefore, none of the proposed antecedents of privacy concern showed significant relationship with this construct.
    Fig. 3
    Download full-size image
    Fig. 3. PLS Results − Path Coefficients (Group 1).
    The results regarding the antecedents of expected personal outcomes of communicating PHI in VHCs showed that health status (β = −0.114; p < 0.05) and affective commitment (β = 0.427; p < 0.001) impact expected personal outcomes. Therefore, H3 and H6 were supported. Moreover, the results supported the hypothesized relationship between affective commitment and expected community-related outcomes of PHI disclosure (β = 0.404; p < 0.001); hence, H7 was supported. But no significant relationship was detected between health status and expected community-related outcomes. Thus, H4 was not supported. In summary, the results supported three hypotheses (H3, H6, and H7) and did not support the four remaining hypotheses (H1, H2, H4, and H5). Furthermore, the R-squared values showed that the variance of health status, privacy concern, personal outcomes, and community-related outcomes explained by this model were 0.029, 0.003, 0.221, and 0.188, respectively. Considering the number of predictor variables included in the model and the statistical significance of three hypothesized relationships between the predictors and the elements of privacy calculus model, we believe that these coefficients of determination are acceptable.
    5.2. Group 2 results
    5.2.1. Measurement model
    In the second part of the analysis, we performed a PLS-SEM on the group 2 subjects. This model did not contain the affective commitment construct, because the group 2 subjects had not responded to the measurement items associated with that construct. The results of convergent and discriminant validity assessment, presented in Tables 6 and 7, revealed that the factor loadings and cross-loadings as well as the AVEs for the constructs were all within the acceptable range. These results were consistent with the corresponding results associated with the group 1 subjects. Moreover, the composite reliability scores and Cronbach’s alpha values were greater than 0.7; hence, the reliability of the subscales in this model was confirmed.
    Table 6. Convergent Validity and Reliability Assessment (Group 2 Subjects).
    Latent Construct	Indicators	Loadings	Average Variance Extracted	Composite Reliability	Cronbach’s Alpha (α)
    Privacy Concern	PC1	0.861	0.812	0.928	0.885
    PC3	0.934
    PC4	0.908
    Personal Outcomes	PO1	0.778	0.774	0.911	0.869
    PO2	0.948
    PO4	0.904
    Community Outcomes	CO1	0.940	0.878	0.956	0.932
    CO2	0.915
    CO4	0.955
    Health Status	HS1	0.930	0.879	0.936	0.863
    HS2	0.945
    Table 7. Discriminant Validity Assessment and Descriptive Statistics (Group 2 Subjects).
    Latent Construct	Privacy Concern	Personal Outcomes	Community Outcomes	Health Status	Mean	S.D.
    Privacy Concern	0.901				4.69	1.52
    Personal Outcomes	−0.441	0.880			4.70	1.33
    Community Outcomes	−0.300	0.751	0.937		4.97	1.33
    Health Status	0.286	−0.151	−0.120	0.938	4.87	1.62
    5.2.2. Structural model: hypotheses testing
    We retested hypotheses 1 through 4. The results of the structural model are presented in Fig. 4. Accordingly, age has a statistically significant relationship (β = −0.223; p < 0.05) with PHI privacy concern, but interestingly, in the opposite direction of what was proposed in H1. ]]> <h target="2" match="part">It means that according to our results, older people are less concerned about their PHI privacy compared with younger ones.</h><![CDATA[ The results also revealed that health status has a positive relationship ( β= 0.241; p < 0.05) with PHI privacy concern, indicating that healthier people are more concerned about their PHI privacy concern compared with those who are suffering from medical conditions. Nevertheless, our results did not support the proposed relationships between health status and expected personal and community-related outcomes of communicating PHI in VHCs (H3 and H4). As expected, age also has a negative relationship with health status, meaning that younger people in our sample were healthier than older individuals.
    Fig. 4
    Download full-size image
    Fig. 4. PLS Results − Path Coefficients (Group 2).
    5.3. Summary of the results
    A summary of the results across the two samples (models) are provided in Table 8. The cells at the intersections of H4, H5, and H6 with group 2 subjects are blank because those hypotheses were only related to group 1 individuals and were not tested on group 2 subjects.
    Table 8. Summary of the Results.
    Hypothesis	Relation	Results
    Groups 1
    Subjects	Group 2
    Subjects
    H1: Older people are more concerned about their PHI privacy in public VHC discussions.	Age → Privacy Concern	Not Supported	Supported (Opposite Direction)
    H2: People in poorer health conditions are less concerned about their PHI privacy in public VHC discussions.	Health Status → Privacy Concern	Not Supported	Supported
    H3: People in poorer health conditions expect to receive more benefits from communicating PHI in public VHC discussions.	Health Status → Personal Outcomes	Supported	Supported
    H4: People in poorer health conditions expect to provide more benefits to a VHC by communicating PHI in public discussions within that community.	Health Status → Community Outcomes	Not supported	Not supported
    H5: People with higher affective commitment to a VHC are less concerned about their PHI privacy while communicating in public VHC discussions.	Affective Commitment → Privacy Concern	Not Supported	–
    H6: People with higher affective commitment expect to receive more benefits of communicating PHI in public VHC discussions.	Affective Commitment → Personal Outcomes	Supported	–
    H7: People with higher affective commitment expect to provide more benefits to a VHC by communicating PHI in public discussions within that community.	Affective Commitment → Community Outcomes	Supported	–]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Discussion" category="discussion">
        <![CDATA[
    6. Discussion
    The main objective of this study was to examine the potential antecedents of the privacy costs and expected benefits of PHI disclosure in health social media from a privacy calculus perspective. Our findings revealed that the balance between the elements of privacy calculus model can partially be determined by factors such as age, health status, and affective commitment.
    
    The results regarding the antecedents of privacy concern is mixed. According to our results, neither age nor health status of actual members of VHCs determine their privacy concern; whereas, both age and health status affect privacy concern for the individuals who are merely familiar with VHCs. A plausible explanation for these different results is that compared with non-members, actual members of VHCs have a clearer understanding of profile creation, content generation, and PHI communication processes within VHC discussions, because they have already used those websites. Moreover, actual members of VHCs are more aware of the privacy control features provided by VHCs; hence, they know how to better handle the privacy risks associated with PHI disclosure and how to protect anonymity and information privacy to prevent the negative consequences of PHI disclosure in that context. Therefore, the actual members’ privacy-related understandings and awareness may help them control their privacy concerns more effectively. Consequently, their privacy concerns are not significantly determined by their personal characteristics such as age and health status. Whereas, non-members may have a vaguer image of privacy risks and controls on VHCs, thus their privacy concerns are shaped by internal factors such as age and health status. Furthermore, the non-significant relationship observed between health status and privacy concern for actual members may imply that some individuals may differ regarding their concerns about privacy based on the type of illness that they have rather than their overall health status. For example, a person with a potentially terminal, non-communicable illness such as cancer may not be as concerned about their privacy as someone who suffers from a potentially terminal, communicable illness such as Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome (AIDS).
    
    The negative relationship we have observed between age and privacy concern for non-members, which contrasts our hypothesis, may partially be due to the fact that over the past few years, younger individuals have in general become more aware about potential negative consequences of personal information disclosure in online environments. They may now be more protective of their personal information. On the other side of the continuum, older people may have realized that being too concerned about personal information such as PHI, may not be reasonable as long as they can adequately protect their anonymity using privacy protection mechanisms such as the privacy settings on their profile pages within social media websites. Additionally, older people may be less concerned about the negative stigma that sometimes accompany certain illnesses in individuals, but more concerned about getting help for their medical conditions.
    
    On the other side of the privacy calculus model, our findings revealed that VHC actual members’ health status affects their perceived benefits of PHI communication in health social media websites. This suggests that people with poorer health conditions perceive more benefits of PHI communications via social media platforms. This result is directly related to the fact that social support has different values to different people. Those individuals who are in critical need of medical information as well as emotional support, expect to receive more meaningful support from the community once they share their PHI such as medical history with them. Whereas, those individuals who are relatively healthy may not need the immediate support from these communities and may not feel the need to provide their medical information to others in the community.
    
    The results showed that although non-members perceive overall higher benefits of PHI disclosure in VHCs (see Tables 4 and 6), their perceptions are not determined by their health status. This may be due to the non-members’ lack of clear understanding of VHCs and the reciprocal support that they can receive if they disclose information about their health conditions in online VHC discussions. More specifically, the non-members’ higher perceived benefits compared with those of actual members demonstrates that overall, non-members, regardless of their health status, may overestimate the benefits that they could receive from the community.
    Our observations regarding the relationship between health status and community-related outcomes of PHI communication in social media environments revealed that for either members or non-members, health status does not affect those perceived outcomes. This means that healthy and not-too-healthy people seemingly perceive a relatively similar level of benefits that they can provide to an online community by offering their health-related information and experiences to that community.
    
    Another interesting result in this study is that affective commitment can play a role in increasing expected personal and community-related outcomes of PHI revelation in online health communications. Thus, those with higher levels of emotional attachment to an online community are more optimistic about receiving meaningful and helpful support from the community. Moreover, they may believe that because they have established emotional ties with the members of the community, their support, particularly emotional support, will provide relief and help those members to cope with their medical conditions more effectively. This is consistent with prior research which showed that affective commitment increases participation and knowledge contribution within online communities (Bateman et al., 2011; Tsai & Bagozzi, 2014). The non-significant relationship between affective commitment and privacy concern, however, implies that even those individuals who are highly emotionally attached to a VHC may be concerned about their PHI privacy in that context and will try to protect it in different ways.
    6.1. Theoretical implications
    This study adds to the research stream on information privacy, social media, and health communications. Prior privacy literature demonstrated that there is a trade-off between the drivers and barriers of information disclosure in various contexts. Our research showed that this trade-off is influenced by factors such as age, health status, and affective commitment in the realm of health social media. Previous studies showed that affective commitment can play a role in user participation within general purpose online communities. Our results enhanced our understanding of the role of this construct in health-related online communities, and the public discussions within them. Moreover, prior information privacy literature showed that age has a negative relationship with privacy concern in various contexts ranging from e-commerce (Chen et al., 2001; Janda & Fair, 2004) and online advertising (Smit et al., 2014), to general-purpose online social networks (Tufekci, 2008) and health information technology. In those studies older people perceived a higher level of privacy risks of self-disclosure. Our results, however, showed this may not be true in the context of health social media, in particular for those individuals who are not actual members of VHCs.
    6.2. Practical implications
    Developers, providers, and administrators of health social media platforms and websites can use the results of this study to formulate and implement privacy strategies, policies, and mechanisms on those websites. For example, VHC administrators should raise awareness about privacy protection mechanisms on their websites to encourage potential members to become actual members and to actively participate in health-related online VHC discussions. Also, privacy statements should concisely address individuals’ privacy concerns and those statements should be easily accessible to the first time users of those websites. Moreover, because healthy members perceive fewer benefits of PHI communication in online communities, VHCs can implement rewarding mechanisms for active participation of healthy individuals in VHC discussions. In result, even if those individuals do not perceive much health-related benefits of PHI-intensive communications within online discussions, they will still perceive social benefits such as recognition in the community and feeling of importance (Chung, 2011), which can potentially encourage them to become active members of those communities. On the other hand, our results suggest that individuals with poor health conditions perceive more benefits of communicating via discussion boards. Thus, they could be identified and directed to the relevant discussion threads so that they can get engaged in focused online discussions and receive more value from joining and participating in those virtual environments.
    We observed that younger non-member individuals are expected to be less concerned about their privacy on VHCs compared with their older counterparts. Thus, VHCs can identify potential members and classify them based on their age. Then, VHC administrators can send privacy protection tips and advice in the forms of pop-up web pages and personalized emails to the younger individuals more frequently. This will enhance the effectiveness of member acquisition promotion mechanisms on VHCs.
    
    Our findings also imply that emotionally attached users to online communities can be deemed as valuable resources to those communities in that they expect to receive and provide beneficial social support by sharing their health-related knowledge containing PHI with the community. Thus, community providers can identify users with higher affective commitment and support their participation in online discussions by updating them more frequently on what discussion topics have been recently initiated and what comments have been posted to which discussion threads. This will make these users champions or power users (Kordzadeh, Liu, Au, & Clark, 2012) in the community. Also, this will ultimately foster the community’s overall prosper and growth, because discussion threads with power users involved in have been found to be generally more active and vibrant (Kordzadeh et al., 2012).
    At the national level, governmental agencies such as the Department of Health and Human Services that are in charge of enforcing privacy acts and regulations including HIPAA now know that young individuals are more concerned about their PHI privacy. Therefore, those agencies can mandate VHC providers to offer more effective privacy protection settings and mechanisms to young users of those websites, although a basic level of such mechanisms should be provided to everyone.
    
    6.3. Limitations and future research
    This study has limitations. For instance, we did not use a specific VHC to collect data from. Rather, we asked the respondents to think of any VHCs that they were members of. Although this would enhance the generalizability of our results, we did not control for website-specific characteristics such as privacy protection mechanisms and policies that might influence one’s privacy concern. Future studies can address this issue by focusing on specific online communities. Also, we did not consider trust in the VHC participants, nor did we consider trust in the accuracy of the information contained in the discussions. Previous researchers, however, suggest that trust is higher when the participants believe that the betrayal of trust, which can result in privacy concerns, will result in minimal harm (Hocevar, Flanagin, & Metzger, 2014). Future research can include the relationship between trust and privacy concern.
    Another limitation of our study is that we only employed survey methodology to collect data on individuals’ beliefs and perceptions. Future research can collect data on people’s actual behaviors related to information disclosure to eliminate possible common method bias. The ages of the subjects in this study were also skewed toward younger age groups because students made up the majority of the respondents. Future studies can address this issue by collecting more data from elderly population and individuals from non-academic environments as their age distribution may be wider and non-skewed. Furthermore, researchers in the future can take into account the sub-dimensions of privacy concern, such as those suggested by Malhotra, Kim, & Agarwal (2004) including collection, control, and awareness of privacy practices. Researchers can then investigate how each of those sub-dimensions shape one’s perceptions and behaviors in social media environments.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Conclusions" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
    7. Conclusions
    In line with the increasing use of social media technologies for peer-to-peer health communications, we adopted a privacy calculus perspective to investigate the antecedents of expected benefits and privacy concerns of communicating PHI in VHCs. According to our results, the privacy calculus trade-off in health social media can be influenced by age, health status, and affective commitment. Age and health status impact non-members’ privacy concerns but not members’ privacy concerns. Instead, health status affects members’ expected personal outcomes of PHI communication in VHCs, but not non-members’. ]]><h target="4" match="part">Additionally, affective commitment influences personal and community-related outcomes of PHI disclosure.</h><![CDATA[ Our findings imply that providers of socially-integrated health applications and online communities should pay enough attention to the role of those factors to improve the expected benefits and address privacy concerns associated with using social technologies, making people more inclined toward communicating in health-related online communities. In result, those online communities will turn to vibrant and successful communication environments with active participants.]]>
    </section>
</publication>
