<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="li ying">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 1, February 2016, Pages 97-104</time>
    <title>Testing the level of interactivity of institutional websites: From museums 1.0 to museums 2.0</title>
    <author>Paul Capriotti.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Carmen Carretón.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Antonio Castillo.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacec. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
Universitat Rovira i Virgili, Department of Communication Studies, Av. Catalunya, 35. 3rd Floor, Room 323, 43002 Tarragona, Spain
b
Universidad de Alicante, Department of Communication and Social Psychology, Carretera San Vicente del Raspeig s/n 03690, San Vicente del Raspeig, Alicante, Spain
c
Universidad de Málaga, School of Communication Sciences, Campus de Teatinos, 29071 Málaga, Spain
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2015.10.003</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">Web 2.0 is changing the way that museums communication with their publics.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">Museums have a low level of interactivity in relation with the Presentation of Information.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">Museums have a medium level of interactivity with regard the Resources for Interaction.</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">Museums are not using the potential of Web 2.0 to establish dialogue with visitors</highlight>
    <highlight id="5">Museums are progressively implementing more interactive and dialogic sources.</highlight>
Abstract
    <abstract>The Internet has changed the way in which organizations communicate with their publics, and museums are not an exception. The consolidation of Web 2.0 has not only given museums access to a powerful new tool for disseminating information, but <h target="1" match="part">has involved significant changes in the relationship between institutions and their publics, facilitating and enhancing the interaction between them.</h> The overall objective of this paper is to analyze the degree of interactivity implemented in the websites of major international art museums, in order to assess if museums are evolving towards more dialogic systems with relation to their publics. <h target="2;3" match="part;part">The results indicate that museums still have a low level of interactivity on their websites, both in the tools used to present information and the resources available for interaction with virtual visitors.</h> <h target="5" match="part">But it has also observed that museums are progressively implementing interactive and dialogic sources</h>, suggesting a clear trend towards new ways of managing these platforms in order to establish more participatory and collaborative communication systems with virtual users.</abstract>
Keywords
    <keywords>Museums</keywords>
    <keywords>Web 2.0</keywords>
    <keywords>Interactivity</keywords>
    <keywords>Dialogic communication</keywords>
    <keywords>Public relations</keywords>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
The Internet has gradually but radically changed the way in which organizations communicate with their publics. It has opened a wide range of tools for communication and public relations (Zerfass, Tench, Verčič, Verhoeven, & Moreno, 2014), first as a mass medium (accessible 365 days a year, 24 h a day—internet 1.0-), but fundamentally as a tool that facilitates interaction and relationship building between organizations and their publics through interactive and collaborative resources and platforms (internet 2.0) (Kent & Taylor, 1998; Guillory & Sundar, 2014).
The websites of the organizations have also undergone a constant evolution for two decades, from being basically informative/monologic instruments in the beginning to now serving as conversational/dialogic tools (Heinze & Hu, 2006; Capriotti & Pardo Kuklinski, 2012). Thus, websites with a “one-to-many” approach tend to disappear and be replaced by “many-to-many” platforms that favor the open interaction. Dialogic communication is nowadays an essential expectation in the online communication strategy of any organization. It has generated a key challenge for corporate communications and public relations, because as Cobo and Pardo Kuklinski, (2007) the websites are not mere windows onto multimedia content but rather they should be an open platform built for user participation that allows for symmetrical and multidirectional communication between organizations and publics.
In this change of the communication model, museums are no exception. For almost 20 years these institutions have been using the communicative possibilities offered by websites to make their collections, activities and knowledge accessible to a wider public (Crenn & Vidal, 2007; Simon, 2010). The role of the internet in museums is of increasing importance, and will be even more important in the future as more changes occur in the social web and mobile communications (Crenn & Vidal, 2007; Tallon & Walker, 2008; Simon, 2010).
The overall objective of this paper is to analyze the degree of interactivity implemented in the websites (in this case, institutional websites of major international art museums), assessing whether these digital platforms are evolving towards more interactive/dialogic models (2.0 websites) or if they are maintaining a structure and operation which is informative/unidirectional (1.0 websites).]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Literature review;Purpose of the research" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Literature review
2.1. Interactivity and dialogic communication
The emergence and consolidation of Web 2.0 during the first decade of the century has involved significant changes in the relationship between an organization and its publics, facilitating a more symmetrical interaction and negotiation in terms of power and mutual influence, beginning the move towards a full dialogic or interactive form of communication (Kent & Taylor, 1998; Ingenhoff & Koelling, 2009; Capriotti, 2011; Guillory & Sundar, 2014).
Kent and Taylor (1998, 2002) indicate that the dialogic communication is the framework for the building of relationships between an organization and its publics through the Internet. Dialogic communication can be defined as “an ongoing interaction between organizations and their publics using Internet tools, which enables information, comments, opinions, assessment and experiences to be exchanged on a continuous basis” (Capriotti & Pardo Kuklinski, 2012; p.620). Thus, interactivity is the cornerstone on which dialogic communication is built (Guillory & Sundar, 2014), and it is used by organizations to establish an appropriate engagement with their publics (McAllister-Spooner, 2009; Taylor & Kent, 2014).
Interactivity is one of the distinguishing features of Internet (Castells, 2001; Kiousis, 2002; Leiner & Quiring, 2008) and in the field of communication and public relations has been the subject of various studies, since it is the basis on which the study of dialogic communication between an organization and its publics is built. Research on websites (Jo & Kim, 2003; Jo & Jung, 2005; Capriotti & Moreno, 2007; Park & Reber, 2008; McAllister-Spooner, 2009; Kim, Park, & Wertz, 2010; Guillory & Sundar, 2014) has focused mainly on the analysis of the level of interactivity driven and implemented by organizations. Studies have been developed to evaluate the tools and resources available on websites to promote and facilitate interaction (Heinze & Hu, 2006). Thus, it has been identified two main approaches to websites based upon the varying use of the tools or means of interaction: those websites that focus mainly on the dissemination of information and those more oriented to organization-public dialogue (Capriotti &Moreno, 2007). In the first, the level of interactivity is low and the tools used are primarily unidirectional, with the main objective of disseminating information from the organization to its publics in order to influence them. In the second approach, the level of interactivity is high, and the resources available on the website are used to facilitate two-way communication, encouraging dialogue and interaction to establish a stable and continuous relationship.
Those investigations have been made from the evaluation of two key aspects in websites: firstly, analysis of the tools used for the presentation of information (to assess the interaction between visitors and the information on the website and how people receive or get information and interact with it). And, secondly, the use of resources and tools available on the websites to facilitate the interaction of virtual users with the organization (to analyze the virtual interaction between the organization and virtual visitors, and how they communicate and interact with the organization through the website). The results obtained in most of the studies conducted (Jo & Jung, 2005; Heinze & Hu, 2006; Capriotti & Moreno, 2007; Park & Reber, 2008; Ingenhoff and Koeling, 2009; McAllister-Spooner, 2009; Kim et al., 2010; Guillory & Sundar, 2014) indicate that organizations are still at an early stage of migration from a model of informative and unidirectional websites towards a model of dialogic websites. In most cases they are not currently developing the full potential offered by the social web, although a trend has been observed towards greater interactivity.
2.2. Dialogic communication, interactivity and museums
Communication and Public Relations are now playing a key role in the development of postmodern museum (Hooper-Greenhill, 2000; Gürel & Kavak, 2010; Capriotti, 2013) and in recent years the Internet has gained a leading role in these institutions as a communication tool with their publics (Marty, 2007; Simon, 2010; Capriotti & Pardo Kuklinski, 2012).
For a long time, web 1.0 resources (predominantly unidirectional) allowed museums to provide information using an “up-down” strategy (Capriotti & Kuklinki Pardo, 2012). The Internet has expanded the capacity of these institutions to disseminate information in a massive, controlled, quick and easy manner (Marty, 2007; Capriotti, 2011). However, through web 2.0 tools (which are more collaborative, multidirectional and dialogical) museums are offered new options and possibilities for communication, and changing the way museums engage with their publics through involvement and active participation using instruments that allow the exchange of information, debate, discussion and collaboration (Crenn & Vidal, 2007; López et al., 2010; Kidd, 2011).
Several studies (Marty, 2007; Crenn & Vidal, 2007; Tallon & Walker, 2008; Capriotti, 2010; Allen-Greil & Mac Arthur, 2010; Capriotti & Pardo Kuklinski, 2012; Padilla-Meléndez & Del Águila-Obra, 2013) indicate that websites are being used increasingly to generate a more collaborative and interactive relationship between museums and their various publics, analyzing the two previously mentioned aspects of dialogic communication: tools for the presentation of information (Capriotti & Pardo Kuklinski, 2012; Padilla-Meléndez & Del Águila-Obra, 2013), and the use of resources for interaction with the publics on websites (López et al., 2010; Capriotti & González Herrero, 2013). Thus,studies are evaluating whether museum websites are immersed in a process of transition from static spaces of dissemination of information (1.0 websites) into platforms for interaction and dialogue between museums and the public (2.0 websites).
However, most of the research conducted has an unrepresentative number of museums and are implemented at a national level or comparing a few countries at best. And, finally, these studies also tend to focus only on one particular aspect of the analysis. There are few international studies with a large sample of institutions to examine both aspects in an integrated way.

3. Purpose of the research
Thus, this work evaluates the level of interactivity implemented in the institutional websites of the 100 most visited art museums in the world (including museums in 24 countries in three main geographical regions: Europe, America and the Asia/Pacific region). To do so, it will analyze two key aspects in order to ascertain the interactivity of websites: tools used for the presentation of information and the use of resources for interaction with publics, in order to establish whether these digital platforms are evolving towards a more interactive/dialogic model (2.0 websites) or continue with an informative/unidirectional approach (1.0 websites)
    </section>
    <section name=" Methodology" category="methods">
       
4. Methodology
The corpus of the study was the main international art museums. To define the sample, the number of annual visits to museums was identified, and it was decided to analyze the most visited art museums in the world. The sample was selected from the annual ranking of visits made by the prestigious magazine “The Art Newspaper” (http://www.theartnewspaper.com/), which prepares an annual list of the most visited art museums of in the world. To avoid a list with museums that only have a “one hit wonder” temporary exhibition (a very successful exhibition in only one year), the rankings produced for 5 years (2008–2012, published from 2009 to 2013) were compared, and museums that appeared at least 3 times in the five years, or in 2 of the last 3 years analyzed, were selected. The final sample included 100 official institutional websites of these entities from 24 countries: 60 in Europe, 23 in America and 17 in the Asia/Pacific region. The official website was located by searching the most popular Internet search engines, using the name of museums in the search engines.
To achieve the overall objective of the research, two main research questions (RQ) were established, which correspond to the two key criteria identified in the theoretical framework for evaluating the interactivity of websites.

RQ1: What kind of resources or instruments are used to present information on the websites of museums?

RQ2: What tools and resources are available on the websites for interaction with museum virtual visitors?

To answer the research questions, a content analysis methodology of the selected websites was applied.

For the RQ1, the category Presentation of Information Tools allows us to study the different methods used to present information on the entity and its activities. For this reason, three types of resources were identified according to their interactive possibilities: (1) Expositive: those that facilitate the dissemination of information with an essentially passive and receptive visitor. This type of resource was differentiated between “Graphic” (written text and still images, photos or graphics) and “Audiovisual” (which includes elements of audio and video). (2) Hyper-textual: the use of links, which allow a greater degree of interaction than Expositive resources, and facilitate an active search for additional information and in-depth topics within the museum website and elsewhere on the internet. (3) Participative: those that help one learn through interaction with an active and participatory visitor. This category distinguishes between ‘interactive’ elements (such as interactive graphics and/or infographics which allow one to interact with information) and ‘Immersive’ resources (through virtual tours, organized systems for virtually visiting the museum) (Table 1).
Table 1. Presentation of Information Tools.
Categories	Types of tools	Tools
Presentation of Information Resources/Tools	Expositive	Graphic	Texts
Photos/images
Audio–visual	Audio
Video
Hyper-textual	Links	External links
Participative	Interactive	Interactive resources
Immersive	Virtual visits
For the RQ2, the category of Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction was established. This allowed us to assess the type of interaction between the museum and virtual visitors that the website encourages. Thus, 20 types of instruments or resources were identified. These were distributed in 5 dimensions, based on the degree of participation and involvement that they propose or encourage from the user of the website: ‘connecting’ (visitors are limited to requesting the sending of information, with a very low level of interaction and involvement); ‘Sharing’ (users can only distribute or share information with low interaction and involvement on their part); ‘Reviewing’ (visitors can review and comment, indicating greater involvement and interaction); ‘Participating’ (users can participate in activities, which have a high level of interaction) and ‘Collaborating’ (users can create and develop their own or joint spaces with the museum, and the participation and interaction of the visitors is very high). Each dimension was composed of between 3 and 5 tools (Table 2).
Table 2. Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction.
Categories	Dimensions	Tools
Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction	Connecting	Content syndication
Subscription forms
Registration (sign up/registration)
Mobile alerts
Sharing	Tools/buttons for tagging information
Tools/buttons for linking information to external sites
Tools/buttons for sharing information in social networks
Reviewing	Polling/voting
Surveys
Open-ended questions
Message board/commenting box
Online guestbook
Participating	Contests/competitions
Sweepstake
Coupons, barcodes, QR codes
Individual or collective games
Collaborating	Tools for creating a personal gallery
Uploading tools(texts, images, videos, podcasts)
Tools for experiments (simulations, reconstructions, etc.)
Tools for theco-creation of content or displays
Once the categories of analysis had been defined, a Likert scale was implemented by assigning a weighted value to each type of resource (1–5 points, where 1 = very low interactivity and 5 = very high interactivity) to establish the “level of interactivity” of museums, both in relation to the Presentation of Information Tools (RQ1) and to Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction (RQ2) to provide qualitative interpretation of the results value. It was applied using a dichotomous structure of “yes/no”, considering the presence (=1) or absence (=0) of each resource or tool on the websites of each individual museum. Then results were divided by geographical areas (Europe, America and Asia/Pacific) or observed as a trend amongst global museums as a whole.
To establish the “level of interactivity” of websites concerning the Presentation of Information Tools (RQ1), weighted values ​​were assigned to each of the resource types studied in terms of their potential for interaction (Table 3):“Graphics” were assigned a score of 1 point (very low interactivity);“Audiovisual” resources will give 2 points (low interactivity);“Links” were assigned 3 points (mean interactivity); “Interactive” resources were given 4 points (high interactivity) and “Immersive” tools were granted 5 points (very high interactivity).
Table 3. Level of interactivity. Presentation of Information Tools.
Resources for the Presentation of Information	Interactivity scale(Likert Scale)	Value assigned(VA)	Presence
(P)	Points obtained
(PO)	Result (level of interactivity)
NO–YES		
Graphics	Very low	1 points	0–1	VA × P	=Mean (X¯)(PO/5)
Audiovisual	Low	2 points	0–1	VA × P
Links	Mean	3 points	0–1	VA × P
Interactive	High	4 points	0–1	VA × P
Immersive	Very high	5 points	0–1	VA × P
To determine the “level of interactivity” of websites with relation to the Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction (RQ2), weighted values were assigned to each of the dimensions previously established according to their potential for interaction (Table 4):“Connecting” was assigned a score of 1 point (very low interactivity); to “Sharing” will give 2 points (low interactivity); “Reviewing” was assigned 3 points (mean interactivity); “participating” is given 4 points (high interactivity) and “Collaborating” will give 5 points (very high interactivity).
Table 4. Level of interactivity. Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction.
Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction	Interactivity scale
(Likert scale)	Value assigned
(VA)	Presence
(P)	Points obtained
(PO)	Result (level of interactivity)
NO–YES		
Connecting	Very low	1 points	0–1	VA × P	=Mean (X¯)(PO/5)
Sharing	Low	2 points	0–1	VA × P
Reviewing	Mean	3 points	0–1	VA × P
Participating	High	4 points	0–1	VA × P
Collaborating	Very high	5 points	0–1	VA × P
The result (average of the sum of the total weighted value of each resource) allow for three levels of interactivity of websites of museums on a scale of 0–3 points: “low/poor interactivity” (0–1 point), “medium interactivity” (between 1.1 and 2 points), and “high interactivity/good” (between 2.1 and 3 points).

Once the research form had been initially developed, an exploratory analysis of 20 different museums’ sites (representative of the various types of existing features) was performed. This first evaluation allowed us to judge the appropriateness of the methodology for responding to the research questions. Once the necessary modifications were made, the analysis was implemented for the whole sample selected. The information obtained was coded and treated statistically with SPSS V.22 for results.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Results" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
5. Results
The results indicate that all of the museums have websites, but only 78% of them are specific to the museum, while 12% of these entities share their websites with other museums and the remaining 10% share websites with other institutions. The results obtained, based on the research questions posed, are presented below.

5.1. Presentation of Information Tools
As reflected in Table 5, graphic resources are used as a basic tool for presenting information (in 100% of the museums). Other resources have a much smaller presence: audiovisual resources are present in less than 50% cases (43%), interactive resources achieve a frequency of almost 30%, and both external and immersive links are only employed by around 15% of museums.
Table 5. Presentation of Information Tools.
Types of tools	Tools	Global
(GL)	Europe (EU)	America (AM)	Asia/Pacific (AP)
Expositive	Graphic	Texts/images	100%	100%	100%	100%
Audio–visual	Audio/video	43%	45.0%	56.5%	17.6%
Participative	Hyper-Textual	External links	16%	13.3%	17.4%	23.5%
Interactive	Interactive resources	29%	25.0%	39.1%	29.4%
Immersive	Virtual visits	13%	18.3%	4.3%	5.9%
No geographic differences are noted in the use of graphics. However America reaches prevalence in the use of audiovisual resources, European museums are in second position, and in the Asia Pacific a very low presence of such resources is seen (only 17%). Interactive resources are best used by museums in America (almost 40%), followed by those museums in the Asia-Pacific region (almost 30% of institutions) and only 25% of the European museums sampled used these resources. Hyper-textual resources achieve their best score in the Asia-Pacific region and immersive resources in Europe.

]]><h target="2" match="part">The outcome of the assessment of the level of interactivity in the Presentation of information by museums (Table 6) allows us to suggest that the resources used by institutions worldwide to present information are generally at the lower level of the interactivity scale,</h> <![CDATA[with an average score of 0.83 points (on a scale of 0–3 points).
Table 6. Level of interactivity in the Presentation of Information by museums.
Resources used to present information	Value assigned (VA)	Presence (N)	Points awared (N × VA)	Level of interactivity
([P/5]/no. museums)
GL	EU	AM	AP	GL	EU	AM	AP	GL	EU	AM	AP
Graphic	1p	100	60	23	17	100	60	23	17	0.83	0.84	0.89	0.71
Audio–visual	2p	43	27	13	3	86	54	26	6
Hyper-textual	3p	16	8	4	4	48	24	12	12
Interactive	4p	29	15	9	5	116	60	36	20
Immersive	5p	13	11	1	1	65	55	5	5
Total						415	253	102	60
When assessing the results by geographical area, it is observed that there are no major differences between them, and all regions are at low levels of interactivity. Museums in Europe are almost at the world average, while American entities are in a better position with regards to interactivity.
]]><h target="5" match="part">This is due to the higher score of American museums in the interactive and audiovisual resources, which allows them to position as the museums with best level of interactivity, </h><![CDATA[above the global average: 0.89 compared with 0.84 in Europe. On the other hand, museums of the Asia/Pacific region score only 0.71 on average: they are far from the world average, with a low score on the most resources, mainly due to their low use of immersive and audiovisual resources.Finally, the almost nonexistent presence of immersive resources, especially in America and Asia-Pacific, is remarkable.

5.2. Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction
Regarding RQ2, the analysis shows which instruments of interaction with the visitor carry more weight on each of the dimensions and therefore which ones best define the dimension (Table 7). The frequency (N) indicates the number of museums that use such a tool, and percentages (%) indicate the weight of each within the dimension of which they are part, in order to find out which defines it most.To do this, a multiple response frequency analysis was set, which groups elements of each of the dimensions. Then a cross analysis between the dimension and each of the elements was performed. The results obtained allowed for the determination of the relative values in each dimension. In this sense, category performance with optimal scaling procedure gives us the tools to assess correlations in the most appropriate manner.
Table 7. Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction.
Total
Dimension	Tools	N	(%)
Connecting	Content syndication	41	32.28
Subscription forms	58	45.6
Registration (sign up/registration)	27	21.26
Mobile alerts	1	0.78
Total	127	100
Sharing	Tools/buttons for tagging information	1	2.08
Tools for linking information to external sites	2	4.17
Tools/buttons for sharing on Social Networks	45	93.75
Total	48	100
Reviewing	Polling/voting	2	9.09
Surveys	4	18.18
Comments	13	59.09
Open-ended questions	–	–
Message board/commenting box	–	–
Online guestbook	3	13.64
Total	22	100
Participating	Contests/competitions	–	–
Sweepstake	–	–
Coupons, barcodes, QR codes	2	9.52
Individual or collective games	19	90.48
Total	21	100
Colaborating	Tools for creating a personal gallery	52	65
Uploading tools(texts, images, videos, podcasts)	4	5
Tools for experiments (simulations, reconstructions, etc.)	20	25
Tools for theco-creation of content or displays	4	5
Total	80	100
The data indicate that only 6 tools are key to the interaction with visitors of the websites of museums. The resources that best define the “connecting” dimension are ‘subscription forms’ and ‘content syndication’. The “sharing” dimension is defined almost exclusively by the share on social networks' tool. The ‘comments’ tool correlates with the “reviewing” dimension. The use of ‘games’ determines the “participating” dimension while the option to “create a personal gallery” is the tool that defines the dimension related to “collaborating”. So, the other 14 tools have a much less notable presence: just 2 tools have a presence in about 25% of all museums (‘registration’ in the “connecting” dimension and ‘co-creation of content’ in dimension “collaborating”) and 2 other tools have a presence in about 15% of museums (‘surveys’ and ‘online guessbooks’ in the “reviewing” dimension). The other 10 tools have a token presence, with less than 10% of websites making use of them.

In relation to the five dimensions defined (Table 8), the results indicate a majority of museums make use of the less interactive resources (“Connecting”) in 75% of cases, although the dimension “Collaborating” (which has greater level of interaction) has been identified in almost 60% of the websites. The dimension of“Sharing” (closely related to the most basic use of social networks) reached almost 50% of museums. And the “reviewing” and “participating” dimensions have a much less significant presence, around 20% of institutions.
Table 8. Dimensions of Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction.
Dimensions	Global	Europe	America	Asia/Pacific
Connecting	75%	76.7%	87.0%	52.9%
Sharing	46%	45.0%	65.2%	23.5%
Reviewing	19%	21.7%	8.7%	23.5%
Participating	21%	20.0%	21.7%	23.5%
Collaborating	59%	53.3%	69.6%	64.7%
By regions, Europe had a very similar to the overall results. America scores better than average and the other 2 regions, in almost all dimensions, except in the case of “reviewing”, in which it has a very low score (not even 10%), although the low use of resources that define this dimension is decisive in their level of interactivity. Asia-Pacific is the only region where the “Collaborating” dimension (65%) has greater presence than “Connecting” (53%) while the other 3 dimensions have a similar weight (about 25%).

Regarding the level of interactivity with respect to Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction (Table 9), the results indicate that museums are located at a medium/low level of interactivity. These results are conditioned by the majority use of tools related to “connecting”, although the “collaborating” dimension has a strong presence. The score of 603 points puts the level of interactivity at 1.21 out of 3, suggesting that museums are in the lower range of the medium level.
Table 9. Level of interactivity in the Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction.
Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction	Value assigned (VA)	Presence (N)	Points awarded (P) (N × VA)	Level of interactivity
([P/5] / no. museums)
GL	EU	AM	AP	GL	EU	AM	AP	GL	EU	AM	AP
Connecting	1p	75	46	20	9	75	46	20	9	1.21	1.16	1.36	1.18
Sharing	2p	46	27	15	4	92	54	30	8
Reviewing	3p	19	13	2	4	57	39	6	12
Participating	4p	21	12	5	4	84	48	20	16
Collaborating	5p	59	32	16	11	295	160	80	55
Total						603	347	156	100
Observing these results by geographical area, the museums of America are located well above the other two regions, with a nearly 0.20 point difference in the overall assessment of interactivity. In all three regions the “connecting” and “collaborating” dimensions dominated, although in Europe and America “sharing”, is also relevant while the “reviewing” and “participating” dimensions have less presence. In the Asia Pacific, the three dimensions (Sharing, Reviewing y Participating) have a similar weight.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Discussion" category="discussion">
        <![CDATA[
6. Discussion
The analysis reveals that Europe’s performance, in general terms, follows the same trend as the overall results, since it has the 60% of museums analyzed. Still, the data show some differences between geographic regions in the use of various tools offered on their websites.

From the results on Presentation of Information Tools (RQ1), we observe a major use of expositive resources by museums in order to present all the information available on their websites. We showed the preponderance of graphic resources while audiovisual resources come in a distant second place. As for participative resources we see a minor use of interactive tools, while the hyper-textual and immersive tools available are very few. Thus, interactive tools are more prominent than the hyper-textual and interactive resources. This suggests that museums have mostly implemented this specific type of resources on their websites. By region, in Europe there is a trend to a higher use of immersive resources, while in America the use of audiovisual and Interactive resources is more relevant, whilst in the Asia/Pacific hypertext resources are important.

From the Likert scale designed, results show that the degree of interactivity in this type of resource is 0.83 out of 3, which indicates that interactivity is very low. These results are consistent with studies by various authors, both at the level of organizations in general (Capriotti & Moreno, 2007; Heinze & Hu, 2006; McAllister-Spooner, 2009) and specific studies in museums (Capriotti & Pardo Kuklinski, 2012; Padilla-Meléndez & Del Águila-Obra, 2013).
When looking at the Resources for Interaction with the virtual visitor (RQ2), it can be seen that “Connecting” occurs at a higher frequency compared to the rest. In second place is “Collaborating” (according to the analysis performed, this offers the greatest level of interactivity). The third most common is “Sharing”. “Reviewing” and “Participating” are in fourth and fifth place wellbehind the other three, with a very low frequency. The results of the three geographic areas (Europe, America and Asia/Pacific) show little difference from overall results, although the museums of America obtained a level of interactivity rather better than Europe and Asia/Pacific and are close to an “average” rating, mainly due to good results in the dimension “Collaborating”.

A prominent aspect to mention is the high degree of resources allocated at both ends of the level of interactivity (“Connecting” and “Collaborating”). While this was expected with regard to “Connecting” (present in 75% of the museums), it is surprising to note that the most developed type of interactivity (“Collaborating”) is situated in second place (occurring in almost 60% of museums). However, these results in the “Collaborating” section are consistent with the good results for “interactive resources” in the analysis of the RQ1 (Presentation of Information tools), indicating a growing application of specific resources to generate greater virtual interactivity with visitors. In addition, the low presence of “Reviewing” suggests that museums, although facilitating collaboration, are not likely to seek comments and ratings from virtual visitors.

Based on the Likert scale used, the level of interactivity in these resources is 1.21 points. Although this result is far from being regarded as highly interactive, this variable substantially improved compared to the interactivity of the Tools for Presentation of Information (0.83 points).

These results confirm the statements of the many authors who suggest that organizations are gradually improving the interactivity of websites (Heinze & Hu, 2006; McAllister-Spooner, 2009; Guillory & Sundar, 2014) and are consistent with previous research on organizations in general (Capriotti & Moreno, 2007; Park & Reber, 2008; Kim et al., 2010) and specific studies in museums (Marty, 2007; López et al., 2010; Capriotti & Gonzalez-Herrero, 2013).
If we take the two indicators designed to establish the level of interactivity (Tools for Presentation of Information and Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction), we can establish an overall average level (or combined level) of interactivity for each museum, for each of the geographic areas and for the global museum institutions (Fig. 1).
The combined interactivity levels of the museums
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. The combined interactivity levels of the museums.
According to the results observed in Fig. 1, there are very few museums that receive high scores on both indicators and are located at a very high level of interactivity (high/high levels), whilst a third of the museums are located in the worst quadrant for interactivity (low/low levels), with a low score on both indicators which suggests very poor interactivity on their websites.
In addition, the graph also allows us to see that museums obtain better ratings on the indicator of ‘Resources for Virtual Visitor Interaction’, with many entities (about one third) obtaining an average rating and a large number of museums (about 15%) in the high valuation area. In contrast, the indicator for ‘Tools for Presentation of Information’ scores very few museums (less than 10%) with a good or high-level interaction.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Conclusions" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
7. Conclusions
In this study we have analyzed the level of interactivity of leading international museums using an analysis of the resources that they mobilize to present information (expositive, hyper-textual and participative resources) and of their resources for interaction with visitors (based on the dimensions of ‘Connecting’, ‘Sharing’, ‘Reviewing’, ‘Participating’ and ‘Collaborating’). Thus, our research indicates some clear conclusions:

On the one hand, ]]><h target="2" match="part">it is evident that museums rely mostly on traditional forms of reporting (expositive resources), which leads to a low level of interactivity in the use of resources for presentation of information.</h><h target="4" match="part"> The use of tools and methods benefitting from the particular characteristics of the Internet and web 2.0 (participative resources) has a low presence in these websites.</h>

<h target="3" match="part">On the other hand, although the museums made a major use of the least interactive resources to interact with virtual visitors </h><![CDATA[(mainly tools for “Connecting” and “Sharing”), it also seems clear that they are moving in the use of collaborative tools that establish a connection with, and generate engagement for, virtual visitors, especially those that involve active participation of users on the website. However, the very low use of tools related to “Reviewing” also reveals some fear about asking the opinion or evaluation of virtual visitors regarding the organization.

Furthermore, analysis by geographical area shows that the three regions analyzed follow a similar pattern or model of interactivity on their websites (although with some nuances and exceptions), both in the way they present information (with a predominance of expositive resources above participative) and in how they use the tools for interaction with the visitor (the majority use methods related to “connecting” and “collaborating”). ]]><h target="5" match="part">However, it can be noted that the institutions in America are working more with collaborative tools than museums in other regions, and this allows them to obtain better results with regards to their websites interactivity.</h><h target="4" match="part">In short, the overall analysis of the indicators of interactivity allows us to confirm that most museums analyzed have very low level of interactivity, with only a handful of museums that are leveraging the full potential of Web 2.0 to establish dialogue and interaction with virtual visitors.</h><![CDATA[ The application of various resources for 2.0 websites is limited and therefore there is limited interaction and little interest in the opinion and active participation of users.

Finally, we would like to look at the contributions and limitations of this study. The study presents a specific methodology suitable for analyzing the different tools and dimensions of interactivity on the organizations websites, and it was applied to a large number of art museums around the world. From an academic point of view, this work can be used by other researchers in specific cities, regions or countries to analyze these kinds of organizations, and to promote the comparison of results. From a practitioner's perspective, the results of this study can also contribute to identifying some of the strengths and weaknesses of digital communication policies and activities of museums –as well as other types of organizations- and to help in improving their communication management, and to make entities more open and community-oriented. On the other hand, the implementation of that methodology to a specific type of organization such as museums implies the need to test the methodology with other type of entities: private organizations (that is, businesses) and other public institutions (like local, regional or national government departments or agencies), in order to confirm if the results and trends found in museums are being identified in other kinds of organizations.]]>
    </section>

Acknowledgements
This paper is part of the R+D competitive project about “The Digital Communication of the Cultural Heritage of Museums” (CSO2011-25163), granted by the Ministry of Education and Science of Spain.
</publication>