<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="li ying">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 3, June 2016, Pages 271-283</time>
    <title>Seller reputation or product presentation? An empirical investigation from cue utilization perspective</title>
    <author>Qiuzhen Wang.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Xiling Cui.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Liqiang Huang.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Yiling Dai.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacec. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
School of Management, Zhejiang University, 866 Yuhangtang Road, Hangzhou, China
b
Department of Business Administration, Hong Kong Shue Yan University, 10 Wai Tsui Crescent, Hong Kong
c
Department of Social Informatics, Graduate School of Informatics, Kyoto University, Kyoto, Japan
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2015.12.006</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">This study investigates the joint effects of seller reputation and product presentation on perceived product quality.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">The way of cues utilization in customer's product quality assessment is contingent on the product involvement.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">The effect of product presentation on product evaluation is weakened by seller reputation under low-involvement situations.</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">High rich product presentation can capture more attention and the effect is also contingent on the level of product involvement.</highlight>
Abstract
    <abstract>This study examines the interaction effects of two types of cues in different scopes (i.e., seller reputation as a high-scope cue and product presentation as a low-scope cue) on consumer product quality evaluation, under different involvement situations.<h target="2" match="part">Drawing on the cue utilization theory and involvement-related literature, we propose that cues used in people's decision making processes are contingent on product involvement.</h>  Through the conduction of behavioral experiments with eye-tracking technology,<h target="1" match="part"> the findings show that, under high-involvement situations, both seller reputation and product presentation significantly and independently influence product quality evaluation while their interaction effect does not.</h> <h target="3" match="part">While under low-involvement situations, seller reputation significantly influences the product evaluation and moderates the effect of product presentation on consumer product quality evaluation. The effect of product presentation on product evaluation is weakened by seller reputation.</h> The findings, to some extent, are reinforced by the eye-tracking data through the trace and analysis of fixation count and fixation time. Theoretical and practical implications are discussed.</abstract>
Keywords
    <keywords>Product presentation</keywords>
    <keywords>Seller reputation</keywords>
    <keywords>Perceived product quality</keywords>
    <keywords>Product involvement</keywords>
    <keywords>Eye-tracking</keywords>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
With the rapid development of electronic commerce, online sellers have been facing increasingly fierce competition in order to persuade potential consumers. Differentiating from traditional offline markets like Wal-Mart where consumers can touch and try out a product before purchase, it is relatively difficult for an online seller to provide such types of special service to consumers (Haubl & Trifts, 2000). In the online environment, even if two physical products are absolutely the same, they can be perceived as being largely different when they are presented with varying richness or sold by sellers with distinct reputation levels. Therefore, online sellers have to resort to online information cues to increase consumers’ perception of the product quality. This interesting research topic attracts significant attention from both researchers and practitioners.
Two typical types of information prominently available to potential consumers are user-generated content (Ghose, 2009; Goes, Lin, & Au Yeung, 2014) and seller-generated information (Bickart & Schindler, 2001; Goh, Heng, & Lin, 2013). User-generated content refers to evaluations, opinions, and suggestions that come from other users based on their own purchasing or using experience; while seller-generated information typically refers to the information that comes from the seller, which includes the product description information, product promotion advertising, and so forth. Two main manifestations of these kinds of information that are relevant to our study are product presentation (seller-generated information) and seller reputation (user-generated information). In this study, we focus on examining the effects of these two types of information for the following reasons.
First, although either the user-generated content or seller-generated information has been widely investigated in the extant literature and a series of interesting findings has been uncovered in relation to their significant roles in influencing consumers’ judgment and decision making (e.g., Dellarocas, 2006; Kuan, Hui, Prasarnphanich, & Lai, 2015; Kwark, Chen, & Raghunathan, 2014; Oestreicher-Singer & Zalmanson, 2013), little is understood regarding whether these two types of information can have an interactive impact. The examination of whether these two types of information can be interactive in influencing consumers’ evaluation is especially imperative and essential. Second, according to the cue utilization theory (Rao & Monroe, 1988; Slovic & Lichtenstein, 1971), seller reputation and product presentation are typically conceptualized as high versus low-scope cues. However, extant empirical studies with respect to this theory imply some inconsistent findings. Some studies have suggested that a high-scope cue can either facilitate or inhibit a low-scope cue by changing the latter’s diagnosticity (Akdeniz, Calantone, & Voorhees, 2013; Miyazaki, Grewal, & Goodstein, 2005; Purohit & Srivastava, 2001); while others reveal that, when faced with multiple cues, individuals rely more on the high-scope cue to make decisions, and the influence of other cues is attenuated (Hu, Wu, Wu, & Zhang, 2010; Utz, Kerkhof, & van den Bos, 2011). Therefore, the reconsideration of the ways in which high- versus low-scope information can have an impact in this specific research context is valuable. Third, as suggested by the scholars like Snape and Redman (2010) and Salvato and Rerup (2011), the consideration of factors on different levels and their related relationships would make research interesting. Therefore, in our study, we take both the seller level information (i.e., seller reputation) and the product level information (i.e., product presentation) into consideration and seek to explore the potential interactive effects of these factors on different levels. Fourth, past studies have revealed that different types of information would be biasedly used by consumers in judgment or decision making when they are in different involvement levels (e.g., Chaiken & Maheswaran, 1994; Sussman & Siegal, 2003), while research into whether the involvement have an impact on consumers in processing high- versus low-scope information cues remains overlooked. This also leads us to explore the potential impact of consumer involvement in influencing the processing of high- and low-scope information cues.
This study seeks to answer the following question: can product presentation and seller reputation be interactive in influencing consumers’ evaluations of product quality, under the conditions of high- versus low-involvement? ]]><h target="3" match="part">Based on the cue utilization theory and the involvement-related literature, we propose that under different involvement situations, seller reputation can differently moderate the effect of product presentation on product quality evaluations.</h> <![CDATA[Through the conduction of an eye-tracking experiment, the findings of this study greatly contribute to the current literature in the following ways. First, this study, as an initial attempt, explores whether product presentation and seller reputation, as seller-generated and user-generated information cues, can be interactive in influencing consumers’ product quality evaluation, thus extending the current understanding on their independent effect (e.g., Jiang & Benbasat, 2007). Second, through the revisiting of the cue utilization theory which previously emphasized examining the ways in which high versus low-scopes work interactively (Akdeniz et al., 2013; Miyazaki et al., 2005; Purohit & Srivastava, 2001), the findings of this study extend current understanding from a new perspective that consumers' different involvement in information processing can be an important factor in affecting their utilization of information cues. In addition, this research, to some extent, reconciles the previously inconsistent findings regarding the effects of high and low-scope information on people’s evaluations, thus extending the theoretical boundary. Third, unlike single self-report method traditionally used in e-business studies, this study also employs the eye-tracking method to provide unobtrusive and objective measures to explore the effects of these two types of information cues (i.e., seller reputation and product presentation) on consumers’ attention, which provides additional evidences with both the objective and subjective data.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Theoretical background and hypotheses" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Theoretical background and hypotheses
2.1. Online product presentation and seller reputation
In online markets where products cannot be directly observed and physically examined, consumers generally experience a high degree of uncertainty, and it is more difficult for them to make inferences about product quality (Pavlou, Liang, & Xue, 2007). Thus, consumers are more likely to apply information cues to assess product quality in online environments (Wells, Valacich, & Hess, 2011). Two types of information cue, that is: product presentation (one reflection of seller-generated information); and seller reputation (one manifestation of user-generated content), are largely attracting researchers' attention, and have been recognized as having a great impact on customer decision making (Gregg & Walczak, 2008; Park, Lennon, & Stoel, 2005; Yoo & Kim, 2014).
Scholars have typically conceptualized product presentation as a specific communication media which is used to communicate with potential customers and disseminate relevant information to them (Walter, Ortbach, & Niehaves, 2015). According to the media richness theory (Daft & Lengel, 1986), media with different levels of richness have differing impacts on consumers in terms of communication effectiveness. Prior research has demonstrated that the presentation richness of online product demonstrations can lead to better product understanding (Jiang & Benbasat, 2007) and reduce the perception of product quality uncertainty (Dimoka, Hong, & Pavlou, 2012; Mavlanova & Benbunan-Fich, 2010). Since the multimedia format is still in the early stages of development and it is not overly useful in enhancing the diagnosticity of product descriptions (Dimoka et al., 2012), this research will focus on two types of product presentation: textual description, and pictures with text description, which have different information richness. Prior research has shown that pictures are more informative than text (Dimoka et al., 2012; Ottaway, Bruneau, & Evans, 2003) and can be more reliable for assessing product quality (Bone & France, 2001).
Due to the uncertainty and risk of online transactions, seller reputation is considered as an important factor signaling unobservable product quality to consumers and influencing buyer decisions (Gregg & Walczak, 2008; Wu, Huang, & Fu, 2011). Most e-commerce websites have set up a reputation mechanism that allows buyers to rate the seller and apply this feedback information from buyers to establish seller reputation. For example, the feedback mechanism of Taobao.com1 is the primary means through which transactions are facilitated among strangers over the Internet. The information retrieved from this kind of reputation system helps buyers to understand prospective sellers’ trustworthiness and can enhance conviction in conducting online transactions (Wu et al., 2011). This seller reputation cue is always displayed at prominent locations of a retail website. Past research into online transactions has consistently demonstrated that the seller’s reputation can positively impact the buyer’s willingness to pay (McDonald & Slawson, 2002; Melnik & Alm, 2005), decrease buyers’ perceived risk, and increase their favorable attitude toward the website.
Although product presentation and seller reputation have received significant academic attention, the role of these two cues with different source-generated has largely been examined in isolation in previous research. The joint effects between them on product quality perception have rarely been discussed. However, understanding how these cues simultaneously affect quality perceptions is of increasing importance as consumers usually process one product cue in relation to another (Akdeniz et al., 2013). In addition, based on previous advocates who suggest that consumers in different levels of involvement would process information differently, we further consider whether the interactive effects of product presentation and seller reputation on product quality evaluation would be impacted by consumers’ involvement.
2.2. Cue utilization theory
Cue utilization theory holds that a product provides a series of cues, and that consumers judge the quality of the product based on these cues (Cox, 1967; Olson, 1972). The theory suggests that the extent to which a specific cue is utilized in assessing quality varies with its diagnosticity, and the availability of other cues (Purohit & Srivastava, 2001; Slovic & Lichtenstein, 1971). Past research categorized product cues as high- and low-scope according to their diagnosticity (Gidron, Koehler, & Tversky, 1993). High-scope cues are generally established over time, and are more credible and reliable. In contrast, low-scope cues can be easily manipulated, and are perceived to be ambiguous in giving indications of quality. Studies have suggested that a high-scope cue can either facilitate or inhibit a low-scope cue by changing the latter’s diagnosticity. To be specific, positive or negative high-scope cues transmit over their corresponding implications to the low-scope ones, making them more or less diagnostic (Purohit & Srivastava, 2001).
The notion that what types of cues can be used in decision making has been reinforced by a large quantity of empirical studies. For example, Purohit and Srivastava (2001) found that product warranty (a low-scope cue) was used in product quality judgments only when the valence of manufacturer reputation or retailer reputation (high-scope cues) was positive. Similarly, Miyazaki et al. (2005) demonstrated that higher price (a low-scope cue) leads to higher perceived quality when brand name (a high-scope cue) is strong. A recent study examining the effect of brand reputation and price on consumers’ product quality perception also showed that a positive high-scope cue (i.e., brand reputation) would reinforce the diagnosticity of a less diagnostic quality cue (i.e., price) (Akdeniz et al., 2013).
However, other research suggests that when faced with multiple cues, individuals rely more on the high-scope cue to make decisions, and the influence of other cues is attenuated (Hu et al., 2010; Utz et al., 2011). For example, Hu et al. (2010) found attenuating rather than synergistic interaction effects between privacy and security assurance functions as well as between privacy and transaction-integrity assurance functions. In other words, either function's effect on enhancing consumers' initial trust is weakened by the presence of privacy assurance functions. Further research also suggests that various information cues are not combined in a simple additive manner, and the effects of other relatively less diagnostic cues (e.g., assurance seals, store reputation) will not be significant when combined with consumer review (Utz et al., 2011).
In the present study, two significant manifestations (i.e., seller reputation and product presentation) have typically been conceptualized as high-scope and low-scope cues. In detail, seller reputation is a user-generated information cue that comes from other buyers based on their own purchasing or using experience. Reputation evolves over time and considerable investment is required to establish a positive valence (Purohit & Srivastava, 2001). Thus, the stable and credible nature of seller reputation makes it highly diagnostic and, consequently, a high-scope cue. On the other hand, product presentation is a seller-generated information cue that comes from the seller itself. It can be relatively easily and inexpensively manipulated by e-retailers (Mavlanova & Benbunan-Fich, 2010) and thus is generally viewed as a low-scope cue.
As indicated in the literature above, there has not been a clear understanding of the joint effects of high-scope and low-scope cues, and studies have generated inconsistent results. Previous research has neglected to examine the ways that varied cues interact with each other when the focal product is either highly or loosely involved with consumers. ]]><h target="1" match="part">This research tries to investigate the joint effect of seller reputation and product presentation, which are of different information diagnosticity, under the consideration of different product involvement.</h><![CDATA[

2.3. Product involvement
In consumer behavior research, involvement plays an important role in explaining customer decision making and responses to advertising and products (Hong, 2015; Wang & Doong, 2010). Involvement is defined as the individual’s perceived relevance of extrinsic events/objects based on inherent needs, values, and interests (Zaichkowsky, 1985). An extrinsic event/object could be a product, an advertisement, or purchase behavior. Purchase involvement can be seen as the relevance of the purchasing activities to the individual (Slama & Tashchian, 1985). Different from purchasing involvement, product involvement reflects the perceived relevance of the product category to the individual on an ongoing basis, which is independent of situational influences (Quester & Lim, 2003). Similarly, some researchers divided the construct of involvement into two distinct types: situational involvement and enduring involvement (Houston & Rothschild, 1978; Richins & Bloch, 1986). Situational Involvement reflects product involvement that occurs only in specific situations, such as a purchase; while enduring Involvement represents an ongoing concern with a product that transcends situational influences. This study is concerned with enduring product involvement, a more permanent and consumer-based construct.
Previous studies have shown that the level of involvement determines the depth, complexity, and extensiveness of cognitive and behavioral processing during consumers’ decision making (Andrews, Durvasula, & Akhter, 1990; Petty, Cacioppo, & Schumann, 1983). Consumers are more eager to obtain product information on high-involvement products because such products require more cognitive-response mental activities and more complex decision-making processes. In contrast, consumers are likely to pay less attention to product information and engage in less encoding in the decision-making process when considering the purchase of a low-involvement product (Andrews et al., 1990). Previous research suggests that people have different ways of processing, even when faced with the same information (Petty & Cacioppo, 1986). People may engage in heuristic processing, relying primarily on easy-to-process cues (a peripheral or heuristic cue) to form evaluations when the product involvement is low, while requiring more elaborate information cues to make a systematic evaluation when the product involvement is high (Aaker & Sengupta, 2000; Maheswaran & Chaiken, 1991).
In the current study, the focused cues are online product presentation and seller reputation. Based on cue utilization theory and previous research into these two cues, each could play an important role in product quality perception, regardless of whether the product involvement is high or low. However, their interaction effects would be diverse under different conditions of product involvement. Seller reputation (exhibited as numbers and scores), is easier to process and thus can be viewed as a peripheral or heuristic cue, while product presentation needs more time to analyze. At the same time, seller reputation is generally viewed as a high-scope cue. Therefore, when facing a low-involvement product, consumers’ motivation to process the complex product information is likely to decrease and they are more reliant on the easy and credible seller reputation information. Therefore, we conjecture that the effect of product presentation can be attenuated when seller reputation is high under conditions of low-involvement.

When faced with a high-involvement product, consumers may exercise greater care in their information processing, relying on more of the information cues presented on the website in their assessment of the product. Both high-scope cues and low-scope cues will come into play and be utilized to form product evaluation. Because the product is described by the seller, seller reputation is expected to affect the diagnosticity of the product presentation (Dimoka et al., 2012). Previous studies have demonstrated that positive or negative high-scope cues transmit their corresponding implications to the low-scope ones, making them more or less diagnostic (Miyazaki et al., 2005; Purohit & Srivastava, 2001). We conjecture that the positive effect of high-rich product presentation (low-scope cue) can be reinforced when seller reputation (high-scope cue) is high. Therefore, we posit the following hypotheses:
H1

Product presentation richness positively affects perceived product quality under both (a) high and (b) low product involvement.

H2

Seller reputation positively affects perceived product quality under both (a) high and (b) low product involvement.

H3

Seller reputation plays a positive moderating role between product presentation richness and perceived product quality under high product involvement.

H4

Seller reputation plays a negative moderating role between product presentation richness and perceived product quality under low product involvement.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Research methodology" category="methods">
        <![CDATA[
3. Research methodology
3.1. Pretest 1- product involvement confirmation
The objective of this pretest was to confirm which product we would use in the experiment according to the theory suggested above. Specifically, the theory implies that products can be different in eliciting consumers’ involvement in information processing (Wang & Doong, 2010). In our pretest, we listed a series of products to check which ones required high-level involvement and which required low-level involvement. In detail, we recruited 20 students to attend this test. The students were asked to evaluate seven products, (i.e., laptop computer, mobile phone, electronic dictionary, MP4 player, flash disk, digital camera and hair dryer) on a 9-item measure of perceived product involvement (please refer to Table 1) using 7-point Likert-type scale. The results showed that the laptop received the highest involvement score (mean = 6.05), and the electronic dictionary the lowest (mean = 3.46). The paired samples test indicated significant difference between these two products (t = 8.061, p < .001). Thus, the laptop and electronic dictionary were chosen to be experimental products as representative of high-involvement and low-involvement products, respectively.
Table 1. Measurement items of the constructs.
Construct	Measurement items	Source
Product involvement (PI)	PI1: To me, this product is important.	Zaichkowsky (1994)
PI2: To me, this product is interesting.
PI3: To me, this product is relevant.
PI4: To me, this product is exciting.
PI5: To me, this product means a lot to me.
PI6: To me, this product is appealing.
PI7: To me, this product is valuable.
PI8: To me, this product is needed.
PI9: To me, this product is involving.
Product presentation richness (PPR)	PPR1: The product information is sufficiently detailed.	Gregg & Walczak (2008); Mavlanova & Benbunan-Fich (2010)
PPR2: The product information is visually pleasing.
PPR3: The product information is well organized.
Perceived product quality (PPQ)	PPQ1: I perceive the product offered at this website to be durable.	Wells et al. (2011); Teas & Agarwal (2000)
PPQ2: I perceive the product offered at this website to be well crafted.
PPQ3: I perceive the product offered at this website to be of high quality.
PPQ4: I feel safe to buy the product through this website.
3.2. Pretest 2–product presentation confirmation
As explained above, we theorize the ways that product presentations differ in richness according to the suggestions of richness theory. Before conducting the main experiment, we conducted a pretest to check whether the operationalization of the product presentation was valid. Theoretically, we know that pictures offer much richer information for consumers to evaluate a product. Therefore, in both this pretest and the main experiment, we designed two scenarios to represent two levels of richness. In particular, in the low-level richness situation, we presented the product using text-only; while in the high-level richness situation, we presented the product using text and picture. We did not use picture-only because it is essential for consumers to understand the product performance, and the picture-only scenario may lead to unfavorable misunderstandings.

For this pretest, we recruited ten students from the same sample pool as the main experiment. In this pretest, we used with-in design for the two presentation scenarios (see Appendix A for screenshots), where the students were asked to evaluate the two presentations with different levels of richness presented in random sequences. After each scenario, the students were asked to rate the extent of which the product information is sufficiently detailed, visually pleasant and well organized (please refer to Table 1 for the detailed measurement items). Before we compared the differences of these two types of presentation, we measured the validity. The factor loading suggested good validity (loading coefficients were 0.868, 0.940 and 0.947). The t-test suggests that these two types of presentation typically bring different levels of richness perception to subjects (meanhigh = 4.667; meanlow = 3.133; t = 2.453; p < .05).
3.3. Main experiment
3.3.1. Experimental design
A two- (product presentation: high rich vs. low rich) by-two (seller reputation: high reputation vs. low reputation) full factorial experiment, considering two situations of product involvement, was conducted to test the hypotheses. We chose to conduct the experiment in a controlled lab environment in order to avoid the possible biased interruptions.

3.3.1.1. Independent variables
Three independent variables were used in our experiment. We examined the joint effects of product presentation and seller reputation, under low and high levels of involvement. As shown in Pretest 1, we used the laptop and electronic dictionary as experimental products to represent high and low-involvement products. With respect to the operationalization of product presentation, as indicated in Pretest 2, we used the description with text-only to represent low richness presentation, and the presentation with both text and picture to represent high level richness presentation. With regard to the seller reputation, this was classified as high reputation or low reputation based on the reputation system of Taobao.com, which indicates seller reputation by the number of historic transactions a seller has made and their relative credit score compared with other sellers in the same industry.

3.3.1.2. Dependent variables
The main focus of this study is consumers’ evaluation of the product quality. Previous studies have widely and consistently shown the significant role of perceived product quality in influencing consumers’ purchase decision making (Sjolander, 1992; Teas & Agarwal, 2000). The perceived product quality was measured by consumers’ perception of the durability, craft, quality, and purchase safety on the products offered by the website (please refer to Table 1 for the detailed measurement items).
3.3.2. Experiment apparatus
The eye-tracking device used in this research was the iView X Hi-Speed eye-tracker produced by German company SMI. Its sampling rate is 500 HZ. The tracker uses an infrared camera to capture a video picture of the participant’s left eye. The signal exported from the camera is first coded using the MPEG coding rule, and then entered into a computer for the collection and analysis of picture data, thus allowing the moving distance, speed, pupil diameter and fixation position of the eye to be calculated in real time. The experimental webpages were presented on a 19-inch monitor with a resolution of 1024 × 768 pixels. The distance between monitor and participant was approximately 60 cm. The eye-tracking data from website browsing were recorded automatically by the eye-tracker, and then analyzed using BeGaze 2.5 software.
3.3.3. Participants
Eighty Chinese college students were recruited from an online discussion forum affiliated with a major university in southern China. College students are the appropriate participants for this experiment as this group represents the majority of Chinese Internet users at present.2 Participants were screened to ensure normal or corrected to normal vision. After screening out missing data, 75 valid samples were retained for further data analysis. The participants were randomly assigned to each of the four treatment conditions. Among the 75 participants, 49 were female and 26 were male, and 66.7% were undergraduates. Their average age was 22.57 years. All of the participants had prior online shopping experience, and 93.1% engaged in online shopping at least once or twice a month. Participants were paid RMB30 (around $5) for their participation.
3.3.4. Experiment procedures
We firstly conducted a pilot experiment with four participants to test the experimental process and appropriateness of the experimental setting. With no concerns raised from the pilot study, the formal experiment was conducted in a sound-proof, dimly lit laboratory. The participants read and signed an informed consent form before taking part in the eye-tracking experiment. They were then given the following instructions: “Imagine that you want to buy a laptop (Lenovo Z470A-ITH(T)) and an electronic dictionary (GGV E638) for study and entertainment purposes. You have enough money to buy both. You will now browse two webpages (presented in random order) with information on each product. Click “Exit” each time you finish browsing a page, and then fill in the paper questionnaire.” Participants were calibrated with the eye-tracker, which took about three minutes on average, before browsing the webpages. After calibration, they browsed two webpages with the same level of product presentation and seller reputation, but different product types for the high-involvement and low-involvement conditions. The two pages were presented in a random order to avoid latent order effects. Participants’ eye movement data were automatically recorded by the eye tracker. After viewing each page, subjects were asked to answer some questions. After the experiment, they were sincerely thanked.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Results" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
4. Results
4.1. Control and manipulation check
Our initial analysis demonstrated that there was no significant difference among treatments in the control variables, including gender (F = 1.195, p = .318), age (F = 2.364, p = .079), education (F = 2.105, p = .108), or shopping experience (F = .517, p = .672), and thus the random assignment of the participants to the four experimental treatments was successful. As there were more female than male participants in the experiment, we compared the dependent variables for the groups using t-tests. There were no significant differences between female and male participants' perceived quality in both the low-involvement condition (tlow = −1.053, plow = .296) and the high–involvement condition (thigh = −1.451, phigh = .151), indicating that the participants’ gender did not affect the dependent variable under investigation. There were no significant correlations between other control variables and the dependent variables. Thus, none of the control variables had an effect on the dependent variables.
With regard to the check of product presentation, we used the same measurement of Pretest 2 to check the manipulation. The results show that a significant difference exists (t = 3.939, p < .001) between the high level richness presentation (mean = 4.040; SD = 1.336) and low level richness presentation (mean = 3.209; SD = 1.247). As regard to seller reputation, we used items from previous studies, such as Money and Hillenbrand (2006), which were: (1) this seller wants to be known as one who keeps promises and commitments; and (2) I trust this seller keeps my best interest in mind. The results show that there is significant difference (t = 5.670; p < .001) between high (mean = 5.023; SD = 0.925) and low (mean = 4.006; SD = 1.199) levels of reputations. The independent-sample t-test results for product involvement also confirmed the validity of its manipulation, with a significant difference (t = 10.583, p < .001) in product involvement found between the laptop (mean = 5.74, SD = 1.13) and electronic dictionary (mean = 3.60, SD = 1.33).
4.2. Hypotheses testing
The exploratory factor analysis results of the multiple-item construct (i.e., perceived product quality) demonstrated adequate reliability and construct validity. The Cronbach’s alpha of this variable is 0.929. The factor loadings show the high convergent validity (loading coefficients are 0.902, 0.906, 0.944, 0.882). The analyses of the dependent measures were conducted using SPSS 16.0 for Windows at the five percent significant level. Table 2 shows the descriptive analysis results. We ran ANOVA to analyze our data. We analyzed the joint effect of product presentation and seller reputation on perceived product quality under each of the high and low-involvement situations. In detail, under the high-involvement situation, the ANOVA analysis shows that both the main effects of product presentation (F = 4.441; p = .039 < .05) and seller reputation (F = 8.706; p = .004 < .05) on product quality evaluations are significant, supporting H1a and H2a, but the interaction effect is not significant (F = .246, p > .1), failing to support H3. ]]><h target="4" match="part">The results show that high rich product presentation and high seller reputation lead to better product quality perception.</h><![CDATA[ Further, our ANOVA analysis under the low level involvement situation suggests the following results: (1) the main effect of product presentation on perceived product quality is marginally significant (F = 3.432; p = .068), marginally supporting H1b; (2) the main effect of seller reputation on perceived product quality is significant (F = 6.152; p < .05), supporting H2b; and (3) the interaction effect of product presentation and seller reputation on perceived product quality is significant (F = 5.001; p < .05), supporting H4. Fig. 1 displays the mean levels of perceived product quality in different treatments under high-involvement and low-involvement conditions.
Table 2. Descriptive statistics of perceived product quality.
Seller reputation	Product presentation
Mean (SD)
Low rich	High rich
High-involvement	Low	3.54 (1.34)	4.33 (1.59)
High	4.58 (1.05)	5.07 (1.03)
Low-involvement	Low	3.09 (1.09)	4.25 (1.38)
High	4.43 (1.23)	4.32 (1.14)
Mean levels of perceived product quality
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Mean levels of perceived product quality.
To further understand the interaction effect under the low-involvement condition, we conducted a simple effect analysis of the product presentation for each level of seller reputation. The LSD test showed that when seller reputation was low, high rich product presentation led to significantly better quality perception (mean difference [high rich vs. low rich] = 1.163, p = .002). However, when seller reputation was high, an increase in the richness of product presentation did not imply better product quality perception (mean difference [high rich vs. low rich] = −.109, p = .801).]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Discussions" category="discussion">
        
5. Discussions
<h target="1" match="part">The findings of our study suggest that, under different levels of product involvement, the joint effects of seller reputation and product presentation on consumers’ evaluation of the product quality differ.Specifically, under the high-involvement situation, both the seller reputation and product presentation can affect product quality evaluations, but the interactive effect does not exist.</h> <![CDATA[ On the other hand, under the low product involvement situation, although the product presentation marginally significantly impacts consumers’ evaluation of the product quality, the seller reputation can significantly and positively affect the product quality evaluation and there is attenuating interaction between seller reputation and product presentation. The findings, although they do not fully match what we predicted, provide interesting knowledge for us to reconsider the previous theoretical predictions.

Under the high-involvement situation, as argued in the theoretical section, people would be more likely to engage in deeper and broader information processing where multiple cues are available (Bhattacherjee & Sanford, 2006; Ho & Bodoff, 2014). According to the theory, and relating to our specific research context, when consumers are evaluating product quality under the high level product involvement situation, low-scope cues, such as product presentation can be an important factor for consideration, in addition to high-scope information cues (seller reputation). This generally supports our main effect hypotheses. With respect to the insignificant finding of the interaction effect, we conjecture that these two types of cues play different roles in influencing consumers’ judgment. In other words, when consumers are considering these two types of cues under the high product involvement situation, both of these two types of cues can be significant in influencing their decision making, while leaving the room in understanding the interaction effect with each other. This is also in line with previous literature in relation to how high-scope and low-scope information cues can be used (e.g., Chaiken & Maheswaran, 1994).
Under the low-involvement situation, consumers would be more likely to use more important, easily accessible and diagnostic information to make a relatively more simple judgment or decision, because consumers, most of the time, are considered cognitive miser (Bargh, 2002; Drolet & Luce, 2004; Ebenbach & Keltner, 1998; Ratneshwar & Chaiken, 1991). Therefore, our findings from the study show that seller reputation (as a high-scope information cue) dominantly influences product quality evaluation and weakens the effect of product presentation (as a low-scope information cue) on product quality evaluation. This is also consistent with the findings of Cheung, Luo, Sia, and Chen (2009), who reveal the interesting principles around why and how peripheral information can be effective in influencing the effect generated by central information.
Further, we were keen to understand how consumers’ cognitive status and information processing would be different varying on involvement situations. Consumers’ information processing for each webpage was reflected in their visual attention. For example, a long fixation time and more fixations on some areas of the webpage infer a deep level of information processing toward that specific area (Pan, Gay, Granka, Feusner, & Newman, 2004). Jiang and Benbasat (2007) also proposed that the way that product presentations capture consumers’ attention of product features would be very important. This is an important reason why we conducted this study using the eye-tracking experiment, rather than the common behavioral study. Previous researchers have widely argued that, although consumers’ responses are one important way to obtain what happens in consumer information processing, they are subjective and may bring potential biases (e.g., Huang, Tan, Ke, & Wei, 2013). The eye-tracking method, as one important way to trace consumers' behavior, can provide another perspective for scholars to understand consumers (Chen & Macredie, 2010; Cian, Krishna, & Elder, 2015). In this study, we defined the detailed product information as an area of interest (AOI) on each webpage. We used the fixation count (the total amount of fixation in that area) and fixation time (the sum of the durations of all fixations in that area) to measure attention capture and engagement in the specific AOI (Pieters & Wedel, 2004; Wedel & Pieters, 2000).
As shown in Tables 3 and 4,]]><h target="4" match="part"> we learn that in both the high and low product level situations, the high rich product presentation can lead to a greater fixation count (the total amount of fixation in that area) and fixation time, which suggest that product presentation is one important factor in capturing consumers' attention in both situations.</h> <![CDATA[This finding is in line with Pieters and Wedel (2004) and Goodrich (2011), who found that pictures are superior to text in capturing attention. However, we found that the effect of product presentation on attention also depends on the level of product involvement.
Table 3. Descriptive statistics of fixation indicators.
Dependent variables	Seller reputation	Mean (SD)
Product information presentation
Low-level	High-level
High-involvement	Fixation counts	Low	118.26 (84.53)	300.00 (169.55)
High	125.27 (63.49)	276.56 (127.08)
Fixation time (s)	Low	29.96 (22.75)	70.19 (42.58)
High	34.89 (21.47)	60.32 (30.87)
Low-involvement	Fixation counts	Low	73.70 (35.10)	179.40 (112.79)
High	83.14 (49.82)	123.50 (33.12)
Fixation time (s)	Low	18.77 (10.37)	41.16 (25.66)
High	22.79 (15.03)	27.52 (7.29)
Table 4. ANOVA analysis results of fixation indicators.
High-involvement	Low-involvement
Fixation counts	Fixation time	Fixation counts	Fixation time
Seller reputation	F = .087
p = .768	F = .119
p = .731	F = 2.174
p = .145	F = 1.595
p = .211
Product information presentation	F = 35.865
p = .000***	F = 21.025
p = .000***	F = 21.491
p = .000***	F = 12.664
p = .001**
Seller reputation* product information presentation	F = .300
p = .586	F = 1.069
p = .305	F = 4.302
p = .042*	F = 5.368
p = .023*
*
p < .05.
**
p < .01.
***
p < .001.
]]><h target="1" match="part"><![CDATA[The results show that the interaction effects of seller reputation and product presentation on fixation count (F = 4.302; p = .042) and fixation time (F = 5.368; p = .023) are significant in low level product involvement situations (Fig. 2 presents the nature of interaction effects), but not significant in high level product involvement circumstances (F = .300, p = .586 for fixation count; and F = 1.069, p = .305 for fixation time).]]></h> <h target="4" match="part">As Fig. 2 and the results of the LSD test reveal, for the low-involvement condition, high rich product presentation can draw more attention to product information when seller reputation is low </h>><![CDATA[(mean difference of fixation counts [high rich vs. low rich] = 105.704, p < .001; mean difference of fixation time [high rich vs. low rich] = 22394.341 ms, p < .001). However, when seller reputation is high, an increase in the richness of product presentation does not imply capturing more attention (mean difference of fixation counts [high rich vs. low rich] = 40.357, p = .096; mean difference of fixation time [high rich vs. low rich] = 4733.108 ms, p = .416). However, for high-involvement products, participants pay more attention to product information for high rich product presentation, regardless of whether seller reputation is high or low. These findings on interaction effects are consistent with the analysis results of behavioral data about product quality perception and provide possible explanations on a physiological level.
Mean levels of Fixation Count and Fixation Time under the Low-involvement…
Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Mean levels of Fixation Count and Fixation Time under the Low-involvement Condition.
5.1. Implications
The findings of this study provide additional knowledge based on our current understanding, as well as practical guidelines for managers.

First, with the rapid development of electronic commerce, the topic that how online information cues (generated by consumers as well as sellers) influence potential consumers has attracted great research attention. Although various interesting findings have been explored from the current studies (Dellarocas, 2006; Kuan et al., 2015; Kwark et al., 2014; Oestreicher-Singer & Zalmanson, 2013), researchers have typically neglected the joint effects caused by user-generated content and seller-generated information cues. This calls for innovative studies in uncovering the important joint effect in online markets because consumers are generally exposed to various cues that seldom operate in isolation. The findings of this study, as one of the initial attempts, uncovered the joint effect of these two types of information in influencing consumers' evaluation on the product quality. The findings of this study thus extend the current understanding regarding the effects of online information cues on consumers.
Second, current empirical studies using cue utilization theory have generated inconsistent findings on the joint effects between high-scope and low-scope cues: some studies found the synergistic interaction effects (Akdeniz et al., 2013; Miyazaki et al., 2005; Purohit & Srivastava, 2001) whereas others found the attenuating interaction effects (Hu et al., 2010; Utz et al., 2011). This study reconciles the previous inconsistent findings by incorporating product involvement when examining consumers’ utilization of high-scope and low-scope information. Product involvement has been regarded as an important factor that influences consumers’ judgment and information processing (e.g., Chaiken & Maheswaran, 1994; Petty & Cacioppo, 1986). The findings of this study provide additional evidence showing that consumers' judgment and decision making are influenced by both high and low-scope cues and their effects are determined by the degree of product involvement the consumers experience, thus, extending the boundary of the cue utilization theory.
Third, it is important to study consumers’ attention in online market research. Rather than merely being a first stage, as is often erroneously assumed, attention is central in the processing of visual stimuli (Lee & Ahn, 2012; Pieters & Wedel, 2007). How product presentations capture consumers’ attention was believed to be very important (Jiang & Benbasat, 2007). However, there has been little research effort directed at exploring the impacts of product presentation and seller reputation on consumers’ attention. ]]><h target="4" match="full">The analysis of eye-tracking data showed that although high rich product presentation can capture more attention, the effect of product presentation on attention is also contingent on the level of product involvement.</h> <![CDATA[These findings are consistent with the results of survey data and provide more insights into consumers' cognitive status and information processing. The analysis of subjective and objective data collected using different methods renders the research results more solid and convincing and, represents an improvement over the single methods traditionally used in e-business studies.
Fourth, according to the findings shown from this study, practitioners should consider how to better spend their investments, especially for new sellers. In reality, it is not easy for new sellers to build very high reputations based on a limited number of transactions, particularly when they compete with reputable sellers. The findings suggest that a seller's strategy for investing in product presentation is contingent upon what types of products they sell. In detail, if sellers focus on high level involvement products, the product presentation is independently important to consumers' evaluation of its products, regardless of whether the seller's reputation is good or poor. Therefore, as sellers, it is important to provide nice product presentations. If sellers focus on low level involvement products, the results show that seller reputation could alleviate the effect of product presentation on product quality evaluation, and product presentation does not independently influence the product quality. In this specific situation, it would be better for sellers to make greater effort into building a better reputation, rather than investing more in the product presentation.

5.2. Limitations and research directions
As with all other studies, this study also has a series of limitations which provide research opportunities for future works. First, we used student samples in this study. Although previous research studies have widely argued that college students constitute a large proportion of online buyers and they have no significant performance differences with broader samples in online information comprehension and judgment (e.g., Huang et al., 2013), broader sample investigation may also bring other potentially interesting findings. Therefore, this would be in line with previous studies which have demonstrated exciting findings, such as Sia et al. (2009), through the consideration of broader samples or even cross-cultural examinations. Second, product presentation can differ from various perspectives. For instance, in Hong, Thong, and Tam (2004) study, the authors uncovered that different presentations of products with list or matrix would be differently evaluated by consumers with the intention of browsing and searching. Although our study, through the lens of information richness, reveals interesting findings, it is still unclear whether different richness presentation would be different under the list and matrix situations. We expect to see findings from future research regarding this aspect. Third, our findings may also be limited by the products used in the experiment. Based on the products natural differences, prior studies have classically categorized products as search and experience products, and shown that these two types of product would be different in transferring information to consumers in their judgment and decision making (e.g., Huang, Lurie, & Mitra, 2009; Mudambi & Schuff, 2010). However, our study focuses on the search products only, while does not consider the potential differences elicited by experience products. Future studies can also consider using some products other than digital ones to generalize the research findings. We hope researchers could reveal more interesting findings in this regard in future research.]]>
    </section>
    <section name="Conclusions" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
6. Conclusions
This study has examined the joint effects of online product presentation (low-scope cue) and seller reputation (high-scope cue) in influencing consumers' product quality evaluations.]]><h target="2" match="part"> Drawing on the cue utilization theory and involvement-related literature, our analysis suggests that the roles of these two types of cues in influencing consumers' judgment are dependent on consumer product involvement. </h>Specifically, under the high-involvement situation, both the seller reputation and the product presentation can positively affect product quality evaluations, but the interactive effect does not exist. While under low-involvement situations, seller reputation significantly and positively influences the product evaluation and moderates the effect of product presentation on consumer product quality evaluation. <h target="3" match="part">The effect of product presentation on product evaluation is weakened by seller reputation. The findings, to some extent, are reinforced by the eye-tracking data analysis.</h>
    </section>

Acknowledgement
This research was supported by the grants from National Natural Science Foundation of China (No: 71272167, No: 71401154), Ministry of Education of the People's Republic of China (No: 11YJA630130), and Research Grants Council of the Hong Kong Special Administration Region (No: UGC/FDS15/B02/14).
</publication>
