<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="li ying">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 6, Part A, December 2016, Pages 945-962</time>
    <title>Building relationships within corporate SNS accounts through social presence formation</title>
    <author>Sehee Han. </author>Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace <author>Jinyoung Min.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace <author>Heeseok Lee.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacec. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
Information Technology Research Center, Yonsei University, 50 Yonseiro, Seodaemungu, Seoul, 120-749, South Korea
b
School of Business, Chosun University, 309 Pilmundaero, Donggu, Gwangju, 501-759, South Korea
c
Business School, Korea Advanced Institute of Science and Technology, 207-43, Cheongyangri-dong, Dongdaemoon-gu, Seoul, 130-012, South Korea
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.06.004</doi>
Highlights
<highlight id="1">We provide a deeper understanding of how corporate SNS accounts can effectively engage SNS users by focusing on social presence.</highlight>
<highlight id="2">Through an experiment with 809 Twitter users, we find the antecedents of social presence formation in the form and content characteristics of SNS.</highlight>
<highlight id="3">The findings suggest that social presence is formed through machine interactivity, person interactivity, and self-disclosure.</highlight>
<highlight id="4">The findings also suggest that social presence contributes to SNS users⿿ engagement by increasing the usefulness of information and their trust.</highlight>
    <abstract> 
        <![CDATA[
Although many companies have attempted to use SNS to attract and communicate with current and potential customers, these efforts have not always been fruitful. ]]><h target="1" match="part">To provide a deeper understanding of how corporate SNS accounts can effectively engage SNS users, this study examines the social aspects of the corporate SNS context by focusing on social presence.</h> More specifically, <h target="2" match="part">we investigate how social presence is formed within corporate SNS accounts by establishing its antecedents in the form and content characteristics of SNS and how it increases utilitarian values and facilitates relationships between SNS users and companies Through an experiment with 809 Twitter users, .</h><h target="3" match="part">the study finds that social presence is formed through machine interactivity, person interactivity, and self-disclosure</h>; <h target="4" match="part">that greater social presence increases users⿿ perception of the usefulness of information and their trust in the company</h>; and that increases in those utilitarian values contribute to SNS users⿿ positive engagement in relationships with corporate SNS accounts.</abstract>
    <keywords>Corporate SNS account</keywords>
    <keywords>Social presence formation</keywords>
    <keywords>Social presence outcomes</keywords>
    <keywords> Engaging relationships with corporate SNS</keywords>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
The rapid advances in and diffusion of social network sites (SNS) has substantially changed the way people exchange information and develop relationships, including the communication and relationship building between companies and their customers (Hennig-Thurau et al., 2010). SNS users communicate freely about their satisfaction and dissatisfaction with companies on SNS, which they generally perceive as more trustworthy sources of information about products than corporate-sponsored communications transmitted via traditional media (Foux, 2006). Because SNS communications between companies and SNS users are open to public view and diffused rapidly and widely through connected links, particularly through the widespread mobile usage of SNS (Cheng, Liang, & Leung, 2014; Lee et al., 2013), building and managing good relationships with SNS users have become increasingly critical to a business⿿s marketing efforts and sustainability (Hennig-Thurau et al., 2010; Trusov, Bodapati, & Bucklin, 2010). A company⿿s failure to effectively manage such relationships can lead not only to dissatisfaction among specific customers but to a poor reputation among a broader public. For instance, when one unsatisfied customer sent a complaint about lost baggage directly to the followers of the airline company⿿s sponsored tweets, other customers and competitors jumped in to share their own unsatisfactory experiences and created a wave of public resentment toward the company before it could offer an apology (Popken, 2013). In this case, the company⿿s efforts to create positive relationships and word of mouth through SNS ironically became the means of spreading a negative impression. Therefore, operating a corporate SNS account can be in vain or even counterproductive if companies inadequately understand the nature of those relationships and what drives SNS users to voluntarily engage with a corporate SNS account.
Traditionally, companies have conceived of building engaging relationships with consumers in utilitarian terms, such as providing useful information about products (Chien & Moutinho, 2000) and promoting trust (Cyr & Head, 2008). Research taking this perspective has found that customers⿿ expectations of tangible benefits from this engagement drive their satisfaction and continuing relationship with the company (Gronroos, 1990; Shani & Chalasani, 1992). Extending this perspective to SNS, researchers have attributed SNS users⿿ building a relationship with a corporate SNS account to their intention of engaging in communication and receiving information from that company (Group, 2008; Sashi, 2012).
However, as online communications have progressively provided users with a more personalized environment (Cenfetelli, Benbasat, & Al-Natour, 2005), researchers have suggested that companies should focus not only on the utilitarian value of such communications but also on enriching their social ambience through interactive marketing (Maru File, Judd, & Prince, 1992). Such researchers suggest that satisfying relationships through online marketing efforts depend on social as well as economic satisfaction (Dabholkar, van Dolen, & de Ruyter, 2009), which is produced by offering social experiences and interactions that can feel ⿿human⿿ (e.g., Kelleher & Miller, 2006; Kwon & Sung, 2011; Nambisan & Watt, 2011; Park & Lee, 2013).
The importance of a social ambience appears a natural aspect of SNS, which are founded on and function through social interactions. The relationship building starts with such social actions as ⿿making friends⿿ with or choosing to ⿿follow⿿ corporate SNS accounts. Communication within these relationships takes such forms as ⿿dialogue⿿ through direct speaking (2013) and eliciting users⿿ personal stories (Kwak, Choi, & Lee, 2014). If such communication is continuous and repetitive, it can even become intimate (Roberts & Dunbar, 2011). The relationships formed in the SNS context thus are not merely one-directional and utility-driven but also interactive, multi-directional, and socially driven. Therefore,]]><h target="1" match="part"><![CDATA[ it is important for companies to understand how the characteristics of SNS communications facilitate these social aspects of their corporate SNS accounts and how those characteristics influence the relationships SNS users build with them.]]></h> <![CDATA[To advance such understanding, we focus on social presence, which has been shown to play an important role in providing satisfying interactions and relationship building in computer-mediated communication (Han, Min, & Lee, 2015; Kreijns, Kirschner, & Jochems, 2003; Rovai, 2000).In an SNS context, social presence has also been found to be a significant antecedent of increased interaction (Dunlap & Lowenthal, 2009) and gratification of social connection needs (Han et al., 2015). Although their terms may differ, relationship marketing researchers also consider social presence a key factor in building relationships with consumers (Dabholkar et al., 2009; Kelleher & Miller, 2006; Kwon & Sung, 2011; Park & Lee, 2013). Despite this agreement, little is yet known about how social presence can be formed through the communication characteristics enabled by SNS. We thus adopt social presence theory (Short, Williams, & Christie, 1976) and Lombard and Ditton⿿s (1997) integrated view of social presence formation to examine the effect of those communication characteristics on the formation of social presence. Such an approach, we argue, can help us better understand how well-managed communications leveraged by SNS characteristics can lead to engaging and sustained relationships between corporate SNS accounts and SNS users.
To that end, this study attempts to answer two main questions: (1) how social presence within corporate SNS accounts is formed by the communication characteristics enabled by the SNS environment, and (2) how social presence affects other utilitarian values and facilitates SNS users⿿ relationships with corporate SNS accounts. To answer the first of these questions, ]]><h target="2" match="part">we conducted an experiment with 809 Twitter users to investigate how form- and content-based factors may create social presence in corporate SNS account communications.</h><![CDATA[ To address the second, we conducted a cross-sectional survey with those participants to examine how social presence affects trust and the perceived usefulness of the information acquisition and how both may induce SNS users to develop relationships with corporate SNS accounts.

In the following section, we provide the theoretical background of our research, describing what is currently known about social presence formation and outcomes and the current knowledge gap in that literature. In the third section, we conceptualize our research model and propose hypotheses. In the fourth and fifth sections, we explain the methods used in our research and present the results of our empirical tests. The sixth and seventh sections discuss the theoretical and practical implications of these findings. The eighth section identifies the limitations of the study and makes suggestions for future study, followed by a conclusion.]]></section>
    <section name="Theoretical background: social presence theory" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Theoretical background: social presence theory
Social presence is generally defined as ⿿the degree of salience of the other person in the interaction and the consequent salience of the interpersonal relationships⿿ (Short et al., 1976, p. 65). In the context of computer-mediated interaction, Walther (1992) defined social presence as ⿿the degree to which users can feel others⿿ presence in the result of interpersonal interactions during the communication process⿿ (p. 54). The central premise of social presence theory is that social presence is a quality inherent in a communication medium. As seen from this perspective, social presence is related to a medium⿿s capacity to transmit socially rich information, such as communicators⿿ facial expressions and non-verbal social cues, which can be enhanced by such attributes of a medium as cue multiplicity, feedback immediacy, and message personalization (Daft & Lengel, 1984). According to this theory, social presence in mediated communication leads people to experience that communication as non-mediated and personalized and is operationalized in terms of how sociable, warm, sensitive, and personal users perceive the communication medium to be (Short et al., 1976).
2.1. Social presence formation
Given its significant impact, how to enhance social presence has also received much scholarly attention. Yet only a few studies have investigated social presence formation in SNS, let alone in corporate SNS. Extending our literature search to include research on social technology, which shares the social characteristics of SNS, we identified three categories of antecedents of social presence, as shown in Table 1: user characteristics, interaction characteristics, and medium characteristics. The identified research in the first of these categories, user characteristics, has found that individual users feel social presence differently depending on such inherent personal characteristics as personality, motivations, and usage experience. Research in the second category has focused on interactions between people and has concluded that social interactions supported by technology increase social presence. Research in characteristics of the medium itself, the third category, has focused on the specific environmental conditions in which social presence can be formed.
Table 1. Operational definitions of constructs.
Research	Found Antecedents	context	Category
User Characteristics
Lim, Hwang, Kim, and Biocca (2015)	Functional engagement, Communication engagement	Social TV (real-time backchannel communication on SNS during a live television broadcast)	Engagement
Siriaraya and Ang (2012)	Prior experience with text messaging in older users and prior experience with 3D games in younger users	3D virtual world as a tool for social interaction	Prior Experience
Ogara, Koh, and Prybutok (2014)	Prior experience with mobile instant messaging	Mobile instant messaging
Lee and Shin (2012)	Individual⿿s interpersonal orientation	SNS	Personalities
Tang, Wang, and Norman (2013)	Extroversion of personalities	Group communication (MS NetMeeting)
Lee, Yejean Park, Kim, Kim, and Moon (2011)	Self-expression motivation	music sharing on SNS	Motivations
Hwang and Lim (2015)	Information and excitement motives	Social TV
Park, Shin, and Ju (2015)	Social surveillance and self-surveillance tendencies	SNS	Usage tendency
Interaction Characteristics
Chen, Ho, and Wu (2014)	Social influence of others connected on SNS	SNS	Social influence of others
Ogara et al. (2014)	Perceived social influence in communication	Mobile instant messaging
Cheikh-Ammar and Barki (2014)	The amount of feedback received from and provided to others	SNS	Feedback to and from others
Medium Characteristics
Choi, Kim, and Qu (2015)	Perceived ubiquitous connectivity of infrastructure	smartphone-based SNS	Infrastructure characteristics
Ogara et al. (2014)	Medium capability to enable a variety of signs, visual cues, and non-word utterances	Mobile instant messaging	Medium capabilities
Tang et al. (2013)	Positive Effect
Symbol sets: allowing communicators to use natural symbol sets
Rehearsability: enabling senders to rehearse and craft messages before sending
Negative Effect
Parallelism: assisting users to transmit messages simultaneously
Reprocessability: allowing messages to be reexamined	Group communication (MS NetMeeting)
Although these studies have advanced our understanding of social presence formation from their given perspectives, they do not provide specific information about how corporate SNS accounts can form social presence in their SNS-enabled communications. The research in the first category has not addressed the ways in which the medium shapes not only communication but also individual experiences and preferences. The studies in the second category have not examined the particular characteristics of communication enabled by a given medium. And those in the third category have not considered the role played by users in constructing the communication enabled by a medium.

According to Walther (1996), online communications are shaped by the channel in which the communication takes place, the senders and receivers of the communication, and the feedback conveyed between senders and receivers through that channel. We therefore propose an integrated approach to understanding social presence formation that considers the intertwined nature of the elements that together construct online communication. Because all those elements are manifested through a medium, we also argue that such an approach should specifically articulate how the given medium materializes those elements to form social presence.
In their explanation of how social presence is manifested, Lombard and Ditton (1997) suggest that it is determined by the form features and content features of a given medium and by the characteristics of medium users. Form features are the structural characteristics of media that serve to encourage or discourage social presence, and content features are the characteristics of the content delivered within the form or structure of media that do the same. Examples of form features that generate presence are such visual display characteristics as image quality, image size, and viewing distance; aural presentation characteristics; and interactivity (Heeter, 1992; Steuer, 1992). The most studied form features are those that enhance sensory richness or vividness, such as a medium⿿s number of sensory outputs, visual display characteristics, and interactivity (e.g., Heeter, 1992; Steuer, Biocca, & Levy, 1995; Zeltzer, 1992). This focus on form features as determinants of social presence implies that how well a medium engenders social presence depends on how well it offers real-world-like experiences by imitating the stimuli that exist in one⿿s surroundings and the user⿿s ability to influence these surroundings. Although content features also attempt to imitate real-world experiences, studies of content features have focused on the content that is delivered within the form of a medium and how socially realistic, authentic, and plausible those are (Barker, 1988; Rice, 1992; Short et al., 1976). Lastly, given that form and content features may generate social presence for one media user but not another, such media user characteristics as prior knowledge of and experience with the medium and the need to overcome loneliness can also serve as determinants of social presence (Lombard & Ditton, 1997).
Lombard and Ditton⿿s (1997) framework is consistent with Walther⿿s (1996) basic elements of computer-mediated communication: form features are the specific materialization of a channel element, content features represent the form of feedback that can be conveyed through the particular channel, and medium user characteristics reflect the characteristics of senders and receivers. Therefore, we adopt this framework to help us articulate specific SNS features that can form social presence within a corporate SNS account. Given that online social presence is a quality inherent in a communication medium and that the aim of this study is to examine how corporate SNS accounts can take advantage of SNS characteristics to form social presence, we focus on form and content features rather than on how individual users experience social presence differently. Using Walther⿿s (1996) terms, we focus on senders rather than receivers. We therefore examine how senders (corporations) manifest themselves through feedback (content features) enabled by channels (form features). This approach is also in line with recent studies that expand the sources of social presence from human beings to include IT artifacts (e.g., Choi, Lee, & Kim, 2011; Kumar & Benbasat, 2006; Qiu & Benbasat, 2009). We discuss how this framework is specifically represented in the SNS context in more detail in Section 3.
2.2. Social presence outcomes: affective vs. cognitive
Social presence is known to shape people⿿s physiological and psychological responses to objects in their environment (Lombard & Ditton, 1997). Because social presence establishes the illusion of non-mediation, research has shown that it can have an intensifying effect on the affective and cognitive responses to communications (Lombard, Reich, Grabe, Bracken, & Ditton, 2000). Affective responses found to be induced by social presence include increased enjoyment (Cyr, Hassanein, Head, & Ivanov, 2007), embarrassment (Dahl, Manchanda, & Argo, 2001), satisfaction with relationships (Kim, Park, & Sundar, 2013), para-social interaction with the characters within a medium (Heeter, 1995; Horton & Richard Wohl, 1956), and trust (Choi et al., 2011). Cognitive responses shown to be affected by social presence include task performance (Sheridan, 1992), memory and persuasion (Kim, 1996), and perceived usefulness of online product assessments (Hassanein & Head, 2007).
The cognitive and affective responses engendered by social presence have been investigated in various users and medium interaction contexts. In a learning environment, for example, researchers have found that social presence enhances students⿿ cognitive abilities and achievement of learning objectives. It has also been shown to help students accomplish more by facilitating such affective aspects of learning as making group interactions more appealing, engaging, and thus intrinsically rewarding (Rourke, Anderson, Garrison, & Archer, 1999). In virtual environments, Li, Daugherty, and Biocca (2002) have shown that social presence improves such cognitive outcomes as product knowledge and such affective outcomes as attitudes toward brands. In website environments, social presence has also been found to produce such affective responses as trust, enjoyment, and satisfaction and such cognitive responses as perceived usefulness and ease of use (Cyr et al., 2007; Gefen & Straub, 2003).
2.3. Social presence outcome to relationship building
Methods that have been found to help corporations achieve the goal of establishing relationships with consumers are strengthening interactivity with consumers and promoting social values such as empathy and presence (Duncan & Moriarty, 1998; Maru File et al., 1992). When applied to an online context, the goal of making people feel that a company is there for them can be represented as social presence. Research on such technology-driven contexts as online shopping and social media has therefore widely accepted and examined the concept of social presence, though exact terms may differ. For example, Kwon and Sung (2011) have shown that injecting a sense of human personality into corporate SNS accounts can be useful in building relationships with consumers, and Kelleher and Miller (2006) have discovered that using a conversational human voice in a company⿿s social media communications also enhanced their relationship-building. Similarly, Park and Lee (2013) have found that creating a human-seeming presence in SNS can promote SNS users⿿ engaging in online communication and word-of-mouth behavior. Particularly, Dabholkar et al. (2009) have identified social presence as a core element of social satisfaction, which they link to cognitive and affective commitment in relationship formation in a B2C context, and Johnson and Grayson (2005) have found that affective and cognitive processes mediate the relationship between users⿿ satisfaction with previous interactions and their expectation to engage in future interactions.
Thus, we contend, both the marketing literature and social presence theory can help us better understand how social presence can enhance effective relationship building. Together, these bodies of research hold that the outcomes of social presence and the antecedents of relationship building are both affective and cognitive.

Building upon the insights of this prior research, we theorize that SNS users feel social presence that is formed by a certain set of SNS-enabled antecedents during their interaction with a corporate SNS account and that the affective and cognitive outcomes of this social presence contribute to users⿿ relationship building with that account. In the next section, we discuss each of the major factors in this framework in more detail.]]></section>
    <section name="Research model and hypotheses" category="research model and hypotheses">
        <![CDATA[
3. Research model and hypotheses
3.1. Social presence formation
3.1.1. Form-based social presence formation
Although traditional media such as television and radio provide a variety of sensory stimuli, they provide their users with very little ability to influence how the delivered content is tailored for them (Hoffman & Novak, 1996). The online context, in contrast, emphasizes this ability by enabling changes in texts, images, and hyperlinks (Coyle & Thorson, 2001; Ha & James, 1998; Macias, 2003; Sicilia, Ruiz, & Munuera, 2005). SNS, which offer users a flexible environment in which to create and control their own space in which to communicate, particularly enrich this ability through the high level of interactivity between the system and its users. Interactivity is defined as ⿿the degree to which participants in a communication process have control over and can exchange roles in their mutual discourse⿿ (Williams, Rice, & Rogers, 1988, p. 10). Because the interactivity of a medium influences the perceptions and attitudes of users (Hoffman & Novak, 1996; Johnson, Bruner, & Kumar, 2006), it also affects social presence formation (Fortin & Dholakia, 2005). For example, the interactivity of a website has been found to increase the social presence of advertising on that website and to thereby improve customer participation (Fortin & Dholakia, 2005).
Given that this interactivity in a mediated presentation is operationalized by the range or amount of change possible, the way in which participants communicate within a medium depends on how that medium is designed. As noted above, Lombard and Ditton (1997) argue that this interactivity is accomplished by the form features of a medium. As interactivity can be multidimensional (Koolstra & Bos, 2009), researchers have posited that two representative dimensions of interactivity materialized by such features are machine interactivity and person interactivity (Hoffman & Novak, 1996; Sicilia et al., 2005; Song & Zinkhan, 2008).
Steuer (1992) defined machine interactivity as ⿿the extent to which users can participate in modifying the form and content of a mediated environment in real time⿿ (p. 84). Szuprowicz (1996) identified two levels of this machine interactivity by content manipulation capability: user-system interactivity and user-document interactivity. At the level of user-system interactivity, users can manipulate the content by changing its characteristics, such as by querying the search engine so the content changes to match the user⿿s needs. At the user-document level, users can interact with content through its given form but are unable to influence or manipulate that content, such as by browsing through the given hypertext links (Szuprowicz, 1996; Teo, Oh, Liu, & Wei, 2003). In the SNS context, the senders of a message can control what is shown and how it is shown. If an intended message is long or includes multimedia, the sender can choose to present it as it is or change some into a hyperlink form that receivers can view but not modify themselves. Therefore, senders can take advantage of both levels of machine interactivity, but receivers can employ only one. Since the subjects of social presence in the context of corporate SNS accounts are the receivers⿿SNS users⿿rather than the senders, the machine interactivity we refer to in the context of this study is user-document level machine interactivity, as in other SNS-related studies (e.g., Burton & Soboleva, 2011).
Previous research has demonstrated that if the messages of a corporate SNS account are rich in machine interactivity, their receivers are more likely to become immersed in the usage environment (Biocca & Delaney, 1995). For example, using a combination of text, logo, and photos in a website design, for example, has been shown to induce greater social presence than a text-only or photo-only design (Cyr et al., 2007; Gefen & Straub, 2003), and machine interactivity has also been found to affect social presence in a virtual world (Yeh, Chuan-Chuan Lin, & Lu, 2011). Current evidence thus suggests that the enriched multiplicity of corporate SNS accounts that deliver various types of content via hyperlink to users may stimulate SNS users to imagine they are interacting with other humans and to feel a richness of social interaction and thus social presence (Hassanein & Head, 2007). Hence, we posit the following hypothesis:
Hypothesis 1a

SNS users will perceive greater social presence when interacting with a corporate SNS account with high machine interactivity than when interacting with a corporate SNS account with low machine interactivity.


Whereas machine interactivity refers to interactivity with a medium, person interactivity refers to interactivity through a medium⿿that is, to interactivity between people that is enabled by a medium (Hoffman & Novak, 1996). In a marketing context, person interactivity can be defined as ⿿the degree of social interconnectedness between customers and other participants, including salespersons and other customers, in the communication process through an online medium⿿ (Suntornpithug & Khamalah, 2010, p. 301). Person interactivity in mediated communication can be demonstrated through communication between individuals and/or organizations in which a sequence of messages are related to each other and later messages indicate their relatedness to earlier messages (Hoffman & Novak, 1996; Rafaeli & Sudweeks, 1997). In this sense, the person interactivity of a medium can be understood as a form-based factor that facilitates human interpersonal interaction (McMillan & Hwang, 2002).
This person interactivity has also been shown to affect social presence (Suntornpithug & Khamalah, 2010). For example, researchers have found that when an e-commerce site creates a feeling of interaction by displaying consumer reviews, the social presence of the site increases (Dholakia, Zhao, Dholakia, & Fortin, 2000). Similarly, Kumar and Benbasat (2006) have observed that providing recommendations and consumer reviews increases both the usefulness and social presence of the website. A site⿿s handling of a customer⿿s question in the form of one-to-one dialogue in a customized web page also has been shown to give customers a sense of personal connection with the website and to increase their feeling of social presence (Fogg, 2003). The increase in social presence produced by this type of person interaction has also been reported in the context of virtual worlds (Yeh et al., 2011). Corporate SNS accounts can similarly provide person interactivity by answering questions via SNS in a personalized manner. In other words, SNS users communicating with a corporate account that answers their questions and forwards communications between individual users and the company to other users tend to experience the medium as warm, sensitive, sociable, and personal, much like they would feel to a person in a similar social interaction. Such person interactivity in a corporate SNS account gives SNS users a feeling that the company is responding to their needs and helps form a sense of social presence within the corporate SNS account (Choi et al., 2011; Kumar & Benbasat, 2006). Thus, we hypothesize the following:
Hypothesis 1b

SNS users will perceive greater social presence when interacting with a corporate SNS account with high person interactivity than when interacting with a corporate SNS account with low person interactivity.


3.1.2. Content-based social presence formation
In a low-cue environment such as online communication, the delivered content plays an important role in forming social presence. As noted earlier, if content is to establish social presence, it needs to be socially realistic, authentic, and plausible and involve ambiguous verbal and nonverbal social cues and sensitive personal information (Lombard & Ditton, 1997; Rice, 1992; Short et al., 1976). Given that online environments lack such non-verbal cues as gestures and facial expressions, people interacting in these environments attempt to find other ways to deliver the subtle nuances and ambience of those non-verbal cues (Walther, 1992). For example, embedding humorous content and emoticons are documented ways to help convey nonverbal cues and reduce social distance (Hu, Wood, Smith, & Westbrook, 2004).
Another effective way of embedding real-world⿿like cues in online messages is self-disclosure (Rourke et al., 1999). Self-disclosure refers to any message about oneself that one communicates to another, including one⿿s thoughts, feelings, and experiences (Cozby, 1973; Wheeless, 1978; Wheeless & Grotz, 1977). For example, it has been shown that when instructors share personal stories and experiences with students in online education environments, students see their online presence as more real and human and feel a greater closeness to them (Aragon, 2003). Thus, self-disclosure has been shown to promote social attraction and bonding between individuals (Altman & Taylor, 1973) and to contribute to the formation of social presence.
In a SNS environment, corporate SNS accounts are managed by account administrators, many of whom adopt a strategy of posting information with a human touch by including their personal feelings and thoughts in messages. The research suggests that such posts make SNS users feel more psychologically connected to a corporate SNS account and to perceive it as sociable and warm. Thus, we propose the following hypothesis:
Hypothesis 1c

SNS users will perceive greater social presence when interacting with a corporate SNS account with high self-disclosure than when interacting with a corporate SNS account with low self-disclosure.


3.2. Social presence outcomes
Given that the context of our study is a corporate SNS account designed to communicate with potential customers, we selected trust and usefulness as this investigation⿿s target affective and cognitive outcomes, respectively.

The corporate SNS context is, as the term implies, the combination of two aspects. First aspect is that, the corporate SNS context is about a company⿿s efforts to build relationships through communication with their customers. Second aspect is that, at the same time, communication conduit in this context is SNS in which people are linked through and messages are delivered by IT artifacts. Therefore, we chose to examine constructs that are the outcomes of social presence and that significantly related to both of the two aspects.

Regarding first aspect, trust is experienced as a feeling and is known to be a key to relationship building with customers (Achrol, 1991; Becker, 1960; Dwyer, Schurr, & Oh, 1987; Morgan & Hunt, 1994). Trust has been shown to be an indispensable element of many effective business interactions (Kumar, Scheer, & Steenkamp, 1995) because it reduces the uncertainty that the need to depend on others creates for customers (Deutsch, 1958; Kim & Benbasat, 2003; Luhmann, 2000) and builds customers⿿ confidence in the company (Morgan & Hunt, 1994). Even in an online environment, trust has been found to play a significant role in creating a user⿿s intention to purchase (Gefen & Straub, 2003) and in website loyalty (Flavián, Guinalíu, & Gurrea, 2006). The second target outcome, usefulness, has also been found to be a vital element of relationship-building (Kent & Taylor, 1998), as seeking and utilizing useful information to inform their purchasing decisions is a main reason customers begin a relationship with a corporate SNS account (Lempert, 2006; Vollmer & Precourt, 2008).
Regarding second aspect, trust and usefulness have also been widely studied within a SNS context. The literature has emphasized the importance of trust because of the relative difficulty of establishing one⿿s authenticity in an SNS environment because of its reduced environmental cues (Marwick & boyd, 2011). Researchers have demonstrated that trust is vital to retaining SNS users (Risius & Beck, 2015), to leading them to participate in corporate SNS accounts (Mangold & Faulds, 2009; Sharma & Crossler, 2014), to constructing SNS fan page loyalty (Ruiz-Mafe, Martí-Parreño, & Sanz-Blas, 2014), and to increasing the publicity of information (Liu, Liu, & Li, 2012). Usefulness has also been shown to be an important element in why people use SNS. Previous studies have demonstrated that the perceived usefulness of information acquisition is an important rationale for media usage (Cyr, Head, Larios, & Pan, 2009; Davis, 1989) and that social media functions as an extension of such information management tools as online publishing media (Gomez, 2005; Johnson & Kaye, 2009) and as an important information source (Lu & Hsiao, 2007). Given that gathering and sharing useful information is also an important motivation for using SNS (Scanfeld, Scanfeld, & Larson, 2010), delivering useful information to SNS users through corporate SNS accounts has been shown to be an effective strategy for building relationships with current and potential customers (Shin, Pang, & Kim, 2015).
The existing literature, therefore, supports our decision to use trust and usefulness as social presence outcomes because of their important role to building relationships within an SNS context.

3.2.1. Trust as an affective outcome of social presence
Trust is an affective attitude of optimism about the goodwill and competence of another, including the expectation that the trusted party will be directly and favorably moved by the thought that one is counting on them (Jones, 1996). It is an affective construct because it is based on dimensions such as honesty and benevolence that have a strong emotional component (Crosby, Evans, & Cowles, 1990; Doney & Cannon, 1997; Moliner, Sánchez, Rodríguez, & Callarisa, 2007). Research indicates that trust is likely to be developed under high social presence because it is difficult to hide information and engage in unreliable behavior in socially rich contents (Gefen & Straub, 2003). In a relationship between consumers and companies, the perception that an e-vendor is providing human contact and the sense of connection with other users on its e-commerce website has also been shown to increase consumer trust (Gefen & Straub, 2004). Hassanein and Head (2007) have also shown that social presence on e-commerce websites significantly increases users⿿ trust in an online vendor. Since corporate SNS accounts are communicating with potential consumers in a socially rich communication environment, we argue that these prior research insights can be applied to our target context as well. Therefore, we hypothesize the following:
Hypothesis 2a

The perceived social presence of a corporate SNS account has a positive effect on SNS users⿿ trust in that company.


3.2.2. Usefulness as a cognitive outcome of social presence
The perceived usefulness of an information system is defined as ⿿the degree to which a person believes that using a particular system would enhance his or her job performance⿿ (Davis, 1989, p. 320). More specific to the target context of this study, we define usefulness as the perceived extent to which the medium enhances the effectiveness of information acquisition, as this is the performance that SNS users want to enhance through interaction with a corporate SNS account. Previous research has shown that information acquisition about a company, brand, or product is the primary reason users visit, like, and use corporate SNS (Men & Tsai, 2013) and that information seeking is one of the most common purposes for sending messages to corporate SNS (Men & Tsai, 2012)
Given that a medium with a low social presence may have difficulty delivering subtle cues, research has found that its users tend to consider it less useful than a medium with high social presence (Straub, 1994). The social presence of a medium has thus been shown to affect users⿿ evaluation of its usefulness as a mode of exchanging information (Gefen & Straub, 2003) and to increase the perceived usefulness of information provided on a website (Hassanein & Head, 2007). In addition, people who feel a greater social presence when using a medium have demonstrated more confidence in their decision making, indicating that social presence tends to enhance the persuasiveness of media content (Fogg & Tseng, 1999; Kim, 1996). Therefore, we hypothesize the following:
Hypothesis 2b

The perceived social presence of a corporate SNS account has a positive effect on SNS users⿿ perceived usefulness of information acquisition.


3.3. Social presence outcomes in relationship building
As indicated earlier, trust is a fundamental mechanism in building and maintaining relationships (Li, Browne, & Wetherbe, 2006), including long-term relationships between a company and its customers (Anderson & Weitz, 1989; Ganesan, 1994). Researchers have shown that the more customers trust a company, the more willing they are to take the risk of interaction (Crosby et al., 1990; Deutsch, 1958; Garbarino & Johnson, 1999; Morgan & Hunt, 1994).
In an online context, research has shown that the more customers trust a company, the more frequently they visit its e-commerce website and the more likely they are to purchase its products in the future (Cyr et al., 2007). In the specific context examined in this study, SNS users who have trust in a company have been found to be more likely to build relationships with it through a corporate SNS account (Kang & Park, 2013). For the purposes of this study, we use SNS users⿿ intention to engage with a company⿿s corporate SNS account as a proxy for relationship building with corporate SNS to reflect that it represents not just a simple link between one SNS node and another but current and potential customers⿿ connecting with a company of interest. Thus, we propose the following hypothesis:
Hypothesis 3a

Trust in a company has a positive effect on SNS users⿿ intention to engage with its corporate SNS account.


The relationship between the usefulness of a technology for achieving a goal and the continued use of that technology is well established in the IS literature (Davis, 1989; Kim & Son, 2009). Perceived usefulness of an e-commerce website has also been shown to affect the frequency of future revisits and purchases in that website (Cyr et al., 2007). If a corporate SNS account effectively provides desired information, researchers have demonstrated, more SNS users tend to link to it (Lempert, 2006; Vollmer & Precourt, 2008). Therefore, we can project that if SNS users believe a corporate SNS account is useful for gaining information, they are more likely to connect and engage in future interactions with it. Therefore, we posit the following hypothesis:
Hypothesis 3b

The perceived usefulness of information acquisition has a positive effect on SNS users⿿ intention to engage with a corporate SNS account.


Fig. 1 illustrates the research model for this study. Hypotheses 1a⿿1c address the conditions under which social presence is formed, and the remaining hypotheses address the effect of one variable on another. Therefore, following Jiang and Benbasat (2007), our research model combines these two sets of hypotheses, as shown in Fig. 1. The analysis of social presence formation illustrated on the left side of Fig. 1 will be tested by Analysis of Variance (ANOVA), and the outcomes represented on the right side will be tested by structural equation modeling. In addition to the constructs identified in the hypotheses stated above, our model includes two control variables⿿involvement with product and knowledge of product⿿that have been long known to affect relationship building between companies and their consumers (Mishra, Umesh, & Stem, 1993; Wakefield & Baker, 1998; Zaichkowsky, 1985)
Fig. 1
Download high-res image (495KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Research model.]]></section>
<section name=" Method" category="methods">
        <![CDATA[
4. Method
Our research model was tested through an experiment employing a 2 ÿ 2 ÿ 2 full factorial design (all between-subject) using all eight combinations of the three variables that influence social presence formation: (1) the presence or absence of machine interactivity, (2) the presence or absence of person interactivity, and (3) the presence or absence of an administrator⿿s self-disclosure.
To support or disprove the hypotheses, social presence formation was tested by ANOVA. Social presence consequences were tested by AMOS 20.0, the covariance-based structural equation modeling tool (Arbuckle, 1994) using a maximum likelihood-based estimation algorithm.
4.1. Experimental design
We chose to test our hypotheses on Twitter, for three reasons. First, Twitter is one of the most representative SNSs, with the second-largest SNS user base (eBizMBA, 2015). Second, mutual agreement is not necessary for initiating or ending the links among users in Twitter, and thus a user can build a connection without being worried about rejection or acceptance. Third, the consequential impact of relationship building between users and corporate Twitter accounts is potentially significant because the ⿿retweet⿿ function in Twitter typically propagates postings to a broader network than a user⿿s own social network (Jansen, Zhang, Sobel, & Chowdury, 2009); a retweeted tweet has been shown to reach an average of 1000 users regardless of the original tweet sender⿿s number of followers (Kwak et al., 2014). Therefore, not only will this study of Twitter contribute to the variety of SNS research, but Twitter⿿s representativeness in SNS and its potential impact on business will make its findings generalizable and widely valuable.
For this experiment, we created two fictitious corporate Twitter accounts: ABC Securities to represent a utilitarian product and ABC Travel to represent a hedonic product. We chose to use fictitious companies to avoid possible bias caused by users⿿ past experiences with existing companies. The use of two rather than a single account was intended to prevent either the hedonic or utilitarian characteristics of the products of the corporate SNS accounts from inadvertently affecting social presence formation. We selected a securities and a travel company because they are considered representative examples of utilitarian and hedonic products, respectively (Albers-Miller, Straughan, & Prenshaw, 2007; Mort & Rose, 2004; Plakoyiannaki & Zotos, 2009). The participants were asked to read eight tweets supposedly produced by either ABC Securities or ABC Travel.
Machine interactivity was manipulated by hyperlinks connecting to a movie clip, a photograph, or a webpage. For the presence of the machine interactivity condition, four of the eight tweets included such hyperlinks. One example of these tweets is ⿿ABC Securities start Retire Rich Service to provide experience on retirement planning on-line. We will show you the way to use service. Click! http://bit.ly/MBw6bC.⿿ Person interactivity was manipulated by replies and retweets to other users. For the presence of the person interactivity condition, four of the eight messages included replies and retweets. One example of these messages is ⿿If you wonder about KOSPI index, please register for KOSPI alarm service. You can get it on mobile phone. RT @stock_god81: Is it possible to get KOSPI index every day?⿿ Self-disclosure was manipulated by references to the Twitter account administrators⿿ personal life, feelings, or beliefs in their tweets. For the presence of the self-disclosure condition, four of the eight tweets embedded self-disclosing messages such as ⿿The night view from ABC Securities building is truly beautiful tonight. I always cheer for those who work at night.⿿
After reading the eight tweets created for each group, the participants were asked to respond to a questionnaire that asked about the constructs and manipulation variables of our research model.

4.2. Measurements
Table 2 shows the operational definitions of our constructs and their sources. All measures were adopted from existing studies with minor changes in wording to represent the Twitter context. Because there was no suitable existing measure for the intention to engage with a corporate SNS account, we combined two measures. First, we adopted three items from Lutz⿿s (1977) method of measuring behavior intention by changing its wording to fit to our target context. Then, because the concept of engagement includes not only general behavior intention but also a commitment to an active relationship (Mollen & Wilson, 2010), we added the item ⿿intention to recommend corporate SNS account to other people⿿ to the other three. This is in line with previous literature that uses recommendation intention to capture the commitment aspect of usage intention (e.g., Chiang & Dholakia, 2003; Kim et al., 2013; Liang, Ho, Li, & Turban, 2011). All six constructs were measured by multiple items based on a seven-point Likert scale ranging from ⿿strongly disagree⿿ to ⿿strongly agree.⿿ (See Appendix A for detailed measurement items.)
Table 2. Operational definitions of constructs.
Construct	Operational Definition	Related Studies
Machine interactivity	The degree to which a corporate SNS account provides images, video clips, audio clips, and animated graphics via hyperlink	Steuer (1992)
Person interactivity	The degree to which a company communicates with SNS users by answering their questions and forwarding communications between one user and the company to other users	Rafaeli (1988)
Self-disclosure	The degree to which a SNS administrator verbally reveals personal things about himself or herself to others, including thoughts, feelings, and experiences	Wheeless and Grotz (1977)
Social presence	The degree to which a SNS user perceives that a corporate SNS account conveys a feeling of human contact, sociability, warmth, and sensitivity	Gefen and Straub (2003)
Trust in company	The degree to which a SNS user believes a company operating a corporate SNS account will tell the truth	Newell and Goldsmith (2001)
Perceived usefulness of information acquisition	The perceived extent to which a corporate SNS account enhances the effectiveness of information acquisition	Davis (1989)
Intention to engage with corporate SNS account	The perceived extent to which SNS users intend to engage in a relationship with a corporate SNS even far into the future	Chiang and Dholakia, (2003), Kim et al., 2013
Involvement with product	The degree of inherent interests, values, or needs that motivate users toward the product the corporate SNS account promotes	Wakefield and Baker (1998)
Knowledge of product	The degree to which users have enough knowledge about the product class the corporate SNS account promotes	Mishra et al., 1993
To ensure the content validity of these constructs, the questionnaire was examined by practitioners and researchers in the relevant field and further revised based on their comments. Prior to the study reported here, a pilot test with 71 Twitter users showed that the manipulation was accurately perceived and the scales were acceptable in reliability and validity.

4.3. Data collection
To recruit participants for our experiment, we obtained the cooperation of the leading research company in Korea, which has about 500,000 people on its panel, the largest panel base in Korea. We restricted participants to those who had used Twitter for more than six months to ensure that respondents were quite familiar with Twitter. The online link to our questionnaire was emailed to 16,006 members of the panel and advertised on the site of the company for a week, leading to responses from 824 panel members. Participants were randomly assigned to one of the 16 experimental interfaces. After eliminating 15 responses with missing answers, the responses from 809 participants (421 for the securities company and 388 for the travel company) were used for further analysis. The number of participants in each of the 16 groups ranged from 46 to 61. Table 3 shows the demographic profile of all respondents and each group of users.
Table 3. Demographic profiles of participants.
Item	Category	Frequency (Percentage)
Securities (N = 421)	Travel (N = 388)
Gender	Male	214 (50.8%)	196 (50.5%)
Female	207 (49.2%)	192 (49.5%)

Age	20⿿29 years	126 (29.9%)	103 (26.5%)
30⿿39 years	162 (38.5%)	141 (41.5%)
40⿿49 years	133 (31.6%)	124 (32.0%)

Average time of usage per day	Less than 10 min	23 (5.5%)	23 (5.9%)
10⿿less than 20 min	47 (11.2%)	31 (8.0%)
20⿿less than 30 min	59 (14.0%)	41 (10.6%)
30 min⿿less than 1 h	72 (17.1%)	77 (19.8%)
1⿿less than 2 h	103 (24.5%)	90 (23.2%)
2⿿less than 3 h	56 (13.3%)	43(11.1%)
Equal to or more than 3 h	61 (14.5%)	83(21.4%)c

Average usage period	6 to less than 12 months	177 (42.0%)	161 (41.5%)
1 to less than 2 years	191 (45.4%)	166 (42.8%)
2 years or more	53 (12.6%)	61 (15.7%)

Average number of visits per month	less than once a month	11 (2.6%)	7 (1.8%)
once a month	15 (3.6%)	16 (4.1%)
a few times a month	95 (22.6%)	86 (22.2%)
a few times a week	97 (23.0%)	101 (26.0%)
about once a day	80 (19.0%)	55 (14.2%)
several times a day	123 (29.2%)	123 (31.7%)
We conducted a t-test to ensure there were no significant demographic differences among the 16 experimental groups in terms of gender, age, average time of usage per day, average usage period, and average number of visits per month.]]></section>
    <section name="Results" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
5. Results
5.1. Testing social presence formation
5.1.1. Manipulation checks
To ensure that the participants perceived the experiment conditions as we manipulated them, we conducted a t-test for machine interactivity, person interactivity, and self-disclosure. As shown in Table 4, participants in the high condition perceived each of the corresponding constructs higher than those in the low condition, which suggests that our manipulation was perceived as expected.
Table 4. Manipulation check result.
Securities	Travel
Mean (Std.Dev)	t (sig.)	Mean (Std.Dev)	t (sig.)
Condition	High	Low		High	Low	
Machine interactivity	5.13 (1.11)	3.58 (1.66)	11.28 (p < 0.001)	5.18 (1.11)	3.56 (1.69)	10.98 (p < 0.001)
Person interactivity	5.07 (1.06)	3.53 (1.59)	11.75 (p < 0.001)	5.05 (1.07)	3.43 (1.63)	11.59 (p < 0.001)
Self-disclosure	4.53 (1.16)	3.15 (1.49)	10.68 (p < 0.001)	4.66 (1.10)	3.24 (1.39)	11.13 (p < 0.001)
5.1.2. ANOVA results for social presence formation
The ANOVA results are summarized in Table 5. Machine interactivity and person interactivity were found to exert significant influence on forming social presence for both of the companies. Participants also reported a stronger sense of social presence for both products when the self-disclosure level was high. Therefore, H1a, H1b, and H1c are all supported.
Table 5. ANOVA results on social presence.
Main effect	Securities	Travel
d.f.	F-statistics	sig.	d.f.	F-statistics	sig.
Machine interactivity	1	4.649	p < 0.05	1	4.152	p < 0.05
Person interactivity	1	37.891	p < 0.001	1	23.841	p < 0.001
Self-disclosure	1	15.863	p < 0.001	1	35.850	p < 0.001
5.2. Testing social presence outcome
5.2.1. Assessment of measurement model
Reliability was assessed by computing Cronbach⿿s alpha, composite reliability, and average variance extracted (AVE) (Fornell & Larcker, 1981). As shown in Table 6, both composite reliability and Cronbach⿿s alpha exceeded the recommended threshold of 0.70, and the AVE for each construct exceeded 0.50. Convergent validity was assessed by reviewing the AVE and the t-statistics for the factor loadings. All items showed highly significant t-statistics (p < 0.01), and the AVE values ranged from 0.688 to 0.857, which exceeded the cutoff value of 0.5. These results indicate sufficient convergent validity of all indicators.
Table 6. Composite reliability, correlations, and AVE of constructs.

Note: The shaded numbers of the diagonal are the square root of the variance shared between the constructs and their measures. Off-diagonal elements are correlations among constructs.

For discriminant validity, the AVE for a construct should exceed the variance shared between the construct and other constructs in the model. Table 6 shows that the square root of AVE for each construct exceeded the correlations between the constructs and all other constructs (i.e., the off-diagonal elements in the corresponding rows and columns), indicating sufficient discriminant validity (Chin, 1998).
Next, we conducted a confirmatory factor analysis (CFA) using AMOS. The testing results are presented in Table 7 and indicate good fitness of the measurement model (Segars & Grover, 1998). The 
Ͽ
Ͽ2/d.f. was 3.176 for the securities company group and exceeded the desired threshold of 3.0. However, chi-square is dependent on data size, so chi-square can be increased as the data size increases even in the same model (Marsh & Hocevar, 1985), and researchers have recommended using ratios less than 5 to indicate a reasonable fit (Bentler & Bonett, 1980). GFI for both the securities and travel companies are slightly below the cut-off level, and RMSEA for the travel company group is slightly above the cut-off level. However, considering the factor loadings shown in Appendix A and other goodness-of-fit indices shown in Table 6, the result of the CFA overall confirms the convergent and discriminant validity of the measure.
Table 7. Goodness of fit indices of the CFA.
Group	Chi-square	d.f.	Chi-square/d.f.	GFI	AGFI	NFI	CFI	SRMR	RMSEA
Securities	981.532	309	3.176	0.849	0.816	0.918	0.942	0.0448	0.072
Travel	864.233	309	2.797	0.857	0.825	0.916	0.944	0.0427	0.068
Recommended value	<=5.0	>=0.90	>=0.80	>=0.90	>=0.92	<0.08	<=0.07
Common method bias was assessed by two methods. First, we carried out a Chi-square values comparison of three models (Song & Zahedi, 2005). The null model (MM0) presumes no common factors underlying any of the measures, MM1 assumes that all the measures have one single underlying factor, and MM2 represents the measurement model for this study. The results of the three measurement models are summarized in Table 8. Delta in Straub et al. (1995) suggests that the percentage explained by each model of the total variation and an indication of the extent to which the Chi-square of the null model can be improved by a superior model. Deltas of MM1 and MM2 for the securities company group explain 46.6% and 91.8% of the total variance among the measures, respectively. Deltas of MM1 and MM2 for the travel company group explain 49.0% and 91.7% of the total variance among the measures, respectively. Furthermore, the results show that the difference between the Chi-square values of MM1 and MM2 is significant (p < 0.000) (Straub, Limayem, & Karahanna-Evaristo, 1995) and that MM2 has better fit indices. Thus, these results show that the measurement model fits the data better than a single-factor model (Hair, Black, Babin, & Anderson, 2009).
Table 8. Chi-square model comparison for common method bias analysis.
Model	
Ͽ
Ͽ2	df	
Ͽ
οϿ2	οdf	p-value	Delta	GFI	AGFI	NFI	CFI	RMSEA
Securities
MM0	12022.261	351					0.152	0.087	0.000	0.000	0.281
MM1	6417.657	324				0.466	0.386	0.284	0.466	0.478	0.212
MM2	981.532	309	5436.137	15	p < 0.001	0.918	0.849	0.816	0.918	0.942	0.072

Travel
MM0	10246.703	351					0.166	0.102	0.000	0.000	0.270
MM1	5227.459	324				0.490	0.415	0.318	0.490	0.504	0.198
MM2	864.233	309	4381.226	15	p < 0.001	0.917	0.857	0.825	0.916	0.944	0.068
Delta = [
Ͽ
Ͽ2MM0 ⿿ 
Ͽ
Ͽ2MMi]/
Ͽ
Ͽ2MM0.

Then, to explicitly decompose the total variance into variance explained by constructs and method factor, we performed a confirmatory factor model with a common method latent variable as suggested by Liang, Saraf, Hu, and Xue (2007). The results, as reported in Appendices B and C, indicate that the average substantively explained variance of the indicators was 0.819 for the securities company group and 0.805 for the travel company group, whereas the average method-based variance was 0.007 for the securities company group and 0.005 for the travel company group. Therefore, the results of the two tests suggest that common method bias is not a serious concern for this study.
5.2.2. Results of structural model
The results of structural model testing, as shown in Table 9, show that most fit indices are satisfactory for both the securities company and the travel company groups. Because different types of indices have their own advantages and disadvantages, using multiple indices of differing types is recommended (Hair et al., 2009). In our model fit, although GFI is slightly lower and RMSEA is greater than the cut-off level, other indices are satisfactory (Hair et al., 2009; Hartwick & Barki, 1994; Hu & Bentler, 1999; Segars & Grover, 1993), indicating that our structural model is overall acceptable.
Table 9. Goodness of fit indices of the structural model.
Group	Chi-square	d.f.	Chi-square/d.f.	GFI	AGFI	NFI	CFI	SRMR	RMSEA
Securities	1077.153	315	3.420	0.836	0.803	0.910	0.935	0.0601	0.076
Travel	957.528	315	3.040	0.844	0.813	0.907	0.935	0.0588	0.073
Recommended value	<=5.0	>=0.90	>=0.80	>=0.90	>=0.92	<0.08	<=0.07
The results of the structural model test for the securities company group and the travel company group are presented in Fig. 2. For both groups, the relationships between social presence and trust in the company and the relationship between social presence and perceived usefulness of information acquisition are all significant. Thus, H2a and H2b are accepted. The results reveal that the effects of trust in the company and the perceived usefulness of information acquisition upon participants⿿ intention to engage with the corporate SNS account are both significant for both company groups, supporting H3a and H3b. Regarding control variables, the effect of involvement with the product is significant for the securities company group but not for the travel company group; the effect of knowledge of the product is significant in both cases.
Fig. 2
Download high-res image (368KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Results of structural model test.
5.3. Additional analyses
We ran several additional analyses to provide further insights. First, as the aim of this study is to understand how social presence is formed within corporate SNS as enabled by SNS characteristics, user characteristics were not included in the research model. To test whether user characteristics may have also affected social presence formation, we examined the effect of individual experiences of SNS as measured by the effects of age, average time of SNS usage per day, average SNS usage period, and average number of visits to SNS per month upon social presence. As summarized in Table 10, these factors do not have statistically significant effects on social presence in either the securities company group or travel company group.
Table 10. The effect of user characteristics on social presence.
Estimate (sig.)
Securities	Travel
Age	0.063 (n.s.)	0.086 (n.s.)
Average time of usage per day	0.073 (n.s.)	0.018 (n.s.)
Average usage period	⿿0.050 (n.s.)	0.011 (n.s.)
Average number of visits per month	⿿0.024 (n.s.)	⿿0.057 (n.s.)
Second, we conducted ANOVA to test for interaction effects among three antecedents of social presence formation. We found no interaction among machine interactivity, person interactivity, and self-disclosure for the securities company group, but the interaction between self-disclosure and person interactivity was significant for the travel company group. These results are summarized in Table 11.
Table 11. Interaction effect on social presence.
Interaction effect	Securities	Travel
d.f.	F-statistics (sig.)	d.f.	F-statistics (sig.)
Machine interactivity ÿ Person interactivity	1	2.254 (n.s.)	1	1.269 (n.s.)
Machine interactivity ÿ Self-disclosure	1	2.316 (n.s.)	1	0.936 (n.s.)
Person interactivity ÿ Self-disclosure	1	0.341 (n.s.)	1	5.490 (p < 0.05)
Machine interactivity ÿ Person interactivity ÿ Self-disclosure	1	0.838 (n.s.)	1	1.046 (n.s.)
Third, given that the research model of this study is intended to be applicable to the corporate SNS account context in general, the experiment and cross-sectional survey were conducted for two different fictitious companies to increase external validity. To test whether the research model operates differently depending on the type of corporate SNS accounts, we performed a t-test on social presence between the securities and travel company groups. As shown in Table 12, there was no significant difference between the two company groups on any of the experiment conditions.
Table 12. The result of t-test on self-presence between securities and travel groups.
Condition	Mean (Std.Dev)	t (sig.)
(Machine-Interactivity ⿿ Person-Interactivity ⿿ Self-disclosure)	Securities	Travel	
Low ⿿ Low ⿿ Low	3.24 (1.28)	3.20 (1.35)	0.19 (n.s.)
Low ⿿ Low ⿿ High	3.98 (1.15)	4.32 (1.18)	⿿1.49 (n.s.)
Low ⿿ High ⿿ Low	4.20 (0.92)	4.22 (1.04)	⿿0.06 (n.s.)
Low ⿿ High ⿿ High	4.63 (1.03)	4.61 (0.93)	0.14 (n.s.)
High ⿿ Low ⿿ Low	3.88 (0.95)	3.76 (1.05)	0.58 (n.s.)
High ⿿ Low ⿿ High	4.11 (1.25)	4.45 (1.00)	⿿1.47 (n.s.)
High ⿿ High ⿿ Low	4.34 (1.05)	4.31 (1.04)	0.17 (n.s.)
High ⿿ High ⿿ High	4.63 (0.88)	4.71 (0.89)	⿿0.46 (n.s.)
We next conducted a multi-group invariance test to see whether the particular path coefficients of the model for the securities company group and for the travel company group statistically differ from one another. The multi-group invariance test imposes equality constraints on particular parameters of a model among groups and compares a constrained model estimate to a base (unconstrained) model estimate. As the constrained model is nested within the base model, a chi-square difference, the result of the comparison of two models, provides an indicator of whether the equality constraint holds across different groups (Byrne, 2004). The results, as indicated in Table 13, show that none of the equality constraints imposed on the path coefficients holds across the models of the securities company and travel company groups.
Table 13. Comparison of base and constrained models.
Model	Path	Coefficients of
securities/travel groups	Ͽ2	d.f.	οϿ2	sig.
Unconstrained base model	2034.678	630		
Constrained model	between SP and TC	0.775/0.799	2035.842	631	1.164	n.s.
between SP and PU	0.659/0.683	2034.693	631	0.019	n.s.
between TC and IE	0.375/0.447	2034.997	631	0.319	n.s.
between PU and IE	0.426/0.406	2034.697	631	0.019	n.s.
between IP and IE	0.148/0.060	2035.881	631	1.203	n.s.
between KP and IE	0.100/0.097	2034.749	631	0.071	n.s.
SP = Social Presence, TC = Trust in Company, PU = Perceived Usefulness of Information Acquisition, IE = Intention to Engage with corporate SNS, IP = Involvement with Product, KP = Knowledge with Product.

Lastly, we tested whether the difference in social presence between the condition groups is statistically significant. As shown in Table 14, the results indicate that the group with all low conditions shows the lowest social presence and the group with all high conditions shows the highest social presence.
Table 14. Scale mean differences of social presence.
Securities
Condition	Mean	1	2	3	4	5	6	7	8
1	Low ⿿ Low ⿿ Low	3.24	⿿							
2	Low ⿿ Low ⿿ High	3.98	0.733*	⿿						
3	Low ⿿ High ⿿ Low	4.20	0.969***	0.228	⿿					
4	Low ⿿ High ⿿ High	4.63	1.390***	0.657	0.430	⿿				
5	High ⿿ Low ⿿ Low	3.88	0.637	⿿0.096	⿿0.323	⿿0.753**	⿿			
6	High ⿿ Low ⿿ High	4.11	0.868*	0.136	⿿0.091	⿿0.521	0.232	⿿		
7	High ⿿ High ⿿ Low	4.34	1.100***	0.367	0.140	⿿0.290	0.463	0.232	⿿	
8	High ⿿ High ⿿ High	4.63	1.388***	0.655*	0.428	⿿0.002	0.751**	0.520	0.288	⿿

Travel
1	Low ⿿ Low ⿿ Low	3.20	⿿							
2	Low ⿿ Low ⿿ High	4.32	1.124***	⿿						
3	Low ⿿ High ⿿ Low	4.22	1.021**	⿿0.103	⿿					
4	Low ⿿ High ⿿ High.	4.61	1.412***	0.288.	0.391	⿿				
5	High ⿿ Low ⿿ Low	3.76	0.561	⿿0.563	⿿0.460	⿿0.850**	⿿			
6	High ⿿ Low ⿿ High	4.45	1.252***	0.128	0.231	⿿0.160	0.690*	⿿		
7	High ⿿ High ⿿ Low	4.31	1.114***	⿿0.010	0.093	⿿0.298	0.553	⿿0.138	⿿	
8	High ⿿ High ⿿ High	4.71	1.517***	0.393	0.496	0.105	0.956***	0.265	0.403	⿿
Condition (Machine-Interactivity ⿿ Person-Interactivity ⿿ Self-disclosure).]]></section>
    <section name="Discussion" category="discussion">
        <![CDATA[
6. Discussion
The experimental results show that machine interactivity and person interactivity significantly affect social presence formation. ]]><h target="1" match="part">They demonstrate that how the characteristics of SNS are designed to interact with users and how communication is enabled by those characteristics are important in forming social presence. </h><![CDATA[The more that these communications included rich cues such as movie clips, photographs, and communication interaction, the more participants felt social presence in the corporate SNS account. Worth noting is that this interactivity is realized not through how frequently a particular user interacts with a certain corporate SNS account but through the general interactivity embedded in the form design, indicating that mutual interaction is possible at a personal level and can enable interactions even with external resources. Therefore, we conclude that social presence can be formed not only by actual interaction but also by the possibility of rich interaction.

In addition, our results show that self-disclosure by corporate SNS account administrators also affects social presence formation, suggesting that the way in which postings are delivered and the social cues embedded in them can make SNS users view corporate SNS accounts as more human and accessible. Although this tendency is shown across product types, the findings suggest that in the case of hedonic products, self-disclosed postings embedded with social cues can magnify this tendency.

The results of the structural model tests indicate that social presence indeed affects SNS users⿿ trust in a company and their perceptions of the usefulness of information acquisition and that those two constructs affect SNS users⿿ intention to engage with a corporate SNS account. In the context of traditional consumer marketing, those affective and cognitive values are considered important antecedents of relationship building (Barry, Dion, & Johnson, 2008) and are known to be based on a company⿿s effective communication about its products and itself (Li et al., 2006). Our findings, however, suggest that in the context of SNS, which are founded on social drives and needs, those values can be engendered by the social presence that is formed regardless of whether the communication is about the company⿿s products and itself.
An examination of the control variables also provides important insights. The results show that involvement with and knowledge of a product, which are known to significantly affect relationship building, actually have marginal effects on SNS users⿿ intention to engage with a corporate SNS account. Particularly in the case of a hedonic product, involvement with product shows no effect on relationship building. An important insight of these findings is that, in a SNS context, the prerequisites of relationship building are not how much people know about or are involved with products but how involved they are with the medium and the communication themselves.

Our additional analyses also reveal that, in general, the more present the antecedents of social presence formation, the greater the social presence that is felt. When we examine this relationship in more detail, however, several interesting findings are uncovered. First, although the presence of either person interactivity or self-disclosure can significantly increase social presence, machine interactivity alone does not increase it to a statistically significant level when personal interactivity and self-disclosure are absent for both company groups, further confirming the relatively low significance level of the main effect of machine interactivity. Second, when person interactivity is low in the travel company group, increasing self-disclosure can significantly increase social presence, although the securities company group does not show this tendency. The opposite is not established, however: increasing person interactivity when self-disclosure is low does not show a consistently significant difference in social presence. In this result, we can see how the interaction effect between person interactivity and self-disclosure that is present in the travel company group operates.]]></section>
<section name="Implications; Limitations and directions for future research;Conclusion" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
7. Implications
7.1. Theoretical implications
This study makes several important theoretical contributions. First, it identifies the antecedents of social presence in terms of the characteristics of SNS design and its usage. Although investigating how social presence is formed in SNS context is important to understand how users are gratified in SNS interaction and lead to subsequent relationship building (Han et al., 2015; Kreijns et al., 2003; Rovai, 2000), previous research has not provided sufficient and integrated knowledge. By using Lombard and Ditton⿿s (1997) framework, we delineate how the form design and content delivery of SNS affect social presence formation and thus enrich our current understanding of social presence formation in SNS.
Second, this study further extends the existing research on social presence to the domain of corporate SNS. While the influence of social presence in various IT environments has been previously investigated, relatively few studies have examined how corporate SNS interact with SNS users. Our findings show that in this context, the traditional utilitarian values that induce consumers⿿ relationships with companies can stem from and be increased by social drives, demonstrating that users⿿ perceptions of how trustworthy companies are and how useful their information is are dependent on the way corporate SNS accounts build the feeling of social presence through using inherent characteristics of SNS.

Third, the relationship between person interactivity and social presence formation demonstrated by this study shows that the dyadic relationship between a company and its customers does not have to be built through real-time communication between them, which has been the subject of much of the traditional relationship marketing research (e.g., Crosby & Stephens, 1987; De Wulf & Odekerken-Schröder, 2003). The communication that occurs in SNS, which is represented as person interactivity in our study, has different communication characteristics: it usually does not happen in real time, is less volatile than verbal communication, contains the history of the conversation as it has evolved over time, and is broadcast to users who did not participate in that particular conversation. Our description of this form of interaction provides new insights into relationship marketing, showing that relationships can be built by various communication modes in such technologically enabled contexts as corporate use of SNS.
Fourth, this study⿿s finding that self-disclosing content can create social presence indicates that the SNS context is significantly affected by personal and emotional aspects of communication, supporting earlier findings regarding the effectiveness of emotional and personal engagement in corporate SNS communications (Huy & Shipilov, 2012). By offering new insights into how this mechanism operates, the study thus contributes to a more accurate understanding of the SNS usage environment.
Fifth, by using the intention to engage with corporate SNS, we show that the relationships built by corporate SNS accounts with SNS users are not just simple links among social network nodes but are engaging connections that may even provide companies with positive word of mouth marketing to other users.

Lastly, the study contributes to previous research that has demonstrated the importance of establishing trust in a company and of delivering useful information in relationship building between a company and its customers. Previously, Kent and Taylor (1998) had suggested that delivering useful information is one of the important strategies by which companies can build good relationships with current and potential customers and that it should be done in a dialogic form that can respond to those customers⿿ needs and curiosity. Our research advances this knowledge by revealing that the machine and person interactivities and self-disclosure embedded in a message together construct a dialogic form of communication that enhances social presence, which in turn increases the usefulness of information. Therefore, our findings suggest that increased social presence is the central factor that makes the dialogic form of communication effective in intensifying the usefulness of messages.
7.2. Practical implications
Our findings have several practical implications for managers of companies that aim to build good relationships with present and potential customers through SNS and SNS providers.

First, by identifying the antecedents of evoking social presence within corporate SNS accounts, we offer specific ways that companies can use SNS as an effective marketing channel. Because simply linking users to corporate SNS accounts does not guarantee that people will favorably assess the information they gain from those accounts, companies need guidance on how to build positive relationships with SNS users. Our study suggests that promoting social presence is one way to build these engaging relationships.

Second, our findings indicate that controlling form features by embedding multiple external links in a message is good way to increase social presence. This seems particularly useful in the context of Twitter, which is designed to deliver short messages limited to 140 characters. To work around this limitation, marketers often insert external links to direct viewers to much richer sources of information. While these links are often useful in introducing a company⿿s website to consumers, opening the link requires an additional click and therefore might be disregarded, which can make marketers worry that embedding links only reduces the available space for conveying information. Our findings, however, suggest that whether the link is opened or disregarded is not essential in terms of creating social presence, as it signals to users that a message is connected to something else and a part of a broader world. Therefore, the study suggests, carefully tailoring Twitter messages with external links can help give its viewers a feeling of being social.

Third, our findings also offer insights into how company marketers can most effectively design communications with consumers through SNS. The operation of person interactivity suggests that displaying the history of the footage of particular conversations and broadcasting other users⿿ messages is a good way to show SNS users that corporate SNS accounts value the conversation and that other people are also engaged in it, thereby providing a sense of community and increasing social presence.

Fourth, the results of this study suggest that the administrators of SNS accounts should be carefully chosen and given discretion to engage in self-disclosure, as they demonstrate that corporate SNS accounts that embed a personal touch are more effective in forming social presence. This finding is in line with previous research indicating that organizational SNS that discourage communicating personal matters are ultimately ineffective (Huy & Shipilov, 2012). Our findings also imply that to be successful, SNS administrators should be perceived by SNS users not just as representatives of the company but also as fellow SNS users. Given that social presence increases not only the usefulness of postings but also trust in the company itself, the role of the administrator who makes this possible deserves more recognition.
Fifth, this study demonstrates that relationship building in SNS operates differently from that in traditional marketing efforts. It indicates, for example, that in the case of a hedonic product, people may engage with corporate SNS accounts without an involvement with the company⿿s products. Receiving information about a hedonic product can simply be fun, regardless of consumers⿿ current intention to purchase that product. Once built, however, that relationship can lead to future purchases (Law, Bai, Ip, Leung, & Law, 2011). This suggests that managers should attempt to capture the interest even of SNS users who may not currently appear to be likely customers by promoting the entertaining aspects of their products and of SNS communications.
Sixth, these findings provide guidance for choosing which social presence former to employ when it is not possible to incorporate all of those shown to increase social presence. A lack of space, for instance, may make it impossible to simultaneously embed machine interactivity and deliver information in a personal manner. In such cases, our findings indicate that increasing machine interactivity without raising person interactivity and self-disclosure is not a good choice and that increasing self-disclosure can be an effective strategy if the product promoted by the corporate SNS account is a hedonic one.

Taken together, our results demonstrate that SNS can greatly benefit companies⿿ efforts to attract and retain current and future customers and provide insights into how corporations can better understand and employ this low-cost digital means to operate much like a high-cost one-to-one communication tool with its customers.

8. Limitations and directions for future research
This study conducted an experiment using fictitious companies and Twitter accounts to control and investigate which elements contribute to social presence formation. Although this design was advantageous for capturing trust established from social presence engendered by particular SNS artifacts, it has some limitations. First, although we believe that showing eight tweets to participants was appropriate because most Twitter users use mobile rather than desktop devices to connect with SNS (Twitter, 2015) and eight tweets can be shown on a mobile screen with a single scroll, this choice has limitations in reproducing real Twitter usage. Second, although both initial relationship building and relationship maintenance are critical to managing effective corporate communications, it is difficult to capture a continued relationship with fictitious companies created for an experiment. Therefore, future research might conduct longitudinal studies to mimic real SNS environments in which participants can continue their relationships with real corporate SNS accounts.

9. Conclusion
SNS opened an era in which customers can connect with companies and voluntarily enter relationships with them with a single click. As those relationships are clearly visible and easy to manage, the central question is not whether companies should attempt to build such relationships in SNS but how they can create engaging and lasting ones. ]]><h target="4" match="part">Our findings indicate that building social presence in SNS is an effective way to increase the usefulness of companies⿿ messages and users⿿ trust in them and thereby help companies achieve their desired goals.</h> <h target="2" match="part">This study also demonstrates that social presence formation can be easily achieved through form and content features provided by SNS and helps untangle the logic behind the operation of the dialogic form of communication on building relationships with customers.</h> The effect of fulfilling SNS users⿿ social drives by providing social presence offers an unprecedented opportunity to transform simple digital connections with SNS users into long-lasting and engaging relationships.</section>
</publication>