<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="li ying">
<journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
<time>Volume 36, Issue 6, Part A, December 2016, Pages 1144-1151</time>
<title>The structure of conversations on social networks: Between dialogic and dialectic threads</title>
<author>Stefano Pace.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Stefano Buzzanca.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Luciano Fratocchi.</author><![CDATA[ Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
Kedge Business School, Department of Marketing, Rue Antoine Bourdelle, Domaine de Luminy BP 921, 13 288 Marseille Cedex 9, France
b
Department of Industrial and Information Engineering & Economics, University of L’Aquila, c/o ex Felix Impianti, Via G. Gronchi 18, Zona Industriale Pile, 67100 L’AQUILA, AQ, Italy
Show more]]>
<doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.04.001</doi>
Highlights
<highlight id="1">Conversations on social media can be dialogic or dialectic.</highlight>
<highlight id="2">In dialogic conversations, social media users interact among themselves.</highlight>
<highlight id="3">In dialectic conversations, social media users interact with the company.</highlight>
<highlight id="4">Modern social media are characterized by dialogic conversations.</highlight>
<highlight id="5">Young users consider dialogic conversations more informative than dialectic ones.</highlight>
<abstract> 
<![CDATA[
The structure of conversations on social networks may affect the users’ perceptions regarding the informative value of the conversations. Consequently, to draw the maximum benefit from social networks, companies should understand which form these online conversations take. The paper argues that the conversations on social networks can have two forms: (1) dialogic: users interacting among themselves; (2) dialectic: users interacting with the company. Through three empirical studies,]]><h target="5" match="part"> the research suggests that users express some preference for dialogic conversations, and young users have a higher tendency than senior users to consider dialogic conversations more informative than the dialectic alternative.</h> <h target="4" match="part">These results suggest that social media managers should shape the layout and design of social media platforms to support dialogic conversations, encouraging horizontal interactions among users.</h></abstract>
<keywords>Social media</keywords>
<keywords>Online conversations</keywords>
<keywords>Dialogic/ dialectic conversations</keywords>
<keywords>User-generated content</keywords>
<section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
<![CDATA[
1. Introduction
Social media represent a radical revolution through which companies redefine the manner in which they conduct business. The new era of the Web is characterized by user-generated content (UGC) and co-creation (Kozinets, Hemetsberger, & Schau, 2008), and social media are the ideal platform for the co-creation of value. Value creation is no longer the exclusive terrain of the company – offering consumers the final output of its process – and now encompasses the direct interaction between the company and an empowered customer (Antorini, Muñiz, & Askildsen, 2012; Füller et al., 2009; Ritzer, 2014). The typical form of online interaction is that of conversations through which actors create knowledge and value (Kuk, 2006). ]]><h target="1" match="part"> There is today a renewed need to understand the best structure of conversations on social media so that the company can improve its communications strategy performance and user experiences. The paper argues that conversations in social media take two main forms: dialogic (i.e., horizontal interactions among peers) and dialectic (i.e., exclusively vertical interaction with the source of an input, such as the company’s comment initiating the thread). </h><![CDATA[Through three empirical studies, the paper investigates social media users’ preference between dialogic and dialectic conversations, both in general and in a product-related context. The results emerging from the study and managerial implications are then discussed. The paper aims to answer the question of how organizations can effectively and efficiently exploit social media by monitoring and managing the structure of online conversations.
In Information Systems studies, a “growing body of research is examining […] networks to gain a better understanding of how firms interact with their consumers, how people interact with each other” (Sundararajan et al., 2013; p. 883). The focus of those studies is in the network and its structure, while less is known about the preferences of users for a given conversational structure. By analyzing both the network structure of a conversation and the perception of online users, our work contributes to advance the knowledge on this gap by studying the preference of online users towards a dialogic vs. a dialectic structure of conversations.]]></section>
<section name="Dialogic and dialectic conversations on social media" category="background">
<![CDATA[
2. Dialogic and dialectic conversations on social media
2.1. Interactions on social media
The variety of social media available for business is striking. Today, collaborative platforms, blogs, virtual worlds, and social networks of any sort offer enterprises of any size a vast repertoire of communication and collaborative tools (Kaplan & Haenlein, 2010). A key mandate for firms is to integrate all these tools into a common communication strategy (Hanna, Rohm, & Crittenden, 2011). One aspect of this integration is to adopt key performance indicators (KPIs) that would be used as cross-platforms and would thus be viable for any of the many forms of social media.
Winer (2009) assigns a central role to the metrics and measurements of the new ways to interact with customers, especially given that “[t]here is considerable uncertainty about what metrics to use to gauge the effectiveness of the new media” (p. 112). We can distinguish two types of KPIs for business communication on social media. The first is platform-specific, like the number of Likes and shares of a post on Facebook or the number of retweets on Twitter. The second type – more interesting for companies and the focus of the present work – consists of communication KPIs that are applicable to all social media uses. In order to develop cross-platform KPIs, it is necessary to unfold the structure of communications in social media. The structure of conversations on different social platforms is a cross-platform KPI, because it may be applied to Twitter, Facebook, internal social media and other platforms.
The extant literature has dealt with a variety of KPIs, such as the size and resilience of an online community (that is the willingness to remain involved with the community in spite of variability in the topics discussed; Butler et al., 2014), the distribution of contributions among participants (whether skewed or flat; Johnson, Faraj, & Kuradavalli, 2014), the presence of a leadership (Faraj, Kuradavalli, & Wasko, 2015). However, less attention has been given to the structure of the conversation, that is how users address their comments and contributions (whether towards other users or towards a company-provided input). Online environments are complex systems made of many factors, including individual traits and technological affordances (Butler et al., 2014; Zammuto et al., 2007). The structure of an online conversation is a synthetic outcome of those factors. Therefore, the structure of conversation is a salient KPI because it can summarize that complex intertwining of factors defining how users interact online.
The vertical interaction between the company and its customers is a distinctive feature of communication on social media. This interaction can extend to other users, thereby creating horizontal conversations among users. It is through these company-customers and customer–customer interactions that value is co-created. To be useful, communication KPIs need to assess the type of structure that these interactions take, whether vertical and horizontal, that is, dialectic or dialogic, as will be illustrated below.

We can consider two kinds of interaction: vertical (between the company and its customers) and horizontal (among customers). The literature has recently shifted from a view that considers the company-customer interaction as the most valuable form of interaction to one in which a wider base of users discussing among themselves has become accepted, thus subscribing to a customer-to-customer form of interaction. The vertical interaction (company-customer) is the oldest kind of contact, born with the development of websites. Companies adopts the vertical interaction to collaborate with lead users. This interaction assumes that few lead users create the greater component of value (Von Hippel, 2005). This view usually observes a power law distribution of contributions online whereby few users account for the most part of the interactions (Johnson, Faraj, & Kuradavalli, 2014). Indeed, in social media, a small number of users account for most of the content, and only a small segment of online users are active in interacting with the company. Mathwick et al. (2008), in their study of a peer-to-peer problem-solving community, find that 25% of the community members do not contribute to the discussion; 60% do it occasionally; and only 12% regularly. These users then interact with the company and co-create value with it.
By moving toward large online platforms, the idea of the company-customer interaction as the best form of co-creation persists. Many online initiatives by companies to interact with customers involve some form of vote or selection whereby the user is required to select options without much interaction with other users. In this “empowerment-to-select”, a company can “give customers a sense of control over a company’s product selection process, allowing them to collectively select the final products the company will later sell to the broader market” (Fuchs, Prandelli, & Schreier, 2010, p. 65).
Today, social media have unleashed the power of users by adding a horizontal (i.e., customer-to-customer) dimension to the traditional vertical interaction. The development of social media brings a new light to the debate on whether company-customer or customer-to-customer interaction is more valuable. We can distinguish three types of value co-creation: value facilitation occurring in the provider’s domain, value co-creation in the interaction between provider and customer, and value-in-use occurring in the customer domain (Grönroos & Voima, 2013). The current literature emphasizes the latter two elements, exalting the autonomous role of customers, without the company’s involvement. Discussion on social media may start from an input provided by the company and scale up to involve different users in a complex ramification of the conversation. This latter discussion, though not directly referred to the company’s original input, is valuable because it enriches the input and offers a wide repertoire of ideas.
2.2. Dialogic and dialectic conversations
We can classify online conversations as either dialectic or dialogic. Dialectic processes follow the logic of thesis, antithesis, and synthesis. Each party in a dialectic conversation tries to impose his argument over that of others. In online conversations, one can find a dialectic form in the vertical interactions, when the company provides an input (a comment that starts a discussion thread), which seeks comments, votes, or other reactions from individual customers. The company then draws a synthesis from the mass of replies it receives. For instance, the company determines which new product design is preferred by the voters. In this process, there is no real interaction among users. Dialogic conversations are based on the premise that knowledge does not advance by means of opposition of different views. In the dialogic process, the parties reciprocally enrich the position of the other. While the ideas of all participants are meshed together, the final outcome is not a synthesis of the different contributions. Actually, the outcome of a dialogic process may be flexible and never final, distinct from the synthesis of a dialectic interaction, which represents an endpoint. Dialogic conversation is horizontal, involving peers interacting together. Dialogic processes have some more value, as shown by Sennett (2012), who attributes the failure of Google Wave to the fact that its creators framed it as a dialectic process instead of a dialogic one. Google Wave was an online collaboration platform. Each participant could see the stream of content on her screen constantly updated immediately as this new material was put online. Google Wave was dialectic because the contributions that received few direct replies were automatically moved to the periphery of the stream so that content sharing only involved the content with more contacts, rather than the most discussed content among peers. Instead of creating new knowledge through dialogic conversations, this dialectic process tended to create a consensus around extant knowledge (Sennett, 2012).
Social media and online collaborative platforms today are the ideal context to advance knowledge and create value through dialogic processes. For example, Wikipedia articles represent the outcome a dialogic process. Each Wikipedian works on what fellow Wikipedians wrote before, adapting her additions and modifications to the overall article. In the marketing field, word-of-mouth in the era of traditional media (and the first Internet) consisted of users forwarding their impressions to other users, forming a general opinion through a dialectic addition of individual opinions. In modern social media, bloggers insert the promoted brand in their narratives (Kozinets et al., 2010), thus creating dialogic interactions between their stories and the brand. In collaborative innovation, the notion of “coat-tailing” (Hemetsberger & Reinhardt, 2009) is another example of a dialogic process. Collaborative innovation projects, such as open-source software, rely on uncoordinated efforts of dispersed actors with no central authority. Coat-tailing is the process through which the tensions of individual efforts are overcome so that individual action is inscribed into the collective aim (Hemetsberger & Reinhardt, 2009). This is another instance of dialogic, as opposed to dialectic, interaction because the dialogic process shapes the individual effort to fit with the collective activity and generate a final outcome (e.g., open-source software) that is not the sum of the single effort, but their collective configuration. Overall, a conversation involving a horizontal interaction among users may be considered more dialogic than the one-to-one dialectic interaction between the company and the users.
Does social media express more dialogic interactions than dialectic ones? A study on baseball fans using the hashtag #WorldSeries showed that 87% of the messages originated from laypersons, instead of companies or organizations; 23% of the tweets were a form of interactivity, that is, a communication between parties; 30% of the tweets were horizontal, with fans referring to other fans; and less than 5% referred to a company or product (Blaszka et al., 2012). These results, though limited to a sporting event, show that the bulk of social media content is between users. Analogously, a study in a different sector, that of food, showed that interactions among customers on Twitter formed a relevant part of the conversations while “a few messages were simply brief responses [by the company] to customers’ tweets about their purchasing decision” (He, Zha, & Li, 2013, p. 468). Yardi and boyd (2010) analyze the Twitter interactions of users commenting on a fiercely debated breaking news. They discover that most interactions occurred among users: among the 11,017 tweets analyzed, 3582 (33%) commented on the tweets of other users (dialogic conversation) (Yardi & boyd, 2010). The authors also observe “that most users did not interact with most news sources” (2010, p. 321), which means a limited number of interactions with the organization-made content. This result is in line with the idea of the presence of dialogic conversations on social media.
2.3. Network analysis and dialogic/dialectic conversations
Network analysis (Borgatti et al., 2012; Wasserman & Faust, 1994) visualizes relationships as edges between interactive subjects, which are represented by nodes. Comments and replies in an online conversation form a network where each node is a comment (or other kinds of content) or an actor. Two main streams of literature apply the social network analysis and are useful to address the structure of online conversations: studies of social sciences focused on online deliberations and the Information Systems literature on online interactions. The first stream of literature shows the advantage of a dialogic conversation. The Information Systems literature focuses on the structure of the interactions.
Concerning the first stream, a context where the benefits of a dialogic structure has been studied is that of online deliberative discussions, that are discussions where a group of people need to reach a consensus around a decision through a debate. Gonzalez-Bailon, Kaltenbrunner, and Banchs (2010) have analyzed online political discussion groups and demonstrate that deliberation as well as the ultimate quality of the entire discussion depend on how the process of discussion is shaped in terms of the number of comments and their structure. As the authors claim, “not all networks allow the same flows of information, and […] users might form different networks even when using the same internet technology” (p. 2). The authors show that the outcome of a discussion thread depends on the number of comments (the width of the discussion) and the number of nested layers in the network (the depth), which refers to comments in reply to previous comments. We can conclude that the configuration of a social media conversation – in terms of its balance between vertical and horizontal interactions – affects its final outcome.
The deliberation taken by an online group is of high quality when subjects interact with multiple individuals, instead of engaging in limited interactions with few people isolated from the core of the discussion (Black et al., 2011). Reciprocity is a recognized rule for good online deliberations. Reciprocity involves the consideration of others’ opinions and the responses to them. In addition, the structure prevails over the sheer quantity of participation. A more intense level of participation does not account for the most deliberative contribution. In fact, a high number of comments may indicate an ongoing conflict, rather than a positive participation (Black et al., 2011). For some observers, the Internet does not take the structure of a democratic and deliberative context. During electoral campaigns, Twitter users may indulge in multiple retweets of few sources (preferred politicians and media) and not engage in exchange of opinions with other users (Borondo et al., 2014). Some studies suggest that in online political discussions the majority of comments are not replies to other comments, but just affirmation of one’s view. This situation would bring far from a deliberative discussion and towards a polarization or balkanization of the political debate (Wright & Street, 2007). These remarks confirm that the dialectic structure (represented by subjects affirming their view, rather than elaborating others’ opinions) have negative effects on the conversation. The design of the online space can affect the structure of the conversation, increasing the frequency of replies to messages previously posted (Wright & Street, 2007).
In the “information systems research, social network analysis is being used extensively to study digital and online social networks” (Faraj et al., 2015, p. 397). The studies of the Information Systems literature on the structure of discussions within online communities provide supporting theories regarding the preference of individuals for a dialogic structure instead of a dialectic one. Within the boundaries of organizations, enterprise social media are characterized by dialogic exchanges of question-answer that create knowledge. The interactions include “symbols and functions that allow for communication in the form of dialogues, through which knowledge contributors can adjust their messages in response to the relational and individual aspects they observe from the knowledge seeker’s logs and profiles in the network” (Beck, Pahlke, & Seebach, 2014, p. 1246). Knowledge accrues through interactions where the reciprocal relation between the seeker and the contributor of knowledge (that is their dialogue) matter more than other factors, such as the search for reputation or the level of identification with the community.
Outside enterprise social media – and thus in the proper social media context – the notion of reciprocity applies, that “is the tendency of any two participants (a dyad) to maintain mutuality in their relationship (see Wasserman & Faust 1994). Indirect reciprocity is the tendency of a participant to maintain symmetry in their relationship with the community” (Johnson, Faraj, & Kuradavalli, 2014, p. 798). There is the tendency to reciprocate a specific person within a community online and to give back to the whole community in relation to what one has received. Direct and indirect reciprocity explain online interactions more than the assumption that people in online communities interact only with popular others (preferential attachment). In fact, “network exchange patterns in online community communication networks are characterized by direct reciprocity and indirect reciprocity patterns and, surprisingly, a tendency away from preferential attachment” (Faraj & Johnson, 2011; p. 1464). These tendencies towards reciprocity lead to expect that individuals would prefer a dialogic structure of conversation, because it is the structure where one can full express and find reciprocity. Instead of focusing on the content provided by a single source (dialectic interaction), even a popular one, the subject engages in horizontal exchanges with her peers (dialogic interaction).
Finally, in online communities, sociability is a key characteristic. It fosters participation and enlivens the interactions. Sociability takes form of answering others’ questions and engaging in dialogic interactions. In fact, “the simple act of responding to others has been shown to influence the continued participation of new members, even if the response does not answer the newcomer’s question” (Farajet al., 2015, p. 396).
The extant streams of literature, from different points of views, acknowledge that the dialogic structure has a variety of benefits compared to the dialectic structure of an online conversation. Previous studies also show that dialogic structures are common in online interactions. However, those studies do not address the preference of users between the two structures. The present work contributes to cover this gap. We can expect that, given the (1) advantages of a dialogic structure and (2) the tendency of online users to engage in a dialogic conversation, individuals would prefer a dialogic to a dialectic structure of online conversation. We can formalize the following research question.
RQ1

Do social media users consider dialogic conversations more informative than dialectic conversations?


2.4. Young and senior users with respect to dialogic/dialectic conversations
The literature recognizes that the behavior of young social media users is different from that of senior users (boyd, 2007; Hayta, 2013). For instance, in some cultures, teenagers actively seek to post content online that would spark reactions from their friends, and content that fails to achieve this aim is often removed (Almansa, Fonseca, & Castillo, 2013). Teenagers tend to manage their social media profiles as a form of impression management to develop and consolidate their identity (boyd, 2007). This rich behavior of self-building can stimulate conversations among young users.
As for senior users, Spiliotopoulos and Oakley (2013) find that age is positively correlated with the use of Facebook for “social identity” purposes, which include organizing events, joining groups, and communicating with like-minded people. A user can conduct these activities via a dialectic structure. For instance, organizing an event on Facebook implies the simple action of registering for the event by pressing a button. This would suggest that dialectic may be a key form of conversation for older users. Other motivations for using Facebook, such as reconnecting with old friends or exploring new social connections, are not characteristic of senior users. On the contrary, younger users, such as students, use Facebook to keep in touch with current social ties and to maintain pre-existing relationships (Ellison, Steinfield, & Lampe, 2007). These types of connections are likely nurtured by dialogic conversations. Students report social connectivity as an essential motivation to use Facebook and instant messaging (Quan-Haase & Young, 2010), and social connectivity requires some degree of dialogic conversation. In addition, for students, age is negatively associated with the frequency of Facebook use, and Facebook use is then positively associated with sociability (Quan-Haase & Young, 2010). This implies that younger users use Facebook for sociability purposes, which implies dialogic use.
We can expect a different preference for dialogic and dialectic conversation depending on the age of the user. In particular, younger users may prefer dialogic conversations compared to senior users.

The following research question addresses this issue.
RQ2

Do young and senior users differ in terms of their preference towards dialogic vs. dialectic online conversations?]]></section>

<section name="Empirical studies: users’ perceptions of the structures of online conversations" category="results">
<![CDATA[
3. Empirical studies: users’ perceptions of the structures of online conversations
As noted above, there is no much knowledge about the perceptions of users on dialogic vs. dialectic structures. We therefore illustrate the empirical study addressing the perceptions of users. Study 1 addresses RQ1; Study 2 and 3 address RQ2. Study 1 assesses the general preference of online users for dialogic or dialectic conversations. Study 2 analyzes the difference between young and senior users in terms of their preference. Finally, Study 3 adopts a product-related conversation among online users to investigate whether the preference between young and senior users applies to a market context. Study 1 and 2 employ the platform of Google Consumer Surveys; Study 3 adopts an experimental design and employs a different online platform to collect data.

3.1. Study 1: survey on users’ preference between dialogic vs. dialectic conversations
The method employed is an online survey, specifically Google Consumer Surveys. The system allows one to pose a question as a pop-up window to a random sample of US online users while they are navigating online. The possible survey designs are necessarily simple as the pop-up window may contain short stimuli or questions, but this method presents key benefits, such as (1) the number of reachable online users is large and varied and can thus provide insights into actual behaviors; (2) online users reply in their natural environment while browsing online; this feature eliminates the limitations of lab-like research. In addition, the service provider draws socio-demographic data from the respondents, which may be used in the data analysis. According to an assessment by the research institute Pew Research Center, for some socio-demographic parameters, “the profile of internet users who respond to Google Consumer Surveys is similar to that of internet users in Pew Research Center surveys” (Keeter & Christian, 2013). Moreover, some past contributions have adopted Google Consumer Surveys for empirical studies (e.g., Perera & Zaslavsky, 2014).
The aims of the survey in study 1 was to explore whether social media users considered dialogic conversations more informative than dialectic ones. We posed the question, “Consider a conversation or thread on a social network. In your view, which type of conversation is more informative?”. Two answer options were provided: “People replying to each other” (dialogic structure) and “People replying to the initial comment” (dialectic structure). The question generated 1031 impressions and a response rate of 28%. The final sample consisted of 289 US online users. Table 1 shows the socio-demographic data of the respondents in survey 1.
Table 1. Inferred socio-demographic data of the sample in survey 1 (source: Google Consumer Surveys).
Group	Response	Non-response	Internet Population	Bias
Gender
Male	64.8%	62.3%	48.0%	16.8%
Female	35.2%	37.7%	52.0%	−16.8%
Age
18–24	5.0%	11.3%	14.1%	−9.1%
25–34	12.5%	11.3%	19.4%	−6.9%
35–44	18.3%	17.8%	18.7%	−0.4%
45–54	16.7%	12.7%	19.4%	−2.7%
55–64	35.0%	30.2%	16.0%	19.0%
65+	12.5%	16.7%	12.3%	0.2%
US region
Midwest	44.6%	39.9%	22.0%	22.7%
Northeast	12.9%	19.0%	18.9%	−6.0%
South	17.2%	24.1%	35.3%	−18.1%
West	25.3%	17.0%	23.8%	1.5%
With respect to the overall US Internet population, in our sample some differences emerged in terms of gender and the 18–24 and 55–64-year age groups (differences in terms of region of residence are less relevant for a study addressing digital habits); however, the overall root-mean-square error was 0.061. The differences in terms of age were also addressed in study 2 (see below).

Table 2 presents the results of the survey in study 1.
Table 2. Results of study 1: the informative value of dialectic/dialogic conversations.
Consider a conversation or thread on a social network. In your view, which type of conversation is more informative?
People replying to each other	51.6% (+5.7/−5.7)
People replying to the initial comment	43.9% (+5.8/−5.6)
Other	4.5% (+3.0/−1.9)
The results address RQ1 by showing a slight preference for dialogic conversations as a more informative structure; however, there is no significant difference in terms of the preference between the dialogic and dialectic structures. In the analysis of the results for the different segments of respondents, young users (18–24 years) showed a higher preference for dialogic conversations compared to the rest of the population: 88.2% of young users considered the situation of “People replying to each other” as more informative compared to 50.9% of the rest of the sample. To increase the robustness of this result, to address RQ2, and given the limited number of young respondents in survey 1, a specific survey (study 2 below) was conducted.

3.2. Study 2: comparative survey between young and senior users
To investigate the differences between young and senior social media users, as suggested by RQ2, we conducted two new parallel surveys (using the Google Consumer Surveys platform described in Study 1). One survey targeted young users (18–24 years), and the other targeted senior users (55+ years). For both surveys, we posed the same question of the previous survey (i.e., “Consider a conversation or thread on a social network. In your view, which type of conversation is more informative?”).

Table 3 shows the results of the answers by the two targets. Each cell in Table 3 contains the number of subjects indicating their preferred conversation structure.
Table 3. Results of survey 2: comparison between young and senior social media users.
Consider a conversation or thread on a social network. In your view, which type of conversation is more informative?
Young users (18–24)
N = 119	Senior users (55 + )
N = 163
Dialogic structure
(“People replying to each other”)	72	79
Dialectic structure
(“People replying to the initial comment”)	47	84
The differences between young and senior users were statistically significant: the odds ratio was 0.61 and its 95% confidence interval did not include 1 (lower limit: 0.380; upper limit: 0.991; log odds ratio: −0.48; SD: 0.244). The Fisher exact test reported a p value of 0.053, which was slightly higher than the 0.05 threshold, and the chi-square test reported a value of 4.01 (p = 0.045).
]]><h target="5" match="part">The results show that, compared to senior users, young social media users prefer dialogic conversations to dialectic ones. Young users consider this dialogic structure more informative that senior users.</h>
<![CDATA[
3.3. Study 3: product threads
Studies 1 and 2 assessed the general preferences of users toward dialogic or dialectic conversations, regardless of the context (social issues, politics, entertainment, or others). Study 3 now focuses on threads that make reference to products. This study therefore assessed the relevance of structure of conversations in a managerial context. To enrich the methods used, and to avoid bias due to the adoption of a single method, study 3 was based on a different type of input from the respondents. We prepared two fictional threads whereby a fictional company X asked its customers for advice on the color of its new phone (Fig. 1). The threads where identical in content, however, they differed in their structure: thread A was dialogic, with users answering to each other, forming a chain of comments; thread B was dialectic, representing users answering only to the company’s comment. The threads were kept short for comparative purposes and to increase their readability. To avoid effects in relation to brand familiarity and brand attitude, we did not to use real brands. With a fictional brand, respondents could focus on the comments and their structure rather than the brand’s features.
Fig. 1
Download high-res image (600KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Dialogic thread (A) and dialectal thread (B).
To run study 3, we adopted a crowd-working service (Crowd Flower) that allowed us to design more complex surveys and address an international sample (made of respondents who are paid by the platform a small amount of money for their participation). The adoption of a different platform for data collection (instead of Google Consumer Surveys used in the first two studies) would also reduce the common method bias. Each anonymous participant was required to review the two threads and answer questions measuring their evaluation of the threads and their willingness to participate in one or the other conversation. Socio-demographic data were also requested. To avoid order-related effects due to the presentation of the two threads, we ran two distinct waves of data collection with two distinct samples, changing the order of presentation of the two threads (so that the dialogic thread A was on the right for the first data collection and on the left for the second). The questions assessed which of the two threads was more informative. The 5-point items on the scales had the form of a semantic differential, with “Thread B” and “Thread A” as poles, so that 5 indicated the maximum preference for the dialogic thread and 1 illustrated the maximum preference for the dialectic thread.

The final sample consisted of 224 individuals. The modal age cohort was 25–34 years (39.3%), followed by 18–24 years (26.8%) and 35–44 years (20.1%). The sample consisted of 66.7% of male respondents. The majority of respondents held a bachelor’s degree (36.7%) or a master’s degree (16.2%). On a 1–5 scale, the average self-reported English proficiency was 4.0 (SD 0.84). Forty-seven countries were represented, with India (12.9%), Romania (7.7%), Bulgaria (6.3%), and Great Britain (5.8%) reporting the majority of respondents. In the previous week, the majority of respondents (51.3%) spent at least one hour per day in social networks, with 17.1% spending three hours per day or more.

Table 4 reports on the ANOVA analysis with the five age cohorts (from 18 to 24 to over 55) as categorical independent variables; the dependent variable is the preference for the dialogic thread as more informative.
Table 4. ANOVA: the effects of age on the preference for dialogic conversations as more informative.
Squared sum	Degrees of freedom	Squared mean	F	Significance
Inter-groups	16.983	4	4.246	2.076	0.085
Intra-groups	447.856	219	2.045		
Total	464.839	223			
The results of the ANOVA are not strong as they are significant at the 90% level, but they suggest a difference among the age cohorts as per their preference for dialogic conversations as more informative. As Fig. 2 shows, the preference for dialogic conversations decreases with age.
Fig. 2
Download high-res image (267KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Preference for dialogic conversations for different users according to age.
The results were reinforced by introducing a control variable in a regression analysis (Table 5). By considering the intensity of the use of social media as control variable, age had a significant negative coefficient (−0.152, p < 0.01). Other models introducing different control variables, such as educational level and gender, did not alter these results.
Table 5. Regression analysis (dependent variable: preference for dialogic conversations as more informative).
Non-standardized coefficients		Standardized coefficients	t	Sig.
A	Standard error	Beta		
(Constant)	2286	0.335		6.821	0.000
Age	−0.199	0.088	−0.152***	−2.252	0.025
Intensity of social media use	0.107	0.059	0.123	1.826	0.069
***
p < 0.01.
The results of Study 3 suggest that young users – compared to senior users – prefer dialogic structure in product-related online conversations.]]></section>
<section name="Discussion and conclusions; Limits and future research" category="conclusion">
<![CDATA[
4. Discussion and conclusions
Conversation structures in social networks play a crucial role. A simple Like, retweet, or single replies to online content cannot satisfy a company’s need for a rich conversation around content posted online.]]><h target="2" match="part"> Dialogic conversations are richer than dialectic conversations because they engage users in interactions among themselves rather than simple interactions with the initial content.</h> Modern forms of social media (e.g., Facebook) are more likely to host dialogic conversations than past social networks (e.g., newsgroups). Users, however, do not express a clear preference for dialogic or dialectic conversations. A social media user likely changes his/her style of interaction according to the content. For instance, he/she may comment on the tweet of a celebrity (dialectic interaction) and engage with other users on a long thread discussing a different issue (dialogic).
A result of the study is that young users tend more toward a dialogic structure of conversation. This does not mean that senior users do not engage in dialogic conversations online. As the results of our survey suggest, users can freely adopt a dialogic or dialectic structure, and the preference is relative and not absolute.

These results provide social media managers with some KPIs to monitor and manage. Through the design of their social media platforms, and a careful crafting of their online posts, companies can stimulate dialogic or dialectic conversations according to the aim/s they pursue. <h target="3" match="part">A company can stimulate dialectic conversations whenever it needs a more direct and simple form of interaction.</h> Systems such as voting for different options may stimulate dialectic conversations. Dialogic conversations are richer and are useful for more creative and complex tasks, such as proposing new ideas and helping with the launch of new products. At a practical level, the social media manager can provide open tasks, such as commenting on a Twitter hashtag, or repost/retweet users contributions so that other users can comment on it and hopefully create a dialogue. On Facebook, the distinction between community and page becomes essential. The layout of a Facebook community fosters dialogic conversations, because the comments of users are all at the same level. On the contrary, the layout of Facebook page gives prominence to the company’s posts, limiting dialogue and enhancing dialectic interactions. Social media managers can thus select layouts for the unfolding of dialogic conversations. Layouts that allow collective dialogues can encourage cooperative conversations among users.
Some modern online platforms try to provide tools for a dialogic structure of conversations. It is the case of Slack, an online team collaboration tool. The design of Slack is based on persistent chat rooms. Users can participate in some of these discussion rooms, so that the number of users is limited enough to achieve efficient interactions on a given topic. Slack was developed as an internal software of Glitch, an online videogame. This root in videogames is coherent with the results that younger users prefer dialogic interactions.

Also Facebook has added a dialogic dimension to its layout, to increase the user engagement. In 2013, Facebook introduced the option of replying to individual comments of other users in addition to replies to the opening comment of a thread. In the words of Lavrusik (2013), Journalism Program Manager of Facebook, “After months of testing, we have seen how the new feature can improve conversations and be used to start open dialogues with the community”.
Given the above reflections, a useful KPI for social media managers is a measure of dialogic vs. dialectic conversations. By adopting the measures of social network analysis, a manager can assess the dialogic/dialectic structure by considering the degree of centrality of comments. A comment by the company receiving exclusively incoming comments by users has the maximum degree of centrality and the other comments has a zero centrality; it is a dialectic interaction. On the contrary, if the comment sparks a conversation among users, those comments get some degree of centrality too and the initial comment reduces its degree score. The average centrality degree of the comments can provide the social media manager with a first proxy of the dialogic or dialectic structure of the conversations.

Companies can draw the maximum benefit from the preferences of audiences with respect to conversational structures. In particular, by segmenting users according to their age, social media managers might expect young users to assign a higher informative power to dialogic conversations.

5. Limits and future research
In our research, respondents were presented with a simulation of dialogic and dialectic conversations. This research design ensures that the respondents would focus on the structure of the conversation rather than the specificities of its content. However, this design presents a limit that future researches can overcome, by studying the preference of users with respect to real conversations. The study asked respondent to evaluate conversations in which they were not involved. Further studies can improve this limit by focusing on users experience with their own conversations.

Future researches may address the issue of personal traits, in addition to age, that may explain the preference towards a given type of online interaction. Among the possible traits we can mention the user expertise with online tools, the involvement in the topic, the individual tendency to reciprocate. Future research can also improve the results of the present work by deepening the investigation of whether the different social network platforms stimulate different types of conversations. Finally, an area requiring further investigation is the outcome of the types of conversations across different contexts, such as general discussions, product innovation, and communication.</section>
</publication>
