<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="li ying">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 3, June 2016, Pages 348-359</time>
    <title>Information management for innovation networks—an empirical study on the “who, what and how” in networked innovation</title>
    <author>Sven-Volker Rehm. </author>Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Lakshmi Goel. </author>Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Iris Junglas.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacec. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
WHU—Otto Beisheim School of Management, Burgplatz 2, 56179 Vallendar, Germany
b
University of North Florida, Coggin College of Business, 1 UNF Drive, Jacksonville, FL 32224, USA
c
Florida State University, College of Business, 821 Academic Way, Tallahassee, FL 32306, USA
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2015.11.004</doi>
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">Innovation networks are vital in advancing new product and service development for small and medium enterprises.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">Three principal challenges have to be overcome when forming innovation networks: building partnerships, integrating value contributions, and coordinating innovation processes.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">Information systems play a central role in tackling these three challenges.</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">Information management must pay attention to managing the aspects of “who, what and how” in networked innovation.</highlight>
    <abstract> 
      
<h target="1" match="part">Innovation networks are vital in advancing new product and service development. Particularly for small and medium-sized enterprises, partnering within innovation networks allows to enlarge innovation capabilities and to reach new markets.</h> <![CDATA[In order to create effective innovation networks, however, firms are required to adapt to the network. To do so, ]]><h target="2" match="part">they must overcome three principal challenges: they need to build partnerships, integrate the partners’ value contributions, and coordinate innovation processes.</h> <h targey="3" match="part">We followed three innovation networks over a three-year period and examined how they successfully used information systems (IS) to respond to these challenges.</h> On the basis of their experiences we identify IS categories and measures that support setting up an information management for networked innovation.<h target="4" match="part"> We explicate relevant tasks for managing the aspects of “who, what and how” in networked innovation.</h></abstract>
    <keywords>Innovation network</keywords>
    <keywords>New product development</keywords>
    <keywords>Small and medium enterprise</keywords>
    <keywords>IS Infrastructure</keywords>
    <keywords>Networking </keywords>
    <keywords>Partnership</keywords>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
New Product Development (NPD), or the process of bringing a novel product or service to market, can be difficult to accomplish. The assumption that one firm is able to do it on its own mostly applies to large corporations (Tushman & Anderson, 1986; Christensen, 1997). But even large corporations, to a rising degree, rely on the resources, processes and skill sets of others. Joint business developments, licensing, venturing, and spin-offs are just some of the strategies that large corporations use to bring a product or service to its fruition (Ahmed & Shepherd, 2010). Consequently, a large number of innovations reaching the market today are not introduced by one firm alone, but by a set of partners. These partners have agreed to temporarily join forces as part of an innovation network (Rehm, Goel, & Junglas, 2015). Particularly for small and medium-sized enterprises (SMEs) that lack the size, breadth and experience to shoulder innovation efforts on their own, innovation networks are often the only way to outdo larger competitors (Chesbrough, 2003).
The strategic benefits that an innovation network brings to an individual organization are plentiful (Davenport, Leibold, & Voelpel, 2006). Reaching and opening new markets is just one of them; another is the prospect of forming long-term partnerships that outlast several NPD projects and pave the way for future innovations (Chesbrough, Vanhaverbeke, & West, 2006). By the same token, participating in innovation networks poses significant task requirements (Pisano & Verganti, 2008; Davenport, De Long, & Beers, 1998; Popadiuk & Choo, 2006): SMEs are required to systematically seek and integrate complementary knowledge and know-how outside their own core competences along with effective cooperative innovation processes using a network of partners (Esterhuizen, Schutte, & Du Toit, 2012). ]]><h target="2" match="part">The use of information systems (IS) is therefore key to innovate in networks—even if the NPD objective is still obscure at the onset of the project.</h><![CDATA[ As an entrepreneur of our study explained:
“Right now – I am not completely sure what the start of this idea is – but I am sure that, with the possibility to build a network, it is possible to develop products and services, and the (participants) are really able to exchange all information without huge problems and staying fully informed in real time.”

1.1. Analysis scheme for an empirical study of three innovation networks
To find out how IS help to innovate in networks, we studied three innovation networks of SMEs over a three-year period. Our analysis unveiled three core challenges:
A.
Building partnerships (Who).

B.
Integrating value contributions (What).

C.
Coordinating innovation processes (How).


These three challenges can be understood as three basic questions that need to be answered to implement a comprehensive information management in an innovation network (see Fig. 1).
Analysis scheme defining the three challenges of “who, what and how” in…
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Analysis scheme defining the three challenges of “who, what and how” in networked innovation.
During our study, we observed that each innovation network is unique in its objective. Likewise, we learned that each innovation network is unique in the way it goes about building partnerships (addressing the question: who?), the way it integrates the distinct value contributions of partners (addressing the question: what?), and the way it coordinates innovation processes (addressing the question: how?). The right combination of these factors of Who–What–How is instrumental to the success of innovation networks (see Table 1). Since partners usually bring different capabilities and qualifications to the table, they are required to mutually adjust in order to leverage the partners’ specific know-how and experience and to extend their market potential with their partners’ capacities (Pavlou & El Sawy, 2006; Johannessen & Olsen, 2010). The networking partners need to get to know each other, communicate the contributions that they are able to provide, and develop a joint process to manage innovation. Hence, they need to develop a joint information management as a basis for their cooperation. IS act as facilitators in this respect; their technological details and implementation however, depend on the actual innovation project and its objective.
Table 1. Who, what and how in innovation networks as the three core challenges.
Challenge	What it is about?	What are the benefits for SMEs?
A. Who: building partnerships	Finding a suitable set of partners sharing a common vision.
Achieving agreement of objectives.
Maintaining flexibility to adapt partnerships.
Establishing partnerships as a strategic asset.	Acquiring knowledge from outside the firm to improve NPD capacity.
Reaching or creating new markets, and detecting trends.
Improving the capability to engage in partnerships.
Getting access to new business models and perspectives.
B. What: integrating value contributions	Evaluating the current project status.
Identifying problems and opportunities in the innovation process.
Systematically integrating partners’ knowledge and capabilities into the innovation process.
Bringing forward the innovation process in difficult situations.	Benefitting directly from partners’ knowledge, competences and resources.
Leveraging synergies from partners’ experiences.
Improving own NPD competence.
Enhancing competences and autonomy of individual staff and stimulating creative thinking.
Solving previously inaccessible technical problems.
C. How: coordinating innovation processes	Developing a shared approach to cooperating.
Implementing effective information exchange.
Remaining flexible to adapt processes and react quickly.	Improving the capability to organize NPD.
Becoming more flexible in cooperative work.
Establishing an open, cooperative corporate work culture.
Implementing agile operative and management processes.
While existing enterprise application software is often utilized as IS-support in these contexts, it has not been designed with this purpose in mind. Much is known about IS supporting specific innovation activities, such as computer-aided design or manufacturing, virtual prototyping, expert systems, or project management software. However, it is less clear which IS functionalities effectively support the various steps involved in building, integrating and coordinating innovation networks.

Many examples of successful network creation exist (e.g., Chesbrough, 2009), yet one of the key problems of innovating in networks remains “the question of how to plan, organize and control the innovation processes that are distributed over several partners” (p. 138, Rese & Baier, 2011). Developing a systematic approach to sense and seize the opportunities of partnering for innovating in networks is still an open issue, in particular when it comes to selecting effective IS (Lindič, Baloh, Ribière, & Desouza, 2011).
In our study, we accompanied three SME innovation networks, situated in the medical device, textile, and automotive safety industry. Our particular focus was on networks that targeted disruptive innovations (Christensen, 2003; Popadiuk & Choo, 2006). Each of the three networks identified for this study pursues novel products and services where the base material, design or production approach presents a disruptive force in the market space (Christensen & Raynor, 2003; Gilbert, 2003).
We explored how participating SMEs built partnerships, integrated value contributions, and coordinated processes with the help of IS. More specifically, we set out to address the following questions:
1.
What are the challenges SMEs face when partnering with others as part of innovation networks?

2.
How do SMEs overcome these challenges, and what types of IS do they use for it? How can SMEs systematically approach IS-support for networked innovation?


We start with a discussion of our analysis scheme which consists of three major challenges: who, what and how. We structure our narrative accordingly and provide evidence for each challenge as observed in one of the innovation networks of our study. Next, we analyze the use of IS in each network in response to the challenge. Based on our analysis, we discuss how IS can help overcoming network challenges and how SMEs can create a joint approach for an information management when attempting networked innovation. We provide an overview for R&D and project managers, CIOs and other practitioners about the tasks that guide the systematic use of IS in innovation networks.]]></section>
    <section name="Research setting and networking challenges" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Research setting and networking challenges
2.1. Challenge A: building partnerships (who)
The first challenge is about “who” firms want to cooperate with as part of an innovation project. It refers to questions such as: what type of partner do we need to bring into the innovation process? Who is equipped with the appropriate skills and ready to contribute? How can we arrange our cooperation? What arrangement do we aim for after the NPD project is over?

Finding a suitable set of partners who share a common vision of the new products and services to be developed is crucial. Evaluating the suitability of partners involves numerous considerations, including their level of expertise, access to resources, the level of complementarity, and their openness to engage in new business models. Often, the exact constellation of partners cannot be determined at the onset of a project, but has to evolve as the network matures. Partners need to adapt to one another, and entire partnerships might need to be re-adjusted at times—for example, when new business models become viable due to market changes or new technological developments, or when during the progression of the project a partner decides to leave the network. Dissolving existing partnerships as well as adding new ones should take place seamlessly.

2.1.1. The role of IS in building partnerships
In order to find trustful and reliable partners that are able to provide complementary competences to a cooperative NPD project, most entrepreneurs in SMEs and micro companies rely on individuals’ expertise and personal professional networks. While successful examples among large companies exist that make use of social media (Heath, Singh, Ganesh, & Taube, 2013), SMEs often miss out on the opportunity to leverage “partners of partners” in order to enlarge their reach (Kodama, 1999).
Professional social network sites often advertise the number of direct contacts versus the number of contacts-of-contacts versus third degree contacts, alluding to the theoretic extended reach an individual member has. Such numbers can be impressive (particularly in the third degree), but can rarely be used for innovation networks. While useful in general, professional social networks do not support specifying technical requirements that need to be provided by a potential partner. They also do not help match economic and business requirements. A useful IS tool would provide the ability to analytically map out the potential space for partnerships, thus aiding the identification of the required type of partner and preparing the definition of likely partnerships.

2.1.2. The medical device network
Building partnerships (or Who) was the dominant challenge for our first network, which we refer to as the “Medical Device Network” (see Appendix 1, for information on the innovation networks of our study). The seven partners of the network had tasked themselves with developing a stent graft—a tube-like product consisting of a textile mesh (graft) stabilized through a metallic wire grid (stent) and used in endovascular surgery to repair aneurysms (see Fig. 2). A stent graft is a complex product. There are several parts and services that form the actual stent graft, such as a delivery system that facilitates the insertion of the stent into the human body, as well as control processes necessary for the final assembly. Each part and service was developed and provided by a specialized partner (see Appendix 1). The use of new materials as well as the high compliance demands imposed on the medical device production process created significant pressures that necessitated the use of IS to support building partnerships within the innovation network.
Cardiovascular stent graft with its arrow-shaped delivery system
Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Cardiovascular stent graft with its arrow-shaped delivery system.
2.2. Challenge B: integrating value contributions (what)
The second challenge is about “what” contributions are provided by each partner as part of the innovation network. It refers to questions such as: what are the next steps in the NPD project? What kind of knowledge and resources are required to carry out particular tasks? How can contributions from different partners be systematically integrated?

Defining potential value contributions of each partner is a primary concern. During the NPD project, it is an arduous task to identify, balance, and merge the objectives and results of each partner’s activities on an ongoing basis. What makes it further complicated is the fact that innovations are often serendipitous and do not necessarily follow a planned schedule of deliverables. For example, an engineering endeavor might provide prototypes of varying qualities, and a shared decision has to be made about which of these should enter the next development phase. Also, the innovation network might encounter technical difficulties, or discover better alternatives, which prompt a revision of the innovation deliverables. At any point in time, there needs to be transparency of whether the contributions of individual partners are still in line with the overall vision (Johannessen & Olsen, 2011). If not – or if the target market changes – adjustments might become necessary. Then, new deliverables have to be determined that are best suited to continue current and planned developments.
2.2.1. The role of IS in integrating value contributions
Value contributions are usually determined through an initial dialogue between representatives of two or more partners. However, value contributions that have been agreed upon at one point in time might need to be revisited in light of the overall project progress. The resulting changes are often ad hoc responses to a partner’s activities, and may be documented informally by means of e-mail conversations. Such changes – which mostly take place at the operational level – make it hard to foresee, plan and control contributions. In this context, a useful IS tool would allow collaborative work to take place along logically organized procedures and would help identify, integrate and merge the value contributions of partners in a systematic way.

2.2.2. The helmet network
Integrating value contributions was the dominant challenge for our second network, which we refer to as the “Helmet Network”. The innovation network’s six partners came together to develop a motorbike helmet using a newly synthesized chemical as a dampening material for the helmet’s shell (see Fig. 3). Three partners started the project with only a rudimentary idea about the material’s potential in the automotive market. Initial lab tests substantiated their expectations about the material’s extraordinary qualities regarding safety and quality. Gradually, partners developed a comprehensive design and processing framework for industrial production. All existing designs and manufacturing elements needed to be re-engineered due to the material’s novel chemical characteristics. Support was sought from complementary partners (as described in Appendix 1). Helmet prototypes regularly needed to be compared against legal safety regulations that defined specific parameters for measuring helmet performance. In order to assess the project status and flexibly react to unforeseen situations, the NPD team needed IS to effectively identify and integrate required value contributions.
Base material, production equipment, and prototype from the motor bike helmet…
Download full-size image
Fig. 3. Base material, production equipment, and prototype from the motor bike helmet development.
2.3. Challenge C: coordinating innovation processes (how)
The third challenge is about “how” to coordinate operative processes between partnering firms. It refers to questions such as: how should firms arrange information exchanges among partners? How to consolidate and merge innovation processes? How to systematically integrate approaches as part of the innovation process?

Coordinating processes entails sharing a common approach to cooperate collectively. The innovation network needs to have methodologies in place that support cooperative work processes as well as a shared information base that can flexibly support ad hoc activities. Because of the emergent nature of the innovation process, it is important to seek out appropriate methodologies at the onset of the NPD project. This way, partners have a safe net available that they can rely on in difficult times to help them advance the progression of the project.

2.3.1. The role of IS in coordinating innovation processes
Aligning processes within innovation networks is often driven by the project schedule. Commonly, one partner takes a lead in attempting to coordinate workflows and tasks that are distributed amongst partners. Using Excel-based lists, shared via e-mail, is not uncommon. Gantt charts, on the other hand, prepared with professional office software and commonly used for internal project management are less prevalent in innovation networks due to software licensing issues. Often, firms maintain a proprietary database or file repository for technical project documentation. However, these are rarely equipped with adequate tagging or retrieval functionality and often lack the ability to connect to shared workflows.

Industry sectors with highly formalized procedures (due to compliance stipulations, for example) require IS that support the systematic documentation of cooperative processes, activities, testing and results. This ensures a comprehensive electronic account of all product and production process parameters. IS are required that can integrate with corporate documentation systems, both technically and from a process point of view, and that offer the possibility to document R&D processes in detail. Particularly for reasons of intellectual property rights protection, a system needs to be able to keep track of who contributed what.

2.3.2. The textile network
Coordinating innovation processes was the dominant challenge for our third innovation network, which we refer to as the “Textile Network.” The seven partners of the network came together to develop a novel coating technique deployable to textiles. The innovation network was initiated in response to an idea of a large interior textile producer that wanted to create a fabric coating with superior characteristics. Often called ‘technical textiles’, this type of textiles provides increased scratch and abrasion resistance, as well as heat reflection and resistance to other chemicals (see Fig. 4). A coating producer and a research services provider joined as core partners of the network (see Appendix 1). Developing such new functionalities involved numerous trial-and-errors and created high demands on coordinating processes and their support through IS.
Fabric nano-coatings
Download full-size image
Fig. 4. Fabric nano-coatings.]]></section>
    <section name="Research method" category="methods">
        <![CDATA[
3. Research method
The research for this article was part of a larger project sponsored by the European Commission (see also Rehm et al., 2015). The project involved four research institutes (two in the area of applied management research, two in technical research areas), a software provider who provided a digital work environment for the three networks, a management consultancy, as well as nine SMEs that formed the core of the three innovation networks. Over a three-year time frame the research team collected data from all partners through in-depth interviews and through observations during project and work meetings. Interviews were primarily conducted with team members who were decidedly involved with the project, and also with firm owners, general managers, R&D managers, and IT managers. In all, more than 30 people were interviewed. The data comprised more than 50 interviews of about 70 min in average duration; further research materials include more than 1100 pages of project reports and documentation, 425 pages of public documents, project reports, technical documentations hosted in a web-based team space, various collected brochures and (web) catalogues, and more than 100 pages of personal research notes.
We observed a different approach in each of the three SME networks and witnessed how they developed new products and services over the lifespan of their respective project. The gathered data allowed us to identify the challenges arising as part of the innovation networking efforts and the approaches to overcome them (see Table 2 for an overview of the three networks). Interview questions focused on the team cooperations, how team members developed shared ways of working, and how they made use of IS in particular situations. During the long-term involvement with the project, researchers gained deep insights into both the operational challenges and the strategic considerations of each partner.
Table 2. Overview of the three SME networks.
Network	Medical Device Network	Helmet Network	Textile Network
Core innovation idea	Cardiovascular stent graft involving innovative materials; improving in-body application and product reliability	Motor bike safety helmet using a novel dampening material; improving safety parameters	Sol–gel coating for furniture; later: easy-clean coating; providing novel product functionalities
Number of partner organizations interacting for production/for R&D servicesa	5/7	3/6	3/7
Approximate number of directly involved team members	35	25	30
Geographic range	Czech Republic, Germany, Italy	Italy, United Kingdom, Germany	Belgium, Germany, Italy
Specific requirements for IS support in the innovation process	High demands for building partnerships
in the heterogeneous network:
IS need to safeguard compliance to health care standards	High demands for integrating value contributions
as product design and production processes require re-engineering due to use of a new chemical material:
IS need to enable systematic knowledge and information exchanges	High demands for implementing effective operational processes
due to low predictability of R&D outcomes:
IS need to provide an agile project management environment
a
These numbers do not include partners that were only briefly involved in the NPD projects.

Each innovation network was supported by management consultants who provided advice on innovation management and application software. Based on their input, each network adopted a shared collaborative work environment (CWE) from the onset of the NPD project. This type of IS provided a wiki-based work space that comprised workflow, deliverables and project management functionalities. Each network underwent varying experiences with regard to particular challenges, and during the course of the projects adopted diverse IS, instruments, procedures and tools (an overview of these IS is given in Appendix 2). Apart from a few exceptions, for the majority of participating partners the role of the CIO was assumed by R&D or project managers, being responsible to represent each partner’s interest regarding technology adoption and information management questions.]]></section>
    <section name="Analysis" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
4. Analysis
4.1. Building partnerships in the Medical Device Network
With the creation of the Medical Device Network, participating SMEs expected to achieve a competitive advantage in the market by using new materials superior in functionality and lifespan to extant industry standards. Until then, large, older players dominated the surgical device market. Retaining the original product architecture for implanting the product into the body was decidedly important as it simplified its adoption by surgeons. However, due to the new functional design of the product, production processes and machinery had to be remodeled in their entirety. This also required the consultation of a university’s institute of physics and medical doctors, mostly surgeons, who were not considered part of the innovation network. Because of legal regulations, the time frame for bringing a new medical device to market is long-term and often exceeds a decade. For the medical device producer, as a major driver within the innovation network, it was therefore, of utmost importance to pay meticulous attention to the trifecta of functionality, quality, and compliance. Ensuring intellectual property rights as well as conducting base research on the product’s effects at in-body-conditions was also of primary concern. At the time of reporting, the project had achieved a prototypical design with acceptable functional characteristics.

A primary challenge of the Medical Device Network was to identify potential partners for the innovation project. The need for IS support was realized early on for the process of building partnerships. This was done in the following manner, recognizing the aspects of: the business innovation ecosystem, the network partners’ expertise and capabilities, and the complementarity of partnerships.

4.1.1. Business innovation ecosystem
The project idea originated when the medical device producer recognized the possibility of using an innovative hybrid material for the graft, composed of the Nickel–Titanium composite Nitinol, covered by polyester. Using a new material motivated the initiation of partnerships with the textile industry. The medical device producer established contacts with a variety of partners that seemed capable of providing suitable value contributions, including relevant know-how on material and processing methods. As a result, an innovation network with vastly heterogeneous backgrounds emerged.
“We more or less understand each other when we meet. We meet, but, after the meeting we go back and everyone more or less continues into his own direction.” (Principal Researcher/Research Services Provider)

None of the involved SME partners was able to anticipate the complexity of the entire NPD process since essential parts of the target product were far outside their core competences.
“It is difficult to find a person having knowledge in textiles and Nitinol and medical devices...” (Emphasis added; Material Researcher/ Research Services Provider)

To address this challenge, the partners in the innovation network cooperatively generated Knowledge Maps (KM) that were implemented with the help of open source business process modeling software. KMs captured value chain structures, types of partners, and the required services or manufacturing capacities that were deemed necessary for the NPD project to succeed (see Appendix 2, for a characterization of KMs).
4.1.2. Network partners’ expertise and capabilities
The selection of partners took complementary experiences in similar contexts into consideration, as well as expertise and competences in relevant technologies, and the right mix of resources to support NPD and later industrial production. Neither a clear assessment of expected efforts, nor a detailed agreement about project conditions was feasible at the onset of the project; instead, partners had to build their partnerships along the way.
“Within this collaboration I miss one person who… has an idea what’s going on in our [the service provider’s] laboratory and at the Medical Device Manufacturer. This person should have the overview of what’s going on everywhere and what the requirements are of each of the partners.” (Material Researcher/ Research Services Provider)

KMs were used and filled with information about the partners’ existing expertise and competences. These maps described the overall positioning of partners within the innovation network. They also allowed to document the partners’ capacities outside the project’s scope and to view each value contribution as a set of services available to the network. Captured information also included responsibilities and technical foci of involved partners.
“…just one click and there you find everything… This is the most important thing, that you don’t have to go from one Excel file to another, or through listings in e-mail (software). … Our head of department is now preparing lists of what the company is doing concerning each topic, and he will start to enter this into (the software).” (R&D Manager/Medical Device Producer)

With the help of KMs, partners were able to compile their individual perspectives into a shared view of the innovation idea, the involved partners, and the project. Furthermore, they helped identify knowledge gaps, and eventually knowledge overlaps, as well as the need for future cooperation partners. Separating the particular roles of each partner through KMs was also important in order to deal with the project’s complexity. In the late phases of the NPD project, for example, the Collaborative Work Environment (CWE) that was used for project management contained 15 sub-projects, each dedicated to the engineering of sub-parts for the product.
4.1.3. Complementarity of partnerships
The partners cooperatively maintained a shared Knowledge Space (KS) for technical content and other information relevant to the project. The KS was implemented with the help of a wiki-based workspace as part of the CWE. It aided in navigating the complex product development, because it furthered the understanding of technical details and links between interrelated parameters. For example, team members from partner firms could inform themselves about the practical application of the product during surgeries, and thus develop a better understanding of the relevance of product features.
“(The KS is) useful for storing key information and data related to the object of the research… (for) all key requirements from all related aspects, material, medical, and so on. Anybody can go there and look at it and immediately see... what the basic issues are, what the requirements are, ..., and so on. Usually we encounter problems related to misunderstandings concerning basic definitions, for example, restoring force or radial force... So, in (the KS) we should see all basic aspects, definitions, key parameters...” (Material Researcher/Research Services Provider)

Such insights helped in evaluating and discussing the role of involved partners. The KS was also helpful in integrating new partners at a later point in time. In this respect, the partners collected information about interesting firms, as well as about competitors and their products. Tracking functionality was important to assure retention of intellectual property rights by logging who contributed what information at what point in time. Partners who had formerly not documented their R&D efforts in a systematic way were now able to carry out tasks that complied with the high standards of medical device production.
“All the steps defined by the FDA (Food and Drug Administration agency1) have already been included (into the system). … We couldn’t do that before, but this year we had the audit… and if we want to cooperate (further), we have to incorporate all these (steps) into our design control. And we did.” (R&D Manager/Medical Device Producer)

For instance, for compliance reasons, data structures capturing the parameters of a newly developed supply material were cooperatively defined among partners. In this way, partners were able to align each other’s efforts, objectives and strategies, and the partnerships became firmer and more formalized in each step.

4.2. Integrating contributions in the Helmet Network
The core partners of the Helmet Network included the provider of the chemical base material, the engineering service provider in charge of engineering tasks, and the helmet producer responsible for product design and design-related engineering tasks, as well as marketing and business model issues. Although the partnerships were clearly defined from the onset of the project, value contributions of partners remained to be determined. Their planning and integration was influenced by a number of factors, including unforeseen events, differing modes of working, and problematic situations that necessitated multiple adaptions to value contributions. The integration of value contributions was tackled in the following ways, recognizing the need for a cooperative project and innovation management, and for innovation methodologies.

4.2.1. Cooperative project management
Contributions needed to be aligned—even in the face of unforeseen events that impacted the dynamics of the NPD project. Helmet prototypes had to undergo regular performance tests to ensure conformance to legal safety specifications. At one point, a market test in a national trade journal indicated that the prototype was already exceeding most performance indicators as compared to its competitors. As a result, a decision was made to speed up the development, which necessitated revisiting the technical objectives. Situations like this demanded a re-evaluation of the project status, and made the cooperative use of the shared Knowledge Space (KS) with technical project contents mandatory. Technical objectives, responsibilities, task lists, achieved results and open issues had to be revised. As a lesson learned from this experience, the team decided to make extensive use of the CWE to document their individual activities and progress. One team member took on the role of preparing and overseeing the structure of the created work space. This allowed all partners to quickly gain a comprehensive view of the overall situation and to proceed without the need for a detailed (and binding) project plan.
“We do not really have a strict work plan… So that’s why yes, we are collecting information, but (at the same time) we are continuously developing the material and the possible applications. That’s why we don’t have a strict work plan for the life cycle, like the precise date, but roughly we know that to provide this kind of analysis we need a couple of months for each step.” (Project Manager/Specialized R&D Services Provider 3)

Another factor influencing the definition of value contributions was the development of an interactive, cooperative working mode that encouraged sharing of information between the team members. One engineer said:
“The idea of sharing means: if I miss the opportunity to exchange information and knowledge, I lose the effort.” (Entrepreneur/Material Supplier)

In addition to just documenting, the team members developed mutually balanced work routines that allowed for regular information exchanges. This was promoted by the flexibility to combine different tools within the CWE, including wikis, workflow, task and project management applications, as well as various personal software tools for messaging, telephony, screen sharing, etc.
“It was a shift from simple positive relationships to structured relationships between companies. … Balance was critical because of the changing rules and roles…” (R&D Manager/Helmet Producer)

Together, the team configured the CWE to align individual preferences with those of the team.
“(Firstly, we used our own tools to prepare this work.) But at the end of course… we created a specific page inside the CWE where the other partners can contribute and edit the same page. So we are working on the same platform.” (Project Manager/Specialized R&D Services Provider 3)

4.2.2. Innovation methodologies
An additional factor regarding the integration of value contributions became apparent when problematic situations occurred, including events of technical problems, balancing risk factors, or deciding which alternatives to proceed with. The project team applied systematic methodologies to identify which value contributions and knowledge were required to explore viable next steps (Hidalgo & Albors, 2008). Methods such as Quality Function Deployment (QFD)2 and Theory of Inventive Problem Solving (TRIZ)3 were implemented as procedures in the CWE:
“One example is when we are using TRIZ… (this method) speaks about the possibility to split the product into different parts and analyze them and try to put the functioning a step ahead because you reduce the complexity of the product…” (Entrepreneur/Material Supplier)

Consultants of one of the network’s service providers acted as facilitators in the implementation. In workshops, they prompted participants to discuss the methods and to analyze available inputs by using the information stored in the KS. They also encouraged participants to use the CWE for creating wiki pages that reflected the sequence of activities required to carry out a selected procedure. Team members later added workflow tasks through the CWE’s project management functionality and were thus able to keep track and coordinate activities after the workshop was over.
“It is a kind of structural change, because you can do more faster than before.” (R&D Manager/Helmet Producer)

Virtual meetings were often used to continue discussions.
“When we have to fill the matrix of the QFD together, one of us takes the position to write into the matrix, showing it through TeamViewer to the others…writing directly in the CWE.” (Entrepreneur/Material Supplier)

The wiki pages dedicated to particular innovation procedures were later stored as blueprints for future use.4 In this way, a set of “applications” was created, viewed as an Innovation Procedure Toolkit (IPT). This toolkit turned into a resource that was freely available to every partner; it was used in the later stages of the project as well as during follow-up projects.
“And this exchange of information is what we do… maybe to solve the matrix of QFD—and I recognized that, and now I understand it is possible to do the job in a different way, more organized... you focus on what is the next step, to arrive at the result, more (orderly).” (Entrepreneur/Material Supplier)

4.2.3. Cooperative innovation management
Due to the uncertainty involved in the technical outcomes and objectives of the project, it was difficult to reliably plan for sequential project phases (Ahmed & Shepherd, 2010).
“At a certain moment of the project we realized that probably we need that kind of analysis (i.e., Life Cycle Assessment), not only to be aware of the environmental impact of this project, but also to have a really unique documentation and added value... It is of particular importance for the future commercial application. Not only for the helmet (prototype).” (Project Manager/Specialized R&D Services Provider 3)

Thus, the NPD team used a generic reference model of the innovation process to develop a joint perspective and to evaluate the overall project status. The reference model, which was part of the IPT, was implemented within the CWE in a way that allowed the automatic allocation of tasks and deliverables to phases of the innovation process. This way, project progress could be monitored and forecasting could be facilitated. The team used this reference model to decide on innovation methods and to re-orient the project after encountered failures. The latter was relevant for instance, when specific technical problems could not be solved among the set of partners and necessitated to contact external firms. In such cases, handing over the necessary information to external firms was simplified.5
“So they [the external firms] are testing other solutions, where some of them are maybe really interesting, but we don’t have enough data to make a decision. … Of course they needed to know more about the material, but no sensible data was provided to them, because, you know, for IPR [Intellectual Property Rights] issues.” (Project Manager/Specialized R&D Services Provider 3)

4.3. Coordinating processes in the Textile Network
While the partners and their relative contributions were known in the Textile Network, the primary challenge was coordination such that individual firm processes aligned with those of the network. This was achieved in the following ways, recognizing the need for communities of practice, for agile project coordination, and for a network-wide information management strategy.

4.3.1. Communities of practice
From its inception, the NPD team members of the Textile Network struggled to get the project going with respect to the joint use of the CWE, KSs and KMs.
“In the network, at the beginning of the project, there was some skepticism towards the CWE. They do not yet really use all functionalities. They use the possibilities which are (suggested) to them, but they do not yet show self-initiative to make use of all functionalities themselves.” (Consultant/Management Service Provider)

Partners only gradually adopted the CWE by discovering its benefits, including the availability of shared content (e.g., academic publications) and easier access to relevant information (e.g., task descriptions). The CWE, together with the KS, improved the exchange of technical knowledge. Over time, the domain experts even developed shared modes of working as a community of practice across network partners.
“Yes, we created some pages about different subjects… Now with the CWE, it is better to inform other people. When we change a page, we send a link. I think that with the CWE it’s really better to work and it’s really easy.” (Textile Researcher/Research Services Provider)

The network had originally targeted a novel sol–gel finishing technique to be used with a large customer in the furniture industry. This customer, however, was not part of the innovation network and soon signaled a waning interest in the development. As a result, the primary product idea was abandoned. Due to the existing shared cooperation experience, the NPD team was motivated enough to explore other product ideas.

After the project’s initial strategic goal was abandoned, an alternative product idea was identified through the use of a product-focused Portfolio Analysis6 as a systematic innovation method from the IPT, comparing the different finishing techniques used in the textile sector. The procedure was implemented as a blueprint in the CWE which helped coordinating partners in this critical situation.
“I see it as a logical evolution… If you can prepare a couple of templates, it makes it easier to use this type of system. … The way it works with the wiki is very convenient. … you collect all the little pieces of information there and it is already shared…” (Textile Researcher/Research Services Provider)

The idea of “easy clean” emerged—a coating where cleaning would simply equal wiping off dirt. The set of existing partnerships provided the core asset for the identification of a product alternative, utilizing the complementarity of expertise and experience present in the network.
“We can totally use all information that we have now. … Yes, we will use it and already we started to work with another customer to develop some tests to see where we can go…” (Textile Engineer/Coating Producer)

Thus, the combined use of CWE, KS, KM, and IPT allowed to coordinate the NPD team to seamlessly continue their cooperation.

4.3.2. Agile project coordination
Coordinating the team to work toward its new objective was challenging, because the new developments involved lots of trial-and-errors and required procedures for quality testing that were not standardized at the time.
“One of the typical things is of course that... the testing of something like the ‘easy-clean’ is not really standardized. Meaning that if you have let’s say five suppliers of different products for easy-clean, they might all try their own way to convince you.” (Textile Researcher/Research Services Provider)

The team had to painstakingly go through all the details of material definition, testing procedures, parameters for describing washing procedures, and even techniques for subjecting the textile samples to different types of dirt and stains. They had to carefully keep records of all interjections during work meetings and translate these diverse notes into lists of interrelated tasks as part of an agile approach to NPD. Those tasks were used to structure and inform each involved expert’s activities and to link sequences of activities to team members.
“When we have a meeting, we create the meeting in the CWE and we put all information discussed in the meeting in there... So it’s easy to... if we have to find some information about different meetings or other things, we put everything in the CWE and it’s really nice to work with this tool because I think it’s really easy to find the information and to exchange it with all partners.” (R&D Engineer/Interior Textiles Producer)

4.3.3. Network information management strategy
Although network partners in all three networks appreciated the functionality, they did not succeed in establishing the CWE, or the tools within it, as a permanent infrastructure for their respective innovation network. One reason for the failure of permanent adoption was that the software provider of the CWE could not work out a model for continued service support. Another possible reason was the lack of self-confidence among partners to continue the cooperation after the completion of the current NPD project.
“Right now (the CWE) is structured not exactly (right) for me… Because we have to grow about ten people – probably – in the factory to use the CWE efficiently. Right now we are a little bit small for this tool. It is only a feeling, but I understand it is not really helpful for me. Because for me, I have to force me to use that because I lose more time to use the CWE than I gain not using (it). This is the reason.” (Entrepreneur/Material Supplier)

However, three partners adopted the CWE for their own use. For example, they used the CWE to support their R&D departments, to connect teams dispersed across different branch offices, and to cooperate with partner firms in R&D.]]></section>
    <section name="A cross-case view: challenges and information management measures for networked innovation" category="discussion">
        <![CDATA[
5. A cross-case view: challenges and information management measures for networked innovation
While each network had to cope with all three challenges, we only highlighted the most significant challenge faced by each network. Table 3 summarizes our insights and provides a comprehensive overview of the challenges, beyond those presented in the analysis.
Table 3. Information management measures taken in response to networking challenges by the three SME networks of the studya.
Medical Device Network	Helmet Network	Textile Network
A. Who: building partnerships	High complexity of the product/service bundle requires a pronouncedly heterogeneous group of partners:
KMs and KSs are used to capture relevant knowledge.	Project planning needs to be revised ad hoc:
A shared KS provides a reliable basis to evaluate the project status.	A major network partner leaves the network:
Previous efforts to cooperate create shared resources (e.g., CWE, IPTs) which can be leveraged in follow-up activities.
B. What: integrating value contributions	The need for very diverse contributions increases project complexity:
Cooperatively structuring CWE into sub-projects mediates complexity.	Unforeseen events repeatedly impact the innovation process:
Establishment of interactive, cooperative modes of working using various tools (e.g., CWE) encourage information sharing.	New NPD objectives need to be defined on the basis of existing competences:
IPTs provide procedures to implement “best practices” in the CWE.
C. How: coordinating innovation processes	Complexity of the product places high demands on compliance and project documentation:
Growing data structures (CWE) allow to progressively integrate partners’ processes.	Critical situations arise from technical issues in the R&D process:
IPTs provide applications to continue the innovation process.	Trial-and-error approaches make R&D planning and outcomes unpredictable:
Thorough gathering of joint discussions and data (e.g., through CWE) allow ad hoc task definitions and an agile project management approach.
a
For each network, the most prominent challenges have been highlighted in the table.

We find that the three challenges are interlinked (see also Fig. 1). This means that the “right” adjustment of who, what and how needs to be re-evaluated frequently—particularly in an uncertain and often tumultuous innovation environment. For reaching their objectives, the firms in our case studies adopted a variety of software functionalities. Thus, a ‘one-size-fits-all system’ for innovating in networks seems impractical. Rather, each cooperative NPD project should create its own unique “ecology” of people, processes, procedures, tools and contents that frame and shape an adequate solution for IS support (Moore, 1993). The problem that R&D and project managers of the firms partnering in an innovation network are facing is not missing or inadequate IS. Rather, it is a constant challenge to align IS within a joint information management, to support the changing needs of cooperative innovation processes. We find that what is needed in innovation networks is a shared IS infrastructure to represent and implement the specific fit of partnerships, value contributions and innovation processes.
In our study of three innovation networks, we observed the use of specific types of application software that enabled responding to the core networking challenges. As illustrated in Table 4, these categories of IS outline a portfolio of key IS categories that can aid in addressing networking challenges. Implemented together for a specific network, they can form a unique IS infrastructure that extends the set of typically deployed enterprise application software. While most application software is directed towards supporting specific NPD tasks, the IS categories observed in this study aim at creating and managing networked relationships. In particular, they allow an SME to develop and exercise relevant competences for network management. Together with their network partners, SMEs can transfer the insights from our study to creating their network’s own information management approach.
Table 4. IS categories for networked innovation.
Challenge	IS-related tasks in managing networked innovation	IS categoriesa
CWE	KM	KS	IPT	SN
A. Who: building partnerships	Principal contributions to resolving challenge A:	◐	●	●	○	◐
Collecting and sharing information about potential partners.		X	X		X
Combining information about value creation processes, partner types and project objectives into a shared project blueprint.	X	X	X		
Capturing partners’ roles, capacities, expertise into one project model.		X	X		
Identifying knowledge gaps and overlaps between partners.		X			
Configuring own contributions as “services” to the network.		X	(X)		
Creating a shared repository on principle competences, capabilities, and services of each partner.		X	X		
Managing overall project complexity.	X	X			
Collecting information for detecting and reacting to changing market and technology trends.	(X)		X		
Monitoring and evaluating project objectives and progress.	X	X	X		
Screening partnering and business opportunities mediated by network partners.		X	X		(X)
B. What: integrating value contributions	Principal contributions to resolving challenge B:	●	◐	●	●	○
Documenting network activities and reporting activity progress.	X		X	X	
Collecting and storing relevant technical contents.			X		
Creating shared cooperative work structures and practices.	X		X		
Evaluating quality and success of project phases/tasks.	X		X	X	
Identifying and integrating multiple contributions into a systematic process.	X	X	X	X	
Implementing systematic innovation procedures.	X	X	X	X	
Implementing adaptive innovation management processes.	X			X	
C. How: coordinating innovation processes	Principal contributions to resolving challenge C:	●	◐	◐	●	○
Coordinating tasks across network partners through operative work environments, e.g. through workflows.	X				
Flexibly setting up and synchronizing ad hoc team interactions.	X		(X)		
Maintaining a shared repository of processes and innovation procedures.	X	X		X	
Implementing and adapting blueprints of systematic innovation procedures.	X			X	
Defining requirements for effective information exchange.	X		(X)		
Understanding impacts of options to proceed with regard to project phases.	X			X	
a
CWE..Collaborative Work Environments; KM..Knowledge Maps; KS..Knowledge Spaces; IPT..Innovation Procedure Toolkits; SN..Social Networking Sites. The marks indicate to what extent each category contributes to resolving the challenges: ● strong support; ◐ medium support; ○ no significant support.

Table 4 outlines how these IS categories support essential tasks related to managing innovating in networks, and their principal contribution to resolving challenges. R&D and project managers can use the set of tasks as a checklist for identifying IS functionalities and evaluating concrete application software. The mere adoption of application software from these categories, however, neither guarantees the successful application of competences, nor overall project success. But their combined and shared usage by network partners can effectively aid in meeting networking challenges. More specifically, we have learned that:
•
Building partnerships (who) can primarily be addressed through KMs and KSs.

•
Integrating value contributions (what) can be aided through joint use of CWEs, KSs, and IPTs.

•
Coordinating innovation processes (how) can be supported through CWEs and IPTs.

•
In addition, SNs are useful, particularly to SMEs, for reaching out to potential partners and for opening up new business opportunities.]]></section>
    <section name="Conclusions" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
6. Conclusions
Innovation networks are vital in advancing NPD.]]><h target="2" match="part"> We find that innovation networks of SMEs face three networking challenges: building partnerships (who), integrating value contributions (what), and coordinating innovation processes (how). </h><h target="4" match="part">Each network requires a unique implementation of who, what, and how to achieve project success.</h><![CDATA[ In this study, we illustrated how specific categories of IS help partners address the networking challenges. R&D and project managers together with their network counterparts need to establish a balanced portfolio of IS that builds the basis for a joint information management for networked innovation. By following such a joint approach, partnering SMEs have the opportunity to tap a unique potential of competitive advantage as an innovation network.]]></section>
</publication>