<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication maker="liu bin">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 3, June 2016, Pages 433-440</time>
International Journal of Information Management
    <title>Debunking the instant messaging myth?</title>
    <author>Angela R. Lebbon.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Jón G. Sigurjónsson.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
State University of New York, New Paltz, United States
b
The City College of New York, City University of New York, United States
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.02.003</doi>Get rights and content
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">Overall, IM-ing does not significantly affect work performance.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">Data appear to show IM-ers type faster to compensate for lost time due to IM-ing.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">No significant difference in completion time to type a post-hoc character number.</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">No significant differences when examining cumulative effects of 18 IM exchanges.</highlight>
    <highlight id="5">Separation of work and personal IMs demonstrated no performance differences.</highlight>

<abstract><![CDATA[
Abstract
Instant messaging is a beneficial tool in the workplace that aids communication and decision-making, yet it’s widely accepted that productivity suffers due to frequent interruptions.  ]]><h target="1" match="full">Previous research conducted with surveys and atypical IM interactions support such claims; however, prior research demonstrated with a systematic study and behavioral measures that IM-ing is not detrimental to quality and timeliness of work.</h> <![CDATA[ The current study expands the research literature by examining the effects of frequent IM-ing on productivity, quality of work, and time on-task in a laboratory setting. Data were analyzed using ANOVA and independent samples t-tests for group and IM type. Data demonstrated little performance differences between those who received IMs and those who did not. This research appears to suggest that IM-ing has some impact on overall task completion time but IM-ers productivity time was faster. Therefore, it may be more harmful to resort to the commonly held notion that all off-task behavior equates negative effects and unproductive employees. Future directions for researchers and managers are discussed.

]]></abstract>
    
    <keywords>Workplace leisure behavior</keywords>
    <keywords>Social media leisure behavior</keywords>
    <keywords>Technology</keywords>
    <keywords>Social media</keywords>
    <keywords>Interruptions</keywords>
    <keywords>Text messages</keywords>
    
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction"><![CDATA[
1. Introduction
Social media has emerged as a great source for information and interaction (Madden & Jones, 2008).1 An overwhelming majority of individuals report engaging in instant messaging (or IM-ing) and text messaging in order to maintain connections and relationships with co-workers, family, and friends (Li, Chau, & Lou, 2005; Lenhart, Rainie & Lewis, 2001; SilkRoad Technology, 2012). However, these interactions occur during work-hours and involve non-work-related messages, which are often accompanied by auditory, visual, or tactile notifications that entice individuals away from their work. Thus, speculation remains around the benefits of social media leisure behavior in the workplace.
Researchers project that IM-ing will substitute email communication in the coming years because it is preferred among younger workers and aids quick decision-making, but productivity will suffer because of the frequent interruptions during the workday (Cameron & Webster, 2004; Evans & Eber, 2013; Duggan, 2013; Rennecker & Godwin, 2003). Conversely, a small number of researchers are advocating for personal Internet access and IM-ing in the workplace suggesting it improves motivation and concentration and results in more efficient and effective workers (Coker, 2011; Oravec, 2002).
1.1. Instant messaging
Instant messaging consists of written real-time communication between two or more individuals in separate locations via the Internet. Analysts have estimated that 2.5 billion IM accounts are currently active, roughly 47 billion IMs are exchanged each day world-wide, and 10 trillion IMs are delivered annually (Evans & Eber, 2013; Pingdom, 2010). Furthermore, researchers estimate that cell phone IM-ers will increase to 1.3 billion by 2016 (Ashdown, 2011). Given that 91% of individuals own cell phones and 81% are using their cell phones to engage in text and IM-ing (Duggan, 2013), it is not surprising that IM-ing is becoming more prevalent in the workplace.
Employees report a preference for IMs (over emails) when a response needs to be delivered immediately and the topic being communicated is superficial (Spira & Feintuch, 2005). Instant messages are also preferred over telephones when more than two people are involved in the communication, or when one of the communicators is unable to maintain privacy given the presence of others who may hear the communication (Spira & Feintuch, 2005). Additionally, IM-ing is an enticing social activity that many find highly rewarding and difficult to ignore when an auditory, visual, or tactile notification signals the arrival of a new message. The pervasive use of IMs throughout the workday can be explained as a function of the immediate feedback and reinforcement that occurs after delivering a message and receiving a response. This history of reinforcement develops quickly and is always operating for individuals; especially for workers seeking social interaction, whether those reinforcers are sought as a way to escape or avoid aversive work conditions, redistribute inequity in the workplace, alleviate stress, and/or harm one’s organization and co-workers when feeling bored, unmotivated, unappreciated, or exploited.
In summary, workers are engaging in IM-ing because information and interaction are easily accessible due to technological devices (i.e., computers and cell phones) being readily available and powered on for work purposes and family emergencies. Furthermore, individuals’ reinforcement history influences their future use of social networking to obtain reinforcers. With the majority of workers using cell phones to engage in work and personal emails, texts, and IMs, employers will have greater difficulty tracking and preventing such behavior. Given that monitoring is timely and expensive, and may result in perceptions of injustice or mistrust, managers and researchers must be confident that IM-ing is detrimental to performance. However, if the possible variables affecting the relationship between IM-ing and performance have not been examined fully then researchers cannot prescribe that management endorse or punish such social media leisure behavior.

1.2. Previous research
Previous research has examined the effects of IM-ing on productivity with behavioral observation and surveys; surveys in particular have extensively described IM-ing and its relationship to work behavior (Cameron & Webster, 2005; Junco & Cotton, 2011; Ou, Davison, Zhong, & Liang, 2010; Shaw, Scheufele, & Catalano, 2007). For example, Garrett and Danziger (2008) investigated the relationship between IM-ing and work through a telephone survey of approximately 900 employees. Data showed that 49% of those surveyed either agreed or strongly agreed that they rarely completed a work-task due to IM interruptions; however, those IMs did enhance communication and work. Additionally, 24% of respondents either disagreed or strongly disagreed that IM interruptions interfered with their work, while 27% of those surveyed neither agreed nor disagreed. Coker (2011) conducted survey research with more than 250 workers who reported their weekly hours worked, productivity, and amount of non-work-related Internet behavior, and found that workplace Internet leisure behavior improved workers’ productivity by 9 percent. Behavioral research by Lebbon and Hurley (2013) appear to support Coker’s findings that individuals who spend less than 15% of total work hours on leisure do experience an increase in productivity. Others have conducted simulations and found that IM-ing is greatly restricted to lower workload tasks (Salvucci & Bogunovich, 2010) and those who are interrupted demonstrate higher levels of work output in comparison to those who are not interrupted (Speier, Valacich, & Vessey, 1999; Zijlstra, Roe, Leonora, & Krediet, 1999). Interestingly, 60% of recent survey respondents report performance improvements after Internet use (Salary.com, 2013). Regardless, one must be critical of such research using surveys given the issues with internal validity and inaccuracies with self-reported data (Rhodes & Dean, 2009). Empirical research has found that interruptions decrease task performance and produce a time lapse between the interruption and resuming work (Bailey & Iqbal, 2008; Monk, Trafton, & Boehm-Davis, 2008; Trafton, Altmann, Brock, & Mintz, 2003). For example, researchers examined the effects of IMs on college students’ reading comprehension and found that IM-ing affected completion time for the reading task, but not comprehension scores (e.g., Fox, Rosen, & Crawford, 2009; Bowman, Levine, Waite, & Gendron, 2010). While the above mentioned studies have added to the literature and provide strong implications for workers, some are not without limitation and include: (a) examination of non-work-related behavior; (b) measurement of effects through pupil dilation for mental workload, or memory tasks that are not analogous to work behavior; (c) employing dummy variables in analyses; (d) analyses that do not include quantity and quality of work, and/or (e) small participant sample size.
Research using behavioral measures to examine the effects of IM-ing on productivity with work-related tasks is not as prevalent in the research literature. Czerwinski, Cutrell, and Horvitz (2000) examined the effects of IM-ing on productivity with relevant work-related variables. The experiment entailed a targeted website search wherein participants searched for a website, typed three terms into the Internet, and selected the best match to their target website. Results found that participants took longer to return to their task after an IM and were slower to complete the task. Unfortunately, generalization problems are present due to a relatively small participant size (i.e., 9 participants) and the use of only one IM interruption. Given that researchers have found most IM conversations last approximately 4.5 min with multiple IM exchanges (Isaacs, Walendowski, Whittaker, Schiano, & Kamm, 2002), research examining the effects of IM-ing behavior with a greater number of IM exchanges and interruptions is warranted.
Most recently, Mansi and Levy (2013) attempted to fill this gap and conducted the most analogous examination of IM interruptions in the workplace. Mansi and Levy analyzed the frequency of IM delivery, and the effects on simple and complex tasks. Overall, their systematic evaluation with behavioral measures found that IM-ing did not significantly affect task accuracy or completion time. In discussing potential reasons for a lack of detrimental effects, Mansi and Levy noted their research was conducted in the field and involved short, non-task related IMs in comparison to laboratory research using work-related IMs that did demonstrate performance differences. As a result of inconsistent findings present in the literature, Mansi and Levy recommend examination of delivering more than four IMs and analysis of cumulative amounts of IM-ing on performance. Others have made similar calls for more research as much remains unclear about IM-ing and its impact on workers’ performance. For example, Avrahami and Hudson (2006) called for research on how social and work-related IMs affect performance differently, along with Fox et al. (2009) and Cameron and Weber (2004) who called for examination of the nuances of IM-ing and how such interruptions affect individual perspectives on receiving IMs (e.g., is it welcomed or viewed as a distraction).
1.3. Purpose of proposed research
In response to calls, the current research was designed to examine the effects of frequent IM-ing on individuals’ productivity, quality of work, and time on-task with more common work-related behavior and non-task-related IMs. The following research questions are proposed:

RQ1. What are the performance differences between those who engage in IM-ing versus those who do not?
RQ2. What are the cumulative effects of IM-ing on performance?
RQ3. Do IMs increase task completion time? What are the differences when accounting for time to attend to IMs and get back to work?
RQ4. What are the performance differences after receiving non-task-related work IMs versus personal IMs?
RQ5. What are individuals’ perceptions of the benefits and effects of IM-ing on their on-task behavior and productivity?

]]></section>

    <section name="Method" category="methods"><![CDATA[
2. Method
2.1. Participants and setting
Participants in this study were 38 undergraduate students (25 females, 13 males) enrolled in introductory business classes at a large urban college located in the northeast region of the United States. Participants were paid $25.00 for their participation. In order to be eligible for the study, participants had to demonstrate the ability to touch-type on a computer. Participants were experienced with IM-ing on computers and text messages on cell phones. To minimize the possible effects of demand characteristics where participants are aware of the true purpose of the study and alter their behavior accordingly (McCambridge, de Bruin & Witton, 2012), the true purpose of the study was concealed and individuals were informed that the study was investigating body discomfort due to typing at a computer workstation.
The current study was conducted in a 20 ft × 10 ft office located in the administration building on campus. The office was furnished with a desk, computer, adjustable office chair, radio, and two bookshelves containing various books. An adjoining room (5 ft × 10 ft) next to the experimental room contained a desk with a computer that was used by the experimenter to communicate with participants using IM-ing, yet remained out of view of participants during the entire experimental task.
2.2. Experimental task
Participants engaged in a simple computer typing task that required typing an article into Microsoft Word® document with a PC computer (Operating system is Windows 7). This typing task was selected to simulate an office job of transcribing information, creating internal support materials, or preparing Human Resource training documents by transferring information from one file to another file. Each participant was presented the same article to type. An experimental session lasted approximately 35–40 min, depending on the experimental group assignment.
2.3. Experimental design
The experimental design consisted of a between group design. One group of participants was exposed to the IM-ing intervention, while the other group was not exposed to any intervention. Participants were randomly assigned to one of the two groups. The experimenter used a randomizer located on a website (www.randomizer.org) to randomly draw group 1 (participants who received IMs) and group 2 (participants who did not receive IMs). As participants arrived for the experiment they were assigned to the groups in the order according to the group number that was drawn. To prevent an unequal number of participants assigned to each group, participants were grouped into blocks. Therefore, with two groups, the first two participants who appeared in the experiment were handled as one block. Twenty participants were assigned to the IM Group and 20 participants were assigned to No IM Group. Two participants were removed from the data analysis because one participant failed to return to sign the consent form, and the other participant’s data were not recorded due to a macro error.
2.4. Independent variable
The independent variable was IMs delivered via Yahoo Messenger by the experimenter to participants. Following a 5-min baseline, each participant was prompted to engage in IM-ing interruptions six times during the experimental session in 5 min intervals. Each IM interruption consisted of 3 back-and-forth IM exchanges where the experimenter prompted the IM exchange with a question and waited for the participant to respond. The experimenter sent another question followed by a participant response, and so on. The interruptions were given this schedule based on previous research that found: (a) participants exchange an average of 3.7 messages per conversation (Isaacs et al., 2002), (b) participants averaged less than 6 min on a task prior to switching to social media (Rosen, Carrier, & Cheever, 2013), and (c) short breaks provided periodically throughout a day have greater benefits than a few long breaks (e.g., Coker, 2011; Doerr, Mitchell, Klastorin, & Brown, 1986; Henning, Jacques, Kissel, Sullivan, & Alteras-Webb, 1997). Participants were not aware of this IM schedule, but were told that IMs would be delivered during the work session and they needed to attend and respond.
Each IM exchange contained simple mathematical or personal questions in order to establish analog workplace interruptions. The mathematical questions required cognitive skills to develop an answer and therefore, these interruptions simulated work interruptions. The math questions are a replication of Hsu, Man, Gizicki, Feldman, and Fried (2008) who delivered “moderately difficult” mathematical questions that required carrying a digit to correctly answer the question. The personal questions required memory recall and did not have a predetermined right or wrong answer; these interruptions simulated IMs that workers receive from friends and family throughout a workday. The questions presented to participants included the following:
Personal questions	Mathematical questions
1. What is your favorite sound?	1. What is 24 + 56?
2. What is the farthest state you have traveled to?	2. What is 39 + 44?
3. What is your favorite food?	3. What is 65 + 28?
4. What is your favorite animal?	4. What is 19 + 19?
5. If you could visit anywhere in the world, where would you go?	5. What is 36 + 39?
6. What is your favorite song of the moment?	6. What is 18 + 35?
7. What time did you wake up today?	7. What is 16 + 28?
8. What type of industry are you currently employed in?	8. What is 27 + 36?
9. What year were you born?	9. What is 48 + 29?

Questions asked during the IM exchange were randomized with 20 sets (i.e., for the 20 participants) of 9 numbers (i.e., nine different mathematical questions) per set; this randomization procedure was repeated with the 9 different personal questions. Since the questions were presented to participants in blocks of 3 questions (e.g., 3 mathematical questions or 3 personal questions; mathematical questions were never presented with personal questions), another 20 sets of 6 numbers were produced by the randomizer to ensure that the order of the blocks of mathematical and personal questions were randomly presented to participants.

2.5. Dependent variables
The dependent variables in this study consisted of: (a) 2 production measures based on the number of characters and words typed, (b) 4 quality measures based on the number of spelling errors, corrections, omitted words, and added words typed, (c) time spent on task, and (d) time spent IM-ing and getting back on task (for the IM Group only). A quality of performance index (QPI) was calculated by dividing spelling errors by words typed to account for the possibility that the number of errors typed was a function number of words typed.

2.5.1. Time on-task
The duration spent transcribing the article into a Word document file. Time spent on-task was recorded in 10-s intervals by a Visual Basic Editor macro

2.5.2. Production and quality measures
The production and quality measures included the number of characters, words, spelling errors, corrections, omitted words, and added words that were typed during the experimental task. A Visual Basic Editor macro (utilizing a frequency count in 10-s intervals) recorded the number of characters, words, spelling errors, and corrections. The number of omitted and added words were independently recorded by research assistants trained to compare the original article presented to participants to the typed article produced by participants. ‘Omitted words’ refers to words that were present in the original article but participants failed to include those words in their transcribed article. ‘Added words’ refers to words that were not present in the original article yet which participants included those words in their transcribed article. Research assistants counted the frequency of these omitted and added words during the document comparison.

2.5.3. IM behavior
A software program (System Surveillance Pro) was installed on the experimental computer to take screenshots of participants’ computer behavior in 10-s intervals, in addition to recording participants’ Internet use and IM-ing behavior. After recording participants’ computer behavior, the software program created activity logs with timestamps for all keystrokes, including an activity log for IM-ing behavior.

]]></section>

    <section name="Results" category="results"><![CDATA[
3. Results
3.1. Group differences
To help determine if typing skill was related to any potential group differences, independent samples t-tests were conducted to compare the number of characters typed and the number of words typed during a 5-min baseline. No significant difference was found in the scores for characters typed by the IM group (M = 803.58, SD = 271.46) and the No IM group (M = 831.79, SD = 325.39); t(36), p = .773). Furthermore, no significant difference was found in the scores for words typed by the IM group (M = 159.53, SD = 51.1) and the No IM group (M = 164.84, SD = 59.7); t(36), p = .770). Therefore, it does not appear that differences in typing skill and speed were present between the IM group and No IM group during baseline.
Table 1 displays the mean scores for each variable and the significance after conducting One-Way ANOVAs to determine significance (at α = 0.05) to reduce the likelihood of a Type I Error. The results show that statistically significant differences were not found between the groups for all variables. That is, participants who received IMs while working did not demonstrate statistically significant differences with respect to their productivity and quality of work in comparison to participants who did not receive IMs. ]]><h target="4" match="full"> To determine if group differences would be observed due to a cumulative effect of IM-ing, data were separated by baseline, after the 1st IM, after the 3rd IM, and after the 6th IM and compared by “session periods”. Statistically significant differences were not found between the groups and session periods for all 7 variables.
Table 1. Overall results between IM and No IM groups following baseline.</h> <![CDATA[
IM (n = 19)	No IM (n = 19)	Analysis of variance
Variables	Mean	SD	Mean	SD	F	p
QPI	0.019	0.012	0.020	0.014	0.07	0.80
Errors	16.95	13.99	16.00	10.35	0.06	0.81
Characters	5032.05	1565.47	5122.16	1744.92	0.03	0.87
Words	900.84	273.15	914.21	309.78	0.02	0.89
Time On-task	1713.16	50.01	1747.37	87.17	2.20	0.15
Corrections	−24.05	64.36	−18.68	31.81	0.11	0.75
Omits	41.26	39.07	43.53	28.79	0.04	0.84
Adds	12.37	12.02	9.21	14.08	0.55	0.46
]]><h target="3" match="part">In order to determine if performance differences would be observed when data were analyzed up to a specific performance amount, a post-hoc number was employed that each participant had obtained (i.e., typing 2340 characters). This minimum character number allowed for analysis of the percentage of time spent IM-ing and getting back to typing after an IM, and the duration to type the minimum character number. Additionally, QPI, errors, corrections, and time on task were calculated up to this minimum character number for a different analysis of group difference. One-Way ANOVAs were performed on these variables and again, statistically significant differences were not observed between the groups (refer to Table 2).</h> <![CDATA[
Table 2. Results of the minimum character number between IM and No IM groups following baseline.
IM (n = 19)	No IM (n = 19)	Mean difference	Analysis of variance
Variables	Mean	SD	Mean	SD		F	p
Completion Time (including IM-ing)	1076.84	326.07	929.47	382.60	2 min, 27 s	1.63	0.21
Completion Time (excluding IM-ing)	917.05	248.32	929.47	382.60	12 s	0.01	0.91
QPI	0.017	0.014	0.022	0.015	0.005	0.98	0.33
Errors	7.21	6.13	9.11	6.45	1.9	0.86	0.36
Time On-task	891.58	229.45	877.58	305.87	14 s	0.03	0.87
Corrections	−15.63	55.65	−13.26	30.42	−2.37	0.03	0.87
Two independent samples t-tests were conducted to determine if there was a difference between the groups for time needed to complete the 2340 minimum character number. First, the time the IM group spent IM-ing was deducted from the total task completion time [a method used by Mansi & Levy (2013) and Speier, Vessey, & Valacich (2003)], and that time was compared to the completion time of the No IM group. No significant differences (t(36), −0.119, p = 0.906) were found between the IM (M = 917.05, SD = 248.323) and No IM (M = 929.47, SD = 382.6) groups. Subsequently, the completion time of the No IM group (M = 929.47, SD = 326.072) was compared to the completion time of the IM group (M = 1076.84, SD = 382.6) to determine the effects of the additional time that IM-ing added to the task completion time, but no significant effects were found (t(36), 1.278, p = 0.209). The results show that after removing the time spent IM-ing and getting back on task from the analysis, there was no significant difference (12 s) in completion time to type the minimum character number between those that engaged in IM-ing and those that did not. When time spent IM-ing and getting back on task was included in the analysis, the group difference in completion time to reach the minimum character number was about 2½ min more for the IM group.]]> <h target="2" match="full">Interestingly, participants’ average time to IM and get back on task was 5 min and 15 s, suggesting that the IM group typed faster to compensate for lost time on IM-ing and getting back to work. </h><![CDATA[Refer to Fig. 1 for a scatterplot demonstrating the relationship between the duration to type the minimum character number and the percentage of time IM-ing and getting back on task.
Fig. 1
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Relationship between duration to type the minimum character number and the percentage of time IM-ing and getting back on task.
3.2. IM type differences
For participants who received IMs, data were analyzed with One-Way ANOVAs to determine if there was a difference in performance after receiving work interruptions versus personal interruptions. No statistically significance differences were observed for QPI, errors, characters, and time on task. Table 3 displays the mean scores and analysis of variance for each variable.
Table 3. Overall IM group results between IM types.
Work IMs (n = 19)	Personal IMs (n = 19)	Analysis of variance
Variables	Mean	SD	Mean	SD	F	p
QPI	0.021	0.013	0.017	0.015	0.69	0.41
Characters	2500.00	749.29	2532.05	825.19	0.02	0.90
Words	445.47	130.94	455.37	144.76	0.05	0.83
Errors	9.53	8.42	7.42	6.96	0.71	0.41
Time On-task	853.68	23.38	859.47	36.43	0.34	0.56
3.3. Qualitative results
Following the conclusion of all participant experimental sessions, a follow-up interview was conducted with each participant separately. The interview consisted of questions presented orally to participants to inquire about their perceptions of the benefits and effects of IM-ing on their on-task behavior and productivity.

Participants were asked how much time was spent IM-ing during the session and responses indicated that 47.37% under estimated the time they spent IM-ing, whereas 52.63% over estimated the time they spent IM-ing (see Table 4). Of those, only 16% were within 1 min or less of estimating the time spent IM-ing. When asked if it was beneficial for their work and concentration levels to IM with the experimenter, 79% responded that it was not, 16% responded that it was, and 5% responded that it was both beneficial and detrimental. When asked to describe the benefits they received from IM-ing, a good number responded by explaining why they answered that IM-ing was not beneficial for their work and concentration. Some of the common responses include the following:
“Changes mode from simple paper to thinking and answering questions”

“Kept losing where I was at in the document and couldn’t do both at same time.”

“Because I was distracted, thought about the questions after IM.”

“Got distracted, lost the line where I was typing, I had to go back and find my spot.”

“Because it slows down typing, made me unfocused.”


Table 4. Comparison of self-reported IM-ing time.
Perception	Actual
Participant	(min:s)	(min:s)
6	2:00	3:04
7	15:00	7:49
10	3:30	3:59
12	7:00	5:10
13	4:00	3:00
15	2:00	3:29
18	1:30	4:27
20	3:00	3:23
22	2:00	3:34
23	15:00	6:43
26	1:00	3:23
27	4:00	2:56
29	2:00	3:19
32	15:00	3:54
34	15:00	4:38
35	1:30	3:40
38	5:00	2:42
40	15:00	4:37
41	10:00	5:17
A sample of responses explaining why IM-ing was beneficial include:
“Took my mind off typing the paper, answering questions got my mind to think of something besides the paper.”

“Kinda helped me a because the long period of time typing made my brain hurt so the IM gave me small break, long periods with small breaks help me to stay focused.”

“At times it was a distraction and it was hard to go back to document, other times the distraction helped me focus on the topic and typing again.”

“Basically refreshed me, then got back to work without exhausted mind.”


When participants were asked if it was more difficult to get back to work after receiving the IM, 74% said it was more difficult to return to work. When participants were asked to elaborate why it was more difficult, 93% of those participants (n = 13) said it was due to failing to remember where they were working within the transcription. Of those 13 participants, 7 continued to elaborate with such reasons:
“Because I couldn’t find my place and I was rewriting paragraphs, erasing, and then typing over, kinda lost focus”

“Because I was thinking about the questions you asked before and finding where I was in the document”

“Because I focused on the questions you were asking, then had to go back and trace where I was typing in the document, would lose my place, and just getting back into the flow of typing”

“Because I lost track of the paragraph I was on. Also, thought about the last question you asked and the way I answered it”

“Because I was in a rhythm and it messed with the flow”


When participants were asked what they thought about after the math IMs, 58% (n = 11) responded that they were still thinking about the IM exchange, wondered if they responded correctly, and that it was distracting for their work. When asked if they were happy to get back to transcribing the document after the work IMs, 58% (n = 11) responded “Yes” with 45% of those participants citing that they didn’t like the math problems and preferred typing. Of the 42% (n = 9) of participants that were not happy to return to typing after math IMs, 22% of those participants cited preferring math over typing the document and 22% said typing the document was boring.
When participants were asked what they thought about after the personal IMs, there was no consistent theme possibly suggesting that response to personal IM interruptions is idiosyncratic. Examples of their thoughts included:
“Took my mind off typing, good, I liked it better than typing the paper” (n = 2)
“Wanted to keep answering more questions”

“Felt better because questions were funny and interesting”

“Easier to get back to typing the document than the math because it wasn’t as much of a distraction, because not as much thinking involved”

“Liked these because they were less intense, didn’t have to think and found that it was easier to go back to article after these questions”

“Liked those, funny questions, but kinda distracted me in a bad way”

“Felt normal typing back and forth, relief from looking at document and the words but it was very distracting because I was thinking about personal stuff, big distraction”


When asked if they were happy to get back to transcribing the document after the personal IMs, 63% (n = 12) responded “No”, with 42% of those participants citing that the personal IMs were more entertaining and fun than typing the document, and three other participants reporting that they wanted more IMs and one participant reporting that it was easier to return to work. Lastly, 21% reported that they resisted going back to transcribing the document after the math IMs, however, 37% resisted going back to transcribing the document after the personal IMs. These results possibly suggest the reinforcing nature of personal IMs makes returning to work more difficult, especially if the work is considered aversive or boring.

]]></section>

    <section name="Discussion" category="disscussion"><![CDATA[
4. Discussion
]]><h target="1;2" match="full;full">This study answered calls by researchers to examine IM behavior in greater detail, and found that IM-ing does not have a statistically significant impact on overall task completion time (see Table 2, row 1). However, IM-ers seem to compensate for time lost IM-ing. When the time spent IM-ing is deducted from the total completion time the IM group’s average was lower than the No IM group (see Table 2, row 2).</h><![CDATA[ An increase in the number of IM interruptions did not seem to change performance in the current study. Mansi and Levy (2013) found that a small number of interruptions increased task completion time on a complex spatial task, but when participants were exposed to a higher number of interruptions their task completion time decreased. This decrease in completion time was due to participants ignoring IMs when they felt that the IM was interfering with their work. The shift between detrimental and no effects was coined “the breaking point” (p. 595) and the identification of this breaking point may provide a better understanding of the effects that IM-ing can have on performance. It could be argued that the amount of IM-ing in the current study went past the breaking point, participants realized the detrimental effects that IM-ing had on their performance, and consequently sped up their typing to compensate for time lost. Future research would therefore have to focus on what characteristics cause participants to change their rate of work and break the detrimental effects of IM-ing.
Lastly, qualitative analysis showed overall, participants were not able to accurately estimate their time spent engaging in IM-ing behavior, which adds to the research literature showing inaccuracies with workers’ self-reports of off-task behavior. Nearly 80% of participants reported that IM-ing was not beneficial for their work (and concentration levels), yet data show a change of rate to account for lost work time. Perceptions regarding work versus personal IMs largely appeared idiosyncratic in its disruptive nature, preferences, and impact on returning to work.

4.1. Implications
]]><h target="5" match="part">With the prevalence of IM-ing and text messaging in organizations, these data suggest that organizations may not need to be as concerned with such social media leisure behavior. </h> <![CDATA[Furthermore, it may no longer make sense to monitor and/or block messaging behavior since little may be gained and more may be lost in the forms of finances, trust, and engagement. Given the easy access of social media and the complicated reinforcement history with these social interactions, it may be more harmful to resort to the commonly held notion that all off-task behavior equates negative effects and unproductive employees. It may be more beneficial for employee engagement and morale to allow employees to use social media when they deem appropriate since employees will likely appreciate management’s trust that they are organized and committed to fulfilling their responsibilities, especially since management hired the employee for such competencies. Additionally, the data showing that IM-ers type faster to compensate for lost work-time due to IM-ing indicates that individuals are aware of primary work responsibilities and regulate their behavior to ensure attainment to avoid possible negative consequences.

]]><h target="5" match="part">In support of our findings that IM-ing does not negatively affect performance, Mansi and Levy (2013) also found that IM-ing did not have a significant affect on task completion time (after removing time spent on IM-ing) or accuracy. </h> <![CDATA[Mansi and Levy note “if a participant performs all tasks with a set number of interruptions for each task, the interruptions cease to be disruptive in nature, because the participant gets accustomed to their presence” (p. 593). Today’s workers (and participants) are more accustomed to IM-ing and the presence of IMs in the workplace given the frequency of delivery by co-workers, family, and friends over the course of days, months, and years, regardless if there is a set number of interruptions or not. Therefore, one would need to seriously question, and consider further examination, to determine if IM-ing is no longer disruptive to today’s workers with a pervasive history of IM-ing. It is possible that this study reflects a population that is more “accustom” to IMs, especially since a set number of IMs and schedule was used in this study based on research findings of typical interruptive work behavior by Isaacs et al. (2002) and Rosen et al. (2013). It should be stated again that participants in this study were not aware of the schedule of IM-ing and work, which may be further indication that one’s history with a common schedule of IM-ing and working affects performance differently, in combination with the type of work one is completing and whether the individual views IMs as distracting or beneficial.
It is also possible that performance differences were not observed in the current study because the experimental task was relatively simple, and as other researchers have noted, interruptions do not inhibit performance when the task is simple, but is more likely to negatively impact performance with complex tasks. For example, Fox et al. (2009) found that IM-ing resulted in slower reading and task completion; however, performance did not differ on the comprehension assessment. The increase in task completion that was observed in the current study (when including time to IM and get back to work) supports Bailey and Konstan (2006). Conversely, the error-rate and corrections to their work was not statistically different between the groups, which does not support the findings by Bailey and Konstan (2006) and Speier et al. (2003), but this difference might be influenced by the task itself.
Our study also replicated Mansi and Levy (2013) with a different type of worker and in a different setting. That is, Mansi and Levy found that IM-ing did not affect work tasks associated with knowledge workers; the current study had similar findings with work tasks associated with administrative workers. The tasks that our participants engaged in did not require problem solving or locating knowledge, instead it involved routine work-behavior that would be associated with support staff and in most circumstances, would not apply to many of the characteristics that are used to define knowledge workers. Furthermore, Mansi and Levy conducted their research in the field and noted this as a key difference between other studies conducted in laboratories that did find significant performance differences with IM-ing. Our study was the first to support Mansi and Levy’s findings and was conducted in the laboratory, which demonstrates that their data were not limited because of data collection in the field, as they speculated. The current study additionally replicated Mansi and Levy’s use of IMs that were not related to the experimental task, and did involve short IM questions and answers; that is, delivering IMs that are analogous to an individuals’ typical communication style via social networking, text messaging, and IM-ing. Lastly, this study answered calls by Mansi and Levy to deliver more than four IMs by delivering 18 IMs. However, such an increase did not show significant performance differences between the number of IM interruptions.
4.2. Limitations and future directions
The current study is not without limitations and includes a relatively small sample size, a fixed schedule of IM delivery, and a lack of observation of complex work behavior. Complex work behavior could be addressed by conducting research on the effects of IMs when individuals are told they have a deadline or a performance goal to obtain. This sort of experimental arrangement would allow for systematic examination of rate of change that occurs when adjusting for lost time due to IM-ing. It would also be interesting to determine if individuals who make up for lost time and obtain the deadline/goal simultaneously demonstrate declines in quality of work as a result of rate of change. A future study could also consider increasing the duration of observation over the course of days and weeks for more analogous data collection procedures to better reflect workers’ behavior throughout the course of a full day and week. Such an extension in the data collection procedures can capture variability that is likely present in worker behavior and will allow for greater variable in the delivery schedule of IMs. More specifically, one could introduce both a fixed and variable interval schedule of IM-ing to see if the uncertainty of IM interruption results in greater distraction and impedes concentration levels more. Future research should continue to conduct separate analysis of work and personal IMs that are non-task-related since these are the most common type of interruptions in the work place, especially in the form of work interruptions that are not related to current task one is engaging in, but is related to some other work project. The technological devices used to send and receive IMs and complete work tasks should be interchanged and examined. For example, examining the effects of personal IMs sent to an individual’s cell phone and worked-related IMs sent to their computers while measuring work behavior over a computer desktop would increase ecological validity.

Another manipulation of IM delivery involves examination of IMs that are initiated by the participant versus by another individual. Given the variety of reasons that employees engage in non-work related IM-ing, it would seem logical that someone who IMs to escape aversive work situations may be more prone to greater performance declines and greater time lapse to regain concentration and work momentum. However, if an individual views the IM as a structured break that is necessary for resting and restoring energy, or is deserved as a reward for meeting a smaller self-established goal, then the effects of IM-ing may be more beneficial/less detrimental. Or, maybe the critical factor affecting performance relates to having control over the interruption. Namely, is it less disruptive to one’s thought process to choose to stop working to send an IM than to be interrupted with receiving an IM while working? Lastly, how does volume of IMs affect performance, and what is the difference in performance when IM volume is small, medium, and large? These types of analysis would provide answers to a relatively unexamined area but could also isolate whether being the IM initiator or receiver, or frequency of IM-ing, or duration of each IM interruption, or the overall percentage of work-time spent IM-ing has a greater impact on performance, both positively and negatively. For these reasons, more research is warranted on a variety of variables and contingencies (e.g., reinforcement, equity theory, counterproductive behavior) in place at one time. Until these investigations occur, researchers and consultants should be cautious with their recommendations to organizations regarding monitoring and creating rules around such off-task, non-work-related IM behavior. It is entirely possible that IM behavior is not the behavior that organizations need to attempt to change, prevent, or punish, and instead, managers may need to focus their efforts on improving areas within the job that are influencing employees to seek and use IM-ing as a tool for restoring balance as the employees see fit.
]]></section>
</publication>