<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="li ying">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 5, October 2016, Pages 773-783</time>
    <title>How system quality influences mobile BI use: The mediating role of engagement</title>
    <author>Twan Peters. </author>Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace <author>Öykü Işık.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace <author>Olgerta Tona.</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacec. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace <author>Aleš Popovič. </author>Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspaced. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspacee. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
Tilburg University, The Netherlands
b
Vlerick Business School, Belgium
c
School of Economics and Management, Lund University, Sweden
d
Faculty of Economics, University of Ljubljana, Slovenia
e
NOVA IMS, Lisbon, Portugal
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.05.003</doi>
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">We explored the relationship between a utilitarian view of an IS and its use in the mobile BI context.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">We introduce engagement to broaden our understanding of the system quality–m-BI use relationship.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">We show how mobile BI system quality influences mobile BI use through different levels of user engagement.</highlight>
    <highlight id="4">Findings contribute to the understanding of the complexity of IS use involving mobile technologies.</highlight>
    <abstract> 
        <![CDATA[
Despite the recognized value that mobile BI (m-BI) brings to firms, our understanding of the use of m-BI and its determinants are limited. In this study, we suggest that m-BI system quality characteristics may be among the factors that influence m-BI use. Yet, in the information systems (IS) literature there is mixed support for the relationship between system quality and system use at the individual level. Given there is research suggesting that engaged users are an indication of the technology’s success, we believe that ‘engagement’ may be the key to understanding the relationship discrepancy between system quality and use. To address this gap, we conducted a quantitative study of key informants who use m-BI, to understand what the key m-BI capabilities are and other success dimensions perceived as important by users. The results indicate that m-BI system quality attributes affect m-BI use indirectly through engagement, with this finding contributing to understanding of the complexity of IS use in mobile technologies.]]></abstract>
    <keywords>Mobile business intelligence</keywords>
    <keywords>Engagement Use System quality</keywords>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
Firms decide to invest in new information systems (IS) for various reasons, such as the pressure to reduce costs or to produce more without increasing costs, or simply to improve the quality of services or products in order to stay competitive. In firm performance studies, IS had been found to support timely decisions, promote innovation, and offer a means to manage the uncertainty inherent to the business environment (Dewett and Jones, 2001).
IS that possess high quality characteristics, such as flexibility, ease of use, or accessibility, have been shown to perform better and to have higher adoption rates among end users (DeLone and McLean, 2003), and consecutively promote improvements in firm performance. Many studies focusing on IS success suggest system quality is one of the most important elements to consider for organizations as it leads to higher value creation with the system by positively impacting system use (e.g. Petter and McLean, 2009; Sabherwal, Jeyaraj, & Chowa, 2006). Yet, despite the awareness of the criticality of system quality, other studies show that many high-quality systems still fail to deliver the expected results and that no relationship exists between system quality and use (e.g. Klein, 2007; McGill, Hobbs, & Klobas, 2003). This phenomenon calls on researchers to concentrate their efforts on identifying factors that could facilitate the way system quality impacts use, and hence better embed IS into business processes.
Understanding the use of technology is important for both theory and practice. As a main dependent variable in IS value/success studies, exploring use is attracting growing theoretical interest. It is also of growing practical importance because understanding the determinants of IS use helps ensure the effective deployment of IT resources in an organization (Taylor and Todd, 1995). However, there has been mixed empirical support for the determinants of IS use, and more research is needed to understand the processes and forces that shape and alter perceptions of technology use (Petter, DeLone, & McLean, 2008).
Drawing on the fusion view on IS (El Sawy, 2003), where an IS merges with its users and business environment in such a way that it becomes almost impossible to perceive the IS as a standalone tool, studies (e.g. (Orlikowski, 2007, 2010) have steered researchers’ attention to the blurring of boundaries between technical and social matters (Orlikowski and Scott, 2008). A key example in this perspective is sociomateriality in which material and social are intertwined and conceptualized as such during entanglement in practice (Orlikowski, 2007). However, it becomes necessary to untangle social and material to be able to understand what a technology allows a user to do and in what kind of way they are related together (Leonardi and Barley, 2010). Engaging with mobile devices by checking incoming emails and responding to them (Mazmanian, Orlikowski, & Yates, 2005) is one empirical example showing employees’ entanglement with mobile technologies (Orlikowski, 2007). The email notifications onto employees’ mobile devices captures their attention and consequently engages them to the point where they no longer can draw boundaries between work and non-work activities (Mazmanian et al., 2005; Orlikowski, 2007).
In the IS and business intelligence (BI) literature, BI systems are well recognized as contributing to decision-making, especially when firms operate in highly competitive environments (Popovič, Hackney, Coelho, & Jaklič, 2012). BI systems are most commonly identified as enterprise-wide technological solutions holding quality information in well-designed data stores, connected with business-friendly tools that provide users with timely access, effective analysis, and an insightful presentation of the information generated by enterprise-wide applications, enabling them to make the right decisions or take the right actions (Elbashir, Collier, & Davern, 2008; Popovič, Coelho, & Jaklič, 2009). As core systems within an organization, BI continuously advances to keep up with recent industry changes such as the ‘big data’ era (Phillips-Wren, Iyer, Kulkarni, & Ariyachandra, 2015) or the rapid growth of mobile computing (Arnott and Pervan, 2014; Hosack, Hall, Paradice, & Courtney, 2012). In the context of mobile enterprise solutions, mobile BI systems have “the potential to significantly support decision-making outside the office by providing critical (near) real-time information to mobile workers” (Brockmann, Stieglitz, Kmieciak, & Diederich, 2012). To respond to the needs of decision-makers, firms have been heavily relying on mobile BI technologies that carry the promise of improving operational and overall firm performance (Brockmann et al., 2012; Brodzinski, Crable, Ariyachandra, & Frolick, 2013; Power, 2013). Mobile BI is a system comprising both technical and organizational elements that present historical and/or real-time information to its users for analysis on mobile devices such as smartphones and tablets (not laptops), to enable effective decision-making and management support, for the overall purpose of increasing firm performance (Peters, Popovič, Isik, & Weigand, 2014). Even though m-BI is considered as a sub-field or sub-market of BI, it is complementary to traditional BI rather than a substitute. This is because m-BI differs from traditional BI in terms of the system characteristics as well as the user experience (Tona and Carlsson, 2013).
Understanding the determinants of BI use has been extensively investigated (Bosilj Vukšić, Pejić Bach, & Popovič, 2013; Hou, 2012; Işık, Jones, & Sidorova, 2013; Popovič et al., 2012). Yet, in the mobile BI field the evidence regarding the determinants of mobile BI use is not so clear. This topic is worth exploring because mobile BI is introducing a new way to deliver information through the new generation of mobile devices. Given the increasing interest in mobile work in the industry, it is surprising to observe that the adoption process of mobile BI is occurring at a slower pace than expected (Brockmann et al., 2012). Therefore, it is beneficial that we understand which determinants of mobile BI use help to ensure the effective deployment of IT resources in an organization.
Mobile BI system quality characteristics may be among the factors that influence mobile BI use. In the IS literature there is mixed support for the relationship between system quality and system use at the individual level. While some studies suggest a positive relationship between system quality and system use (e.g. Hsieh and Wang, 2007; Rai, Lang, & Welker, 2002), other studies offer no support (e.g. Klein, 2007; Straub, Limayem, & Karahanna-Evaristo, 1995). In an m-BI setting, given that (1) users feel engaged when interacting with mobile technologies due to the technical features, such as accessibility and ease of use (Kim, Kim, & Wachter, 2013), and (2) engaged users are an indication of the technology’s success (O'Brien and Toms, 2008), we believe that ‘engagement’ may be the key to advancing the quest to explain the relationship discrepancy between system quality and use. It has previously been suggested that mobile BI influences the focus of attention of decision-makers (Tona and Carlsson, 2014) due to (1) its capability to provide access anytime and anywhere to the answers and issues on which decision-makers need to focus and (2) the fact that it becomes part of the contexts and situations decision-makers find themselves in, because m-BI runs on mobile devices that can be easily carried everywhere. When a mobile BI system provides a positive experience to the user in terms of curiosity, attention, and control, this will likely result in their greater use of that system (Hsu & Lu, 2004; Trevino & Webster, 1992).
Despite increasing recognition of the importance of system quality for BI system use as well as the value that mobile BI systems can bring to firms and their mobile workers, our understanding of how mobile workers’ engagement experience links an individual’s perceptions regarding mobile BI system use with its key determinants remains limited. To address this gap, we conducted a quantitative research study of key informants within firms who regularly rely on a mobile BI system in their decision-making processes. Our overarching research question was: How does a mobile BI system quality influence mobile BI use, considering the engagement level of users?

Our contribution to the IS success and BI literature is twofold. First, we find that mobile workers view engagement as an important link between mobile BI system quality characteristics (e.g. ease of use, attractiveness, accessibility and flexibility) and overall mobile BI system use. Second, flexibility also appears to have a direct impact on mobile BI system use, even though this influence is partially mediated by engagement.

The remainder of this paper is organized as follows. In the next section, the theoretical background underlying our research is presented. The research model is then conceptualized. The second part of the paper presents the research design, methodology, and results. Finally, the results are discussed, including the implications for IS theory and practice, while further possible research directions are outlined.]]></section>
    <section name="System quality and system use at the individual level;Engagement" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. System quality and system use at the individual level
We understand system use as the degree and manner in which users use the capabilities of an IS (e.g. amount of use and frequency of use) (Petter, DeLone, & McLean, 2013). In IS success literature, system use has long been recognized as playing a central role in understanding IS success (Burton-Jones & Straub, 2006; DeLone & McLean, 1992, 2003; Petter et al., 2008, 2013; Petter and McLean, 2009). System quality represents the quality of the IS processing itself, which includes software and data components, and is a measure of the extent to which the system is technically sound. System quality is linked to attributes such as ease of use, functionality, reliability, and flexibility (DeLone and McLean, 2003). Drawing on previous research (Gorla, Somers, & Wong, 2010), attributes for system quality can be grouped into two broad categories—system features from the system designer perspective and system features from the end user perspective. The system features from the end user perspective denotes a user-friendly system that is easy to use, well documented, has a quick turnaround time, and employs modern technology enabling the user-friendliness of systems (Gorla et al., 2010).
In the BI system context, existing studies suggest a positive influence of BI system quality on BI system use (e.g. Popovič et al., 2012; Wixom & Todd, 2005; Wixom & Watson, 2001). A high-quality system can enable users to perform decision-making tasks faster and more systematically (Haley, Watson, & Goodhue, 1999), and increase their decision-making productivity (Wixom and Watson, 2001). Overall, a BI system can modify the processes for providing users with access to information while reducing the time and effort required to provide such access (Wixom and Watson, 2001). For the purpose of this study, we selected only the desired system quality characteristics that are relevant to the BI and m-BI contexts and can be measured from the users’ perspectives; namely, accessibility, attractiveness, ease of use, and flexibility. The choice of these attributes was inspired by what has been suggested as the critical characteristics of mobile BI, not only by an academic literature review on system quality but also by industry expertise. For instance, Gartner suggests that ease of use and the attractiveness of the interface are critical capabilities for mobile BI (Tapadinhas, 2012). It is also suggested that having a mobile BI system that is flexible enough to be customized according to the end user’s needs is a critical functionality, along with accessibility being a must-have characteristic of mobile BI systems (García, 2012).

3. Engagement
The concept of engagement has received considerable attention in various research fields. In work psychology research, for instance, engagement is widely applied to understand an employee’s experience with a work activity (Maslach, Schaufeli, & Leiter, 2001; Schaufeli and Bakker, 2004). In the IS field, engagement describes the state of a user whose attention and interest is fully captured and held (Jacques, 1995) in an intrinsically enjoyable experience (Jacques, 1995; Webster and Ahuja, 2006Webster & Ahuja, 2006; Webster and Ho, 1997Webster and Ho, 1997). Curiosity, attention focus, intrinsic interest (Jacques, 1995; Webster & Ahuja, 2006; Webster & Ho, 1997) and, in more recent research, control, feedback, and novelty (O'Brien and Toms, 2008) are attributes which often characterize engagement. Users enter an engaging experience when they frequently, actively, vividly, and completely become involved during use of a product or system (Chou and Conley, 2009). For instance, a user interacting with a computer or a mobile phone can feel engaged during the interaction because they can achieve relevant goals through the good-looking and interesting features of the product (Rozendaal, 2007). Even though users are focused on an engaging experience, they can interact with an application with no specific goal in mind while still being aware of their external environment (O'Brien and Toms, 2008).
Similar to a flow experience (Csikszentmihalyi, 1990), engagement is associated with perceived characteristics of a computer software which may result in more positive attitudes, greater system use, and more positive work outcomes, such as perceived communication effectiveness (Webster, Trevino, & Ryan, 1993). Technology functionality is one of the main motivations driving a user’s engagement experience (Kim et al., 2013). Having said that, an easy-to-use system that saves time, provides accessibility, flexibility, and creates a pleasurable experience when interacting with an interface that is attractive enhances the user’s experience with a technology. Moreover, systems that fail to provide user control focus the user’s attention and incite their cognitive enjoyment – i.e. a low level of engagement – result in less system use (O'Brien and Toms, 2008; Webster et al., 1993). Based on the above arguments, we posit that system quality affects use indirectly through engagement.]]></section>
    <section name="Research model and hypotheses" category="research model and hypotheses">
        <![CDATA[
4. Research model and hypotheses
The conceptual framework we put forward suggests that engagement will mediate the relationship between m-BI system quality and m-BI use (Fig. 1). To have a clear understanding of the effects of m-BI system quality on m-BI use, two control variables that have the potential to influence m-BI use are added to the framework. We develop and test four hypotheses representing the relationship between accessibility, ease of use, flexibility, an attractiveness, and m-BI use. The following subsections explain these system quality attributes and argue how engagement mediates their relationship with mobile BI use.
Fig. 1
Download full-size image
Fig. 1. Research model.
4.1. Engagement and ease of use
We propose that ease of use affects use through increased levels of engagement. Ease of use, defined as the degree to which a system is used free of effort (Davis, 1989), has a critical role in system use (Adams, Nelson, & Todd, 1992; Segars and Grover, 1993). Not surprisingly, it is also an important factor influencing BI use in both a traditional setting such as via PC/laptops (Hou, 2012) and a mobile setting such as via smartphones/tablets (Verkooij and Spruit, 2013). Considering the latter, although it becomes challenging to interact with dashboards and other analytics objects on a small-size screen, users should be able to achieve results just as comfortably. Yet, ease of use calls for more attention, especially when users have little time to spend learning how to use an application and/or how to search for the information they need. This is because the biggest user group that m-BI targets is mobile users (Tona and Carlsson, 2013), namely users who perform their work at numerous locations.
Users feel in control when they are able to utilize m-BI features efficiently, increasing their sense of freedom, creating an emotion of engagement where time and energy are willingly invested (Rozendaal, 2007). Yet, a mobile user will be less engaged if he becomes frustrated while manipulating interface features, finds a system very difficult to use, and experiences interruptions in the system (O'Brien and Toms, 2008) which, in turn, will lead to low technology use (Hsu & Lu, 2004; Trevino & Webster, 1992). We thus propose the following hypothesis:
H1

Engagement mediates the relationship between ease of use and use.


4.2. Engagement and accessibility
We argue that accessibility affects use by enhancing the experience of a user while he is engaging with m-BI. Accessibility characterizes the ready access to a certain system and the ability to retrieve relevant information that is within that system (Culnan, 1984; Nelson, Todd, & Wixom, 2005). Since it depends on the characteristics of the BI infrastructure and applications, it is considered a technological and hence a system-related characteristic (Işık et al., 2013). Within the BI context, research shows that accessibility is critical for BI success and decision-making effectiveness (Işık et al., 2013). A virtual private network (VPN) connection is a secure solution, at least to a certain degree, that organization implement to enable BI accessibility even from remote places. That implies that employees working from home can access the BI system and retrieve needed information after a successful VPN connection is established.
Accessibility is also critical for m-BI. In other mobile technologies such as mobile banking (Lee and Chung, 2009), accessibility has a significant impact on system use. Mobile technologies make accessibility possible anytime and anywhere (Perry, O'hara, Sellen, Brown, & Harper, 2001), thereby extending users’ availability (Palen, 2002). Being able to access critical business information just in time empowers users by making them feel more in control, which in turn results in more business opportunities (Lee and Shim, 2006). Accessibility problems such as poor connectivity, which causes low levels of engagement by preventing just-in-time feedback and reducing m-BI users’ sense of freedom, lead to decreased system use (Sarker and Wells, 2003). Other accessibility problems like failing to retrieve information based on users’ needs lead to a lower intention to use due to a users’ loss of attention, focus, and therefore a lower level of engagement with a system (Webster and Ahuja, 2006). Hence, since problems in m-BI accessibility can frustrate a user leading to their low level of engagement and ultimately to reduced m-BI use, we propose the following hypothesis:
H2

Engagement mediates the relationship between accessibility and use.


4.3. Engagement and flexibility
We argue that engagement mediates the relationship between flexibility and use. Due to turbulent business environments most organizations are operating in today, flexibility is becoming a more important aptitude to have for organizations as well as their information systems. Flexibility can be defined as “the ability to change or react with little penalty in time, effort, cost or performance” (Upton, 1994, p.73). Recently, flexibility has been shown to be a critical BI capability that organizations need to foster in order to meet the incremental information needs of business users (Işık et al., 2013; Yeoh & Koronios, 2010). Within this context, flexibility is the BI capability to support decision-making in the presence of variations within business processes, technology, or the business environment in general (Gebauer and Schober, 2006). For organizations to be able to maximize benefits obtained from BI, the system must be compatible and integrated with already existing applications and systems within the organization. This requires careful consideration of the underlying technology to support the BI operations, implying the importance of scalability and flexibility (Dreyer, 2006). While the impact of flexibility on BI success has been studied (Işık et al., 2013), how the flexibility of a BI system impacts its use has still to be researched.
Flexibility, as a system capability, becomes even more central within a m-BI context. Mobility is associated with freedom of movement, speed, and flexibility. Mobile technologies and applications are becoming increasingly widespread because they allow users greater flexibility and information availability (Kim, 2012). Research on mobile applications and systems, even though still in its infancy, already shows that flexibility is one of the highly valued advantages of mobile business applications (Nah, Siau, & Sheng, 2005). M-BI users should easily be able to modify their m-BI to their needs, as insufficient flexibility may be a factor withholding users from using m-BI. Thus, the integrated information provided through mobile devices should respond to the day-to-day changing needs of a mobile user.
To reach higher levels of engagement with m-BI, users’ needs for information should be satisfied (O'Brien and Toms, 2008). Since m-BI runs on lightweight and portable devices, users can carry these devices with them and thus be able to promptly respond to situations by scanning and analyzing information just in time, benefitting from its flexibility. This flexibility attracts users’ interest; by engaging with m-BI that is tailored to their information needs, users have an enhanced experience and achieve their goals, which motivates them to use the system again (Webster et al., 1993).
H3

Engagement mediates the relationship between flexibility and use.


4.4. Engagement and attractiveness
We suggest that the attractiveness of the interface will affect use by increasing the level of engagement. IS strive not only towards functionality, but also external design since business users like and prefer systems with an attractive and appealing user interface (Mishra, 2012; Schrepp, Held, & Laugwitz, 2006). Research shows that a visually appealing interface has a significant positive effect on a user’s experience when information-seeking activities are involved (Santosa, Wei, & Chan, 2005). An attractive interface design is a powerful tool for attracting users, improving the BI adoption rate and supporting the continued use of a particular BI tool (Howson, 2010). Elements such as color, form, and level of detail are some attributes of an interface design that influence a user’s interaction experience and their level of engagement (Rozendaal, 2007).
Appealing visualizations are one of the features that make BI attractive to business users (Imhoff and White, 2011). Touch-screen-based visuals may be even more inviting for mobile users. For example, the user experience of tapping a bar in a bar chart to drill down into data is intuitive and direct, and may be more engaging for an m-BI user. Users’ sensory and cognitive curiosities may heighten (Trevino and Webster, 1992) during m-BI engagement because of the interface design in the form of dashboards, drill-down capabilities, visualization, and other analytical capabilities (Tamm, Seddon, & Shanks, 2013; Watson, 2009) that allow m-BI users to explore data and make sense of current or future organizational issues (Weick, 1995). To this end, m-BI technologies employ alerts to attract a user’s attention to specific events, as well as graphical elements such as color-coding results (i.e., yellow to highlight action that is required). Attractiveness to a system may strongly increase or decrease user engagement depending on the experience a user has with that system (Higgins, 2006). We posit that the positive experience m-BI provides to the user in terms of form, visuals, and design will lead to higher m-BI usage (Hsu & Lu, 2004; Trevino & Webster, 1992):
H4

Engagement mediates the relationship between the attractiveness of the interface and use.


4.5. Control variables
Our research model also incorporates two control variables that may influence system use. These are the time since adoption and the frequency of mobile work. Time since adoption is measured as the length of time mobile BI has been implemented in the organization and the employees started using it. Research shows that a longer period of use enables organizations to develop expertise and use the system more effectively to generate business benefits (Purvis & Robert 2001). It has also been shown in the BI context that time since adoption has a positive influence on individual performance (Hou, 2012).
The frequency of mobile work variable addresses different groups of system users. Frequent mobile workers are employees who perform their work at numerous locations using m-BI (Tona and Carlsson, 2013). However, there may be other employees who access the system from a single location and less frequently. These are employees who do not need to access information at anytime and anywhere, and they thus use m-BI less than frequent mobile workers.]]></section>
    <section name="Research methodology" category="methods">
        <![CDATA[
5. Research methodology
The data for our study were collected via an online, structured questionnaire. All variables in our study were measured using existing published scales to ensure content validity. Following the criteria suggested by Jarvis, MacKenzie, and Podsakoff (2003), accessibility was operationalized as a formative scale. This was deemed as the right approach since, as the indicators predict the accessibility of the system, they all have different antecedents and consequences. Accordingly, dropping one of them would change the nature of the construct and changing one item would not require a change in the others (Jarvis et al., 2003). The other scales were operationalized as reflective ones. All these constructs are measured on a five-point scale. Several BI experts from industry as well as academics with BI expertise refined the final questionnaire. Based on their suggestions, ambiguity, sequencing, and flow of questions issues were addressed. Appendix A1 includes a detailed list of the indicators used in the measurement model, as well as their sources.
The target population of this study is business users who employ m-BI for day-to-day business activities, across a range of organizations and industries. Data were collected in Spring 2013. Personal contacts, mailings to service subscribers, and social networking sites were used to reach out to our target group. To increase the response rate, pre-notifications, reminders, and monetary incentives were used (Deutskens, De Ruyter, Wetzels, & Oosterveld, 2004; Edwards, Thomas, Rosenfeld, & Booth-Kewley, 1997) such as a USD 150 lottery and a USD 1 donation to the World Wide Fund for Nature for every completed questionnaire. The questionnaire was completed by 205 respondents from 142 organizations. Among the 205 responses, six were incomplete and therefore dropped from subsequent analyses. Using a boxplot visualization and standard deviation, we screened for outliers and detected three where respondents had answered the questions systematically (e.g. picked the middle value of the five-point Likert scale for all questions). After deleting them from our data set, we ended up with 196 usable responses.]]></section>
    <section name="Data analysis and results" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
6. Data analysis and results
In order to assess if there are significant differences between respondent groups from different data sources, i.e. respondents from social networking sites versus respondents from personal contacts, t-tests were used. There were no significant differences between groups for dependent, independent or control variables at the 0.05 significance level. The nature of the respondents in terms of their age, education, functional area, work position, which kind of mobile device they used for mobile BI, and how long they had used mobile BI is presented in Table A2 in the Appendix.
Following the guidelines suggested by Hair, Ringle, and Sarstedt (2011) and (Henseler, Ringle, & Sinkovics, 2009) we decided to carry out our data analysis using partial least squares (PLS), a component-based structural equation modeling (SEM) technique. PLS is established as a frequently used multivariate analysis method in strategic management research (Hair et al., 2011; Klarner, Sarstedt, Hoeck, & Ringle, 2013). PLS is known to be good at handling both reflective and formative constructs (Esposito, Chin, Henseler, & Wang, 2010; Hair et al., 2011) and it does not assume a multivariate normal distribution (Li, Gupta, Zhang, & Sarathy, 2014). Recent research shows evidence of PLS’s appropriateness for theory exploration and building. For instance, Lowry and Gaskin (2014) have argued that PLS should be selected for studies that include formative constructs as well as for studies that explore possible extensions of an existing theory, as we have worked to accomplish in this research. There are also publication examples in several respected outlets that have used PLS in theory extension/building, e.g. Venkatesh, Thong, and Xu (2012)’s publication that extends UTAUT by including several new constructs and Keith, Anderson, Dean, and Gaskin (2014)’s work that incorporates the flow concept into the theory on team performance as a function of goal commitment and team cohesion.
The minimum sample size required by PLS is ten times the largest number of formative indicators or ten times the largest number of paths leading to an endogenous reflective construct (Chin, 1998). In our research model, the maximum number of formative indicators is three and the maximum number of paths leading to an endogenous reflective construct is six. Therefore, a sample size of 196 is sufficient to test our research model with PLS. SmartPLS version 3.0 was used to analyze the research model (Henseler et al., 2009). We followed recent guidelines for PLS-SEM given by (Chin, 1998) and (Hair et al., 2011) and assessed the measurement models before evaluating the structural model.
The hypothesized mediations were tested via the significance of indirect paths, using the bootstrapping procedures embedded in SmartPLS 3.0. Recent mediation literature suggests that using the bootstrapping approach is superior to the Sobel test, especially in terms of type I and II error rates (Shrout and Bolger, 2002; Zhao, Lynch, & Chen, 2010). Zhao et al. (2010)’s guidelines for assessing the mediation are adopted; thus, we only assessed the significance of the indirect path. Yet, to be able to classify the type of the mediation, the four steps suggested by Baron and Kenny (1986) were followed. To quantify the strength of the mediation effects, effect ratios were calculated so that the amount of (indirect) effect accounted for by the mediator was considered. This is a well-established manner of going beyond the full vs. partial mediation dichotomy, with the assumption that no obvious suppression effects are observed (Shrout and Bolger, 2002).
6.1. Measurement model
The acceptability of the measurement model was assessed based on the model’s construct validity and internal consistency between the items for reflective constructs (Au, Ngai, & Cheng, 2008). Moreover, correlations between items were checked for the formative construct accessibility (Hair et al., 2011; Henseler et al., 2009). Of the five reflective constructs, four had Cronbach alpha values above the recommended level of 0.7. Cronbach’s alpha for attractiveness is 0.69, which is acceptable. As illustrated in Table 1, the composite reliabilities ranged from 0.86 to 0.95. Both composite reliability and the Cronbach alpha estimates indicate that the instrument is reliable and internally consistent for reflective constructs (Hair et al., 2011; Nunnally, 1978).
Table 1. Reliability and validity measures of the research model.
Constructs	Items	Construct reliability and validity
Factor loadings	t-value	Cronbach’s alpha	Composite reliability	Average variance extracted
Ease of use	SQEU1	0.9552	26.3598	0.902	0.953	0.910
SQEU2	0.9531	28.2388			
Flexibility	SQF1	0.7908	12.2944	0.756	0.860	0.673
SQF2	0.8703	15.6702			
SQF3	0.7970	11.5922			
Attractiveness	SQID1	0.9255	11.5126	0.686	0.859	0.753
SQID2	0.8059	8.9564			
Use	U1	0.8831	15.5654	0.717	0.876	0.779
U2	0.8823	15.7149			
Engagement	EG1	0. 8224	19.1439	0.867	0.904	0.653
EG2	0.8333	19.6139			
EG3	0.7880	16.1875			
EG4	0.7474	14.4745			
EG5	0.8467	20.4679			
Reliability of the formative construct was assessed via the assumption of no multicollinearity (Petter, Straub, & Rai, 2007). To reveal multicollinearity, the variance inflation factor (VIF) (Hair et al., 2011) and the tolerance values (O'Brien, 2007) were evaluated. The VIF values of accessibility range from 1.229 to 1.465, which is below the generally accepted cut-off value of five (Hair et al., 2011). The tolerance values range from 0.682 to 0.813, which is above the cut-off value of 0.2 (O'Brien, 2007), see Table 2.
Table 2. Multicollinearity and validity test for the formative construct.
Construct	Item	Tolerance	VIF	Weight	t-values	
Accessibility	SQA1	0.721	1.386	0.722	8.244	****
SQA2	0.682	1.465	0.308	2.905	***
SQA3	0.813	1.229	0.174	1.843	*
* p < 0.1, *** p < 0.01, **** p < 0.001.

The reflective variables were assessed for measurement quality through convergent and discriminant validity (Hair et al., 2011). Convergent validity was assessed according to the average variance extracted (AVE). The AVE for each construct is higher than 0.6, as recommend by Hair et al. (2011). In addition, the resulting factor loadings with t-values were found, without exception, to be significant at the 0.1% significance level, and confirm the high convergent validity of the measurement model (Table 1). Discriminant validity was assessed by comparing the square root of the AVE associated with each construct with the correlations among the constructs. As suggested for discriminant validity, the values on the diagonal presented in bold, which represent the square root of the AVE, were all larger than the off-diagonal values (see Table 3), indicating the satisfactory discriminant validity of all the constructs values (Hair et al., 2011).
Table 3. Correlations between the latent variables and square roots of AVE.
Ease of Use	Flexibility	Attractiveness	Use	Engagement
Ease of use	0.954				
Flexibility	0.525	0.820			
Attractiveness	0.646	0. 399	0.868		
Use	0.376	0.460	0.346	0.883	
Engagement	0.668	0.589	0.557	0.478	0.808
For the formative construct – accessibility – construct validity was assessed by examining the item loadings to observe their relative contribution to the relevant construct (Esposito et al., 2010; Petter et al., 2007). Two of the three accessibility items are significant at the 0.05% significance level. However, formative constructs can include non-significant indicators if there is no multicollinearity (Li et al., 2014). Given that this is not an issue with our items, we decided to retain all items in order to preserve the content domain of information quality (Fornell and Bookstein, 1981; Mathieson, Peacock, & Chin, 2001). We conclude from our assessment of the measurement model that all construct measures are reliable and valid, and we thus proceed to evaluating the structural model’s results and hypotheses.
Last, but not least, we are aware of the potential that common method might have on our results. We conducted Harman’s Single-Factor Test (Podsakoff, MacKenzie, Lee, & Podsakoff, 2003) to examine the existence of common method bias. Given that more than one factor was extracted from the analysis and the first factor accounted for less than 50% of the variance, common method bias is unlikely to be a significant issue with the collected data.
6.2. Structural model
For the hypothesized mediating effects of engagement, we maintained a step-by-step process and followed the guidelines of Zhao et al. (2010). To be able to assess the existence of mediation effect and its type, we only focused on the relationships between system quality dimensions (ease of use, flexibility, attractiveness, and flexibility) and use in our first step. In step 2, we introduced engagement as the mediator and assessed the full PLS model. We used the bootstrapping procedure with 5000 bootstrap samples and 196 cases, which is equal to the number of observations in the original sample of this study (Chin, 1998; Hair et al., 2011) to assess the significance of the path models.
The results of the first step of our PLS analysis can be seen in Table 4. We assessed the structural model’s predictive validity by the coefficient of determination R-square, which was 28% for use, indicating high predictive validity (Falk and Miller, 1992; Hair et al., 2011). This finding is also supported by the Q-square value of the predictive relevance (Geisser, 1974; Stone, 1974). After running the blindfolding procedure in SmartPLS 3.0 (Chin, 1998; Henseler et al., 2009), we obtained the Q-square value of 0.211 for use, which is well above zero, indicating the predictive relevance of the PLS path model.
Table 4. Direct effects—model without the mediator.
Path: from → to	Path Coefficient (β)	t-value	significance
Accessibility → Use	0.076	0.819	–
Attractiveness → Use	0.139	1.557	–
Ease of use → Use	0.044	0.402	–
Flexibility → Use	0.301	3.739	****
Time since adoption → Use	0.106	1.647	*
Mobile Worker → Use	0.113	1.801	*
* p < 0.1, **** p < 0.001.

The direct effect of flexibility on use has a significant (p < 0.001) value of 0.301. The other system characteristics – attractiveness, ease of use, and accessibility – do not have a significant direct impact on use. The control variables, time since adoption and frequency of mobile work, also have a significant (p < 0.1) impact on use.
As suggested by Zhao et al. (2010), there does not need to be a direct effect to be mediated, contrary to Baron and Kenny (1986)’s suggestion. Due to the potential substantial difference between the direct and indirect effect, the ‘effect to be mediated’ may appear to be of the wrong sign, leading to a misinterpretation of the mediation effect. Thus, it is still possible that we are observing direct-only or indirect-only mediation, so we carry on with step 2.
In step 2, we introduced the engagement construct as the mediator and re-assessed the PLS model. Fig. 2 shows the estimates of this path model (p values in parentheses). The results show that accessibility significantly impacts (p < 0.01) engagement, and so does ease of use, attractiveness, and flexibility (p < 0.05). Further, engagement in turn has a significant effect on use (p < 0.01).
Fig. 2
Download full-size image
Fig. 2. Path coefficients and significance levels, model with the mediator.
The positive indirect effect of accessibility on use is significant (p < 0.05). Interestingly, even though the direct mediated path remains insignificant, it changes sign. This is in line with the suppression effect explained by Shrout and Bolger (2002); suppression occurs when the indirect effect has the opposite sign of the mediated direct effect. The total effect of accessibility on use in the original model (without a mediator) is 0.076, which is smaller than the indirect effect of 0.113. The direct effect of accessibility on use, holding engagement constant is −0.037. In this case, the mediated direct effect explains more than 100% of the total effect (Shrout and Bolger, 2002). The 95% confidence interval of the indirect effect (0.025, 0.223) excludes 0, also indicating that mediation is established (Zhao et al., 2010).
The positive indirect effect of attractiveness is significant at the 0.1 level (p = 0.08), where a positive direct effect remains non-significant, suggesting indirect-only mediation (Zhao et al., 2010) and confirming hypothesis 2. The results also show a positive significant indirect effect (p = 0.06) for ease of use. The positive direct effect remains non-significant, indicating indirect-only mediation and supporting hypothesis 3. The indirect effects of flexibility are observed to be positive and significant at the 0.1 level (p = 0.07). Yet, the mediated direct effect remains significant at the 0.05 level (p = 0.02), suggesting complementary mediation and providing support for hypothesis 4. Table 5 provides the direct, indirect, and total effects of the model including the mediator, along with the effect ratios and 95% confidence intervals.
Table 5. Direct indirect, and total effects of the mediator model.
Path: from → to	Total effect (mediated)	Direct effect	Indirect effect	Effect ratio	95% CI
Accessibility → Use	0.038	−0.075	0.113**	100%	(0.025, 0.223)
Attractiveness → Use	0.140	0.101	0.039*	28%	(0.001, 0.092)
Ease of use → Use	0.062	0.002	0.060*	100%	(0.005, 0.125)
Flexibility → Use	0.315	0.269***	0.046*	15%	(0.003, 0.101)
* p < 0.1, ** p < 0.05, *** p < 0.01.]]></section>
    <section name="Discussion" category="discussion">
        <![CDATA[
7. Discussion
We contribute to the IS success and BI literature by unpacking how engagement affects the m-BI system quality-use relationship. This study shows that system quality significantly affects m-BI use through engagement. An m-BI user who enters an engaging experience will use the m-BI system more frequently, with this indicating that m-BI use is not only driven by the functional aspects of IS, but also by emotions. Consistent with our theoretical foundations in IS success research, our study makes several theoretical contributions.

First, our research shows that attractiveness is an important system quality of a m-BI solution. Our finding indicates that, when used appropriately, attractive visualizations such as graphs, colors, dashboard layouts, and drillable objects engage users more actively. Our finding is in line with other studies which argue that IS are not only judged by their functionalities, but also on their looks (Mishra, 2012; Schrepp et al., 2006). Several studies show that variations in the forms and objects embedded in the interfaces affect how users interact with the content (Sundar, Bellur, Oh, Xu, & Jia, 2014), suggesting that how these interfaces are designed are very important and have a great impact on use. While the importance of users’ assessment of the interface has mainly been established for website interfaces, research has still not clearly established whether an attractive mobile interface for a business application would result in similar results. To our knowledge, our study is one of the first to make this contribution. This also implies the much needed focus on user experience and engagement, and the importance of looking beyond usability concerns (Hassenzahl and Tractinsky, 2006; Sundar et al., 2014). Given how mobile applications have permeated our business life, and yet how too few application development teams appreciate the value of mobile user experience design (Gualtieri, Gilpin, Jeffrey S. Hammond, & Knoll, 2011), this finding also suggests an important managerial implication. It is necessary to investigate how to design for the end users by considering their context (e.g. on the move on a train vs. next to the customer) as well as different user profiles (e.g. a sales representative vs. an analyst) (Gualtieri et al., 2011). This also clearly shows that focusing on designing for a smaller screen size is not enough and that there are several other key design factors, such as making the app ‘lovable’ and promoting positive emotion to ensure user engagement.
This study reveals that an easy-to-use system does not lead to higher m-BI use unless it succeeds in engaging users. This is especially true in an m-BI setting where users are consumers rather than authors of the information (Tona and Carlsson, 2013), largely due to the form factors of mobile devices, the user’s mobility and the characteristics of the tasks they are involved in (Sarker and Wells, 2003). Time restrictions to learn yet another application, unwillingness to conduct detailed analyses on mobile devices, and a need to consume pre-analyzed information on-the-go are some of the motivations that drive a user’s inclination towards an easy-to-use mobile system (Mayer, Bischoff, Winter, & Weitzel, 2012). Users’ interest and attention are best captured when information search and scanning activities are curtailed to a minimum. Further, providing users with core information built upon deviations and main KPIs of interest requires minimum effort from a user perspective (Mayer et al., 2012). That being said, this finding holds some implications in terms of design principles. To engage users more, designers should put an emphasis on the ways users search and consume information guided by the time it takes for each search method, for instance predefined navigation as suggested by (Mayer and Weitzel, 2012). At the same time, since the amount of information is positively linked to the search time, it is recommended that information be tailored to user needs to make it easier to consume information at a glance. Moreover, m-BI functions should be organized in an orderly fashion and time delays between human action and m-BI feedback should be minimized to decrease any possible user frustration.
Third, our research shows that higher levels of use are reached when the capability to access m-BI and the information it provides in time from anywhere results in a more engaged user. This is an important finding since one of the main highlighted capabilities that promotes m-BI as a technology is that it enables decision-makers to access and retrieve the BI information just in time (Tona and Carlsson, 2013). This is in line with recent research showing accessibility is critical for BI success and decision-making effectiveness (Işık et al., 2013). We advance this existing understanding by asserting that, in a mobile BI setting, the more the users perceive that the system is readily available to them, the more they become involved and engaged with its various features. This can also enable the m-BI user to explore other functionalities of m-BI that can be used to fit their information requests due a constantly changing business environment (Işık et al., 2013; Wixom, Watson, & Werner, 2011). In terms of managerial implications, this finding suggests that organizations should strive to achieve a comprehensive view on the kind of access the m-BI user needs, depending on their work responsibility and the types of decisions they make. Moreover, a balance should be found between the security measures used to protect the data on m-BI and the risks in order to avoid a frustrating accessibility experience.
Our results indicate that the impact of accessibility, attractiveness, and ease of use on use are completely transmitted by engagement. This suggests that these capabilities first and foremost influence users’ state of involvement with the system. It does not matter how technically sophisticated the system is. Unless the user is engaged, having an easy-to-use or accessible or attractive interface system will not increase system use. The findings are different for flexibility. The existence of both a significant indirect and significant direct effect may imply that, even though flexibility is an important element for fostering engagement, even those users who are not engaged might be motivated to use the system thanks to its flexibility. Thus, one can argue that flexibility is the most important m-BI capability. It is important to note that several other studies have also looked into flexibility as an organizational capability, being as influential as technological capabilities (e.g. Işık et al., 2013). It might be interesting to consider other organizational capabilities within the m-BI context to see if similar results are observed.
Another interesting finding of our study is that, while flexibility’s impact on system use is mediated via engagement, a direct effect still also exists. This is different than the other system quality characteristics. Looking more closely at our system quality constructs, we can observe two groups: (1) criteria related to merely the system itself (accessibility, attractiveness, and ease of use); and (2) a criterion that spans across the system border to reach the final product of the system (i.e. information). In fact, while accessibility, attractiveness, and ease of use evaluate a user’s experience with the tool, flexibility also links users to the product. For example, presenting information in different ways (tables, charts, pivoting dimensions, different levels of detail) helps meet a user’s particular needs and preferences, and also helps a user better understand the product (i.e. information obtained from a system). Information visualization studies (e.g. Bacic and Henry, 2012) have previously shown that information presented in a way that meets users’ preferences is better accepted and utilized in the decision-making process. This suggests that there is more to the flexibility construct than the system quality construct. Other studies looking at flexibility from different perspectives (e.g. Işık et al., 2013) (studying it as an organizational capability) provide support for this view.
Despite its contributions to theory and practice, our study has limitations and also opens opportunities for future research. Our conclusions are limited to four m-BI system quality attributes that were identified through a comprehensive literature review. Considering that m-BI is a relatively new technology, future research should extend our work and study other potential m-BI capabilities, also considering the effects of firm structure, mobile strategy, people, and routines on the engagement level of a m-BI user. Further, the sample consists of m-BI users from four different work positions: non-management, middle management, first-level supervisor, and top management. The kind of decision-making differs according to the work position level. Therefore, it is possible that a difference exists in the way these four kinds of decision-makers have experienced their m-BI solution. Future research should delve more deeply into potential differences between m-BI experiences for different levels of decision-makers in organizations.]]></section>
    <section name="Conclusion" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
8. Conclusion
IS use has played a central role in IS research in the past decades (Burton-Jones and Straub 2006). It is an important construct to measure the effectiveness of an IS, and is therefore also considered as a key variable in understanding IS success (DeLone and McLean, 2003). If firms want to secure value from their IS investments, it is instrumental to understand the factors that influence IS use in different settings. In this study,]]><h target="1" match="full"> we explored the relationship between a utilitarian view of an IS and its use in the mobile BI context.</h><h target="2" match="part"> We introduce engagement as a fresh concept to broaden our understanding of the system quality–m-BI use relationship.</h> While the link between engagement, and use in computer interactions has previously been recognized (Webster and Ahuja, 2006), present studies have not yet delved more deeply into the related details. <h target="3" match="part">By unwrapping how mobile BI system quality influences mobile BI use through different levels of user engagement, our findings reveal important insights that boost our understanding of the relationship between system quality and use for new mobile technologies.</h> We found that this relationship for the four examined system quality attributes – accessibility, ease of use, flexibility, and attractiveness – is mediated by engagement.<h target="4" match="part"> These system quality attributes affect use indirectly through engagement, with this finding contributing to the understanding of the complexity of IS use involving mobile technologies.</h></section>
</publication>