<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="wang xueyan">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 6, Part B, December 2016, Pages 1265–1273</time>
    <title>Records management practice: The issues and models for classification</title>
    <author>Umi A. Mokhtar,</author> ,<author> Zawiyah M. Yusof</author>
Show more
    <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.09.001</doi>
Highlights
    <highlight id="1">This paper discusses the issues embrace in managing records in Malaysia and the records management models that relate to classifying records.</highlight>
    <highlight id="2">20 records management models were reviewed using a content analysis technique to obtain information and identify gaps in records classification, while the issues were identified to learn the practice carried out in targeted case study.</highlight>
    <highlight id="3">The finding from the case study revealed that the classification and other elements in the records management principles were not referred to, instead the focus was only from the information technology perspective.</highlight>
    <abstract> 
        <![CDATA[
This paper identifies electronic records management practice with particular reference to Syariah Courts in Malaysia specifying on classification matter. Classification is paramount for a complete records management other than safeguarding vital records upon determining their value for business continuity. Prior to that, a number of records management models were analysed with the aim to identify whether the Syariah Courts hold onto a specific model in executing electronic records management. Model generally takes the form of inputs, processes, and outputs or expected results in a simplified representation of a limited part of reality with related elements. The study adopts a survey method with interview and document content analysis as the techniques in analysing the models. The interview served as a snapshot study with the aim to reveal the issues embraced by the e-Syariah systems namely the Syariah Court Case Management System. Upon analysing the existing models, it was discovered there are flaws in the existing models making them inappropriate for implementation as they are too theoretical in nature. Furthermore, none of the models address on records classification. On the other hand, the interviews depicted that the electronic records management carried out in the Syariah Court is without the adoption of any model. It is due to this fact that the system was developed without taking into consideration the classification function but instead was designed for storage and retrieval purposes only.]]></abstract>
    <keywords>E-government</keywords>
    <keywords>Records management</keywords>
    <keywords>Records management model</keywords>
    <keywords>Records classification</keywords>
    <keywords>Malaysia</keywords>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
The introduction of electronic government (e-government) initiative in Malaysia has placed records management (RM) as an inevitable outcome of good governance. E-government has the ability to transform the relations within citizens, businesses and government and could serve a variety of different ends, including: better delivery service to citizens; improved interactions; empowerment of citizens; more efficient government management with less corruption; increased transparency; greater convenience; revenue growth; and cost reduction (World Bank, 2005).

Along with other countries including the US, the UK and the Republic of Korea (to name a few), the Malaysian government has undergone a transition from being paper-based to electronic, in order to achieve the goal of a paperless office and other benefits. This change has affected the working environments particularly in government agencies. Although staff have appeared ready to embrace the change from conventional to electronic systems (Mokhtar & Yusof, 2009), many have yet to experience positive results notably through the implementation of records management initiative (Yusof, 2009). In other words, although RM is essential for government at all stages of development both the process of automating office works and theimplementation of RM initiative are yet to be given priority.

From being initially a provider of infrastructure and human skills, e-government initiatives are now providing user-centric approaches on government websites and in systems (Yusof & Bakhari, 2010). However, the country has yet to deliver up to its mark. Statistics from the Public Complaints Bureau in 2009 listed ten complaints pertaining to poor public service delivery. 46.6% of comments referred to ‘late/no action/feedback’, clearly implying a lack of information or difficulty in retrieving documents at the right time (Bakhari, 2010). Malaysia’s rank as an e-government leader dropped to the 32nd spot in 2010 before further declining to the 40th spot in 2012 (United Nations, 2012).

Haslinda, Azizah & Othman, 2005 assert that the decline in the country’s ranking was due to 53% projects failed to meet either functional requirements, budgets or completion deadline. A total of 36% related to the systems fail to perform against its expected performance, not being used in the way intended or used as intended but not delivering the expected results. Another 11% was caused by user resistance to use the system due to lack of training and capability, and the system being too complex to use. These failures were often caused by a combination of factors including project management, incompetent top management, technology, organisational complexity or size and process. Unlike the practice in the developed countries, the core element of e-government initiative in Malaysia focuses heavily on technological infrastructure for systems which finally raised a range of issues and impediments (Haslinda et al., 2005 ;  Razlini, 2012).

It is apparent that e-government initiative in Malaysia is lack of RM component. Such a component is central in the execution of a complete and successful e-government endeavor. RM is the foundational component that should not be abandoned to yield a successful e-government materialisation since all actions and decision makings should be pivoted on RM (Yusof & Chell, 2005).

Service delivery in particular, is closely related to the classification of records. In 2007, the Malaysian government confirmed the importance, over the next seven years, of developing classification systems as well as retention schedules, before implementing any RM systems (Service Circular, 2007, Chapter vi,vii and viii). However, classification systems not to be practiced as a result of not being given priority (Eusof and Yusof, 2011). As the repercussion, classification of records has rarely been considered and RM professionals are rarely consulted when a RM systems is to be designed (Milne, 2010). Rusnah and Nurrusobah (2010) report that less than 10% of e-government initiatives took into account the need to capture RM requirements, compared to other processes such as retention, disposal, and managing authentic and reliable records.]]></section>
    <section name="Records classification;Review of the records management models;" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. Records classification
Classification is made up of several related principles in RM including access, retrieval, maintenance, retention and disposal. Classification systems allow records to be accessed easily, providing the ability to retrieve all records including annotations and attachments, in the context in which the records belong (Schellenberg, 1956 ;  Wallace, 1987). Classification systems also allow records to be maintained in their business context throughout their life cycle, and then preserved or destroyed based on classification-linked retention schedules that provide control over preservation and custody, and as justification for the destruction of records (MacNeil, 2002).

Records classification is centered on function-based that has been the preferred method to control information and records, and classifying records according to why they exist rather than what the record is about (Mokhtar & Yusof, 2015). That is, it focuses on the context and use of records rather than their content. A functions-based classification (also known as records classification) system benefits organisations because it: provides an understanding of the relationship between the business and its records; identifies records required for their evidential value; prioritises records for business value; and facilitates retention decisions. The classification of records is a holistic concept that is based on the functions of an organisation (Franks, 2013 ;  Schellenberg, 1961).

Most studies on the subject (referring to classification as the subject) tend to emphasise the technological aspects of classification (Roper & Millar, 1999), particularly how to automate classification, even though a theory of classification is yet to be developed (Hjørland & Pedersen, 2005). RM specialists are driven by time and space to study many subjects, but generally do not look closely at classification because this area is has been the domain of Library and Information Science (LIS) and computer specialists (Mokhtar & Yusof 2015). The lack of research on classification from a RM perspective has had an impact on the related literature, on the manual or automatic development of classification systems, and on the implementation of classification schemes. This is due to a number of factors including the complexity in defining the characteristics of records; a thorough preliminary study of organisations and detailed documentary analysis to ensure that correct records are selected and classified. These processes are tedious, and need records management researchers to conduct further studies in this area. Most RM professionals appear to embark on other areas, such as appraisal, preservation, or standards (Hjørland, 2008; Mai, 2004 ;  Xie, 2006).]]>
        <h target="1" match="part">This paper explores the issues in Syariah Court Case Management System (SCCMS) at Syariah Judiciary Malaysia (SJM).The issues and the findings from analysing the models are mutually support each other. </h><h target="3" match="part">The models are too theoretical in nature, while the SCCMS was entirely developed from the technical point of view. Although there are several models relevant for managing records, but the development of the records system still does not fully comply with RM perspective causing the records created are of unknown value, but merely serve as information, communication and technology (ICT) enabler for service delivery only.</h> <![CDATA[

3. Review of the records management models
Models can exist in many forms, including scientific, mathematical and statistical, conceptual, functional, or as visualizations. They are typically represented in graphical or textual form, and often present a simplified version of a concept, phenomenon, relationship, structure, system or aspect of the real world (Carleton College, 2009; O’Neil and Schutt, 2013 ;  Pearce-Moses, 2005). Models helps to facilitate an understanding of something by displaying only the necessary components, to help in decision-making by simulating ‘what if’ scenarios, and to explain, control and predict events on the basis of past observations.

RM models that focus on records classification per se should include all elements related to classification including concepts and precepts of classification development, a plan or schema for implementation, and the way it is implemented or deployed (Upward, 1998). Also, records classification should describe the way functions are developed to establish better communications between records managers and ICT team. The processes involved can be depicted graphically. This would benefit organisations in terms of reducing gaps in the use of terminology, concepts and applications between RM and ICT, and promote good partnerships which, eventually, could minimise RM system failure.

Since there are limited specific RC models, these authors inevitably review 20 documents, related to a certain degree to RM models in general, with 5 are conceptual and 15 are functional.

3.1. Conceptual model

Records classification model in specific is rare compare to general models related to RM. These models are presented either in lengthy textual form which is difficult to understand or presented together with either functional requirement or guidelines. This has posed difficulties to records personnel in implementing RM practice.

RM models are usually presented as a conceptual model type, one that can form the basis for generic and high-level models. Conceptual models are narrative in explanations without any graphical presentation. These type of models contain a lengthy textual explanation that include an introduction, best practices and guiding principles, a description of implementation and technical issues, and a glossary. Conceptual models help to highlight important connections in real world systems and processes, and are usually used as a foundation for the development of more complex systems (Carleton College, 2009).

Table 1 depicts the conceptual model such as Information Management and Office Systems Advancement (IMOSA), The University of Pittsburgh Electronic Recordkeeping Research Project (The Pittsburgh Project), Business Activity Structure Classification System (BASCS), Designing and Implementing Recordkeeping Systems (DIRKS), and Electronic Strategy for Preservation of Government Records and Archives (e-SPARK). Only BASCS discusses specifically on the classification but the explanations contained in the documentation lack clarity and it is advisable to set boundaries for each function to make them sensible and easier to develop the system.

Table 1.
Conceptual Model.
Title	Strength Factor
Coverage
Analysis
Trust-worthy	Authenticity	Classification	Active
Inactive
Theory	Contents	Context
C	M	D	T	P			
C: Creation, M: Maintenance, D: Dissemination, T: Transfer, P: Preservation
IMOSA (McDonald, 1995)	√	√	√ (subject, title)	√	√	√	x	x	Archival
IM	The ability to automate manual process such as creating, retrieving, searching, filing, classifying, editing information and verifying for the purpose of preservation and make available the related government’s corporate memory that has long-term archival value.	A result from inability to access electronic records due to technological obsolescence, lack sufficient documentation to permit ongoing intellectual understanding of context and content, and accountability to ensure such records are identified and protected.
The Pittsburgh Project (Duranti & MacNeil, 1997)	√	√	√ (brief)	√	√	√	√	√	Archival
Continuum
IT	Functional requirements and metadata specifications.
Authenticity, integrity, and reliability based on analysis of literary warrant.
Metadata determines the authenticity of records	Model for developing functional requirements and metadata specifications based on warrant, defined as the laws, regulations, best practices, and customs that regulate recordkeeping.
Radical changes in how documents are generated which needed the system to automatically recognise the author, the authority to write the report, and what format of the report is.
These attributes automatic encapsulated in the document with the information management.
BASCS (Library and Archives Canada, 2006)	x	x	√	√	x	x	x	x	Archival	Methodology developed and promoted by the Library and Archives of Canada for the purpose of constructing FBC system to replace its subject block numeric classification system, which has been in use for decades.	Extensive discussion of benefits, methodological background, implementation guidelines, and models for both operational functions and common administrative functions.
DIRKS(National Achieves of Australia, 2006)	x	x	√	√	√	x	x	x	Archival
RM	Method to develop a business classification scheme.	Conceptual model showing an organisation’s functions, activities, and transactions in a hierarchical relationship and the analysis of the organisation’s business activities and processes.
e-SPARK (Arkib Negara Malaysia, 2008)	x	x	√	√	√	√	√	√	Archival
RM	Guidance to Malaysian organisations in dealing with electronic records. Similar with ICA (which was a reference). A good effort to guide organisations and provides standards and regulations as References	Guidelines for maintaining, storing and preserving electronic records or data in the Malaysian and developing an electronic system.
Table options
3.2. Functional model

Functional models are structured representation of the functions, activities, and processes within the model system or subject (IDEF, 1993). Functional models that are used for FBC depict all processes involved, from inputs, processes and outputs, with both high-level and low-level views with extensive structured explanations. This is to ensure that process flows are depicted smoothly and explanations are clear.

These models are either presented in graphic to ease explanation (the University of British Columbia (UBC) project, Chain of Preservation (CoP), BDR and Department of Defense Records Management Functions and Information (DoD RMFI) models) or conceptual/basic diagramming (FAT, 3rd GF (Cook & Franks Model), Model Requirements for the Management of Electronic Records (MoReqs), ISO, ICA, NOARKs, UK BCS, and Australian Handbook HB5031).

Table 2 tabulates the analysis from functional model with function modelling such as DoD RMFI and COP/BDR from InterPARES2. The four analysed models comprised factors of trustworthiness and authenticity of records into the models. Classification is briefly discussed due to scope of the project which did not focus on the classification itself, but rather on the whole active and inactive records life cycle. Archival Theory were adopted in all the four models, accompanied by Diplomatics for UBC Project and COP/BDR, IT Theory for DoD RMFI and Life Cycle/Continuum for COP/BDR. These theories are important for understanding the records nature and identifying records process/activity. Of the four models analysed, none has discussed specifically on the classification process. The nearest model to refer for functional modelling classification is DoD RMFI model but it discussed on the records making, without visually describing the process for conducting records classification. The model is the result of collaboration efforts between experts in archival science, records managers, and automation personnel in regard to RM and technical issues.

Table 2.
Functional Model with Function Modelling.
Title	Strength Factor
Coverage
Analysis
Trust-worthy	Authenticity	Classification	Active
Inactive
Theory	Contents	Context
C	M	D	T	P			
C: Creation, M: Maintenance, D: Dissemination, T: Transfer, P: Preservation
UBC project (Duranti & MacNeil, 1997)	√	√	√ (brief)	√	√	x	x	√	Diplomatics
Archival −
Custodial	Activity models to guide the development of systems and tools for creating, maintaining, and preserving electronic records.	Define records' trustworthiness in electronic world.
Conceptual analysis of records, reliability, and authenticity.
DoD RMFI (2003)	√	√	√
(called as ‘set aside' and ‘code records')	√	x	x	x	x	Archival
IT	The flows of classification process depicted briefly and glossary is provided as explanations for each activity.
Focused for records making, and mentioned briefly on the classification.	Functional model for RC as reference for records making in whole.
Framework for the development of activities for office automation, automated information system and workflow systems
COP and BDR (InterPARES1, 2002 ;  InterPARES2, 2008)	√	√	√ (brief)	√	√	√	√	√	Diplomatics
Archival
Life cycle
Continuum	Model is not tested in real world.
Content consists of entire records life cycle, which focusing more on long-term preservation of authentic records.	Requirements for authentic electronic textual records generated in administrative environments in databases and document management systems.
Intellectual framework for the development of preservation policies, strategies and standards.
Table options
Table 3 depicts the functional model with conceptual or basic diagram such as Function-Activity-Transaction Model (FAT), Three Generational Records Framework (Cook & Franks Model), Norwegian Recordkeeping System: Functional Description and Specification of Requirements (NOARKS 4 and 5), Model Requirements for the Management of Electronic Records (MoReq), Model Requirements for the Management of Electronic Records, Update and Extension (MoReq2), and The MoReq2010® Core Services & Plug-in Modules (MoReq2010), Business Classification Scheme Design (UK BCS), International Council of Archives’ Principles and Functional Requirements for Records in Electronic Environments (ICA), ISO 16175- Part 2: Guidelines and Functional Requirements for Digital Records Management Systems (ISO 16175), and Australian Records Classification Handbook (HB5031).

Table 3.
Functional Model with Conceptual/Basic Diagram.
Title	Strength Factor
Coverage
Analysis
Trust-worthy	Authenticity	Classification	Active
Inactive
Theory	Contents	Context
C	M	D	T	P			
C: Creation, M: Maintenance, D: Dissemination, T: Transfer, P: Preservation
FAT (Schellenberg, 1956)	x	x	√ (foundation framework)	x	x	x	x	x	Archival Organisational	Widely sought-after and referenced framework.
Debates among records and archives professional due to its practicality and theoretical limitation, especially in electronic environment.	Foundation framework for developing a FBC scheme.
Classification generally a guidelines for preparing classification scheme.
Cook, 1992 ;  Franks, 2013	x	x	x	x	x	x	x	x	RM	Records in the electronic environment have evolved from being simply machine-readable records, into electronic records and digital record.	Concepts of electronic records
Identify challenges in electronic environment
(NOARK4 (The National Archives of Norway, 2000)	√	x	√ (brief)	√	√	√	√	√	Archival
Metadata
IT	Basic recordkeeping requirements (creation, classification, maintenance, and disposition of records) for recordkeeping systems used in Norwegian public administration, including specifications for electronic recordkeeping systems.	Assumption: metadata added during those activities would enable the appraisal, acquisition, description, preservation, and long-term access both for creator and custody transfer for preservation.
Two levels of standardisation with the functional requirements and transfer process.
NOARK5 (The National Archives of Norway, 2009)	√	√	√ (brief)	√	√	√	√	√			Focus to records than technical requirements.
Functional requirements are less rigid, and transfer process improved to 100 percent correct.
MoReq (2001)	√	√	√ (brief)	√	√	√	√	√	Archival
RM
IT	Comprehensive specification requirements.
Applied aggregation files in hierarchy. The files were aggregated into volumes according to predetermined conventions by size, number of records contained, and time span.	Ensure ERMS would have the capabilities to create, maintain, and preserve the evidence required for general operational, legal, and archival purposes.
Wide scope to cater for European countries, no practical aspects, and user centric.
Aggregation files originated from paper files to restrict them to a manageable size and weight.
In electronic files, this is to limit to a manageable length of appraisal, transfer, or other management purpose. Paper files contained paper records which aggregated into a structure called as classification scheme.
MoReq2 (2008)	√	√	√ (brief)	√	√	√	√	√	RM
IT	Combined the smooth narrative and testing regime of the UK requirements with the flexibility and applicability of the original MoReq.
Language used is more precise and rigorous than in MoReq.
Underwent a testing phase for framework.
Is a modular, that accompanied by an XML schema.
Provided a complete metadata and functional enhancement	Merge the best of both sets of requirements and pool resources to establish a common set of requirements that would benefits the vendors.
Serve as a practical tool in helping organisations meets their business needs for the management of both computer-based and paper-based records.
MoReq2010® (2011)	√	√	√ (brief)	√	√	√	√	√	RM
IT	A set of core services that can be shared by many different types of records system.
Replaced concept of file from MoReq and MoReq2 with aggregation.	A complete rewrite from the MoReq2 (2008) and MoReq (2001).
Addresses the management of electronic records in any business system. It is not only in traditional ERMS/EDRMS applications but also extends the importance and need to recordkeeping requirements to be made available in all business systems.
Sustainable over time as new needs can be incorporated into new modules without having to republish the whole specification
UK BCS (Todd, 2003)	x	x	√	√	√	x	x	x	Archival
RM
IT	The model covers the issues of creating, using, and managing records. It provides four types of classification called intellectual structures.
These are function-based, subject, organisational and hybrid (function and subject-based). Guidelines for retrieval, storage, retention schedule, and disposition.	Useful method of organising information for purposes such as retrieval, storage, retention schedule, and disposition.
Most of the content of the model is about do's and don'ts in classifying records, and does not address how to apply the classification model.
ICA (2008)	√	√	√ (brief)	√	√	√	√	√	Archival
RM	International set of model requirements for ERMS, covering all aspects of recordkeeping. No specific focus on life cycle phase.	Claimed less daunting requirements for a diverse range of users particularly of the developing world because their statements are more principle-based.
Maintained the essential concepts, contents, and structure of the European functional requirements as with the Pittsburgh project’s original articulation.
ISO 16175 (2011)	√	√	√ (brief)	√	√	√	√	√	Archival
RM	Standard set of requirements based on ICA was to align with MoReq2 rather than compete with it, and being less costly to implement, compared with models that were less specific.	Neither (ICA nor ISO) specifically outlines the requirements for RC in detail. Both standards have mentioned the classification of records in conjunction with the electronic/digital RM system but not the RC itself, such as the requirements, methods, strategies and elements of the classification.
HB5031 (2011)	x	x	√	√	x	x	x	x	RM	Four key concepts of RCs: record titling, metadata, current design, and other factors. Each of these concepts has their own explanation and scope.	Handbook describes concepts of RC. But it provides no hands on or flows of classification process to be developed
Table options
Eleven models were analysed and only UK BCS and HB 5031 models discussed the classification specifically. The UK BCS provides a method to organise information for maintenance purpose. The contents of the model discusses the guidelines of do’s and don’ts in classifying records and narratively described with the assistance of basic diagram. Four types of classification methods are discussed giving users the freedom to choose any method which is appropriate to the organisation. Consequently, the users who lack of expertise and experience in classification have a tendency to choose the wrong method. The HB 5031 provides references of classification concept which is acquired at the first stage of classification development. Since classification of records is done through identifying process or function of records, therefore it is crucial to highlight the procedure on how to do the process. This element is neglected in the HB 5031 document.]]></section>
    <section name="Method" category="methods">
        <![CDATA[
4. Method
This paper employs qualitative method that is suitable for surveys by using one case study (Gunnlaugsdottir, 2012). T

•
Open-ended interviews were conducted with the employees;
•
Participant observations took place at the scene where it was studied how employee use the system in their computer; and
•
Available internal/external documentary materials were examined.
A snapshot study was conducted to identify research problems in the case study. Results from the snapshot study are attested from previous researches and secondary resources. Data was obtained from interview sessions with both the IT officer responsible for the Syariah Court Case Management System (SCCMS) and the records officer responsible for the classification and retention activities of paper records for the whole department.

The review of RM models was conducted through content analysis to provide critical assessment on the classification, stating the features and gaps of each model. Examples of the type of documentation reviewed included the current system specifications, comparing products described in literature reviews (InterPARES projects such as Vancouver Police Department and City of Vancouver PREMIS), benchmarking studies (ISO, ICA, and MoReq II), and company memos.]]></section>
    <section name="Case study analysis: Syariah Judiciary Malaysia (SJM)" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
5. Case study analysis: Syariah Judiciary Malaysia (SJM)
SJM was established by the Malaysian Federal Government in 1996 as a central agency with the aim to standardise the Islamic legal system, streamline the provision of Islamic law throughout the country and manage appeal cases effectively and systematically (Department of Syariah Judiciary Malaysia, 2011). The objectives of SJM are to establish Islamic law in relation to administration, provide a standard of practice for syariah courts, ensure that all states use the Gunasama Service Scheme (such as Administrative and Diplomatic Service, Vocational Training officer, IT officer, and Psychology officer, which served under the Director General of Public Services) for Syariah officers, maximise the use of IT for efficient service, and ensure that Appeal Court cases are managed in a fair, efficient and organised manner.

SJM has undertaken several initiatives to improve the current manual systems which include the development of an e-Syariah system, making it one of the pioneer e-government systems in Malaysia. The system consists of six modules: Syariah Court Case Management System (SCCMS), Syariah Lawyer Registration System, Library Management System, e-Syariah Portal, Office Automation System, and e-Syariah System Link. Only the SCCMS serves as a document storage and management system while the other modules provide the functionality required by users to search and retrieve information. The e-Syariah system has been complained for causing delay in case handling. This can be attributed to Islamic law being administered by States instead of the Federal government. This reflects the nature of individual State sovereignty and the way Islamic law was introduced and developed in Malaysia since the 15th century.

To improve consistency in the application of Syariah law and to achieve efficiency in court management and administration, the SJM has initiated certain measures that are common in other courts, such as practice directions, circulars, and other directives. Additionally, the SJM has collaborated with the Malaysian Administrative Modernisation and Management Planning Unit (MAMPU, 2003) to embark on the e-Syariah project. This project was claimed as an ICT enabler that would assist users to create, access, and retrieve all related documents. It would also give Malaysia the opportunity to use state-of-the-art technology to enhance the Islamic law system (Mahathir, 2003).

The e-Syariah system was designed to help the public, judges, courts, prosecutors, and syariah lawyers, as well as law enforcement officers to remand detainees/accused and cases, in addition to being a source of reference (case scheduler) for plaintiffs and defendants. It also keeps a record of judgments and orders. However, as an electronic business system, the e-Syariah system only complies with IT specifications. It is not an electronic records management system (ERMS). An ERMS, by definition, incorporates RM principles which consists of authenticity, availability, security, disposal, compliance, transparency, accountability and preservation. The compliance to the eight principles central to the ERMS to ensure the security and quality of records are not compromised (McLeod and Hare, 2006). However, the e-Syariah system is dedicated for storage and retrieval. This is due to the fact that system is built primarily to support workflows, as characterised by a database that stores the details of the court case and entity profiles (plaintiff, defendants, judges, courts, prosecutors, Syariah lawyers, enforcement officers, and remand detainees/accused, cases).

The SCCMS and the Court’s Records Division work separately in separate ways. SCCMS does not include any RM functions such as retention schedules, appraisal, classification, or preservation. The Court’s retention schedule and classification processes are managed by the Records Division under a different entity. Although the Records Division has developed a classification scheme, it has yet to be implemented.

Version 2.0 of SCCMS was launched in 2012. The new version included an upgrade to the retrieval engine and changes to the features, functions and a new server infrastructure. The improvements has also included two new sub-systems that linked to the e-Syariah Portal, Syariah Registration System and System Link. Thus, the new version includes (i) the ability to register cases at any state, (ii) faster case escalation, (iii) advanced calendaring and scheduling, (iv) alerts and reminders on backlogs, (v) personal profile database, (vi) optimising case assignment, (vii) file tracking, (viii) payment collection and (ix) enhanced security. Due to these new features, a follow-up interview was conducted in order to find out if the classification scheme or any other RM processes are included in the new version.]]><h target="3" match="part"> However, the finding was similar in the sense that no classification scheme was implemented as the core focus of the system pivots around the speedy retrieval of information.</h><![CDATA[

The initiative to propose a classification scheme by the Records Division was praiseworthy. Effort was taken to develop the scheme for classifying paper records. It was also reported that the series number system in SCCMS does not correspond to RM practices. For example, a series system may be numbered [03001]-[001]-[XXXX]-[0001], where 03 represent the State Code and the following three numbers represent the District Code. The second ([001]) block number is Case Type, while the third block ([XXXX]) reflects the running number of the case, which is generated automatically. The last block number ([0001]) represents the year. As can be seen, a problem will arise once the running number reaches a limit of 9999.

The survey revealed that the e-Syariah system does not include any of these functions: records classification, retention schedules, appraisal nor preservation Without these functions, it can be argued that RM has been performed, except for storing and retrieval, the most common characteristics of any other information system (Yusof, 2015).

Another consequence for not having a classification scheme is the inability of organisation in selecting important documents to be retained. In SCCMS, more than 100,000 records were stored since 2005 as a result of the incapability of the systems to perform the function of selecting and classifying documents of enduring value.

The Malaysian government has accordingly realised that it is a pressing issue in terms of providing e-Syariah system for managing court cases. The current system only accommodates basic IT functionality such as creating, saving, searching, in addition to issuing reports (upon request). Such a system cannot accommodate large volume of records. The limited functions of SCCMS have led to a loss or unintentional deletion of documents in addition to uncertainty about the authenticity, reliability, and integrity of documents. Eventually, the system affects the decision-making processes particularly in the defense of an organisation’s rights, or other management processes.

The system provides no additional functionality once a case is completed. Electronic files of completed cases are kept on the server for twelve years to comply with the retention requirements for Syariah records. This has been done with no consideration for or implementation of RM principles, particularly classification before the files are surrendered to the National Archives of Malaysia.

]]><h target="3" match="part">The finding also reveals that ICT team perceived classification differently from RM personnel perspective. ICT team generally believe that classification relates to retrieval, searching and providing reports based on user requirements. The benefits of classification from better service delivery to providing integrity, authenticity, reliability and longevity of records are not well understood or known by ICT staff. Systems are developed by ICT teams with little or no input from RM professionals, and most are used merely for computerising workflow activities. Classification is not featured in the system.</h><![CDATA[

Such a scenario is experienced by the Vancouver Municipality in the mid-1990s. The city had implemented its computer system to bring about better information management, without considering records management requirements resulting in inability to manage records (Xie, 2007). A correcting step was taken by integrating the existing computer system module with two records management modules into a repository/server-based system (Xie, 2007).]]></section>
    <section name="Discussion" category="discussion">
        <![CDATA[
6. Discussion
]]><h target="1" match="full">This paper discusses both aspects: the RM models that relate to classifying records, and the issues embrace in managing records in Malaysia. </h><h target="2" match="full">The models were reviewed to obtain information and identify gaps in records classification, while the issues were identified to learn the practiced carried out in targeted case study.</h><![CDATA[

Observations at the SJM (in 2010, 2012 and 2013) revealed that the execution of records management initiative had not been based on an understanding of and compliance with records management principles. Instead, the focus was only on customising an information system, essentially computerising case management work flows. The process ends once a case has been completed. Files of completed cases are kept on the server for twelve years to comply with the SJM’s system requirements, and then surrendered to the National Archives of Malaysia. This has been done without taking into account classification and other elements in the RM principles. As a result, the SJM’s case management application system was developed solely by the IT team without any input from the RIM professionals. It is exclusively used only for computerising the workflow activities. Classification is not featured in the system.

The reviewed models have common similarities in the sense that all are developed to meet the requirements of recordkeeping from the RM perspective. The models discuss records life cycle in electronic environment. Three models (the UK BCS, BASCS and HB5031) have discussed exclusively on classification although are lack of clarity and too conceptual. Classification as it has to be discussed in relation to organisations structure and functions. Nonetheless, classification is crucial, for managing RM. In this context both professionals from the RM and the technical team should work hand in hand to ensure records are managed accordingly from both fields.]]></section>
</publication>