<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<publication marker="wang xueyan">
    <journal>International Journal of Information Management</journal>
    <time>Volume 36, Issue 6, Part B, December 2016, Pages 1193-1204</time>
    <title>The impact of technology type and life cycle on IT productivity variance: A contingency theoretical perspective</title>
    <author>Xiaobo Xu (Associate Professor).</author> Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspacea. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Weiyong Zhang (Assistant Professor). </author>Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceOpens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace<author>Ling Li (Professor). </author>Author links open the author workspace.Opens the author workspaceb. Numbers and letters correspond to the affiliation list. Click to expose these in author workspace
a
Department of Marketing and Information Systems, School of Business Administration, American University of Sharjah, Sharjah, United Arab Emirates
b
Department of Information Technology and Decision Sciences, Strome College of Business, Old Dominion University, Norfolk, VA 23529, United States
Show more
     <doi>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijinfomgt.2016.08.007</doi>
Highlights
     <highlight id="1">“IT productivity paradox” and “IT productivity variance” are two distinctive but highly related issues. We defined “IT productivity variance” and focused our effort on it in this paper.</highlight>
     <highlight id="2">Through literature review we summarize prevailing explanations to “IT productivity variance,” we then further identify and contrast three underlying theoretical frameworks that guide empirical studies. The effort reveals the necessity of the contingency approach, which augments existing research.</highlight>
     <highlight id="3">We posit that three contextual factors, level of performance measurement, technology type, and technology life cycle, have significant impact on the relationship between IT investment and firm performance. We propose a contingency model with several research propositions.</highlight>
     <highlight id="4">The potential contribution to both the literature and practice of this research is discussed.</highlight>
    <abstract> 
        <h target="1" match="part">The relationship between IT investment and performance improvement has been a classic research subject. In earlier research it was characterized as the famous “IT productivity paradox.” Decades of research effort later, many IS/IT researchers no longer consider this relationship paradoxical, but it remains a challenge to fully explain “IT productivity variance,” that is, a large portion of unexplainable performance variance observed in empirical studies. In this paper, we take a theory development approach to this important issue. Our effort focuses on examining the theoretical foundation of “IT productivity variance.”</h><h target="2" match="part"> Through literature review, we identify and contrast three prevailing theoretical perspectives to suggest the plausibility of a contingency approach.</h><h target="3" match="part"> Contextual factors can significantly affect the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement. We identified three such factors that were not thoroughly examined: level of performance measurement, technology type, and technology life cycle. We subsequently propose a contingency model in light of these factors, and develop a set of research propositions.</h><h target="4" match="full"> Our effort is a first-step toward bridging a major gap in the literature. The proposed model, while awaiting empirical validation, can provide useful guidance to practicing managers.</h></abstract>
    <keywords>IT productivity paradox</keywords>
    <keywords>IT productivity variance</keywords>
    <keywords>Contingency approach</keywords>
    <keywords>Technology type</keywords>
    <keywords>Technology life cycle</keywords>
    <keywords>Performance improvement</keywords>
    <section name="Introduction" category="introduction">
        <![CDATA[
1. Introduction
Information technology (IT) undoubtedly is an indispensable part of business operations in today’s fast-paced world. Modern IT has advanced dramatically to include a variety of technologies such as computer hardware and software, smart devices, databases, telecommunications, and the Internet. IT applications, consisting of enterprise resource planning (ERP), supply chain management (SCM), customer relationship management (CRM), and many more have been widely adopted by numerous firms. Through the use of IT, businesses collect and analyze a variety of information about their operations as well as their customers and suppliers, and then use the information to gain competitive advantage or performance improvement (Huang, Ou, Chen, & Lin, 2006; Powell & Micallef, 1997; Shuit, 2004). Global collaboration and competition based on the Internet are common business practices today. Most recently, e-business, mobile commerce, and the Internet of Things further extend firms’ ability to reach their customers and suppliers (Laukkanen, 2007; Sanders, 2007). In short, the application of IT is deeply woven into business operations.
The application of IT requires a significant amount of investment, and often brings dramatic changes to organizations. Therefore, information systems/information technology (IS/IT) researchers are highly interested in examining benefits and performance implications associated with IT investment. The knowledge gained not only helps understand how IT affects business operations and organizing, but also provides insights on the direction of IT advancement. Meanwhile, practitioners are also concerned with performance implications of IT investment. Almost in all cases, the application of IT requires significant amount of time, effort, and resources. Particularly, large-scale IT solutions such as ERP can cost firms millions of dollars and years of effort to implement (Fontana & Neto, 2009; Olivier, Bourgault, & Pellerin, 2009). Firms certainly want to know what return they can get from such an involved effort.
While both theoretically and intuitively appealing, the expected positive relationship between IT investment and performance improvement remains elusive in empirical studies. Many early studies found insignificant or even negative results, leading to the famous characterization of “IT productivity paradox” (Barua & Lee, 1997; Pinsonneault & Rivard, 1998). Although “IT productivity paradox” was largely refuted by recent studies with stronger methodological rigor (Dedrick, Gurbaxani, & Kraemer, 2003), it is a major challenge that a large portion of performance variance due to IT investment remains unexplained. “IT productivity variance” is probably a more precise term to describe the issue.
We address “IT productivity variance” in this study using a theory development approach. When studying IT investment, researchers expect to observe variation in performance improvement. But a lack of ability to sufficiently explain the variance is problematic, because it suggests an inadequate theoretical understanding.]]><h target="4" match="part"> A theoretical model with stronger explanatory power hence can be a major contribution to the literature. Meanwhile, insights from such a model can help firms be more effective when they make IT investment decisions.</h><![CDATA[

Based on a rather comprehensive review and critique of the literature, we postulate that the contingency perspective should be incorporated more in the study of “IT productivity variance.” ]]><h target="3" match="part">We subsequently develop a theoretical model that considers how three contextual factors affect the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement. Specifically, we argue that level of performance measurement, technology type, and technology life cycle can alter how IT investment leads to performance improvement.</h></section>
    <section name="IT productivity paradox and IT productivity variance" category="background">
        <![CDATA[
2. IT productivity paradox and IT productivity variance
The performance implications of IT investment have been a classic research subject for a long period of time. IS/IT scholars have used a variety of performance measures in their studies. For example, many studies used the term IT payoff to refer to benefits associated with IT investment (e.g., Dewan & Min, 1997; Hitt & Brynjolfsson, 1996). Others have examined the impact of IT investment on firm performance, which can be classified into direct (Cline & Guynes, 2001; Sircar, Turnbow, & Bordoloi, 2000; Yao, Dresner, & Palmer, 2009) versus indirect (Bardhan, Krishnan, & Lin, 2007; Bazaee, 2010; Gonzalez-Benito, 2007; Mittal & Nault, 2009). In addition, researchers have examined conditions and working mechanisms when IT investment leads to firm performance. For instance, Huang et al. (2006) concluded that firm performance can be improved by IT investment when human-IT capability and IT-enabled intangible assets are improved first. Wang, Lai, and Zhao (2008) found a positive effect of IT investment on firms’ financial performance via IT advantage and IT involvement. In other studies, organizational capabilities were used as a mediator to examine the relationship between IT investment and firm performance (Liang, You, & Liu, 2010).
While many studies supported a positive effect attributable to IT investment, IS/IT researchers have been perplexed by what is known as the famous “IT productivity paradox” for at least two decades (Barua & Lee, 1997; Beaudreau, 2010; Pinsonneault & Rivard, 1998). In theory, the application of IT can improve efficiency or provide novel ways to complete tasks, so it is reasonable to expect performance improvement from IT investment (Schryen, 2013). However, early empirical studies presented a highly paradoxical but not consistent picture (Roach, 1987; Strassmann, 1985). Some studies did support positive results (e.g., Bharadwaj, Bharadwaj, & Konsynski, 1999; Byrd, Pitts, Adrian, & Davidson, 2008; Kudyba & Diwan, 2002). But on the other side, many studies showed insignificant or even negative results. Hu and Plant (2001) found no significant relationship between IT investment and concurrent firm performance, though they argued that preceding IT investment would have a significant impact on subsequent firm performance. Alpar and Kim (1990) found the value of IT investment, measured by key ratios such as return on equity, to be inconclusive. In a two-stage analysis, Barua, Kriebel, and Mukhopadhyay (1995) showed that the impact of IT investment at the intermediate level of performance is more significant than at the higher level. It is this inconsistency between theory and empirical evidences made the performance implications of IT investment a perplexing issue.
A lot of research effort since then has been devoted toward a resolution of the “IT productivity paradox.” By late 2000s, enough empirical evidences have been accumulated to support a definitive positive relationship between IT investment and performance improvement. Kohli and Devaraj (2003) reviewed empirical studies published between 1990 and 2000 to draw the conclusion that many empirical studies failed to find a positive relationship due to effects from contexts, study characteristics, data sources, data analysis, and variables employed. In another study, Brynjolfsson and Hitt (2000) conducted an extensive literature review to find that “rather than being paradoxically unproductive, computers have had an impact on economic growth that is disproportionately large compared to their share of capital stock or investment, and this impact is likely to grow further in coming years.” (p. 45). Dedrick et al. (2003) then stated that “the productivity paradox as first formulated has been effectively refuted” (p. 1).
The challenge is not fully resolved though. While the positive effect of IT investment on performance improvement is no longer considered paradoxical by many IS/IT scholars, a large portion of variance observed in empirical studies remains unexplainable. IS/IT researchers found that IT investment can lead to performance improvement and its magnitude of effect varies substantially (Ravichandran, Liu, Han, & Hasan, 2009; Wang, Tai, & Wei, 2006). This variance of performance improvement is expected. But existing theoretical models seem not able to provide sufficient explanatory power for a large portion of the variance. Toward that end, it is reasonable for one to argue that “IT productivity paradox” is not fully resolved.
We examined the literature on “IT productivity paradox” to identify that it actually involves two related but distinctive issues: a definitive positive relationship versus a large amount of unexplained variance. First and foremost, the paradox is about whether there is a positive relationship between IT investment and performance improvement. Research effort has largely reached a consensus, that is, IT investment can lead to performance improvement. To many, this is interpreted as a resolution to the “IT productivity paradox” (Dedrick et al., 2003).
Other researchers have different opinions because their definition of “IT productivity paradox” includes the second issue: a large amount of unexplained variance observed in empirical studies concerning the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement (Schryen, 2013). Large variance in performance is not the issue. In fact, it is expected because even the same information technology will not lead to the same level of performance due to the effect of many factors, e.g., different firms, resources availability, and implementation approaches. The real issue is an insufficient ability to explain the variance.]]><h target="1" match="part"> Sometimes the portion of unexplainable variance in performance becomes so large that even the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement can be challenged as being paradoxical.
            Clearly, these two issues are highly inter-related. The second issue can be characterized as “IT productivity variance,” on which we focus our effort in this research.</h><![CDATA[ Our goal is to gain a better understanding of the issue so that more variance can be convincingly explained, hence making “IT productivity variance” a less severe issue. Meanwhile, such an understanding also contributes to a more complete resolution of the “IT productivity paradox.”]]></section>
    <section name="Research methodology;Current theorizing" category="methods">
        <![CDATA[
3. Research methodology
3.1. Theory development approach
We take a theory development approach to address “IT productivity variance” in this research. A theory is generally considered the highest form of human knowledge (Dubin, 1978), as it reveals relations among concepts within a set of boundary assumptions and constraints (Bacharach, 1989). In the case of “IT productivity variance,” a theory can answer the question of how, when, and why IT investment is related to performance improvement, to the extent that the unexplained portion of variance is small enough to no longer cause major concerns.
Theory development is needed to address “IT productivity variance.” There are plenty of empirical studies on the issue, yet no definitive conclusion has been reached. While another good empirical study can make significant contributions, an examination of current theorizing on the issue holds the key to a resolution. Such an effort will expose the strength and weakness of current theoretical frameworks, and subsequently open the door for refinement.

Theory development must follow a rigorous process. According to organizational theorists, theory development must be based on a thorough understanding of the subject matter (Whetten, 1989). In this research, we started with identifying the relevant literature. Then we performed two rounds of review.]]><h target="2" match="part"> In the first round, we focused on the nature of explanations offered to “IT productivity variance.”The analysis confirmed that the underlying theoretical frameworks of empirical studies are key to “IT productivity variance.” In the second round of review, we identified and contrasted three major theoretical frameworks.</h><h target="4" match="part"> The effort clearly pointed to the necessity of incorporating contextual factors into theorizing, which led us to propose a theoretical framework based on the contingency perspective.</h><![CDATA[
3.2. Literature search
Per the discussion above, the first step in this research is to gain a thorough understanding of the subject matter. To identify relevant studies, we searched major research databases including Business Source Premier, ABI Inform, and Elsevier Science Direct, for research studies published during the period of 1990–2015. The inclusion criterion is empirical studies addressing the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement. We used several keywords including “IT investment,” “IT productivity paradox,” and “performance.” We then reviewed the search results to determine the relevance of each paper. Irrelevant records such as book reviews or trade magazine articles were removed from further review. We focused our review effort on top tier academic journals including Journal of Management Information Systems; Information Systems Research; MIS Quarterly; Management Sciences; Journal of Strategic Information Systems; Journal of Computer Information Systems; and Information Resources Management Journal. These journals are identified based on their reputation; ranking; and objective information such as their impact factor score. They are well-recognized for their high quality and methodological rigor. Our effort identified 226 research articles from more than 20 journals. Table 1 shows a breakdown of these published articles across journals. Next; we report our findings from the literature review effort.
Table 1. Number of identified research articles by journal.
Journal	Articles
MIS Quarterly	36
Information Systems Research	29
Journal of Management Information Systems	27
Management Sciences	18
Journal of Strategic Information Systems	16
Journal of Computer Information Systems	12
Information Resources Management Journal	9
Strategic Management Journal	9
Business Process Management Journal	7
Journal of Business Logistics	6
Industrial Management & Data Systems	5
Decision Sciences	4
Other Journals	48
Total	226
Articles on the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement, found through Business Source Premier, ABI Inform, Elsevier Science Direct, and others (published during 1990–2015).

4. Current theorizing
4.1. Prevailing explanations in the literature
]]><h target="2" match="part">As mentioned earlier, our initial review of this body of the literature focused on the nature of explanations provided to “IT productivity variance.”</h><![CDATA[ Included in the 226 articles are a variety of empirical studies. These studies adopted different theoretical perspectives and used different research methodologies. Some studies were conducted at the firm level, while others were at the division or plant level. Most studies are cross-sectional in nature, with a few of them being longitudinal. Some studies used regression and others used structural equation modeling. Many studies reported positive results but a large number of studies also found either insignificant or contradictory results. In their discussion of the results, it became clear that explanations can be classified into three main types: dynamic and complex relationship, empirical research methodology issues, and implementation effectiveness.
4.1.1. Dynamic and complex relationship
Many scholars view “IT productivity variance” as the natural result of a dynamic and complex relationship. The key argument is that the relationship between IT investment and firm performance is dynamic and complex, and the relationship may even change dramatically under the influence of different conditions such as macro environment (e.g., IT infrastructure, culture) (Doherty & Terry, 2009), performance measurement level (e.g., process, operational, and firm) (Gregor, Martin, Fernandez, Stern, & Vitale, 2006; Tallon, 2007; Wilson & Howcroft, 2005), and type of technology (e.g., sustaining vs. disruptive technology) (Dery, Hall, Wailes, & Wiblen, 2013). This complexity has led researchers to adopt different theoretical perspectives to guide their studies, which use different measurement constructs and provide different explanations and predictions. Researchers are effectively taking snapshots of a large, moving object from different angles. When these studies are put together, the result is a large portion of unexplained variance, that is, “IT productivity variance.”
The dynamic and complex relationship explanation suggests that, for a more in-depth understanding of IT productivity variance, researchers need to be aware of the guiding theoretical perspective as well as important contextual factors. One such effort is Melville, Kraemer, and Gurbaxani (2004). In this seminal work, they compared theoretical perspectives used in previous studies (e.g., microeconomic theory, industrial organization theory, and sociology and socio-political perspectives) to propose an integrative model of IT business value based on the resource-based view. Specifically, they defined IT business value as organizational performance impacts of IT, and argued that it is determined by contextual factors including macro environment, competitive environment, and focal firm factors.
4.1.2. Empirical research methodology issues
Quite some studies have cited empirical research methodology issues as the reason for the occurrence of the “IT productivity paradox” or “IT productivity variance.” According to Brynjolfsson (1993), four methodological issues explain why studies failed to confirm a positive relationship between IT investment and performance improvement: measurement errors, performance lags, benefits redistribution, and mismanagement. In their review of empirical studies conducted during the period of 1990–2000, Kohli and Devaraj (2003) concluded that methodological issues play a critical role in empirical studies that either were incapable of confirming a positive relationship, or failed to sufficiently account for variance observed. The suggestion therefore is very straightforward: improve research methodology rigor.
Meanwhile, IS/IT scholars recognize that empirical research methodology issues are not the sole reason for “IT productivity variance.” Despite much improved methodological rigor, “IT productivity variance” can be still observed in recent empirical studies. It becomes apparent that the context of a research study must be considered. Kohli and Devaraj (2003) specifically pointed out that researchers need to carefully examine the influence of context, study characteristics, data sources, data analysis, and variables employed. Shin (2009) showed that IT spending may not improve firm performance if it does not strategically emphasize related diversification to expand its existing products and services. Ravichandran et al. (2009) found mixed impact of IT spending on firm performance when IT investment interacts with different levels and types of diversification: related, unrelated, and geographic diversification. In short, for a more thorough understanding of “IT productivity variance,” contexts must be considered.
4.1.3. Implementation effectiveness
The third stream of explanation cites implementation effectiveness as the reason for the large unaccounted variance in performance improvement. This explanation argues that IT investment can lead to performance improvement but a positive effect can only be observed if the implementation is successful (Arvidsson, Holmström, & Lyytinen, 2014). Klein and Sorra (1996) defined implementation of an innovation as the process of “gaining targeted employees’ appropriate and committed use” (p. 1055). Implementation many times involves significant organizational changes and inevitably introduces performance variance (Bagayogo, Lapointe, & Bassellier, 2014; Markus, 2004; Orlikowski, 1996). When implementation is not sufficiently considered, the result is a large amount of unaccounted variance in performance improvement, which often times is actually a manifestation of implementation ineffectiveness or failures, i.e., employees did not use an information technology as they are supposed to do, nevertheless “enhanced use” (Bagayogo et al., 2014). Studies have shown that both tangible and intangible benefits of IT investment can be delivered by successful implementation (Haapaniemi, 1996; Nash, 2003). On the other side, a breakdown of implementation can cause substantial financial losses to an organization (Davies, 2002; Zizzo, 2002). Furthermore, a failed implementation can even jeopardize the survival of organizations (Hitt, Wu, & Zhou, 2002; Montealegre & Keil, 2000). IS/IT researchers thus have examined many factors that affect IT project implementation effectiveness, including leadership performance (Nixon, Harrington, & Parker, 2012), leadership styles across life cycle stages of IT projects (Ng & Walker, 2008), commitment to project objectives (Korzaan, 2009), and project monitoring (Mahaney & Lederer, 2011). In short, it is advisable that empirical studies incorporate implementation factors for stronger explanatory power.
4.2. Three existing theoretical frameworks
From the above it is clear that the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement is complicated, and subject to the effect of contextual factors. Incorporating contextual factors in empirical studies may yield fruitful insights. However, before proceeding further, it is vital to have a solid understanding of existing theoretical frameworks.<h target="2" match="part"> Our second round of review hence focused on identifying the underlying theoretical frameworks that guide empirical studies. We identified three major ones and compared them to reveal their strength and weakness: microeconomic theory, resource-based view, and institutional theory.</h>

4.2.1. Microeconomic theory
Many empirical studies are based on the microeconomic theory, characterized by using economic metrics to measure performance improvement due to IT investment. As early as in the 1990s, researchers have used ratios such as return on equity, but they observed high variance for such measures, probably due to the fact that data was collected at different time horizons (Alpar & Kim, 1990). To address the data collection time horizon issue, Bharadwaj et al. (1999) adopted Tobin’s q, a forward looking measure, and captured a positive relationship between IT investment and performance improvement. Other researchers focused on operational efficiency and found a positive IT-profitability relationship (Kudyba & Vitaliano, 2003). Lee (2004) proposed four phases of IT evaluation procedures (strategic analysis, business process redesign, IT configuration, and performance evaluation) to capture the potential value of IT investment. His performance evaluation metrics included financial, strategic, and operational dimensions. Yao et al. (2009) used mixed metrics (order cost reduction, inventory reduction and customer satisfaction) to measure firm performance and his study confirmed a positive impact of IT investment on firm performance.
Several studies have considered the time-lagging effect in investigating the relationship between IT investment and firm profitability (Hu & Plant, 2001; Lee & Kim, 2006). Using data mining techniques (e.g., multivariate adaptive regression splines), researchers found that the impact of IT investment on productivity is complicated and the impact might be mixed due to interactions with other factors, such as non-IT capital and non-IT labor (Ko, Clark, & Ko, 2008; Ko & Osei-Bryson, 2008). Following this line of thinking, Mittal and Nault (2009) utilized a Cobb-Douglas production function to measure and compare the effect of IT between IT-intensive and non-IT-intensive industries. They found that IT-intensive industries are dominated by indirect effect of IT and non-IT-intensive industries are dominated by direct effect. Another empirical study indicated that IS support for product innovation does improve profitability (as measured by return on sales and return on assets) but only when IS/IT support has its complementary firm-specific information and knowledge (Zhang, 2010). Dewan and Ren (2011) concluded that a robust interaction between IT and boundary strategies (diversification and vertical integration) can determine a firm’s performance, measured by return and risk.
It can be inferred from this stream of the literature that microeconomic theory has been widely and successfully used to study the impact of IT investment on performance improvement. Microeconomic theory-based studies focus on the application of a quantitative measurement system. A variety of economic metrics have been used by researchers to measure the value of IT investment. We note that microeconomic theory is a meta-theory but not a specific theory for IT investment. Studies based on the microeconomic theory often rely on the common wisdom to explain a positive relationship between IT investment and performance improvement, that is, IT investment can streamline business processes for better efficiency, hence improving performance (Rai, Patnayakuni, & Patnayakuni, 1997). The microeconomic theory also does not address issues such as the time lag of performance improvement due to the IT investment. Nor can the theory explain the difference of performance at different levels, e.g., process, operations, or firm level performance. Hence the theory can explain a portion of variance in performance, but there is still a substantial amount of variance remains unexplained. The portion of unexplained variance can become large enough to raise the concern of “IT productivity variance.”
4.2.2. Resource-based view
Resource-based view (RBV) posits that a firm’s competitiveness is closely related to the resources at its disposal. Resources can be classified into tangible, intangible, and personnel-based that determine a firm’s capabilities, competitive advantage, and strategy (Barney, 1991; Grant, 1991). RBV states that a firm’s competitive advantage is determined by the inimitability and heterogeneity of resources (Hitt & Brynjolfsson, 1996). The more inimitable and heterogeneous resources a firm owns, the more likelihood of competitive advantage it gains and sustains. Amit and Schoemaker (1993) further divided resources into two dimensions: resources that are interchangeable and non-specific to a firm; and capabilities that are unique and specific to a firm.
RBV is another common theoretical perspective upon which many empirical studies are based. Researchers argued that IT investment leads to inimitable resources which form the basis of a firm’s competitive advantage (Collins, Worthington, & Reyes, 2010). This competitive advantage can help a firm gain market share and eventually, lead to the firm’s good financial performance (Byrd et al., 2008; Huang et al., 2006; Morris & Strickland, 2008/2009; Sanders & Premus, 2005; Santhanam & Hartono, 2003). Bharadwaj (2000) used RBV to conceptualize IT as an organizational capability and found a positive relationship between IT capability and firm performance. The IT competency model developed by Tippins and Sohi (2003) includes three components of IT resources: IT objects, IT knowledge, and IT operations. They found that organizational learning mediates the effects of IT competency on firm performance. Melville et al. (2004) reviewed 202 IT business value articles published between 1990 and 2002 to propose an integrative model of IT business value which includes macro environment, competitive environment, and focal firm. Their model is clearly based on RBV.
Many studies based on RBV found insignificant or negative results though. Ray, Muhanna, and Barney (2005) conducted an analysis for the effect of different IT resources and capabilities on customer service to only find mixed results between them. From RBV and the prisoner’s dilemma perspective, Tangpong (2008) concluded that IT vendors realize more IT investment payoffs than IT investing firms who can only claim limited or insignificant IT investment payoffs. Mixed results were also found in a meta-analysis of 42 RBV related empirical studies that examined how IT and organizational capabilities affect firm performance (Liang et al., 2010).
Among all resources, knowledge has recently become one of the most important for a firm to gain and maintain competitive advantages and to improve firm performance, hence the term knowledge-based view (KBV). IS/IT researchers have examined knowledge to explain the variance of firm performance brought by IT investment (Malhotra, 2005; Sabherwal & Sabherwal, 2005; Sambamurthy, Bharadwaj, & Grover, 2003). To capture specific and technical knowledge, Tippins and Sohi (2003) proposed IT knowledge as one of the IT competency components that links to firm performance. Lee, Kim, Yeonog, and Lee (2009) found a positive effect of IT knowledge on operational performance for small firms.
Recently, IS/IT researchers focused their attention on knowledge management capability (KMC), that is, a firm’s ability to utilize knowledge resources. Tanriverdi (2005) examined the effects of IT relatedness and KMC on firm performance from three different aspects: product, customer, and managerial. Their study found KMC positively mediates IT relatedness and firm performance. KMC derived from IT capability can explain a large portion of process performance variance (Ma, Peng, & Shi, 2009). Collins et al. (2010) proposed a conceptual model, in which they examined the relationship between knowledge-based resources, KMC, supply chain technology investments, supply chain performance, and overall firm performance. Wong and Wong (2011) empirically examined how four dimensions of KMC (technological capability, structural capability, cultural capability, and process capability) and supply chain practices affect firm performance. They found that the interactions between supply chain practices and KMC positively affect firm performance.
Other scholars looked at the knowledge management systems (KMS). Feng, Chen, and Liou (2004/2005) empirically validated the positive benefits of KMS adoption on firm performance. Others found that knowledge management and IT are positively associated with project management performance (Anantatmula & Kanungo, 2008), and firm performance (King, 2002). The study by Liao (2011) revealed that the relationship between knowledge management strategy and firm performance is moderated by human resource management control systems. Some scholars used the knowledge management perspective to study the relationship between IT investment and intangible output such as R&D process performance (Ma et al., 2009), and innovation productivity (Kleis, Chwelos, Ramirez, & Cockburn, 2012). Many of these studies reported mixed results though.
In summary, studies based on RBV (or KBV) provide good explanations to performance variance following IT investment. But it is also worth noting that many studies reported mixed results. There are multiple reasons. The central premise of studies guided by RBV is that IT investment leads to inimitable resources, which in turn leads to performance improvement. However, it is hard to determine whether a resource is inimitable or not because often times it is context dependent. RBV does not explicitly address issues such as performance time lag. In addition, the impact of both internal and external environment is not sufficiently considered in RBV, for instance, how competitors can undermine a firm’s effort to gain competitive advantage.

Further, studies based on RBV may have a self-selection bias that contributes to “IT productivity variance.” The underlying theoretical perspective has significant effect on researchers’ empirical research design. Since RBV states that inimitable resources lead to competitive advantage, the tendency for empirical researchers is not to study information technologies that are pervasive or rather mature in the marketplace, which are unlikely to generate inimitable resources for a firm. An RBV study (e.g., Huang et al., 2006) tends to choose an emerging or unique information technology as its research subject. Such information technologies more than likely will be at an early stage in their life cycle. Intuitively, they may yield high returns but also involve high uncertainties, which translate into “IT productivity variance.”
4.2.3. Institutional theory
Organizational theorists have used the institutional theory to describe how an innovation or technology gets diffused into different organizations. The theory states that an early adopter of a technology focuses on the usefulness of the technology. In other words, firms adopt the technology for performance improvement reasons. As time progresses, the technology gained legitimacy. Late adopting firms are pressured to adopt the technology because it becomes a “standard.” As a result, late adopters of the technology gain legitimacy but not necessarily performance improvement (Westphal, Gulati, & Shortell, 1997). Even though the technology has improved performance in absolute metrics, comparative metrics may still show an inferior performance because the whole industry’s baseline has risen.
The institutional theory has been frequently used by business researchers to explain the adoption pattern of technologies and innovations. For example, Westphal et al. (1997) in their study of the adoption of total quality management (TQM), clearly showed that early adopters demonstrated better performance than non-adopting peer firms, but late adopters did not demonstrate any performance edge. IS/IT researchers have also applied the institutional theory in a wide variety of contexts including consumer adoption of technological innovations (Saaksjarvi, 2003), the diffusion of Internet banking (Lee, Kwon, & Schumann, 2005), the acceptance of IT-based innovation (Yi, Fiedler, & Park, 2006), the adoption of mobile innovations (Marez, Vynche, NBerte, Schuurman, & Moor, 2007), and the diffusion of online reverse auctions (Schoenherr, 2008).
While not its main objective, the institutional theory potentially can explain performance variance following IT investment. The adoption of the same information technology can have different performance implications, depending on the timing of adoption. Firms may expect substantial or little performance improvement depending on whether they are an early or late adopter. The theory further suggests that the intensity of competition is important. The higher the competitive intensity, the less likely a firm can expect performance improvement because the baseline is rising.

Although it can explain performance variance, the institutional theory tends to leave a large portion of variance in performance unaccounted for several reasons. The primary concern of the institutional theory is the technology diffusion pattern involving comparison of early to late adopters. Most of the time, the adoption of a technology in a firm is characterized as a yes-no decision. The dynamics and complexities of the adoption process within a firm are not sufficiently considered. This will unfortunately lead to reduced explanatory power. Meanwhile, firm-level comparative metrics such as sales revenue, market share, or profitability are favored because they reflect a firm’s performance in comparison to competitors. But they are subject to influence of many factors, making performance variance explanation a difficult task. Finally, empirical studies guided by the institutional theory are subject to a self-selection bias in that they often focus on mature information technologies to enable a comparison of early to late adopters. This design is in sharp contrast to studies based on RBV, but the effect is likely the same: more unexplainable variance. In short, studies guided by the institutional theory are unlikely immune from “IT productivity variance.”]]></section>
    <section name="Augmenting existing theoretical frameworks with the contingency perspective" category="results">
        <![CDATA[
5. Augmenting existing theoretical frameworks with the contingency perspective
The review and critique of existing theoretical frameworks show that each has strong merit but also some weakness. Each theoretical framework has its unique explanatory power. Each can explain performance variance due to IT investment but not all of them. The common theme is that a large portion of performance variance remains unexplained, and contextual factors are likely the key to stronger explanatory power.

We propose to augment existing theoretical frameworks with the contingency perspective. The contingency perspective is a well-established theoretical framework in management research. The central premise is that the effectiveness of a management intervention is crucially dependent on a fit between the intervention and an organization’s internal and external environment, i.e., the contexts (Donaldson, 2001; Van de Ven & Drazin, 1985). Generally, a fit leads to high performance and vice versa (Miller, 1992). Management scholars have used the contingency approach to study the effect of contextual factors on performance and gained novel insights. It is commonly recognized that the contingency perspective is an effective approach.
The contingency perspective potentially can help explain more variance in the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement, hence contributing to an in-depth understanding of “IT productivity variance.” It is well suited as a complementary approach to existing theoretical frameworks. It is also highly recommended by IS/IT scholars (Howcroft, Newell, & Wagner, 2004). Our intention is not to replace existing theoretical frameworks but to augment them. Fig. 1 illustrates the conceptual model. We view an IT investment as a management intervention; hence its relationship to performance improvement is subject to the effect of contextual factors. This conceptual model is next developed into a testable theoretical model. We first identify important contextual factors, and then determine their effect. The effect of contextual factors is usually specified in one of the six forms of “fit” (Venkatraman, 1989), with moderation being the most common one.
Fig. 1
Download high-res image (90KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 1. The conceptual model.
Our theory development effort focuses on when an IT investment can lead to performance improvement. The “IT productivity paradox” is concerned with why there is not a positive relationship between IT investment and performance improvement. The essence of “IT productivity variance,” in contrast, is when we can observe performance improvement due to IT investment. This principle guides our effort of contextual factor identification. Since there are numerous contextual factors can be considered, we focus our effort on the crucial ones. The identification work is based on the literature and uses logical reasoning.]]><h target="3" match="part"> Specifically, we propose to consider three contextual factors: the level of performance measurement, type of information technology being implemented, and the stage of the life cycle of an information technology. It is worth noting that level of performance measurement is a research design contextual factor, and the other two are technology application contextual factors.</h><![CDATA[
5.1. Level of performance measurement
The first contextual factor is level of performance measurement. Level of performance measurement refers to at what level performance is measured. Performance measurement is a complicated matter. Individuals and organizations measure their performance at many different levels using a variety of metrics. The literature has recognized that the choice of performance metrics may have significant impact to the results an empirical research study may obtain (Kohli & Devaraj, 2003; Melville et al., 2004).
When it comes to IT investment payoff studies, performance improvement is often measured at three levels: process, operational, and firm (Gregor et al., 2006; Tallon, 2007; Wilson & Howcroft, 2005). At the process level, performance is often measured by productivity or efficiency metrics. At the operational level, conventional performance metrics include cost, quality, delivery, and dependability. Metrics at the firm level vary. Many studies look at return on investment, or return on equity. Sales revenue, market share, and profitability are commonly used as well. A few studies use a firm’s stock price (or derivative metrics of the same nature).
The common knowledge in the performance measurement literature is that the higher the level performance is measured, the more variance one will observe (Gregor et al., 2006). This is highly intuitive and logical. At a lower level, metrics are more “absolute” or “direct” in nature. For example, productivity is measured by the quantity of output divided by the quantity of input. In contrast, metrics at a higher level tend to be more “relative” or “indirect.” For instance, market share is a metric that is often used to measure a firm’s performance. While the definition of market share is clear and without any vagueness, the metric itself is subject to the influence of many factors, particularly competitors’ effort. A firm may have done an excellent job to improve its productivity, but if its competitors also have moved forward, then the market share metric may not show any improvement.
IT investment is a firm’s effort toward improvement and usually is implemented through IT projects. Most IT projects will either improve existing business processes for higher productivity or efficiency, or develop business processes to enable a firm to perform new tasks. It is therefore reasonable to expect a strong relationship between IT projects and process-level performance metrics. Logically, one can expect improved productivity and efficiencies translate into better operational performance, for instance, reduced unit cost, better quality, more on time delivery, and higher dependability. However, operational performance is usually measured at the plant or division level and is subject to the influence of other factors. Hence the strength of the relationship between IT projects and operational performance is attenuated. The same argument can be easily extended to firm-level performance metrics, which is subject to the effect of even more factors. In summary, the strength of the relationship between IT investment and performance attenuates as the level of performance metrics goes higher. We state this as Proposition P1.
Proposition P1

Generally, information technology investment will lead to performance improvement. Specifically, the observed strength of the relationship is the strongest when performance improvement is measured at the process level. The strength attenuates when performance improvement is measured at the operational level, and is the least strong at the firm level.


5.2. Type of information technology
We contend that the type of information technology is an important contextual factor, and it can have significant impact on performance improvement. Christensen (1997) classified technologies into sustaining or disruptive based on the nature of technological innovations. While both types can be new and innovative, sustaining technologies usually provide incremental improvement or better value against current technologies (Christensen, 1997; Garrison, Harvey, & Napier, 2008); disruptive technologies, on the other hand, are more radical new technologies that can create a new market or value network by disrupting the existing ones (Christensen & Raynor, 2003; Christernsen, Johnson, & Rigby, 2002).
Although the distinction of the two types of technologies has been mainly used to investigate new product development (Dooley & Johnson, 2001; Pattinson & Woodside, 2009; Witell, Antoni, & Dahlgaard, 2005), the adapted concepts have also been applied in other business fields, including information technology. For example, on the front of sustaining technologies, research has confirmed the role of knowledge management systems and practices as a continuous improvement initiative for firms to gain competitive advantages (e.g., Barber, Munive-Hernandez, & Keane, 2006; Beckett, Wainwright, & Bance, 2000; Parikh, 2001). Knowledge sharing and collaborative learning has also been demonstrated as an important continuous improvement in the supply chain system (Hyland, Soosay, & Sloan, 2003; Rhodes & Carter, 2003). Meanwhile, on the front of disruptive technologies, Nault and Vandenbosch (2000) explained in a mathematical model how an incumbent maintains competitive advantages over potential entrants. Dhillon, Coss, and Hackney (2001) showed the importance of recognizing disruptive technologies in e-businesses. As a disruptive technology, Internet computing has radically impacted a company’s system development and service innovations (Lyytinen & Rose, 2003).
Sustaining and disruptive technologies can have quite different performance implications at different levels. A solid understanding can help firms make the right choices to achieve their performance goals. Sustaining technologies provide incremental or continuous improvements to existing business processes. Investment in a sustaining technology will directly improve process level performance. Aggregated process performance improvement will lead to operational performance improvement, but this effect is subject to the influence of other factors. This aggregation effect becomes even weaker when performance is measured at the firm level.

The effect of disruptive technologies can be quite different. Disruptive technologies are “typically simpler, cheaper, and more reliable and convenient than established technologies” (Christensen, 1997; p. 174). Investment in disruptive information technologies usually can lead to the development of brand new business processes, or new products so that a new market or value network can be created. Disruptive technologies can bring new capabilities to a firm. They have the potential to significantly improve performance and bring more benefits at the firm level, for instance, increase market share or enhance customer service. Clearly, this is in sharp contrast to sustaining technologies. In summary, we state the above as Proposition P2.
Proposition P2

Both sustaining and disruptive information technologies can lead to performance improvement at all three levels: process, operational, and firm, but with different patterns. Sustaining information technologies can lead to incremental performance improvement through continuous improvement. In comparison, disruptive information technologies can lead to radical performance improvement through developing new capabilities.


5.3. Information technology life cycle
5.3.1. The concept of life cycle
The term “life cycle” originated in biology, referring to “the series of changes that the members of a species undergo as they pass from the beginning of a given developmental stage to the inception of that same developmental stage in a subsequent generation” (Encyclopædia Britannica). Later the term has been used in a variety of fields and disciplines, including business, organization or corporate, project, product and technology. Product life cycle is probably the most well-known application. Business researchers use the term to refer to multiple stages that a new product goes through from its inception to eventual demise. Generally, a product’s life cycle has four stages: introduction, growth, maturity, and decline (Karlsson & Nystrom, 2003; Tibben-Lembke, 2002). Same as products, technologies also have a life cycle composed of the same four stages, although the meaning of the stages is slightly different (Brugha, 2001; Friedman, 1999; Wu, Aytac, & Berger, 2006).
The concept of life cycle is important because of the dynamics involved in the evolution of an organization or a new product. At different stages, both the internal and external environment can change, which can have significant implications. Therefore, researchers have taken the life cycle stages into consideration for precise research findings in areas such as TQM, corporate innovation, and marketing strategies. For example, Parzinger (1997) suggested that a successful implementation of TQM must have several critical factors matching the product life cycle stages. Many studies have shown that organizational life cycle is an effective and insightful theoretical perspective to examine firm performance or firm innovativeness (e.g., Dibrell, Craig, & Hansen, 2011; Lester, Parnell, & Menefee, 2008/2009; Liao, 2006). Additionally, the product life cycle has also been used to examine successful company strategies and marketing programs (Mohan & Krishnaswamy, 2006; Thietart & Vivas, 1984).
Unfortunately, technology life cycle has been largely ignored in the study of “IT productivity variance.” In our review, we found virtually no study explicitly considered an information technology’s life cycle. Yet it is clear that the impact of an IT investment will not remain the same if the information technology is at different stages of its life cycle. For example, if an information technology is newly invented, the information technology could be highly innovative but also very risky. The relationship between the information technology and performance improvement thus is highly unstable and unpredictable. In contrast, if the information technology is mature, we can expect a rather stable effect on performance improvement, although the effect may not be very strong. This simple contrast highlights the necessity of considering technology life cycle in the study of “IT productivity variance.”

5.3.2. Stages of technology life cycle
Similar to the product life cycle, a technology also goes through four stages. At the Introduction stage, the technology is brand new. The effectiveness of the technology is not fully known and proven. Not very many people and firms are familiar or proficient with the technology. Only a few early adopters have adopted the technology and the results may be highly dramatic, either highly successful or disastrous. This stage is best characterized as “unpredictable.” If one is to examine the relationship between IT investment and performance implications at this stage, one would naturally observe an enormous amount of variance. The results will likely be highly mixed with some great successes as well as numerous failures. Many new technologies will actually not make through this stage for a variety of reasons. For instance, a technology may be too expensive, too complicated to be practically usable, or unable to provide stable results.
If a technology has proven its usefulness in the Introduction stage, it will enter the second stage, Growth. In this stage, the technology will be diffused to a wider population. More and more people and firms become familiar with the technology. Protocols for the implementation of the technology start to appear. The relationship between the technology and performance begins to be stable. One would expect to see performance improvement brought by the implementation of the technology, although stability may still be questionable.
The third stage is the Maturity stage. At this stage, the technology has been widely recognized, likely considered as the industrial standard. Firms will have little trouble to find people and protocols for the implementation of the technology. In fact, it is likely most firms in the industry have adopted the technology. A firm who has not adopted the technology will be considered lagging behind. The effectiveness of the technology is hardly questioned. Investing in the technology may lead to the performance improvement at the process, operational, or firm levels. However, it is worth noting that performance improvement at the firm level may not be detectable at this stage. The main reason is that most competitors have also adopted the technology to raise the competitive baseline. While the firm’s performance have improved substantially when compared to its past performance level, such an improvement is not necessarily reflected by relative metrics such as sales revenue, market share, or profitability.
The last stage is Decline. In this stage, the technology is being phased out. Newer or better technologies have appeared and will replace the current technology in the future. Firms are not likely to implement such a technology for performance improvement reasons, but for reasons such as maintaining product compatibility or uninterrupted operations. As the technology is demising, fewer people have knowledge or skills related to the technology. The difficulty of implementing such a technology will gradually increase. In other words, the required investment for such a technology will be high. However, it is hard for any firm to expect great return from such an investment. As stated above, the goal is likely to maintain the performance level of an old process. One would expect to see a weak or even no relationship between the investment of the technology and process level performance. It is also unreasonable to expect any strong relationship between the technology and operational or firm level performance.
In summary, the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement changes as the technology evolves into different stages of its life cycle. At the Introduction stage, the technology is so new that it can become a truly inimitable resource for a firm to gain formidable competitive advantage. If so, then a strong positive relationship to performance improvement can be observed. However, the high uncertainty associated with the new technology also implies the technology can easily fail. Therefore, in the Introduction stage, the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement is highly “unstable.” If the technology makes to the Growth stage, then we should expect to see a “strong positive” relationship toward performance improvement. The technology is still relatively new, hence only a few firms have adopted it. Using RBV’s term, the technology helps firms create inimitable resources to gain competitive advantage. Significant performance improvement is to be expected at all three levels. This proposition is also in line with the institutional theory, which states that early adopters usually can enjoy much performance improvement (e.g., Westphal et al., 1997). In the next stage, Maturity, we would expect the positive relationship remains but the magnitude weakens, particularly at the firm level. As a proven technology, we would expect it to improve process or even operational performance. But according to the RBV, resources created by this technology gradually lose the characteristic of being inimitable; hence they can no longer support firms to gain strong competitive advantage. The institutional theory also states that late adopters usually can only gain legitimacy but not much performance improvement. Finally, as the technology enters the Decline stage, we would not expect performance improvement from such IT investment. The best case will be to maintain the original performance level. In other words, the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement will be negative. We state this as Proposition P3 below. Fig. 2presents the proposed theoretical framework. Each research proposition is labeled in the figure.
Proposition P3

The relationship between IT investment and performance improvement varies at different stages of an technology’s life cycle: It is highly unstable at the Introduction stage, becomes strongly positive at the Growth stage, shrinks to weakly positive at the Maturity stage, and then turns negative at the Decline stage.


Fig. 2
Download high-res image (156KB)Download full-size image
Fig. 2. A contingency framework for IT investment and performance improvement.
The proposed contingency framework potentially contributes to a resolution of “IT productivity variance.” The framework provides a way for empirical researchers to incorporate contextual factors into their studies. According to the proposed contingency framework, the observed “IT productivity variance” is a reflection of a dynamic and complex relationship that changes with different levels of performance measurement, different type of technologies, or different stage of the life cycle of technologies. When researchers choose to study the effect of IT investment, but fail to specify these three important contextual factors, their model’s explanatory power may be limited, hence observing “IT productivity variance.” A clear specification of these important contextual factors, on the contrary, helps obtain a comprehensive understanding of a dynamic and complex relationship. In this regard, we view our effort as a step toward a complete resolution of “IT productivity variance.”]]></section>
    <section name="Discussions and conclusion" category="conclusion">
        <![CDATA[
6. Discussions and conclusion
6.1. Summary of findings
“IT productivity variance” refers to the large portion of unexplained variance observed on the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement (Beaudreau, 2010; Pinsonneault & Rivard, 1998). We view it as a natural extension of the famous “IT productivity paradox.” Many IS/IT scholars today no longer consider the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement paradoxical, but they are still perplexed by the large amount of unexplained variance observed in empirical studies.
We reviewed the literature to search for reasons of “IT productivity variance.” We identified three types of explanations and they all pointed to the necessity of incorporating contextual factors in empirical studies. We further articulated three major theoretical frameworks upon which empirical studies are guided: microeconomics, resource-based view, and institutional theory. Each has its strength and weakness. Each can explain a certain portion of performance variance. But the lack of consideration of contextual factors has caused insufficient explanatory power, hence the observed “IT productivity variance.”
We adopted the theory development approach to propose a contingency framework that augments existing theoretical frameworks. ]]><h target="3" match="part">Our central premise is that the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement is subject to the influence of important contextual factors. According to the literature, level of performance measurement, type of technology, and stages of technology life cycle are three prominent contextual factors</h><![CDATA[ Generally, the higher the level performance is measured, the weaker the relationship. Sustaining and disruptive technologies can have very different impact on performance improvement. As one information technology goes through different stages of its life cycle, its impact on performance improvement can change substantially. Therefore, to examine the relationship between IT investment and performance improvement, researchers ought to carefully consider the effect of these important contextual factors.

6.2. Theoretical contributions
]]><h target="4" match="part">The proposed contingency framework potentially can make a significant contribution to the literature.</h> No doubt that “IT productivity variance” is an important research challenge. An in-depth understanding of the issue is a vital first step toward resolution. Our literature review effort summarized existing research studies to provide an up-to-date understanding, hence laid a solid foundation for future research.

<h target="3" match="past">A more important contribution is that the proposed contingency framework is one of the first to theorizing on important contextual factors.</h>Specifically, our model explicitly points out that researchers’ choice of performance metrics is a significant factor. This proposition can help future research make more precise choices based on their research objectives. Our model further shows that researchers need to clearly specify the type of information technology being investigated because the effect of sustaining and disruptive technologies can be drastically different. The same is true for technology life cycle. In essence, this study argues that researchers should uncover the specifics of information technology being studies before they can draw generalizable conclusions. Such effort can help achieve more in-depth theoretical understanding. In other words, while our research propositions are yet to be empirically validated, the summarization of theoretical thinking in light of contextual factors is an important step toward a better theory, potentially leading to a resolution of “IT productivity variance.”

6.3. Practical implications
        <h target="4" match="part">This research also can provide some useful insights for practicing managers.</h> First, firms need to invest in the correct type of technology to achieve the desired performance improvement. Using a sustaining technology for breakthrough type of performance improvement is a mismatch and it will not lead to desired outcome. The opposite is also true. Firms also need to be aware of the life cycle stage of an information technology. This is important because it helps them set realistic performance improvement goals. Finally, firms should measure performance at the right level for their IT investment. It has been pointed out numerous times that, incorrect expectation does not help IT project success, but instead, could lead to project failure.

6.4. Future research
<![CDATA[This research can be extended in multiple ways. We view the proposed contingency theoretical framework as a starting point rather than a comprehensive one. The reality is always more complicated than models. There are many more contingency factors that our model has not considered. For example, a firm may make an IT investment for competitive advantage reasons, but it is also possible that the firm has done so due to strategic necessity (Besson & Rowe, 2012; Hopper, 1990). It is conceivable such a different context can lead to quite different performance implications even with the same IT investment. It is also not an easy task for firms to identify an information technology as sustaining or disruptive ex ante because so many contextual factors can affect the decision. Future research can consider these and other important contingency factors and dig deeper into these issues.]]>
Since the proposed model is a theoretical model, operationalization for empirical test is naturally the next step. Qualitative analysis such as case studies can be conducted to further refine the proposed model. The research propositions need to be further developed into testable research hypotheses. Measurement instrument development and operationalization is another important task. Then it is possible to conduct a large scale empirical study.</section>
</publication>